<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3772</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">geohealth</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>GeoHealth</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Geohealth</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12710085</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12710085</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12710085</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41416034</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2025GH001409</article-id><title-group><article-title>Assessment of Ambient Multipollutant Exposure and Health Impacts Over India Using the Novel Satellite‐Based Multi‐Pollutant Index</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardra</surname><given-names initials="D">D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gh270081-aff-0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Philip</surname><given-names initials="S">Sajeev</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gh270081-aff-0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names initials="D">Debajit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gh270081-aff-0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names initials="S">Subhadeep</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gh270081-aff-0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>van Donkelaar</surname><given-names initials="A">Aaron</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gh270081-aff-0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names initials="RV">Randall V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gh270081-aff-0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names initials="S">Sagnik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gh270081-aff-0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="gh270081-aff-0003">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="gh270081-aff-0001"><label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>Centre for Atmospheric Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, New Delhi, India</aff><aff id="gh270081-aff-0002"><label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>Department of Energy, Environmental &amp; Chemical Engineering, Washington University in St. Louis, St. Louis, MO, USA</aff><aff id="gh270081-aff-0003"><label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label>Department of Health, Policy and Management, Korea University, Seoul, South Korea</aff><author-notes><fn id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><p>

<bold>Correspondence to:</bold>
 
D. Ardra and S. Philip, 
<email>ardra8034@gmail.com</email>; 
<email>philipsajeev@iitd.ac.in</email>

</p></fn><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e2025GH001409</fpage><page-range>e2025GH001409</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Author(s). GeoHealth published by Wiley Periodicals LLC on behalf of American Geophysical Union.</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non‐commercial and no modifications or adaptations are made.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 7a7a/12710085/64e02c841e3e/GH2-9-e2025GH001409.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2099303?></self-uri><abstract id="abstract1"><title>Abstract</title><p>Ambient air pollutants are reported to have adverse health impacts, which could be better assessed by examining human exposure to multiple criteria pollutants or through a multi‐pollutant Air Quality Index (AQI). As compared to AQIs developed using in situ measurements of pollutants across sparse monitoring stations, satellite‐based products such as ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> or NO<sub>2</sub> provide better spatiotemporal patterns. Here, we examine the long‐term (2005–2019) air pollution exposure and health impacts over India with the novel Satellite‐Based Multi‐Pollutant Index (SMPI). The high spatial resolution (1 km × 1 km) SMPI over India reveals pollution exposure hotspots in most states and districts over the Indo‐Gangetic Plain (IGP) and eastern states. The spatiotemporal patterns in SMPI exposure and its urban‐rural heterogeneity were different from either PM<sub>2.5</sub> or NO<sub>2</sub>, highlighting the importance of multi‐pollutant indices to comprehensively assess air quality. Furthermore, we found a strong association (1.05, 95% UI: 1.025–1.075) between SMPI and odds of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD), which increased with increasing co‐pollutant exposures [1.03 (1.018–1.042) to 1.184 (1.156–2.212)]. The SMPI—COPD association was significantly higher among males, middle class, tribes, and older sub‐populations, highlighting the need for future environmental policies prioritized for vulnerable population subgroups for larger health benefits.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> air pollution, multi‐pollutant index, SMPI, satellite, health, India</p></sec></abstract><abstract id="abstract2" abstract-type="plain-language-summary"><title>Plain Language Summary</title><p>Exposure to ambient air pollutants have been reported to have severe public health impacts. Air pollution is better assessed by examining human exposure to multiple criteria pollutants or through a multi‐pollutant Air Quality Index (AQI). As compared to AQIs developed using in situ measurements of pollutants across sparse monitoring stations, satellite‐based products provide better spatiotemporal patterns. We assess the long‐term air pollution exposure in India using a Satellite‐based Multi‐pollutant Index (SMPI) using satellite derived surface PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>. Our analysis shows air pollution hotspots in the districts of Indo‐Gangetic Plain (IGP) and Eastern states in India. The patterns of SMPI exposure across urban and rural areas were different from those of PM<sub>2.5</sub> or NO<sub>2</sub> alone. This emphasizes the need for multi‐pollutant indices to get a complete understanding of air quality. Our results show that SMPI—Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease association was significantly stronger among males, middle class, tribes, and older sub‐populations. This highlights the need for targeted environmental policies to protect vulnerable groups.</p></abstract><abstract id="abstract3" abstract-type="short"><title>Key Points</title>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Satellite‐Based Multi‐Pollutant Index (SMPI) or similar multi‐pollutant indices may be more suitable for assessing air quality and related health impacts</p></list-item><list-item><p>Long‐term (2005–2019) SMPI analysis in India reveals the air pollution hotspots in the Indo‐Gangetic Plain and Eastern states</p></list-item><list-item><p>Strong association between SMPI exposure and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, with higher risks among males, middle‐class, tribal, and older populations</p></list-item></list>
</abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Revised 2025 Oct 11; Received 2025 Mar 10; Accepted 2025 Oct 18; Collection date 2025 Dec.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="gh270081-sec-0010" disp-level="1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Exposure to ambient air pollutants such as PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> have been reported to have severe public health impacts (Achakulwisut et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Anenberg et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Balakrishnan et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Crouse et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Hamra et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Pandey et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0038" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). The Global Burden of Disease (GBD) study calculated 27.41 (17.69–36.25) and 0.021 (0.018–0.024) million Disability‐Adjusted Life Years (DALYs) in India attributable to PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposures, respectively (Murray, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0035" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). The adverse health impacts of these ambient air pollutants could be better assessed by simultaneously examining exposure to multiple criteria air pollutants (Billionnet et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Coffman et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>; Oakes et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0037" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). To our knowledge, studies based on India have only estimated the single pollutant impacts on various health outcomes (Chaudhary et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>; Chen et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>; Huangfu &amp; Atkinson, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Nori‐Sarma et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Rajak &amp; Chattopadhyay, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0040" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Spears et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0047" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). However, the combined effect of ambient air pollutants is poorly studied over India. Moreover, the nature of the combined exposure effect from these pollutants (whether it is additive, synergistic, antagonistic, or interactive manner) among the Indian population is unknown.</p><p>To incorporate multiple criteria pollutants for assessing deteriorated air quality, Multi‐pollutant Air Quality Index (MAQI) has been introduced in the past (Plaia et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0039" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Similar indices such as Air Quality Health Index (AQHI) and Health‐based Air Quality Index (HAQI) have been formulated to estimate the impact of multi‐pollutants on public health (Hu et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Huang et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). K. Kumar, (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>) conducted a comprehensive review of air quality indices used worldwide from 1960 to 2021, taking into account various factors such as the number of pollutants considered, method of calculation (linear vs. nonlinear), averaging time, mode of estimation (single pollutant vs. multi‐pollutant), and health effects. In India, the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB) formulated the National Air Quality Index (NAQI) and classified the air quality into six categories based on the maximum value of individual pollutant concentrations and their associated health effects (CPCB, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). However, this index has limitations in identifying regions with poorest air quality caused by multiple air pollutants (Gurjar et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Moreover, the traditional indices rely on observational data from ground‐based monitoring sites (K. Kumar, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>), where the stations are sparse and lack continuous databases at higher spatiotemporal resolutions (Brauer et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Martin et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0034" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Since the existing AQIs partially represent the population exposure due to insufficient in situ observations, an index representing continuous spatiotemporal variability in multi‐pollutant exposures is essential for assessing air quality and attributable health impacts. This will also help identify pollution hotspots that require prioritized policies and interventions for pollution mitigation.</p><p>Compared to AQIs calculated using in situ measurements of pollutants at sparse monitoring stations, satellite‐based remote sensing provides better continuous spatiotemporal coverage. The satellite‐based retrievals of Aerosol Optical Depth (AOD) and vertical column density are currently used to derive reliable global and regional surface concentrations of PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>, respectively (Anenberg et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Cooper et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>; Dey et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Katoch et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>; N. Singh et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>; van Donkelaar et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) proposed a new metric to assess multiple pollutants, Satellite‐based Multi‐Pollutant Index (SMPI), utilizing satellite‐derived surface PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> data and scaling by pollutant concentration deviation from WHO guidelines. Although SMPI relies only on two key pollutants (PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>), which are reliably estimated using satellite observations, this new metric provides better spatiotemporal observational coverage than metrics based on in situ data. To our understanding, no further studies examined global or regional air pollution exposure and related adverse human health impacts using SMPI as a metric.</p><p>Therefore, the broad objective of this study is to assess the potential of SMPI as a better metric compared to PM<sub>2.5</sub> or NO<sub>2</sub> to examine air pollution exposure and health impacts in a region (India, in this study). We first assessed air pollution exposure in India from 2005 to 2019 using the SMPI metric derived from satellite‐based ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> data sets. We have used the global data sets for surface PM<sub>2.5</sub> (van Donkelaar et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) and NO<sub>2</sub> (Cooper et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>), both estimated using satellites and chemical transport models (GEOS‐Chem) to ensure data consistency. We then estimated the associations between PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI with the odds of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) among the Indian population using demographic information derived from the national family health survey—5th round (NFHS‐5, 2019–2021). Furthermore, we estimated effect modification of SMPI across the NFHS‐5 survey participant's gender, age, wealth, caste, cooking fuel types, and resident types. Finally, we estimated the reduction in COPD prevalence if Indian states succeed to meet the clean‐air targets in the foreseeable future. The results from this study will highlight the need to have multi‐pollutant indices to assess air quality and provide the metric for further epidemiological research in India, incorporating multiple air pollutants together.</p></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0020" disp-level="1"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="gh270081-sec-0030" disp-level="2"><label>2.1.</label><title>Data</title><sec id="gh270081-sec-0040" disp-level="3"><label>2.1.1.</label><title>Satellite‐Derived Ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub>
</title><p>We used a high resolution (0.01° latitude × 0.01° longitude) ground‐level fine particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub>) annual mean data set for 2005–2019 from van Donkelaar et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), updated to version V5.GL.03. The data set is derived geophysically by relating AOD retrievals combined from three satellite instruments MODIS (Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer), MISR (Multi‐angle Imaging SpectroRadiometer), and SeaWiFS (Sea‐viewing Wide Field‐of‐view Sensor) to surface‐level PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations using the chemical transport model: GEOS‐Chem. These geophysical PM<sub>2.5</sub> estimates are enhanced using in situ measurements from &gt;11,000 global sites, including &gt;3,000 monitors over Asia. These monitors are used within a Geographically Weighted Regression (GWR) framework to predict and adjust for bias in the initial geophysical PM<sub>2.5</sub>, increasing the accuracy of the final hybrid PM<sub>2.5</sub> used in this study. Within Asia, the cross‐validated annual R<sup>2</sup> between the hybrid PM<sub>2.5</sub> and ground‐based observations ranges from 0.66 to 0.74.</p></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0050" disp-level="3"><label>2.1.2.</label><title>Satellite‐Derived Ambient NO<sub>2</sub>
</title><p>We used satellite‐derived high‐resolution (0.01° latitude × 0.01° longitude) ground‐level nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>) data obtained from a recent study (Cooper et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>). The annually averaged data set from 2005 to 2019 is derived from the Ozone Monitoring Instrument (OMI) and TROPOspheric Monitoring Instrument (TROPOMI) satellite NO<sub>2</sub> retrievals. The NO<sub>2</sub> column densities are determined for a given year using OMI observations downscaled to a finer resolution using TROPOMI observations. Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>) utilized the downscaled column densities to derive surface‐level concentrations through the GEOS‐Chem chemical transport model, constraining it with ground monitor observations. The long‐term changes observed in this satellite‐derived NO<sub>2</sub> data exhibit general consistency with the trends noted from available observational data in India (Cooper et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>) while it shows an underestimation by a factor of 4 for the year 2019 (Figure S3 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0060" disp-level="3"><label>2.1.3.</label><title>Ancillary Data</title><p>We used Global Human Settlement Layer (GHSL) level‐2 data, identifying each (1 km × 1 km) grid as one of the eight classes (Schiavina, Melchiorri, &amp; Pesaresi, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Schiavina, Melchiorri, Pesaresi, Politis, et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Figure S1 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). The data is available in distinct years, such as 2005, 2010, and 2015. We combined three rural grids into a single rural grid and four semi‐urban and urban grids into a single urban grid in 2005, 2010, and 2015. We used population data from the World Research Program, which is available for all countries from 2000 to 2020 and represents the number of people per grid cell at a high resolution (1 km × 1 km) (WorldPop &amp; Bondarenko, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0053" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The projection of data sets is the Geographic Coordinate System, WGS84.</p></sec></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0070" disp-level="2"><label>2.2.</label><title>SMPI Calculation and Exposure Analysis</title><p>The satellite observations of surface concentrations can be used to define a SMPI. This approach is demonstrated by Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) by defining globally gridded SMPI products by scaling surface‐level PM<sub>2.5</sub> (multi‐satellite) by NO<sub>2</sub> concentration data (OMI satellite). We followed this approach and estimated SMPI over India using a recently available data set of satellite‐based surface PM<sub>2.5</sub> data from van Donkelaar et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) and NO<sub>2</sub> concentration data from Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>). The following equation is used for the calculation of SMPI,
</p><disp-formula id="gh270081-disp-0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="jats-math-1" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SMPI</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mtext>PM</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2.5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mtext>AQG</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mtext>PM</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2.5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mtext>NO</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mtext>AQG</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mtext>NO</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Here we refer to WHO Air Quality Guidelines 2021 (AQG) PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations of 5 μg/m<sup>3</sup> and NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations of 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. The above AQGs are for the year 2021, which are different from that used in Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). In this study, we have also analyzed the long‐term SMPI values calculated using the Air Quality Guidelines (AQG) from the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS, Central Pollution Control Board of India) for 2019, PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations of 40 μg/m<sup>3</sup> and NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations of 40 μg/m<sup>3</sup>.</p><p>A long‐term analysis of SMPI is conducted from 2005 to 2019. The long‐term means of PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI are determined, and spatial patterns are analyzed. Population‐weighted SMPI is calculated, and long‐term exposure analysis is also carried out. The long‐term (2005–2019) SMPI exposure for each state and district is determined by sampling satellite data within the boundaries of shapefiles obtained from DIVA‐GIS. The SMPI exposure in each state is estimated, and states are ranked based on pollution levels. For further investigation, the study period is divided into three sets of 5‐year mean blocks (2005–2009, 2010–2014, 2015–2019). Exposure analysis is conducted for each state and union territory during these periods, as well as the difference in the exposure between these periods. Additionally, SMPI exposures in urban and rural areas are analyzed for different periods.</p></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0080" disp-level="2"><label>2.3.</label><title>National Family Health Survey (NFHS)</title><sec id="gh270081-sec-0090" disp-level="3"><label>2.3.1.</label><title>Socio‐Demographic Information</title><p>We used the demographic and health information from the 5th round (2019‐21) of the national family health survey (NFHS) for our analysis here. The NFHS is a nationally representative household survey measuring population demographics, household characteristics, nutrition, and health (majorly prioritizing rural residents), and child and maternal health (The DHS Program, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). NFHS has a two‐stage sampling design. At first, the districts were selected and then, the clusters were selected within the districts for the individual and household‐level questionnaires (census enumeration blocks in urban areas, villages in rural areas). The NFHS sampling was carried out by the International Institute of Population Sciences (IIPS) under the Demographic and Health Survey (DHS) curriculum. Each cluster was classified as urban or rural based on individuals' per‐capita income, ownership of household assets, average educational level, and the overall socioeconomic status of the demographic sub‐populations. Within districts, the rural strata were further divided into smaller substrata according to village population size and the proportions of scheduled caste (SC) and scheduled tribe (ST) subgroups.</p><p>The 2011 census was used as the sampling frame to identify Primary Sampling Units (PSUs), also referred to as survey clusters. In rural strata, villages were selected as PSUs, with clusters arranged beforehand by female literacy rates (aged 6 years and above). In urban strata, Census Enumeration Blocks (CEBs) were chosen as PSUs, arranged by the proportion of SC and ST subgroups. In the second stage, 22 households were randomly selected from each cluster through equal‐probability systematic sampling, based on a fresh household listing prepared during mapping operations. PSUs with 300 or more households were divided into segments of about 100–150 households, from which one segment was chosen for the survey. Detailed descriptions of the NFHS sampling design are available in the publicly accessible NFHS reports (The DHS Program, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). For the individual‐level survey, women aged 15–49 years and men aged 15–54 years were selected across the households. An identical questionnaire following standardized measurement methods was used to ensure comparability and compatibility across diverse sites and times. The detailed description of the survey methods is in the DHS‐7 user manual. NFHS‐5 covered 30,197 clusters from 707 districts of India. In the NFHS sampling design, villages in rural areas and CEBs in urban areas were selected as clusters using probability proportional to size (PPS), followed by systematic household sampling within each cluster. The base sampling weight for a household was defined as the inverse of its selection probability, and these weights were subsequently adjusted for household and individual non‐response within each stratum. The adjusted weights were then normalized so that the weighted totals matched the actual sample size at national or subregional levels. These cluster‐level weights ensured that survey estimates remained representative and unbiased across population subgroups (The DHS Program, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).</p><p>We carried out our analysis over a total of 825,954 individuals across India. For the health effect assessment, baseline information on participants' demographic characteristics (age, sex, wealth, caste, education, occupation, marital status, health insurance, resident and cooking‐fuel types), and lifestyle habits (smoking and drinking status) were obtained from the latest NFHS round. We obtained the demographic information from the NFHS questionnaire administered to individual levels (male and female) and at household level. For the wealth index, the sample is divided into five categories, richest, richer, middle class, poorer, and poorest, based on the ranks of standardized scores for each household possessing different types of socio‐demographic and economic assets (The DHS Program, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). We clubbed the richest and richer subgroups as rich, and poorer and poorest subgroups as poor, while keeping the middle‐class sub‐population as separate.</p><p>Among the Indian populace, high exposure to solid fuel‐sourced household air pollution has been linked with various non‐communicable disease (NCD) health outcomes (Chowdhury et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), so the type of cooking‐fuel used by households has been adjusted in this analysis. Liquefied petroleum gas (LPG), electricity, biogas or natural gas was clubbed together as clean‐fuel in the households; while kerosene or biomass fuel (straw/shrubs/grass, wood, animal dung, agricultural crops, charcoal, coal/lignite, and others) were classified as solid‐fuel. The survey captured the information of four levels of an individual's educational attainment as no education, primary, secondary, and higher educational level. The occupation is considered as one key confounder for health outcomes as the types of occupation determines the exposure level and probability of developing various diseases (Chaudhary et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). The occupational classes considered in this analysis were categorized as professionals, farmers or agricultural laborers, workers, households or non‐workers, and others. The smoking status and type of smoking were also captured as for the sub‐groups, where a person smoking cigarettes, bidi, or tobacco was categorized as smokers. We used other dichotomous variables as covariates in the analysis, such as availing health insurance, type of residence (urban/rural), and second‐hand smoke exposure (yes/no). The information of multiple dietary intakes (daily per‐capita beverage, served process food, and packed process food) were captured in the NSSO survey, which were integrated with the NFHS survey data sets across the common households. In both surveys, each household is given a unique ID, these IDs from NFHS and NSSO are merged together using the Hot‐Deck method (Joenssen &amp; Bankhofer, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). We also included the information on marital status (married, unmarried, and widow/separates/divorced) into our adjusted models. And lastly, the models were adjusted for other fixed effects like cluster ID, month, year, state, and district. For the health outcome, we relied on the survey information of individuals' prevalence of COPD in our analysis, which was recorded as binary information (Yes or No) during the interview. We adjusted the cluster‐specific “sample weights” in the models to assess the cluster level variability on the association between chronic PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure and the odds of COPD.</p></sec></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0100" disp-level="2"><label>2.4.</label><title>Health Effect Assessment</title><sec id="gh270081-sec-0110" disp-level="3"><label>2.4.1.</label><title>Multivariate Regression Model</title><p>We extracted the long‐term (2015‐19) annual mean concentration of PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and their corresponding SMPI estimates for each survey cluster (defined as urban or rural) based on their geo‐locations (centroid). These geo‐locations were used to create geospatial buffers with a radius of 5 and 2 km for rural and urban clusters, respectively. For this assessment, it was assumed that respondents remained in their respective clusters during the survey period and were continuously exposed to the cluster‐level long‐term ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration. This assumption allowed temporal alignment between the air pollution estimates and the demographic information of NFHS. Within the NFHS framework, buffer radii of 2 km for urban clusters and 5 km for rural clusters were conventionally applied to generate geospatial buffers. This convention reflected the higher density and smaller spatial extent of urban clusters as compared with the larger, more spatially dispersed rural clusters. The smaller urban buffer minimized the inclusion of surrounding non‐representative areas, whereas the larger rural buffer ensured that representative ambient conditions were captured (The DHS Program, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The mean concentrations of the pollutants within each buffer region were extracted using ArcGIS (v3.8) software. We converted each level of air pollutants' concentration (PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI) into their respective percentile estimates (1st to 100th percentiles) using array.rank(pct = True) command in Python. We then merged the air pollutant estimates with the individual and household level demographic information from NFHS‐5 using the unique code of each NFHS cluster.</p><p>We used the individual‐level hierarchical logistic mixed effects model to assess the association between ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations with the odds of COPD among the Indian populace, accounting for differential clustering effect. We adjusted both the pollutants, PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> in our model and assessed the effect estimates of one pollutant due to the moderation of the other by odds ratio (ORs, with 95% uncertainty intervals, UIs) for per percentile increase in pollutant estimates. Note that the survey respondents were not independent observations but were nested with the clusters, which served as the primary sampling units in the NFHS framework. To account for this hierarchical structure, we specified the cluster as a random intercept in our hierarchical logistic mixed‐effects models. This approach allowed us to control for unobserved within‐cluster similarities (e.g., shared environment or socio‐demographic characteristics) and to produce valid standard errors and effect estimates. We then estimated the association between SMPI exposure and the odds of COPD. However, in the later model, we did not adjust PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> estimates to avoid multicollinearity in the effect estimation. All the statistical analyses were performed using statsmodels.api‐0.14.0 module in Python, and statistical significance is decided by <italic>p</italic>‐value &lt;0.05. We performed the following regression model to estimate association between the air pollution estimates and the health outcomes,
</p><disp-formula id="gh270081-disp-0002"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="jats-math-2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>logit</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced open="{" close="}" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")" separators=""><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Exposure</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Here, <italic>Y</italic>
<sub>
<italic>ij</italic>
</sub> represents the binary health outcome (COPD) for the <italic>j</italic>th individual in <italic>i</italic>th cluster, <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="jats-math-3" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the intercept, <italic>u</italic>
<sub>
<italic>i</italic>
</sub> is the random intercept corresponding to <italic>i</italic>th cluster with <italic>u</italic>
<sub>
<italic>i</italic>
</sub> ∼ N(0, <italic>σ</italic>
<sub>
<italic>u</italic>
</sub>
<sup>2</sup>); in the multi‐pollutant model, <italic>β</italic>
<sub>
<italic>i</italic>
</sub> is the regression coefficient for PM<sub>2.5</sub> or NO<sub>2</sub>, adjusted for its co‐pollutant, and for SMPI; and <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="jats-math-4" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the regression coefficients corresponding to all other confounders <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="jats-math-5" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")" separators=""><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We examined whether multicollinearity exists between ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>, and other relevant covariates. Figure S2 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> depicted the correlation statistics between the covariates, we found lower to moderate correlation (<italic>r</italic> &lt; 0.6, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between the pollutants and among the covariates; therefore, minimizing the potential impact of multicollinearity between these covariates within an epidemiological assessment. The exposure estimates were converted into percentile ranks (1st to 100th percentiles) across their full distributions. And then, the odds ratio (OR) was estimated by <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="jats-math-6" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for each percentile increase in pollutants' exposure and SMPI. The ORs therefore represent the relative change in COPD risk associated with a one‐percentile increase in exposure rank, rather than per unit (in μg/m<sup>3</sup>) increase in pollutants concentration. Note that this percentile scaling was applied to allow comparability between pollutants with different concentration ranges and units. We carried out three additional sets of analyses where we estimated the association between SMPI and the odds of COPD across different ranges of PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>, respectively. In the 1st set of analysis, we stratified the data set into four different ranges of PM<sub>2.5</sub>, such as &lt;25th percentile, 25th to 50th percentile, 50th to 75th percentile, and &gt;75th percentile, while adjusting for NO<sub>2</sub>. Similarly, in the 2nd set, we stratified the data set into four such ranges of NO<sub>2</sub>, while adjusting for PM<sub>2.5</sub>. In the 3rd set of analysis, we stratified the data set into four such exposure ranges of both PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>. We intended to investigate how the association between SMPI and COPD varies across the different exposure ranges of PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> separately and considering both the pollutants together. Thus, stratification refers to subgroup analyses by exposure ranges, not a different method of scaling. Finally, we used an interaction model to assess the effect modification of SMPI on the odds of COPD across participant's gender [male and female (reference)], age [25–35 (reference), 35–45, and over 45 years], wealth [rich (reference), middle class, and poor], caste [general (reference), other backward class (OBC), and scheduled caste and scheduled tribes combined as (SC + ST)], cooking fuel used in the household [clean‐fuel (reference) and solid‐fuel], and the type of residence [urban and rural (reference)]. Table S1 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> shows the regression estimates.</p></sec></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0120" disp-level="2"><label>2.5.</label><title>Health Benefits Assessment</title><p>We examined the expected reduction in COPD prevalence (health benefits) if the states meet three clean‐air targets in the foreseeable future: (a) if the mean ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposures during NFHS‐5 were above national ambient air quality standards (NAAQS) of 40 μg/m<sup>3</sup>or any of the interim‐targets by World Health Organization (WHO) (35, 25, and 15 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and 30 and 20 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for NO<sub>2</sub>) during NFHS‐5, first clean‐air target for the states would be to achieve their nearest exposure reduction target, for which we estimated the reduced SMPI values; (b) similarly, for the 2nd clean‐air target, we considered that the states would meet their next feasible exposure reduction target after achieving 1st clean‐air target, and we calculated the corresponding SMPI values; and finally, (c) we estimated the reduced SMPI while considering the states to achieve the WHO air quality guideline (AQG) of 5 and 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> respectively, in the foreseeable future. For the three exposure reduction scenarios, we first estimated the reduction in SMPI values at the state level. The attributable fraction was derived using the following relation:
</p><disp-formula id="gh270081-disp-0003"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="jats-math-7" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>AF</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo>–</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")" separators=""><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>RR</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Where <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="jats-math-8" display="inline"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RR</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>OR</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>SMPI</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and OR is the estimated odds ratio for each percentile increase in SMPI exposure; and ΔSMPI is the difference in SMPI exposure across the three reduction scenarios with respect to the long‐term mean SMPI estimate during NFHS‐5. Then the expected reduction in state level COPD prevalence (HB) was calculated due to the reduction in SMPI exposure as: HB = AF × State level COPD prevalence during NFHS‐5. We also estimated COPD prevalence across the states during NFHS‐5 and its changes under the three exposure reduction scenarios.</p></sec></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0130" disp-level="1"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><sec id="gh270081-sec-0140" disp-level="2"><label>3.1.</label><title>Spatiotemporal Variability of SMPI Exposure</title><p>Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows long‐term (2005–2019) annual mean surface concentrations of PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI over India. The highly populated Indo‐Gangetic Plain (IGP) region has the highest PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations, primarily from anthropogenic and biomass burning emissions and low ventilation coefficient (Dey et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; N. Singh et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). The long‐term mean PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration is maximum over Delhi National Capital Region (NCR) with a value of 132 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. We found that 99.5% of districts in India (except some regions in Ladakh) fail to meet the WHO AQG (2021) of 5 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. The NO<sub>2</sub> concentration is highest at some distinct hotspots in the Northern (e.g., Delhi, Ghaziabad) and Central‐Eastern (e.g., Chhattisgarh, West Bengal) regions. The nitrogen oxide emissions from transportation, industries, and thermal power plants lead to NO<sub>2</sub> enhancements in these regions (N. Singh et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). The NO<sub>2</sub> concentration over the hotspots is higher than 15 μg/m<sup>3</sup>, exceeding the WHO's AQG (2021) of 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. We found that satellite‐based NO<sub>2</sub> for the year 2019 is underestimated by a factor of 4 compared to in situ observations over India (see Figure S3 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>) even though Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>) states that the long‐term trends in satellite‐derived NO<sub>2</sub> data is consistent with trends observed from in situ data in India. Future studies should explore the persistent underestimate of satellite‐based NO<sub>2</sub> products over India (e.g., N. Singh et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0046" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>).The spatial distribution of SMPI (unitless) reveals significant enhancements in the IGP region, primarily attributed to PM<sub>2.5</sub>. Additionally, Central‐Eastern states exhibit elevated SMPI values due to NO<sub>2</sub> hotspots. Notably, the SMPI values presented in Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, based on the WHO AQG for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>, exceed 30 in both the IGP and Central‐Eastern India. However, when considering the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS) 2019 AQG for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>, the SMPI values over these regions are an order of magnitude lower (Figure S4 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). Here, we followed the WHO AQG (Equation <xref rid="gh270081-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref> and Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) to be consistent with Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) and to follow global AQG standards to compare Indian air quality with other global regions, in future studies.</p><fig id="gh270081-fig-0001" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Long‐term (2005–2019) annual mean surface concentrations of PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI over India. SMPI is calculated using Equation <xref rid="gh270081-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref> based WHO AQG (2021) for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>. The PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> concentration are in μg/m<sup>3</sup> and SMPI is unitless. Satellite‐based ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> data are from van Donkelaar et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) and Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>) respectively.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="jats-graphic-1" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g007.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/d6fc02eefc49/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g007.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 330?><?original-width 1064?><?scaled-height 220?><?scaled-width 709?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g007.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/c2ccb78d44c6/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g007.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the long‐term annual mean PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI exposure (population‐weighted mean concentration) for different states and UTs in India. The spatial maps of state‐wise exposure values are in Figure S5 of Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>. The PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure is highest (&gt;80 μg/m<sup>3</sup>) in states in the IGP region (Delhi, Uttar Pradesh, and Bihar) and lowest (∼25 μg/m<sup>3</sup>) in the southern and northeastern states. The NO<sub>2</sub> exposure in Haryana, Chhattisgarh, Jharkhand, and West Bengal is 4–6 μg/m<sup>3</sup>, whereas exposure over Delhi NCR exceeds 17 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. The SMPI exposure across the IGP states like Punjab, Haryana, Uttar Pradesh, and Bihar exceeds 20. Whereas moderate SMPI values of 12–24 are obtained across the states of Chhattisgarh, Jharkhand, and West Bengal. Interestingly, we obtained the highest SMPI exposure of 60 over the Delhi NCR region, while most of the southern and northeastern states show lowest SMPI exposure (&lt;5).</p><fig id="gh270081-fig-0002" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Long‐term (2005–2019) annual mean PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI exposure for different states and Union Territories in India. The PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposure are in μg/m<sup>3</sup>, whereas SMPI exposure is unitless. The states are arranged in the descending order of SMPI values.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="jats-graphic-3" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g001.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/830d398d38c7/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g001.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1268?><?original-width 1064?><?scaled-height 845?><?scaled-width 709?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g001.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/d386bd9c0977/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g001.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>We further examined the PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI exposure variability within the states by calculating exposure at the district level (Figure S6 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). Our findings reveal that PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure is highest across the IGP districts, with the pollutant concentration exceeding 60 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. PM<sub>2.5</sub> level ranges between 30 and 45 μg/m<sup>3</sup> or higher across most districts over northern India. The NO<sub>2</sub> exposure distribution shows notable patterns. In addition to some districts in the IGP region, certain districts in Chhattisgarh, Orissa, and West Bengal (Eastern India) show elevated NO<sub>2</sub> values (&gt;8 μg/m<sup>3</sup>). Most districts in the IGP region possess higher SMPI exposure (&gt;20). We found that several districts in Chhattisgarh and West Bengal also had enhanced SMPI values similar to that of IGP districts. The observed NO<sub>2</sub> distribution contributes to these elevated SMPI levels in these regions.</p><p>We analyzed the percentage of population exposed to different species from 2005 to 2019 (Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The top left panel of the Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows the population (in percentage) exposed to annual ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations and it indicates that the entire population of India is exposed to PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations above the WHO's AQG of 5 μg/m<sup>3</sup> throughout this period. Furthermore, there is a consistent rise in the number of people exposed to surface PM<sub>2.5</sub> from 2005 to 2019. Notably, 40% of the population was exposed to &gt;50 μg/m<sup>3</sup> ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> in 2005, which has increased to 60% by 2019, highlighting a concerning trend in air quality and its impact on public health. The top right panel of Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> indicates the population (in percentage) exposed to annual ambient NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations, revealing a different pattern. The population exposed to higher NO<sub>2</sub> levels (ranging from 2 to 4 μg/m<sup>3</sup>) has consistently increased from 2005 to 2014. However, a notable change occurred in 2015, as the population exposed to elevated NO<sub>2</sub> levels decreased significantly (&lt;2 μg/m<sup>3</sup>). This reduction may be due to some policies by National Green Tribunal (NGT), GOI and India's vehicular emissions Bharat Stage (BS)‐III and BS‐IV implemented on vehicles in 2005 and 2010 in major metro cities and in 2010 and 2017 countrywide (Singh et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>).The findings by Biswal et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>) also states that there is a decrease in tropospheric NO<sub>2</sub> VCD over non‐attainments cities of India since 2017 which can be attributed to upgrading vehicular exhaust standards, electric vehicle usage, NCAP and other strict implementations. The bottom left panel of the figure shows the percentage of people exposed to SMPI from 2005 to 2019. This metric reflects the combined influence of PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposure. The percentage of people exposed to SMPI levels greater than 15 has increased from 2005 to 2014 from 10% to 21%. However, there is a slight shift in the pattern during 2015 as the population exposed to a higher level of SMPI (&gt;15) has reduced to 16%. The figure reveals that the reduction in NO<sub>2</sub> exposure caused this change in SMPI exposure.</p><fig id="gh270081-fig-0003" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The population exposure (in %) to annual mean surface concentrations of PM<sub>2.5</sub> (top left), NO<sub>2</sub> (top right), and SMPI (bottom left) over India from 2005 to 2019 (years are represented by colors).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="jats-graphic-5" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g005.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/cf5fcc115365/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g005.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1038?><?original-width 1064?><?scaled-height 692?><?scaled-width 709?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g005.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/30aa6efd4c7b/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g005.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>We have analyzed the PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub> and SMPI changes across three distinct periods (2005–2009, 2010–2014, and 2015–2019; Figures S7 and S8 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). The Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref> consistently reveals an increase in the exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI in all states and UTs from 2010 to 2014 compared to 2005–2009. Maximum increase (10–40 (Unitless)) occurred in states like Delhi, Haryana, Punjab, Uttar Pradesh, and Chhattisgarh. The changes in states such as Kerala, Arunachal Pradesh, Puducherry, Daman and Diu during 2010–2014 are minimal (&lt;2). However, from 2015 to 2019, a notable decline in exposure to these pollutants is observed relative to the 2010–2014. States in the IGP, like Delhi, Punjab, Bihar, and Haryana, exhibit the most significant reductions. The maximum reduction in SMPI values (11–45.5) during 2015–2019 is obtained in states such as Delhi, Haryana, Punjab, Uttar Pradesh, and Chandigarh. Analyzing the changes in PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> in all states and UTs during these periods, we can conclude that the reduction in both PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposure resulted in this. In Delhi, the reduction in PM<sub>2.5</sub> (−38.5 μg/m<sup>3</sup>) and NO<sub>2</sub> (−10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>) resulted in lower SMPI values, while in Chandigarh, the reduction in SMPI values (−11) is mainly contributed by the reduction in NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations (−6.7 μg/m<sup>3</sup>). The results suggest that more changes have occurred in states and UTs in the IGP region and Eastern India (e.g., Delhi, Haryana, Punjab, Uttar Pradesh and Chandigarh) compared to other subregions.</p><fig id="gh270081-fig-0004" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The changes in 5‐year average PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI exposure in Indian states and union territories (UTs) from 2010 to 2014 to 2015–2019 (left panel) and from 2005 to 2009 to 2010–2014 (right panel). The PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposure are in μg/m<sup>3</sup>, whereas SMPI exposure is unitless. The negative sign in the left panel indicates that the PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub> and SMPI exposure has reduced during 2015–2019 compared to 2010–2014.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="jats-graphic-7" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g002.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/6cb4cdc4f630/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g002.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 894?><?original-width 1064?><?scaled-height 596?><?scaled-width 709?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g002.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/56c7856cc03d/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g002.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0150" disp-level="2"><label>3.2.</label><title>Urban‐Rural Variability of SMPI Exposure</title><p>The distribution of India's population in urban (upper panel) and rural (lower panel) areas during different periods (2005–2009, 2010–2014, and 2015–2019) in relation to ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations, and SMPI estimates is shown in Figure S9 of Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>. The entire population in the country is exposed to PM<sub>2.5</sub> levels higher than WHO air quality guidelines (5 μg/m<sup>3</sup>). The figure shows that approximately 13%–17% of the rural population is exposed to relatively low ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations (10–30 μg/m<sup>3</sup>). In contrast, a smaller proportion, ∼10% of the rural population is exposed to very high levels of ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> (90–110 μg/m<sup>3</sup>). However, most of the rural population is exposed to a range of 30–90 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. In contrast, analyzing PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure in urban areas reveals a different pattern. The maximum peak occurs within the 30–40 μg/m<sup>3</sup> range, followed by another peak between 100 and 110 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. The distribution of population with respect to ambient NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations shows that above 50% of the population (except urban population during 2010–2014) is exposed to a range of 0–2.5 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. The population exposed to higher values (3–6 μg/m<sup>3</sup>) is minimal (&lt;20%) and more prevalent in urban areas during 2010–2014 (∼30%). The distribution of SMPI shows two distinct peaks in SMPI values of 5–10 and 20–30 in both rural and urban regions. The analysis reveals that SMPI exposure peaked during the 2010–2014 period compared to the adjacent pentads (2005–2009 and 2015–2019). The population distribution with respect to SMPI values shows a similar pattern of population in relation to PM<sub>2.5</sub> values.</p><p>Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref> illustrates the changes in 5‐year average exposure to SMPI in the urban and rural areas of all states and union territories (UTs) in India from 2010 to 2014 to 2015–2019 (left panel) and from 2005 to 2009 to 2010–2014 (right panel). We have analyzed the changes in SMPI in the urban and rural areas of all states and UTs in India across three distinct periods (2005–2009, 2010–2014, and 2015–2019; Figures S10 and S11 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). The spatial distribution of 5‐year mean state‐wise SMPI values for different periods (Figure S10 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>) shows that for most states, SMPI values in urban and rural areas are generally comparable. The figures show increased exposure to SMPI in the urban and rural areas of all states and UTs from 2010 to 2014 compared to 2005–2009. The urban regions of states and UTs in the IGP regions show more changes compared to rural areas. The urban areas in states like Delhi, Haryana, Punjab, Uttar Pradesh, West Bengal, and Chhattisgarh show maximum increase (SMPI values ranging from 4 to 22). While the rural areas in states and UTs like Andaman and Nicobar, Arunachal Pradesh, Daman and Diu, Kerala, Puducherry, Nagaland, Karnataka and Tamil Nadu show an increase in SMPI values (ranging from 3 to 12) compared to urban areas in these states. Due to India's regional scale air pollution problem (Dey et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Karambelas et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Ravishankara et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0041" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>), the changes in SMPI exposure values in urban and rural areas of different states and UTs are comparable. Furthermore, from 2015 to 2019, a notable decline in SMPI exposure (values ranging from 6 to 27) can be observed in the urban areas of states like Delhi, Haryana, Chhattisgarh, and Punjab compared to the 2010–2014 period. Similarly, the reduction of SMPI exposure (4–12.5) in the rural areas was observed in states and UTs like Andaman and Nicobar, Karnataka, Puducherry, Arunachal Pradesh, Nagaland, and Kerala. In general, while urban areas, particularly those within the IGP region, experienced more pronounced changes in pollutant levels, rural areas in states like Kerala, Karnataka, Puducherry, and Nagaland also showed notable changes.</p><fig id="gh270081-fig-0005" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The changes in 5‐year average SMPI exposure in urban and rural regions of Indian states and union territories (UTs) from 2010 to 2014 to 2015–2019 (left panel) and from 2005 to 2009 to 2010–2014 (right panel). The negative sign in the left panel indicates that the SMPI exposure has reduced during 2015–2019 compared to 2010–2014.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="jats-graphic-9" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g006.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/1b229dc04265/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g006.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 894?><?original-width 1064?><?scaled-height 596?><?scaled-width 709?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g006.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/f450b5cdb027/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g006.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0160" disp-level="2"><label>3.3.</label><title>Health Impact Assessment Using SMPI</title><p>In this study, we also assessed the association between SMPI and the odds of COPD among Indian population (see Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Among overall population, we estimated larger association (per percentile increase in exposure) between PM<sub>2.5</sub> and the odds of COPD prevalence (odds ratio of 1.093, 95% uncertainty intervals: 1.067–1.119) as compared to the NO<sub>2</sub>‐COPD association (1.022, 1.014–1.03). Moreover, the formulated SMPI estimate showed strong association with the respiratory health outcome (1.05, 1.025–1.075). We estimated consistent trends of increase in association between SMPI and the COPD prevalence as the air pollution exposure elevated for both the pollutants (Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, left column). The increase in SMPI‐COPD association was higher from PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure as compared to that from NO<sub>2</sub>. For instance, the association between SMPI and COPD was 1.015 (1.005–1.025), 1.056 (1.036–1.076), 1.12 (1.104–1.136), and 1.167 (1.147–1.187), respectively, with the increase in PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure ranges of &lt;25th, 25–50th, 50–75th, and &gt;75th percentiles, adjusting for NO<sub>2</sub>. Similarly, with the increase in NO<sub>2</sub> exposure ranges, the effect of SMPI increased (1.032 (1.024–1.04), 1.041 (1.033–1.049), 1.061 (1.045–1.077), and 1.094 (1.078–1.11)). More importantly, the net association between SMPI and COPD steeply increased as the exposure ranges increased for both the pollutants, relative to PM<sub>2.5</sub> or NO<sub>2</sub> separately. For instance, the association between SMPI and the odds of COPD increased as 1.03 (1.018–1.042), 1.073 (1.053–1.093), 1.131 (1.111–1.151), and 1.184 (1.156–1.212) with the increase in both PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposure ranges. The health effect assessment conducted in this study highlights that the effect of SMPI on the respiratory health outcome is intermediate when compared to the effect from each pollutant, respectively. This signifies that the effect may elevate by manifold among the populace living in higher PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> levels for COPD and other respiratory diseases. Conversely, India could prevent substantial health burden across the subregions if both pollutants are mitigated simultaneously, prioritizing their spatiotemporal distributions, source‐types, population density, or microenvironments.</p><fig id="gh270081-fig-0006" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The association between SMPI exposures with the odds of COPD (left column) and its effect modification assessment for SMPI across the gender, age, wealth, case, cooking fuel types, and the resident types (right column). The circles denote the mean estimate of the association, and the whiskers depict the 95% uncertainty intervals (UIs). The term “pct” in the left panel is the abbreviation of “percentile.” We considered females, 25–35 years, rich, general, clean fuel users, and rural regions as reference while estimating the effect of SMPI across their demographic counterparts.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="jats-graphic-11" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g003.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/d585555c146e/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g003.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1277?><?original-width 1064?><?scaled-height 851?><?scaled-width 709?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g003.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/ae9ac4698057/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g003.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>The effect modification assessment (see Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref> right column) conducted in this study show strong association between SMPI and COPD among males (1.04, 1.028–1.052), solid‐fuel users (1.062, 1.049–1.075), and urban residents (1.056, 1.038–1.074). The association between SMPI and the odds of COPD increased consistently among older age groups (1.075 (1.062–1.088) in 35–45 years and 1.135 (1.112–1.158) in over 45 years). Moreover, we estimated larger SMPI‐COPD association among middle class (1.089, 1.076–1.102) and SC + ST subgroups (1.058, 1.05–1.066) as compared to poor (1.047, 1.035–1.059) and OBC (1.034, 1.013–1.055) sub‐population.</p><p>Table S2 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> shows the socio‐demographic characteristics of the survey. The wealthier subgroup was predominant in the urban regions, while the deprived ones (middle class and poor) in the rural areas. The general, OBC, and wealthier subgroups had adequate education and were professional workers; while the indigent sub‐populations had lower or inadequate education and were associated with farming or household activities. The prevalence of smoking and alcohol‐consumption were higher among males, poor, general, and OBC as compared to their demographic counterparts. The wealthier subgroups and general were associated with higher prevalence of unhealthy diet. The prevalence of COPD was higher among females, middle class, OBC, and older age groups as compared to their demographic counterparts. Among the overall population, mean (±CV: coefficient of variation, that is, the ratio of standard deviation to mean) SMPI estimate was 14.93 ± 0.638. The subgroups, male (15.14 ± 0.636), middle class (16.37 ± 0.62), poor (16.15 ± 0.491), general (16.26 ± 0.684), and OBC (14.72 ± 0.566) suffered from higher SMPI exposure as compared to their demographic counterparts.</p><p>We also estimated the health benefits attributable to meeting clean‐air targets (see Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). During NFHS‐5 (2019‐21), COPD prevalence was higher (&gt;1.2%) across the eastern, north‐eastern, and southern peninsular subregions. Whereas the moderate level of prevalence (0.6%–1.2%) was estimated over the western, central, and IGP regions (Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7b</xref> shows that the subregions over the central and northern regions would obtain larger health benefits as compared to other parts of India, if the states reduce their PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> levels to meet their first clean‐air target. If the states keep on mitigating their air pollution levels to meet the second clean‐air target and eventually meet the WHO's AQG of 5 μg/m<sup>3</sup> and 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>, respectively, then most of the states could alleviate the COPD prevalence by a substantial amount (&gt;40%) in the foreseeable future (see Figures <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7c</xref> and <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7d</xref>). We estimated that northern and central states would obtain larger health benefits as compared to the states over southern peninsular region. We noted that the high COPD prevalence for Kerala in the Figure <xref rid="gh270081-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7d</xref> cannot be mis‐interpreted as no change in COPD prevalence even if this state meets its clean‐air targets for the two pollutants. Table S3 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> shows that the COPD prevalence would reduce from 4.17% during NFHS‐5 to 2.97%, 1.8%, and 1.49%, respectively, if the three clean‐air targets be met. Similarly, we estimated consistent reduction in COPD prevalence for Andhra Pradesh (2.62%–1.96%, 1.33%, and 0.45%), Meghalaya (2.65%–2%, 1.37%, and 0.38%), and Manipur (1.51%–1.14%, 0.78%, and 0.27%).</p><fig id="gh270081-fig-0007" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The prevalence of COPD across the states during NFHS‐5 (a). The reduced COPD prevalence across the states if the three clean‐air targets are met for the foreseeable future (b–d). The color codes (blue to red) denote the increasing ranges of COPD prevalence. Table S3 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> documents the COPD prevalence estimates and the changes in SMPI across the states.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="jats-graphic-13" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g004.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/ed08ce880b5d/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g004.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1179?><?original-width 1064?><?scaled-height 786?><?scaled-width 709?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g004.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/7a7a/12710085/119c92a09cab/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-g004.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0170" disp-level="1"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion and Conclusion</title><p>In this study, we used high‐resolution satellite‐based PM<sub>2.5</sub> from van Donkelaar et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) and NO<sub>2</sub> from Cooper et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>) to calculate SMPI exposure and associated health effects (COPD) over India. Our analysis of the SMPI exposure for each state, district, and urban‐rural area in India during this period has identified air pollution hotspots in various states and districts in Indo‐Gangetic Plain (IGP) and eastern India. The analysis of SMPI exposure for distinct periods reveals an increase in exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SMPI in all states and UTs from 2010 to 2014 compared to the 2005–2009 period. The states and UTs in the IGP region showed large exposure changes. However, from 2015 to 2019, a notable decline in exposure to these pollutants was observed relative to the 2010–2014 period. The reduction in SMPI over recent years could be primarily attributed to a decrease in the ambient pollutant concentrations. The ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure has reduced over the national clean air program (NCAP)‐era (post 2017) due to stricter implementation of air pollution mitigation policies, interventions, and action plans (Katoch et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). On the other hand, reduction in NO<sub>2</sub> could be attributed to more robust adoption of electric vehicles (EVs), stricter monitoring of old vehicles and their renewal process, and accelerated usage of compressed natural gas (CNG) across the metropolitan cities and its peripheral subregions (Balakrishnan et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Furthermore, the analysis of SMPI exposure in rural and urban areas for each state indicates that air pollution in India is not solely an urban problem. The SMPI provides better insights to pollution hotspots by the combined effect of pollution from PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> rather than a single pollutant. Note that the calculation of SMPI uses both the pollutants (PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub>) scaled by pollutant concentration deviation from WHO guidelines. Moreover, the satellite data used to calculate the SMPI offers high spatial and temporal coverage, which is a significant advantage over data from ground‐based monitoring systems. Our findings therefore demonstrate that the SMPI is a valuable tool for assessing air pollution levels and identifying areas needing air quality improvement.</p><p>Furthermore, we demonstrated the multi‐pollutant index approach to assess the adverse health impact of air pollution in India using the SMPI data set. Note that the development of health‐based metrics is emerging from the developed countries and showing potentials for epidemiological and toxicological research (Oakes et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0037" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The results from our health effect assessment are comparable with a few contemporary studies in other countries. A recent cohort study in China revealed a higher impact of PM<sub>2.5</sub> on health outcomes than NO<sub>2</sub>, while the effect was reduced in a multi‐pollutant model (Ji et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Yang et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0054" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>) reported a larger effect from PM<sub>2.5</sub> than from NO<sub>2</sub> over China in both single and multi‐pollutant models, where multiple health outcomes are considered. Another cohort‐based study has obtained mixed effects of these pollutants across the health outcomes and sub‐populations (Y. Wei et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0052" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). They also found that the combined effect from PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> was higher among males, older age groups, deprived sub‐population, and in urban regions.</p><p>Finally, we assessed the disparity in association between SMPI and COPD across the population subgroups in India. The heterogeneity in the association between SMPI and COPD across different PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposure ranges could be due to spatial heterogeneity in population and the exposure distribution of the pollutants. Ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> has larger spatial heterogeneity and more variation in its chemical compositions across the states (Chaudhary et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Katoch et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>; N. Singh et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0044" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). These may influence more varying results in the net SMPI‐COPD association. However, the variation in SMPI‐COPD association attributable to changes in NO<sub>2</sub> exposure is less prominent as compared to changes in co‐pollutant. Note that ambient NO<sub>2</sub> is a short‐lived criteria pollutant and possesses lower spatial heterogeneity (N. Singh et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Therefore, NO<sub>2</sub> may have lesser influence on the net association between SMPI and COPD. The presence of a significant interaction among these two pollutants dictates a complex relationship, when their exposure and associated health effects are considered among the populace. The biological mechanism of the effect of PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure and leading to adverse respiratory health outcomes is well established (Feng et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Mack et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0032" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; T. Wei &amp; Tang, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0051" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Therefore, the disparity in health effects attributable to PM<sub>2.5</sub> across the population subgroups in this study could be explained comprehensively. However, the exposure to ambient NO<sub>2</sub> possesses larger uncertainty and substantial knowledge gaps (Mainka &amp; Żak, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0033" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Sun et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0048" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Note that we estimated a larger effect from participants' age, gender, caste, resident type, status of availing health insurance, and information of having an unhealthy diet on the cause‐effect relationship (Figure S12 in Supporting Information <xref rid="gh270081-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). These socioeconomic and demographic factors influence subgroups' variability in mobility, source‐type and location, microenvironment, socioeconomic status, complex etiology of COPD, and outdoor‐to‐indoor concentration relationships of the pollutants (Venkataraman et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0050" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). For instance, men are more likely to spend more times outdoors and be exposed to outdoor occupational hazards, and more prevalent to tobacco smoking and unhealthy dietary intakes as compared to females (Chaudhary et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). These covariates might play significant roles in the inter‐relationships between NO<sub>2</sub> and COPD association, and larger effects among males. The variation in the distribution of these covariates across the subregions and across diverse demography may have interdependent relationships with the health outcomes that modified the net association.</p><p>Most existing studies from India have estimated the single pollutant effect on various health outcomes (Chaudhary et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>; Nori‐Sarma et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0036" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Rajak &amp; Chattopadhyay, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0040" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Spears et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0047" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Whereas this study shows that co‐exposure assessment could be an effective tool for robust air quality monitoring, managing strategies, and future comprehensive epidemiological studies. This study also shows that SMPI or similar multi‐pollutant indices may be more suitable for assessing air quality and related health impacts and identifying hotspots that require prioritized pollution mitigation. We emphasize on having mitigation policies and interventions targeting the vulnerable subgroups across the states, especially more attention is required for the southern peninsular region. Moreover, stricter air pollution mitigation mandates required to be implemented prioritizing males, middle class, OBC and tribal subgroups, and the older sub‐population. To reduce both the exposure burden and the associated risk of COPD among these subgroups, targeted, equity‐focused policies and interventions are essential, particularly in states and subregions where the demographic density of these populations is higher. The OBC and SC + ST communities are among the economically disadvantaged subgroups in India and require specific interventions, including access to cleaner fuels and improved healthcare services (Apte et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Additionally, air pollution mitigation plans must be strengthened and tailored for regions with high densities of the middle‐class population, who may also face considerable exposure risks. Currently, India's environmental, health, and social policies adopt a universal approach, treating all population subgroups equally. Frameworks such as the NCAP have emphasized city‐level emission reduction targets but lack explicit provisions for addressing intra‐urban disparities or subgroup‐level inequities (Ganguly et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). We therefore recommend incorporating exposure equity indicators such as subgroup‐specific SMPI estimates into the performance assessments, policy prioritization, and funding allocation mechanisms of NCAP and state‐level action plans. Moreover, health outcomes are not yet integrated into the NCAP framework (Katoch et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). We suggest that the effectiveness of clean‐air interventions be assessed not only by pollution reduction but also by their anticipated health benefits. To achieve environmental and health equity and align with the Sustainable Development Goals, future environmental policies in India must directly address disparities in PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> exposure and their health consequences across different states and demographic subgroups.</p><p>Our study possesses a few limitations which warrant discussion. The demographic characteristics and health information (COPD prevalence) captured in the last census were used as the baseline for the sampling framework in recent NFHSs. We used the cluster‐specific sample weight in our analysis to make the assessment best representative of the changing demography of the population. However, the questionnaire‐response of COPD prevalence (Yes or No) was considered as the health outcome information in our assessment. Due to the lack of accurate biomarker measurement of COPD among the populace, the estimated prevalence could be under‐ or overestimated. The future NFHS sampling strategy based on the demographic distributions being captured in the ongoing census of India will further reduce uncertainty in demographic characteristics and COPD prevalence estimates. We found a reduction in the average ambient NO<sub>2</sub> exposure in 2015 across India, which also led to a slight reduction in SMPI exposure and effected on the subsequent health effect assessment as well. Although a detailed investigation of the root cause of this decline was beyond the scope of our analysis, existing literature provided supporting evidence. The observed decline in population exposure to elevated NO<sub>2</sub> levels in India around 2015 likely reflected a combination of early emission control efforts (vehicular and industrial), infrastructure and energy transitions, and favorable meteorological conditions. Singh et al. (<xref rid="gh270081-bib-0045" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>) reported that the reduction in NO<sub>2</sub> over India may have been linked to several policies implemented after 2009, including measures by the National Green Tribunal (NGT) and the rollout of Bharat Stage (BS)‐III and BS‐IV vehicular emission standards in 2005 and 2010 for major metro cities, and in 2010 and 2017 nationwide.</p><p>Finally, future research should incorporate more satellite‐derived criteria air pollutants (sulfur dioxide, ozone) and hazardous air pollutants (formaldehyde) in formulating the SMPI index to estimate the effect from the combination of these pollutants. The component toxicity should also be incorporated in the formulation of air quality metrics to lead such epidemiological assessments more comprehensive and supportive for robust policies and action plans. Future studies of multi‐pollutant models along with the effect modification from other environmental risk factors are required to establish the causal mechanisms among air pollutant mixtures and public health.</p></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0190" disp-level="1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>One of the co‐authors is a member of the editorial board of GeoHealth. The other authors declare no conflicts of interest relevant to this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec19" disp-level="1"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material id="gh270081-sup-0001" position="float"><caption><p>Supporting Information S1</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-s001.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 7a7a/12710085/2e48a3c54d90/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-s001.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 5864117?></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0180" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>AD acknowledges support from the Prime Minister's Research Fellowship (PMRF), Ministry of Education, Government of India. SP and SD acknowledge Clean Air Fund grant to IIT Delhi. DS acknowledges financial support from the Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), Ministry of Education, Govt. of India. RVM acknowledges support from NASA Grant 80NSSC21K0508 and internal funds at Washington University. We thank computational resources provided by the high‐performance computing cluster at IIT Delhi and computational resources obtained through the IIT Delhi New Faculty Seed grant. We thank Matthew Cooper, Environment and Climate Change Canada for the NO<sub>2</sub> data.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><p>


Ardra, D.
, 
Philip, S.
, 
Sarkar, D.
, 
Ghosh, S.
, 
van Donkelaar, A.
, 
Martin, R. V.
, &amp; 
Dey, S.
 (2025). Assessment of ambient multipollutant exposure and health impacts over India using the novel satellite‐based multi‐pollutant index. GeoHealth, 9, e2025GH001409. 10.1029/2025GH001409

</p></sec><sec id="_ci93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="contrib-info" disp-level="1"><title>Contributor Information</title><p>D Ardra, Email: ardra8034@gmail.com.</p><p>Sajeev Philip, Email: philipsajeev@iitd.ac.in.</p></sec><sec id="gh270081-sec-0210" disp-level="1"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The satellite‐derived annual mean surface PM<sub>2.5</sub> data (V5.GL.03) used in this study (van Donkelaar et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) and the high‐resolution surface NO<sub>2</sub> data (Cooper et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>) are publicly available from Washington University Atmospheric composition analysis Group website. The population data is provided by the WorldPop Research program (WorldPop &amp; Bondarenko, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0053" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The human settlement data set developed by the Joint Research Centre (JRC) of the European Commission and the Directorate‐General for Regional and Urban Policy is publicly available as part of the GHS‐SMOD R2022 A data package (Schiavina, Melchiorri, &amp; Pesaresi, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Schiavina, Melchiorri, Pesaresi, Politis, et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="gh270081-bibl-0001" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="gh270081-bibl-0001_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="gh270081-bib-0001"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0001"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Achakulwisut, P.
, 
Brauer, M.
, 
Hystad, P.
, &amp; 
Anenberg, S. C.
 (2019). Global, national, and urban burdens of paediatric asthma incidence attributable to ambient NO<sub>2</sub> pollution: Estimates from global datasets. The Lancet Planetary Health, 3(4), e166–e178. 10.1016/S2542-5196(19)30046-4

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2542-5196(19)30046-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30981709"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=The Lancet Planetary Health&amp;title=Global, national, and urban burdens of paediatric asthma incidence attributable to ambient NO2 pollution: Estimates from global datasets&amp;author=P. Achakulwisut&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;author=P. Hystad&amp;author=S. C. Anenberg&amp;volume=3&amp;issue=4&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=e166-e178&amp;pmid=30981709&amp;doi=10.1016/S2542-5196(19)30046-4&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0002"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0002"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Anenberg, S. C.
, 
Mohegh, A.
, 
Goldberg, D. L.
, 
Kerr, G. H.
, 
Brauer, M.
, 
Burkart, K.
, et al. (2022). Long‐term trends in urban NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations and associated paediatric asthma incidence: Estimates from global datasets. The Lancet Planetary Health, 6(1), e49–e58. 10.1016/S2542-5196(21)00255-2

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2542-5196(21)00255-2"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34998460"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=The Lancet Planetary Health&amp;title=Long‐term trends in urban NO2 concentrations and associated paediatric asthma incidence: Estimates from global datasets&amp;author=S. C. Anenberg&amp;author=A. Mohegh&amp;author=D. L. Goldberg&amp;author=G. H. Kerr&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;volume=6&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=e49-e58&amp;pmid=34998460&amp;doi=10.1016/S2542-5196(21)00255-2&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0003"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0003"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Apte, J. S.
, 
Messier, K. P.
, 
Gani, S.
, 
Brauer, M.
, 
Kirchstetter, T. W.
, 
Lunden, M. M.
, et al. (2017). High‐resolution air pollution mapping with Google street view cars: Exploiting big data. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 51(12), 6999–7008. 10.1021/acs.est.7b00891

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1021/acs.est.7b00891"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28578585"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Science &amp; Technology&amp;title=High‐resolution air pollution mapping with Google street view cars: Exploiting big data&amp;author=J. S. Apte&amp;author=K. P. Messier&amp;author=S. Gani&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;author=T. W. Kirchstetter&amp;volume=51&amp;issue=12&amp;publication_year=2017&amp;pages=6999-7008&amp;pmid=28578585&amp;doi=10.1021/acs.est.7b00891&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0004"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0004"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Balakrishnan, K.
, 
Dey, S.
, 
Gupta, T.
, 
Dhaliwal, R. S.
, 
Brauer, M.
, 
Cohen, A. J.
, et al. (2019). The impact of air pollution on deaths, disease burden, and life expectancy across the states of India: The Global Burden of Disease Study 2017. The Lancet Planetary Health, 3(1), e26–e39. 10.1016/S2542-5196(18)30261-4

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2542-5196(18)30261-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6358127"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30528905"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=The Lancet Planetary Health&amp;title=The impact of air pollution on deaths, disease burden, and life expectancy across the states of India: The Global Burden of Disease Study 2017&amp;author=K. Balakrishnan&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=T. Gupta&amp;author=R. S. Dhaliwal&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;volume=3&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=e26-e39&amp;pmid=30528905&amp;doi=10.1016/S2542-5196(18)30261-4&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0005"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0005"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Billionnet, C.
, 
Sherrill, D.
, &amp; 
Annesi‐Maesano, I.
 (2012). Estimating the health effects of exposure to multi‐pollutant mixture. Annals of Epidemiology, 22(2), 126–141. 10.1016/j.annepidem.2011.11.004

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.annepidem.2011.11.004"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22226033"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Annals of Epidemiology&amp;title=Estimating the health effects of exposure to multi‐pollutant mixture&amp;author=C. Billionnet&amp;author=D. Sherrill&amp;author=I. Annesi‐Maesano&amp;volume=22&amp;issue=2&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=126-141&amp;pmid=22226033&amp;doi=10.1016/j.annepidem.2011.11.004&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0006"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0006"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Biswal, A.
, 
Katoch, V.
, 
Singh, T.
, 
Ravindra, K.
, 
Singh, V.
, &amp; 
Mor, S.
 (2025). Changing tropospheric NO<sub>2</sub> dynamics across Indian air pollution hotspots. Environmental Pollution, 373, 126160. 10.1016/j.envpol.2025.126160

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2025.126160"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40157486"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Pollution&amp;title=Changing tropospheric NO2 dynamics across Indian air pollution hotspots&amp;author=A. Biswal&amp;author=V. Katoch&amp;author=T. Singh&amp;author=K. Ravindra&amp;author=V. Singh&amp;volume=373&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=126160&amp;pmid=40157486&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envpol.2025.126160&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0007"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0007"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Brauer, M.
, 
Guttikunda, S. K.
, 
K a, N.
, 
Dey, S.
, 
Tripathi, S. N.
, 
Weagle, C.
, &amp; 
Martin, R. V.
 (2019). Examination of monitoring approaches for ambient air pollution: A case study for India. Atmospheric Environment, 216, 116940. 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2019.116940
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.atmosenv.2019.116940"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Environment&amp;title=Examination of monitoring approaches for ambient air pollution: A case study for India&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;author=S. K. Guttikunda&amp;author=N. K a&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=S. N. Tripathi&amp;volume=216&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=116940&amp;doi=10.1016/j.atmosenv.2019.116940&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0008"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0008"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Chaudhary, E.
, 
Dey, S.
, 
Ghosh, S.
, 
Sharma, S.
, 
Singh, N.
, 
Agarwal, S.
, et al. (2022). Reducing anemia burden in Indian women of reproductive age with clean‐air targets. In AGU fall meeting abstracts (Vol. 2022, p. 45).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=AGU fall meeting abstracts&amp;author=E. Chaudhary&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=S. Ghosh&amp;author=S. Sharma&amp;author=N. Singh&amp;volume=2022&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=45&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0009"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0009"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Chaudhary, E.
, 
George, F.
, 
Saji, A.
, 
Dey, S.
, 
Ghosh, S.
, 
Thomas, T.
, et al. (2023). Cumulative effect of PM<sub>2.5</sub> components is larger than the effect of PM<sub>2.5</sub> mass on child health in India. Nature Communications, 14(1), 6955. 10.1038/s41467-023-42709-1
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-023-42709-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10618175"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37907499"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nature Communications&amp;title=Cumulative effect of PM2.5 components is larger than the effect of PM2.5 mass on child health in India&amp;author=E. Chaudhary&amp;author=F. George&amp;author=A. Saji&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=S. Ghosh&amp;volume=14&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=6955&amp;pmid=37907499&amp;doi=10.1038/s41467-023-42709-1&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0010"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0010"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Chen, X.
, 
Qi, L.
, 
Li, S.
, &amp; 
Duan, X.
 (2024). Long‐term NO<sub>2</sub> exposure and mortality: A comprehensive meta‐analysis. Environmental Pollution, 341, 122971. 10.1016/j.envpol.2023.122971

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2023.122971"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37984474"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Pollution&amp;title=Long‐term NO2 exposure and mortality: A comprehensive meta‐analysis&amp;author=X. Chen&amp;author=L. Qi&amp;author=S. Li&amp;author=X. Duan&amp;volume=341&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=122971&amp;pmid=37984474&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envpol.2023.122971&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0011"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0011"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Chowdhury, S.
, 
Dey, S.
, 
Guttikunda, S.
, 
Pillarisetti, A.
, 
Smith, K. R.
, &amp; 
Di Girolamo, L.
 (2019). Indian annual ambient air quality standard is achievable by completely mitigating emissions from household sources. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 116(22), 10711–10716. 10.1073/pnas.1900888116
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1900888116"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6561163"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30988190"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&amp;title=Indian annual ambient air quality standard is achievable by completely mitigating emissions from household sources&amp;author=S. Chowdhury&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=S. Guttikunda&amp;author=A. Pillarisetti&amp;author=K. R. Smith&amp;volume=116&amp;issue=22&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=10711-10716&amp;pmid=30988190&amp;doi=10.1073/pnas.1900888116&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0012"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0012"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Coffman, E.
, 
Rappold, A. G.
, 
Nethery, R. C.
, 
Anderton, J.
, 
Amend, M.
, 
Jackson, M. A.
, et al. (2024). Quantifying multipollutant health impacts using the environmental benefits mapping and analysis program–community edition (BenMAP‐CE): A case study in Atlanta, Georgia. Environmental Health Perspectives, 132(3), 037003. 10.1289/EHP12969

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1289/EHP12969"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10916644"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38445893"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Health Perspectives&amp;title=Quantifying multipollutant health impacts using the environmental benefits mapping and analysis program–community edition (BenMAP‐CE): A case study in Atlanta, Georgia&amp;author=E. Coffman&amp;author=A. G. Rappold&amp;author=R. C. Nethery&amp;author=J. Anderton&amp;author=M. Amend&amp;volume=132&amp;issue=3&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=037003&amp;pmid=38445893&amp;doi=10.1289/EHP12969&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0013"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0013"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Cooper, M. J.
, 
Martin, R. V.
, 
Hammer, M. S.
, 
Levelt, P. F.
, 
Veefkind, P.
, 
Lamsal, L. N.
, et al. (2022a). Global fine‐scale changes in ambient NO<sub>2</sub> during COVID‐19 lockdowns. Nature, 601(7893), 380–387. 10.1038/s41586-021-04229-0

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-021-04229-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8770130"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35046607"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nature&amp;title=Global fine‐scale changes in ambient NO2 during COVID‐19 lockdowns&amp;author=M. J. Cooper&amp;author=R. V. Martin&amp;author=M. S. Hammer&amp;author=P. F. Levelt&amp;author=P. Veefkind&amp;volume=601&amp;issue=7893&amp;publication_year=2022a&amp;pages=380-387&amp;pmid=35046607&amp;doi=10.1038/s41586-021-04229-0&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0014"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0014"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Cooper, M. J.
, 
Martin, R. V.
, 
Hammer, M. S.
, 
Levelt, P. F.
, 
Veefkind, P.
, 
Lamsal, L. N.
, et al. (2022b). Satellite‐derived ground‐level NO2 concentrations, 2005–2019 [Dataset]. Zenodo. 10.5281/zenodo.5424752
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5281/zenodo.5424752"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0015"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0015"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Cooper, M. J.
, 
Martin, R. V.
, 
van Donkelaar, A.
, 
Lamsal, L.
, 
Brauer, M.
, &amp; 
Brook, J. R.
 (2012). A satellite‐based multi‐pollutant index of global air quality. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 46(16), 8523–8524. 10.1021/es302672p

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1021/es302672p"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22853810"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Science &amp; Technology&amp;title=A satellite‐based multi‐pollutant index of global air quality&amp;author=M. J. Cooper&amp;author=R. V. Martin&amp;author=A. van Donkelaar&amp;author=L. Lamsal&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;volume=46&amp;issue=16&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=8523-8524&amp;pmid=22853810&amp;doi=10.1021/es302672p&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0016"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0016"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
CPCB
. (2014). National Air Quality Index. Retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cpcb.nic.in/displaypdf.php?id=bmF0aW9uYWwtYWlyLXF1YWxpdHktaW5kZXgvRklOQUwtUkVQT1JUX0FRSV8ucGRm" ext-link-type="uri">https://cpcb.nic.in/displaypdf.php?id=bmF0aW9uYWwtYWlyLXF1YWxpdHktaW5kZXgvRklOQUwtUkVQT1JUX0FRSV8ucGRm</ext-link>
</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0017"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0017"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Crouse, D. L.
, 
Peters, P. A.
, 
Villeneuve, P. J.
, 
Proux, M.‐O.
, 
Shin, H. H.
, 
Goldberg, M. S.
, et al. (2015). Within‐ and between‐city contrasts in nitrogen dioxide and mortality in 10 Canadian cities; a subset of the Canadian Census Health and Environment Cohort (CanCHEC). Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology, 25(5), 482–489. 10.1038/jes.2014.89

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/jes.2014.89"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4542139"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25605445"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Journal of Exposure Science and Environmental Epidemiology&amp;title=Within‐ and between‐city contrasts in nitrogen dioxide and mortality in 10 Canadian cities; a subset of the Canadian Census Health and Environment Cohort (CanCHEC)&amp;author=D. L. Crouse&amp;author=P. A. Peters&amp;author=P. J. Villeneuve&amp;author=M.‐O. Proux&amp;author=H. H. Shin&amp;volume=25&amp;issue=5&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=482-489&amp;pmid=25605445&amp;doi=10.1038/jes.2014.89&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0018"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0018"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Dey, S.
, 
Purohit, B.
, 
Balyan, P.
, 
Dixit, K.
, 
Bali, K.
, 
Kumar, A.
, et al. (2020). A satellite‐based high‐resolution (1‐km) ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> database for India over two decades (2000–2019): Applications for air quality management. Remote Sensing, 12(23), 3872. Article 23. 10.3390/rs12233872
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/rs12233872"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Remote Sensing&amp;title=A satellite‐based high‐resolution (1‐km) ambient PM2.5 database for India over two decades (2000–2019): Applications for air quality management&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=B. Purohit&amp;author=P. Balyan&amp;author=K. Dixit&amp;author=K. Bali&amp;volume=12&amp;issue=23&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=3872&amp;doi=10.3390/rs12233872&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0020"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0020"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Feng, S.
, 
Gao, D.
, 
Liao, F.
, 
Zhou, F.
, &amp; 
Wang, X.
 (2016). The health effects of ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and potential mechanisms. Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety, 128, 67–74. 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2016.01.030

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ecoenv.2016.01.030"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26896893"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety&amp;title=The health effects of ambient PM2.5 and potential mechanisms&amp;author=S. Feng&amp;author=D. Gao&amp;author=F. Liao&amp;author=F. Zhou&amp;author=X. Wang&amp;volume=128&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=67-74&amp;pmid=26896893&amp;doi=10.1016/j.ecoenv.2016.01.030&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0021"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0021"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Ganguly, T.
, 
Selvaraj, K. L.
, &amp; 
Guttikunda, S. K.
 (2020). National Clean Air Programme (NCAP) for Indian cities: Review and outlook of clean air action plans. Atmospheric Environment X, 8, 100096. 10.1016/j.aeaoa.2020.100096
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.aeaoa.2020.100096"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Environment X&amp;title=National Clean Air Programme (NCAP) for Indian cities: Review and outlook of clean air action plans&amp;author=T. Ganguly&amp;author=K. L. Selvaraj&amp;author=S. K. Guttikunda&amp;volume=8&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=100096&amp;doi=10.1016/j.aeaoa.2020.100096&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0022"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0022"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Gurjar, B. R.
, 
Butler, T. M.
, 
Lawrence, M. G.
, &amp; 
Lelieveld, J.
 (2008). Evaluation of emissions and air quality in megacities. Atmospheric Environment, 42(7), 1593–1606. 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2007.10.048
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.atmosenv.2007.10.048"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Environment&amp;title=Evaluation of emissions and air quality in megacities&amp;author=B. R. Gurjar&amp;author=T. M. Butler&amp;author=M. G. Lawrence&amp;author=J. Lelieveld&amp;volume=42&amp;issue=7&amp;publication_year=2008&amp;pages=1593-1606&amp;doi=10.1016/j.atmosenv.2007.10.048&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0023"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0023"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Hamra, G. B.
, 
Laden, F.
, 
Cohen, A. J.
, 
Raaschou‐Nielsen, O.
, 
Brauer, M.
, &amp; 
Loomis, D.
 (2015). Lung cancer and exposure to nitrogen dioxide and traffic: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Environmental Health Perspectives, 123(11), 1107–1112. 10.1289/ehp.1408882

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1289/ehp.1408882"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4629738"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25870974"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Health Perspectives&amp;title=Lung cancer and exposure to nitrogen dioxide and traffic: A systematic review and meta‐analysis&amp;author=G. B. Hamra&amp;author=F. Laden&amp;author=A. J. Cohen&amp;author=O. Raaschou‐Nielsen&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;volume=123&amp;issue=11&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=1107-1112&amp;pmid=25870974&amp;doi=10.1289/ehp.1408882&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0024"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0024"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Hu, J.
, 
Ying, Q.
, 
Wang, Y.
, &amp; 
Zhang, H.
 (2015). Characterizing multi‐pollutant air pollution in China: Comparison of three air quality indices. Environment International, 84, 17–25. 10.1016/j.envint.2015.06.014

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envint.2015.06.014"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26197060"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environment International&amp;title=Characterizing multi‐pollutant air pollution in China: Comparison of three air quality indices&amp;author=J. Hu&amp;author=Q. Ying&amp;author=Y. Wang&amp;author=H. Zhang&amp;volume=84&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=17-25&amp;pmid=26197060&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envint.2015.06.014&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0025"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0025"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Huang, W.‐Z.
, 
He, W.‐Y.
, 
Knibbs, L. D.
, 
Jalaludin, B.
, 
Guo, Y.‐M.
, 
Morawska, L.
, et al. (2022). Improved morbidity‐based air quality health index development using Bayesian multi‐pollutant weighted model. Environmental Research, 204, 112397. 10.1016/j.envres.2021.112397

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envres.2021.112397"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34798120"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Research&amp;title=Improved morbidity‐based air quality health index development using Bayesian multi‐pollutant weighted model&amp;author=W.‐Z. Huang&amp;author=W.‐Y. He&amp;author=L. D. Knibbs&amp;author=B. Jalaludin&amp;author=Y.‐M. Guo&amp;volume=204&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=112397&amp;pmid=34798120&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envres.2021.112397&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0026"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0026"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Huangfu, P.
, &amp; 
Atkinson, R.
 (2020). Long‐term exposure to NO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> and all‐cause and respiratory mortality: A systematic review and meta‐analysis. Environment International, 144, 105998. 10.1016/j.envint.2020.105998

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envint.2020.105998"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7549128"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33032072"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environment International&amp;title=Long‐term exposure to NO2 and O3 and all‐cause and respiratory mortality: A systematic review and meta‐analysis&amp;author=P. Huangfu&amp;author=R. Atkinson&amp;volume=144&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=105998&amp;pmid=33032072&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envint.2020.105998&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0027"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0027"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Ji, J. S.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Kan, H.
, 
Zhao, B.
, 
Burkart, K. G.
, &amp; 
Zeng, Y.
 (2022). NO<sub>2</sub> and PM<sub>2.5</sub> air pollution co‐exposure and temperature effect modification on pre‐mature mortality in advanced age: A longitudinal cohort study in China. Environmental Health, 21(1), 97. 10.1186/s12940-022-00901-8

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12940-022-00901-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9559021"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36229834"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Health&amp;title=NO2 and PM2.5 air pollution co‐exposure and temperature effect modification on pre‐mature mortality in advanced age: A longitudinal cohort study in China&amp;author=J. S. Ji&amp;author=L. Liu&amp;author=J. Zhang&amp;author=H. Kan&amp;author=B. Zhao&amp;volume=21&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=97&amp;pmid=36229834&amp;doi=10.1186/s12940-022-00901-8&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0028"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0028"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Joenssen, D. W.
, &amp; 
Bankhofer, U.
 (2012). Hot deck methods for imputing missing data. In Perner P. (Ed.), Machine learning and data mining in pattern recognition (pp. 63–75). Springer. 10.1007/978-3-642-31537-4_6
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/978-3-642-31537-4_6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="title=Machine learning and data mining in pattern recognition&amp;author=D. W. Joenssen&amp;author=U. Bankhofer&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0029"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0029"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Karambelas, A.
, 
Holloway, T.
, 
Kinney, P. L.
, 
Fiore, A. M.
, 
DeFries, R.
, 
Kiesewetter, G.
, &amp; 
Heyes, C.
 (2018). Urban versus rural health impacts attributable to PM<sub>2.5</sub> and O<sub>3</sub> in northern India. Environmental Research Letters, 13(6), 064010. 10.1088/1748-9326/aac24d
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1088/1748-9326/aac24d"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Research Letters&amp;title=Urban versus rural health impacts attributable to PM2.5 and O3 in northern India&amp;author=A. Karambelas&amp;author=T. Holloway&amp;author=P. L. Kinney&amp;author=A. M. Fiore&amp;author=R. DeFries&amp;volume=13&amp;issue=6&amp;publication_year=2018&amp;pages=064010&amp;doi=10.1088/1748-9326/aac24d&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0030"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0030"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Katoch, V.
, 
Kumar, A.
, 
Imam, F.
, 
Sarkar, D.
, 
Knibbs, L. D.
, 
Liu, Y.
, et al. (2023). Addressing biases in ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure and associated health burden estimates by filling satellite AOD retrieval gaps over India. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 57(48), 19190–19201. 10.1021/acs.est.3c03355

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1021/acs.est.3c03355"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37956255"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Science &amp; Technology&amp;title=Addressing biases in ambient PM2.5 exposure and associated health burden estimates by filling satellite AOD retrieval gaps over India&amp;author=V. Katoch&amp;author=A. Kumar&amp;author=F. Imam&amp;author=D. Sarkar&amp;author=L. D. Knibbs&amp;volume=57&amp;issue=48&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=19190-19201&amp;pmid=37956255&amp;doi=10.1021/acs.est.3c03355&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0031"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0031"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Kumar, P.
, &amp; 
Kumar, P.
 (2022). A critical evaluation of air quality index models (1960–2021). Environmental Monitoring and Assessment, 194(5), 324. 10.1007/s10661-022-09896-8

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s10661-022-09896-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35359193"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Monitoring and Assessment&amp;title=A critical evaluation of air quality index models (1960–2021)&amp;author=P. Kumar&amp;author=P. Kumar&amp;volume=194&amp;issue=5&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=324&amp;pmid=35359193&amp;doi=10.1007/s10661-022-09896-8&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0032"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0032"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Mack, S. M.
, 
Madl, A. K.
, &amp; 
Pinkerton, K. E.
 (2019). Respiratory health effects of exposure to ambient particulate matter and bioaerosols. Comprehensive Physiology, 10(1), 1–20. 10.1002/cphy.c180040

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/cphy.c180040"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7553137"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31853953"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Comprehensive Physiology&amp;title=Respiratory health effects of exposure to ambient particulate matter and bioaerosols&amp;author=S. M. Mack&amp;author=A. K. Madl&amp;author=K. E. Pinkerton&amp;volume=10&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=1-20&amp;pmid=31853953&amp;doi=10.1002/cphy.c180040&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0033"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0033"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Mainka, A.
, &amp; 
Żak, M.
 (2022). Synergistic or antagonistic health effects of Long‐ and short‐term exposure to ambient NO<sub>2</sub> and PM<sub>2.5</sub>: A review. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 19(21), 14079. Article 21. 10.3390/ijerph192114079

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijerph192114079"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9657687"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36360958"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health&amp;title=Synergistic or antagonistic health effects of Long‐ and short‐term exposure to ambient NO2 and PM2.5: A review&amp;author=A. Mainka&amp;author=M. Żak&amp;volume=19&amp;issue=21&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=14079&amp;pmid=36360958&amp;doi=10.3390/ijerph192114079&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0034"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0034"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Martin, R. V.
, 
Brauer, M.
, 
van Donkelaar, A.
, 
Shaddick, G.
, 
Narain, U.
, &amp; 
Dey, S.
 (2019). No one knows which city has the highest concentration of fine particulate matter. Atmospheric Environment X, 3, 100040. 10.1016/j.aeaoa.2019.100040
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.aeaoa.2019.100040"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Environment X&amp;title=No one knows which city has the highest concentration of fine particulate matter&amp;author=R. V. Martin&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;author=A. van Donkelaar&amp;author=G. Shaddick&amp;author=U. Narain&amp;volume=3&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=100040&amp;doi=10.1016/j.aeaoa.2019.100040&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0035"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0035"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Murray, C. J. L.
 (2024). Findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. The Lancet, 403(10440), 2259–2262. 10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00769-4
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00769-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38762327"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=The Lancet&amp;title=Findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021&amp;author=C. J. L. Murray&amp;volume=403&amp;issue=10440&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=2259-2262&amp;pmid=38762327&amp;doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00769-4&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0036"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0036"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Nori‐Sarma, A.
, 
Thimmulappa, R.
, 
Venkataraman, G. V.
, 
Warren, J. L.
, 
Berman, J. D.
, 
Whittaker, S. D.
, et al. (2021). NO<sub>2</sub> exposure and lung function decline in a cohort of adults in Mysore, India. Environmental Research Communications, 3(5), 55001. 10.1088/2515-7620/abf2dd
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1088/2515-7620/abf2dd"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Research Communications&amp;title=NO2 exposure and lung function decline in a cohort of adults in Mysore, India&amp;author=A. Nori‐Sarma&amp;author=R. Thimmulappa&amp;author=G. V. Venkataraman&amp;author=J. L. Warren&amp;author=J. D. Berman&amp;volume=3&amp;issue=5&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=55001&amp;doi=10.1088/2515-7620/abf2dd&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0037"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0037"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Oakes, M.
, 
Baxter, L.
, &amp; 
Long, T. C.
 (2014). Evaluating the application of multipollutant exposure metrics in air pollution health studies. Environment International, 69, 90–99. 10.1016/j.envint.2014.03.030

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envint.2014.03.030"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24815342"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environment International&amp;title=Evaluating the application of multipollutant exposure metrics in air pollution health studies&amp;author=M. Oakes&amp;author=L. Baxter&amp;author=T. C. Long&amp;volume=69&amp;publication_year=2014&amp;pages=90-99&amp;pmid=24815342&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envint.2014.03.030&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0038"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0038"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Pandey, A.
, 
Brauer, M.
, 
Cropper, M. L.
, 
Balakrishnan, K.
, 
Mathur, P.
, 
Dey, S.
, et al. (2021). Health and economic impact of air pollution in the states of India: The Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. The Lancet Planetary Health, 5(1), e25–e38. 10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30298-9

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30298-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7805008"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33357500"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=The Lancet Planetary Health&amp;title=Health and economic impact of air pollution in the states of India: The Global Burden of Disease Study 2019&amp;author=A. Pandey&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;author=M. L. Cropper&amp;author=K. Balakrishnan&amp;author=P. Mathur&amp;volume=5&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=e25-e38&amp;pmid=33357500&amp;doi=10.1016/S2542-5196(20)30298-9&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0039"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0039"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Plaia, A.
, 
Di Salvo, F.
, 
Ruggieri, M.
, &amp; 
Agró, G.
 (2013). A multisite‐multipollutant air quality index. Atmospheric Environment, 70, 387–391. 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2013.01.028
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.atmosenv.2013.01.028"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Environment&amp;title=A multisite‐multipollutant air quality index&amp;author=A. Plaia&amp;author=F. Di Salvo&amp;author=M. Ruggieri&amp;author=G. Agró&amp;volume=70&amp;publication_year=2013&amp;pages=387-391&amp;doi=10.1016/j.atmosenv.2013.01.028&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0040"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0040"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Rajak, R.
, &amp; 
Chattopadhyay, A.
 (2020). Short and long term exposure to ambient air pollution and impact on health in India: A systematic review. International Journal of Environmental Health Research, 30(6), 593–617. 10.1080/09603123.2019.1612042

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/09603123.2019.1612042"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31070475"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=International Journal of Environmental Health Research&amp;title=Short and long term exposure to ambient air pollution and impact on health in India: A systematic review&amp;author=R. Rajak&amp;author=A. Chattopadhyay&amp;volume=30&amp;issue=6&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=593-617&amp;pmid=31070475&amp;doi=10.1080/09603123.2019.1612042&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0041"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0041"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Ravishankara, A. R.
, 
David, L. M.
, 
Pierce, J. R.
, &amp; 
Venkataraman, C.
 (2020). Outdoor air pollution in India is not only an urban problem. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 117(46), 28640–28644. 10.1073/pnas.2007236117
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.2007236117"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7682420"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33139542"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&amp;title=Outdoor air pollution in India is not only an urban problem&amp;author=A. R. Ravishankara&amp;author=L. M. David&amp;author=J. R. Pierce&amp;author=C. Venkataraman&amp;volume=117&amp;issue=46&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=28640-28644&amp;pmid=33139542&amp;doi=10.1073/pnas.2007236117&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0042"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0042"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Schiavina, M.
, 
Melchiorri, M.
, &amp; 
Pesaresi, M.
 (2022). GHS‐SMOD R2022A — GHS settlement layers, application of the Degree of Urbanisation methodology (stage I) to GHS‐POP R2022A and GHS‐BUILT‐S R2022A, multitemporal (1975–2030) [Dataset]. European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC). 10.2905/4606D58A-DC08-463C-86A9-D49EF461C47F
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2905/4606D58A-DC08-463C-86A9-D49EF461C47F"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0043"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0043"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Schiavina, M.
, 
Melchiorri, M.
, 
Pesaresi, M.
, 
Politis, P.
, 
Freire, S.
, 
Maffenini, L.
, et al. (2022). GHSL data package 2022. Publications Office of the European Union. Retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Marcello-Schiavina/publication/361565927_GHSL_Data_Package_2022/links/62b9bc3893242c74cad1ba02/GHSL-Data-Package-2022.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Marcello‐Schiavina/publication/361565927_GHSL_Data_Package_2022/links/62b9bc3893242c74cad1ba02/GHSL‐Data‐Package‐2022.pdf</ext-link>
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="title=GHSL data package 2022&amp;author=M. Schiavina&amp;author=M. Melchiorri&amp;author=M. Pesaresi&amp;author=P. Politis&amp;author=S. Freire&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0044"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0044"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Singh, N.
, 
Agarwal, S.
, 
Sharma, S.
, 
Chatani, S.
, &amp; 
Ramanathan, V.
 (2021). Air pollution over India: Causal factors for the high pollution with implications for mitigation. ACS Earth and Space Chemistry, 5(12), 3297–3312. 10.1021/acsearthspacechem.1c00170
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1021/acsearthspacechem.1c00170"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=ACS Earth and Space Chemistry&amp;title=Air pollution over India: Causal factors for the high pollution with implications for mitigation&amp;author=N. Singh&amp;author=S. Agarwal&amp;author=S. Sharma&amp;author=S. Chatani&amp;author=V. Ramanathan&amp;volume=5&amp;issue=12&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=3297-3312&amp;doi=10.1021/acsearthspacechem.1c00170&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0045"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0045"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Singh, N.
, 
Dey, S.
, &amp; 
Knibbs, L. D.
 (2023). Spatio‐temporal patterns of tropospheric NO<sub>2</sub> over India during 2005–2019. Atmospheric Pollution Research, 14(3), 101692. 10.1016/j.apr.2023.101692
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.apr.2023.101692"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Pollution Research&amp;title=Spatio‐temporal patterns of tropospheric NO2 over India during 2005–2019&amp;author=N. Singh&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=L. D. Knibbs&amp;volume=14&amp;issue=3&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=101692&amp;doi=10.1016/j.apr.2023.101692&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0046"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0046"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Singh, N.
, 
Van Buskirk, J.
, 
Dey, S.
, &amp; 
Knibbs, L. D.
 (2024). National, satellite‐based land‐use regression models for estimating long‐term annual NO<sub>2</sub> exposure across India. Atmospheric Environment X, 23, 100289. 10.1016/j.aeaoa.2024.100289
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.aeaoa.2024.100289"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Environment X&amp;title=National, satellite‐based land‐use regression models for estimating long‐term annual NO2 exposure across India&amp;author=N. Singh&amp;author=J. Van Buskirk&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=L. D. Knibbs&amp;volume=23&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=100289&amp;doi=10.1016/j.aeaoa.2024.100289&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0047"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0047"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Spears, D.
, 
Dey, S.
, 
Chowdhury, S.
, 
Scovronick, N.
, 
Vyas, S.
, &amp; 
Apte, J.
 (2019). The association of early‐life exposure to ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and later‐childhood height‐for‐age in India: An observational study. Environmental Health, 18(1), 62. 10.1186/s12940-019-0501-7

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12940-019-0501-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6617650"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31288809"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Health&amp;title=The association of early‐life exposure to ambient PM2.5 and later‐childhood height‐for‐age in India: An observational study&amp;author=D. Spears&amp;author=S. Dey&amp;author=S. Chowdhury&amp;author=N. Scovronick&amp;author=S. Vyas&amp;volume=18&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=62&amp;pmid=31288809&amp;doi=10.1186/s12940-019-0501-7&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0048"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0048"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Sun, W.
, 
Lu, K.
, &amp; 
Li, R.
 (2024). Global estimates of ambient NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations and long‐term health effects during 2000–2019. Environmental Pollution, 359, 124562. 10.1016/j.envpol.2024.124562

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2024.124562"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39019310"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Pollution&amp;title=Global estimates of ambient NO2 concentrations and long‐term health effects during 2000–2019&amp;author=W. Sun&amp;author=K. Lu&amp;author=R. Li&amp;volume=359&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=124562&amp;pmid=39019310&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envpol.2024.124562&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0019"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0019"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
The DHS Program
. (2018). Guide to DHS Statistics (DHS‐7). Retrieved from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/DHSG1/Guide_to_DHS_Statistics_DHS-7.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/DHSG1/Guide_to_DHS_Statistics_DHS‐7.pdf</ext-link>
</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0049"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0049"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

van Donkelaar, A.
, 
Hammer, M. S.
, 
Bindle, L.
, 
Brauer, M.
, 
Brook, J. R.
, 
Garay, M. J.
, et al. (2021). Monthly global estimates of fine particulate matter and their uncertainty. Environmental Science &amp; Technology, 55(22), 15287–15300. 10.1021/acs.est.1c05309

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1021/acs.est.1c05309"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34724610"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Science &amp; Technology&amp;title=Monthly global estimates of fine particulate matter and their uncertainty&amp;author=A. van Donkelaar&amp;author=M. S. Hammer&amp;author=L. Bindle&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;author=J. R. Brook&amp;volume=55&amp;issue=22&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=15287-15300&amp;pmid=34724610&amp;doi=10.1021/acs.est.1c05309&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0050"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0050"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Venkataraman, C.
, 
Brauer, M.
, 
Tibrewal, K.
, 
Sadavarte, P.
, 
Ma, Q.
, 
Cohen, A.
, et al. (2018). Source influence on emission pathways and ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> pollution over India (2015–2050). Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics, 18(11), 8017–8039. 10.5194/acp-18-8017-2018

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5194/acp-18-8017-2018"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7935015"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33679902"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics&amp;title=Source influence on emission pathways and ambient PM2.5 pollution over India (2015–2050)&amp;author=C. Venkataraman&amp;author=M. Brauer&amp;author=K. Tibrewal&amp;author=P. Sadavarte&amp;author=Q. Ma&amp;volume=18&amp;issue=11&amp;publication_year=2018&amp;pages=8017-8039&amp;pmid=33679902&amp;doi=10.5194/acp-18-8017-2018&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0051"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0051"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Wei, T.
, &amp; 
Tang, M.
 (2018). Biological effects of airborne fine particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub>) exposure on pulmonary immune system. Environmental Toxicology and Pharmacology, 60, 195–201. 10.1016/j.etap.2018.04.004

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.etap.2018.04.004"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29734103"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Toxicology and Pharmacology&amp;title=Biological effects of airborne fine particulate matter (PM2.5) exposure on pulmonary immune system&amp;author=T. Wei&amp;author=M. Tang&amp;volume=60&amp;publication_year=2018&amp;pages=195-201&amp;pmid=29734103&amp;doi=10.1016/j.etap.2018.04.004&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0052"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0052"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Wei, Y.
, 
Danesh Yazdi, M.
, 
Ma, T.
, 
Castro, E.
, 
Liu, C. S.
, 
Qiu, X.
, et al. (2023). Additive effects of 10‐year exposures to PM<sub>2.5</sub> and NO<sub>2</sub> and primary cancer incidence in American older adults. Environmental Epidemiology, 7(4), e265. 10.1097/EE9.0000000000000265

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/EE9.0000000000000265"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10402937"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37545804"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environmental Epidemiology&amp;title=Additive effects of 10‐year exposures to PM2.5 and NO2 and primary cancer incidence in American older adults&amp;author=Y. Wei&amp;author=M. Danesh Yazdi&amp;author=T. Ma&amp;author=E. Castro&amp;author=C. S. Liu&amp;volume=7&amp;issue=4&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=e265&amp;pmid=37545804&amp;doi=10.1097/EE9.0000000000000265&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0053"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0053"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
WorldPop
, &amp; 
Bondarenko, M.
 (2020). Global 1 km Population total adjusted to match the corresponding UNPD estimate [Dataset]. University of Southampton. 10.5258/SOTON/WP00671
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5258/SOTON/WP00671"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="gh270081-bib-0054"><mixed-citation id="gh270081-cit-0054"><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Yang, S.
, 
Liang, X.
, 
Dou, Q.
, 
La, Y.
, 
Cai, J.
, 
Yang, J.
, et al. (2022). Ethnic disparities in the association between ambient air pollution and risk for cardiometabolic abnormalities in China. Science of the Total Environment, 838, 155940. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.155940

</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.155940"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35580681"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Science of the Total Environment&amp;title=Ethnic disparities in the association between ambient air pollution and risk for cardiometabolic abnormalities in China&amp;author=S. Yang&amp;author=X. Liang&amp;author=Q. Dou&amp;author=Y. La&amp;author=J. Cai&amp;volume=838&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=155940&amp;pmid=35580681&amp;doi=10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.155940&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adc93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-citations" disp-level="2"><title>Data Citations</title><ref-list><ref id="_dbx_ref_gh270081-cit-0014"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Cooper, M. J.
, 
Martin, R. V.
, 
Hammer, M. S.
, 
Levelt, P. F.
, 
Veefkind, P.
, 
Lamsal, L. N.
, et al. (2022b). Satellite‐derived ground‐level NO2 concentrations, 2005–2019 [Dataset]. Zenodo. 10.5281/zenodo.5424752
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5281/zenodo.5424752"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="_dbx_ref_gh270081-cit-0042"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">

Schiavina, M.
, 
Melchiorri, M.
, &amp; 
Pesaresi, M.
 (2022). GHS‐SMOD R2022A — GHS settlement layers, application of the Degree of Urbanisation methodology (stage I) to GHS‐POP R2022A and GHS‐BUILT‐S R2022A, multitemporal (1975–2030) [Dataset]. European Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC). 10.2905/4606D58A-DC08-463C-86A9-D49EF461C47F
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2905/4606D58A-DC08-463C-86A9-D49EF461C47F"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="_dbx_ref_gh270081-cit-0053"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">
WorldPop
, &amp; 
Bondarenko, M.
 (2020). Global 1 km Population total adjusted to match the corresponding UNPD estimate [Dataset]. University of Southampton. 10.5258/SOTON/WP00671
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5258/SOTON/WP00671"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><caption><p>Supporting Information S1</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="GH2-9-e2025GH001409-s001.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 7a7a/12710085/2e48a3c54d90/GH2-9-e2025GH001409-s001.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 5864117?></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The satellite‐derived annual mean surface PM<sub>2.5</sub> data (V5.GL.03) used in this study (van Donkelaar et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0049" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) and the high‐resolution surface NO<sub>2</sub> data (Cooper et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2022a</xref>, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2022b</xref>) are publicly available from Washington University Atmospheric composition analysis Group website. The population data is provided by the WorldPop Research program (WorldPop &amp; Bondarenko, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0053" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The human settlement data set developed by the Joint Research Centre (JRC) of the European Commission and the Directorate‐General for Regional and Urban Policy is publicly available as part of the GHS‐SMOD R2022 A data package (Schiavina, Melchiorri, &amp; Pesaresi, <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0042" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>; Schiavina, Melchiorri, Pesaresi, Politis, et al., <xref rid="gh270081-bib-0043" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p></sec></sec></body></article>