
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Glob Heart</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Glob Heart</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3856</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">globheart</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Global Heart</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2211-8160</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2211-8179</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Ubiquity Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13045793</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC13045793.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13045793</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13045793</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41939286</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/gh.1545</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version>VoR</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact of Ambient Air Pollution on Cardiovascular Diseases in Low- and Lower-Middle-Income Countries: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-7658-639X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Adeoye</surname><given-names initials="M">Marvellous</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0009-0001-9732-1390</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names initials="N">Natalie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">**</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0396-0803</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimzadeh</surname><given-names initials="S">Shadi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="afn1" ref-type="author-notes">**</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9647-7855</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrikhande</surname><given-names initials="S">Shreya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5031-3588</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names initials="S">Sean</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2342-301X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Perel</surname><given-names initials="P">Pablo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2825-3419</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names initials="A">Anoop</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3934-3364</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Cesare</surname><given-names initials="M">Mariachiara</given-names><prefix>Prof.</prefix></name><email>m.dicesare@essex.ac.uk</email><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7078-597X</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names initials="MR">Mark R.</given-names><prefix>Prof.</prefix></name><email>mark.miller@ed.ac.uk</email><xref rid="aff-5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label>Institute of Public Health and Wellbeing, University of Essex, Colchester, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label>Department Of Science and Public Health, World Heart Federation, Geneva, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label>Department of Non-Communicable Disease Epidemiology, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="aff-4"><label>4</label>Department of Cardiology, Imperial College NHS Trust, London, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="aff-5"><label>5</label>Institute for Neuroscience and Cardiovascular Research, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><fn id="afn1"><p>**Same contribution</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2026-03-30"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">505183</issue-id><elocation-id>31</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2025-11-20"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2026-03-16"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>03</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-04-06 15:25:13.673"><day>06</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2026 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (CC-BY 4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. See <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="gh-21-1-1545.pdf"><?pdf-name gh-21-1-1545.pdf?><?pdf-size 1310267?><?pdf-md5 bd2ff089cd283259f862a0432c235774?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:49c6/13045793/bd2ff089cd28/gh-21-1-1545.pdf?></self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="Full text of the article" xlink:href="https://globalheartjournal.com/articles/10.5334/gh.1545/"/><abstract><p>Air pollution contributes to over 8.1 million deaths annually, predominantly from cardiovascular causes. The burden of air pollution is significantly higher in low-income countries (LICs) and lower middle-income countries (LMICs), yet most air pollution research is performed in higher-income countries. Our objective was to systematically review the association between exposure to ambient air pollution and cardiovascular disease (CVD) in LICs and LMICs. PubMed and Global Health databases were systematically searched for studies that explore associations between daily increases in gaseous (SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, O<sub>3</sub>) and particulate matter (PM) air pollutants with CVD mortality and hospital admission in adults. Studies were assessed for risk of bias based on outcome validity, exposure measurement quality, and confounder adjustment. A random-effects model was used to estimate overall and per-pollutant risks from short-term exposure studies, standardised to 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increments. Of 1329 articles screened, 48 met the inclusion criteria, of which 22 included a measure of relative risk suitable for meta-analysis. Short-term exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> were associated with increased combined mortality and hospital admission with 0.53% (95% CI: 0.31%–0.75%) and 1.68% (95% CI: 0.17%–3.21%) increase per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>, respectively. NO<sub>2</sub> showed a 0.66% increase (95% CI: 0.36%–0.97%) per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. This systematic review highlights the limited evidence on air pollution and CVD in LICs and LMICs. Nonetheless, this meta-analysis found positive associations between several ambient air pollutants and cardiovascular hospital admissions and mortality. There is the vital need for further research in underrepresented regions, particularly on the effects of long-term exposure, in order to establish the true burden of air pollution on cardiovascular health in regions where air pollution is frequently high, or access to healthcare is limited.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>particulate matter</kwd><kwd>nitrogen dioxide</kwd><kwd>hospital admissions</kwd><kwd>mortality</kwd><kwd>developing countries</kwd><kwd>LMICs</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Air pollution (both indoor and outdoor), which contributed to over eight million deaths globally in 2021, is considered one of the most worrying global health emergencies (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). It is both the second largest modifiable risk factor for mortality and the greatest risk factor for disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Almost 90% of global ambient air pollution related deaths occur in low- and lower-middle-income countries (LICs and LMICs) (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The disproportionate burden of air pollution-related cardiovascular disease in LICs and LMICs stems from multiple factors. While higher ambient pollution concentrations play a significant role, there are also important considerations regarding potential differences in air pollution composition and population demographics that may not be fully captured in current global models. Understanding whether the same exposure produces similar or different cardiovascular effects across diverse settings is critical for accurate burden assessment.</p><p>Ambient (outdoor) air pollution can arise from many sources and consequently contains a large mixture of thousands of chemicals, which vary spatially and temporally depending on source, dispersion, atmospheric reactions and meteorological conditions (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Criteria air pollutants that affect health include particulate matter (PM) of varying size, nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>), ozone (O<sub>3</sub>), sulfur dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub>) and carbon monoxide (CO). Fine particulate matter (PM with aerodynamic diameter ≤2.5 μm; ‘PM<sub>2.5</sub>’) is the air pollutant that is most consistently associated with adverse health effects especially in organ systems beyond the lung.</p><p>In 2021, cardiovascular diseases (CVDs) were responsible for 52% of the total DALYs attributable to ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Both short- and long-term exposure to air pollution is associated with increased risk of CVD (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), including cardiovascular outcomes such as myocardial infarction (MI) (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), stroke (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), and heart failure (HF) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The causality of these observations are supported by a substantial body of mechanistic research that show that inhaled air pollutants, especially PM, induce cardiovascular dysfunction through multiple mechanisms, such as oxidative stress, inflammation, endothelial dysfunction, thrombosis, autonomic imbalance, and acceleration of the growth and instability of atherosclerosis plaques (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>The majority of epidemiological studies on air pollution have been conducted in high-income countries (HICs) (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), and may not be generalisable to LICs and LMICs where sources of air pollution and population demographics and diseases differ. For example, current global estimates of the health impact of air pollution in LICs and LMICs, including those from the Global Burden of Disease (GBD) study, rely heavily on exposure-response functions derived predominantly from HICs. These estimates often apply concentration-response relationships from HICs to pollution levels and demographic profiles in LMICs, with limited validation from local studies. This extrapolation approach, while practical given data limitations, introduces uncertainty in burden estimates. Removing or lowering risk factors is key to the prevention of CVD (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) and is especially important in LMIC settings given that the availability of treatment may be limited.</p><p>Despite recognition of the disproportionate burden of both air pollution exposure and CVD suffered by LICs and LMICs, the evidence base remains relatively limited (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Existing reviews group LMICs with upper-middle-income countries (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) or focus only on particulate matter (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Another notable gap is the absence of pooled estimates of exposure-response relationships, which hinders an adequate burden assessment and means to direct public health policy. Here, we aimed to systematically review and synthesise the evidence on associations between ambient air pollution exposure and cardiovascular outcomes in, specifically, LICs and LMICs. Our review has been designed to include all criteria air pollutants (PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, and O<sub>3</sub>) and both cardiovascular mortality and hospitalisation. The review aims not only to establish and quantify these effects of air pollution in these regions, but also to identify research gaps that are needed to ascertain full burden on health and help guide air quality interventions that could improve cardiovascular health.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>2. Methods</title><sec><title>2.1 Search strategy and selection criteria</title><p>The systematic review and meta-analysis protocol was registered with PROSPERO (registration CRD42023484929) and adhered to the Preferred Reporting Items of Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analysis (PRISMA) guidelines (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>PubMed and Global Health databases were systematically searched for relevant resources. The search terms were a pairwise combination of ‘air pollution’ (including particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> (particles with aerodynamic diameter ≤10 μm)), SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, O<sub>3</sub>) and ‘cardiovascular disease’, ‘myocardial infarction’, ‘stroke’, and ‘heart failure’ (HF), selected to capture both overall CVD outcomes and specific CVDs with well-established links to ambient air pollution exposure. These terms were combined using AND, and OR, and some were expanded, especially those with multiple synonyms, to include all pertinent articles. Adjustments to the search were made as necessary, by the specific requirements of the database used. The search spanned the inception of the database to June 2024 (for full search strategy, see <bold>Supplementary Material</bold>).</p><p>Studies were included if published in English, conducted in LICs or LMICs as from the 2024 World Bank definition (<bold>Figure S1</bold>), and reported associations between ambient air pollution and the aforementioned CVD endpoints. We included studies of all age groups with no restrictions on population demographics. This review focused on ambient air pollution; studies examining indoor air pollution or non-ambient occupational air pollution exposure were excluded. We included both short-term exposure studies (examining acute exposure over days to weeks) and long-term exposure studies (examining chronic exposure over months to years). Various methodological approaches were eligible—including time-series, case-crossover, cohort studies, cross-sectional, ecological, cost analysis, comparative risk assessment designs, and studies using the World Health Organization (WHO) Health Impact Assessment model (e.g., AirQ+), which estimates health impacts of air pollution using standardised assumptions and software tools—as long as they reported quantitative associations between ambient air pollution and cardiovascular outcomes. Summaries, editorials, short commentaries, conference proceedings, non-peer-reviewed studies, and full texts that were not available online were all excluded.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2 Screening and data extraction</title><p>Results from the search were entered into Endnote, and duplicates removed. Rayyan was used to screen the papers. Titles/abstracts and full text-screening, and data extraction process were conducted independently by M.A. and S.R. For each article, meta-data information was extracted via a predefined data-extraction tool previously used (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). In summary, the following were extracted: (1) study characteristics (first author, publication year, study design, country, and data source); (2) ambient air pollution measurement and measurement tools (e.g., fixed monitoring stations, satellite-derived estimates, or personal monitors) and period of exposure (short-term or long-term); and (3) CVD admission and mortality (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>Any disparities between the reviewers were deliberated, and if necessary, resolved by a third reviewer (S.S.).</p></sec><sec><title>2.3 Risk of bias assessment</title><p>The risk of bias assessment tool adapted for this study has been previously reported (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref><xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). This evaluation covers three components: validity of the occurrence of CVD (rated 0 or 1), quality of air pollutant measurements (rated 0 or 1), and the degree of confounder adjustment (rated 0, 1, 2, or 3). Studies were rated as good quality (best scores in all domains), average (mixed scores), or low quality (any domain scored zero). (For full description, see <bold>Supplementary Material</bold>.)</p></sec><sec><title>2.4 Data analysis</title><p>For the meta-analysis, we included only studies reporting relative risk (RR), hazard ratio (HR), or odds ratio (OR) for lag zero or lag one day. Only one study provided cumulative lags (0–1) which was used as the shortest lag. RR were pooled for a standardised increment in pollutant concentration, with all concentrations standardised to a 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increment. For this standardisation, we used the following conversions specific for each pollutant: one part per billion (ppb) was converted to 1.88 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for NO<sub>2</sub>, 2.62 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for SO<sub>2</sub>, and 1.96 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for O<sub>3</sub>. One part per million (ppm) was converted to 1145 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for CO (under the assumption of standard temperature and pressure of 25 °C and 1 atm) (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><p>In line with established methodological practices in air pollution meta-analyses (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), we assumed a linear relationship between exposure and outcome for standardisation purposes. Standardised risk estimates were calculated for each study using the following equation (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="FD1">
<label>1</label>
<alternatives><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="Eq001-mml" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>RR</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>standardised</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>RR</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Increment</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Increment</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>original</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><tex-math id="M1"><?equation-image-name M1.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 2c3e51df44dc69b5b9ee933bf2525c24?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/49c6/13045793/2c3e51df44dc/M1.gif?>\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}
\oddsidemargin -1.0in
\begin{document}
\[RR{\,_{\left({{\mathrm{standardised}}} \right)}} = \,\,RR{\,^{{\mathrm{Increment }}\left({{\mathrm{1}}0} \right)/{\mathrm{Increment}}\left({{\mathrm{original}}} \right)}}\]
\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gh-21-1-1545-e1.jpg"><?image-name gh-21-1-1545-e1.jpg?><?image-size 2249?><?image-md5 83f0877eacdef56371e0ad2e4a828d7f?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-original-height 25?><?image-original-width 209?><?image-scaled-height 25?><?image-scaled-width 209?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/49c6/13045793/83f0877eacde/gh-21-1-1545-e1.jpg?></graphic></alternatives>
</disp-formula><p>To ensure consistency across studies and reduce heterogeneity from differing lag structures, we extracted effect estimates for the shortest lag available (typically lag zero or lag 1) to assess overall risk estimates.</p><p>In studies reporting multiple health CVD outcomes (e.g., stroke, MI, HF) under exposure to the same pollutant and categorised by the same outcome type (admission, mortality), we conducted an internal meta-analysis to derive a single pooled effect. This pooled estimate was then used as a representative measure for that study in the overall meta-analysis of CVD admissions and mortality. For studies reporting both specific CVD outcomes and a broader overall CVD outcome for the same pollutant and endpoint, we exclusively used the overall CVD admission or mortality outcome to avoid double-counting and ensure consistency in the pooled analysis.</p><p>Funnel plots were used to examine publication bias and assessed for asymmetry using Egger’s regression test; correction for asymmetry was performed using the trim and fill method (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p><p>A sensitivity analysis was conducted excluding 1) ORs; 2) studies from Iran (which represented the majority of included studies).</p><p>Because of the diversity in study designs, methods, lag exposures, and geographical and population differences, we used a random-effects model to account for within and between study heterogeneity. Heterogeneity was examined using the standard <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> test. Statistical significance was taken as two-sided p &lt; 0.05. Analysis was performed using R Software (version 4.4.2).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1 Study overview</title><p>The initial literature search identified 1474 research articles. After removing duplicates, the articles were reduced to 1329. Following titles/abstracts and full-text review, 48 studies met the criteria for inclusion (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The majority of studies were conducted in Iran (n = 38), followed by Vietnam (n = 3) and Bangladesh (n = 3). Indonesia, India, Nepal, and Lebanon had one study each (<bold>Figure S2</bold>). This includes one multi-country study (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) covering France, Iran, and Italy, from which only the Iran data were extracted. There were more short-term studies (n = 39) than long-term studies (n = 9). Time series and case-crossover studies were the most frequently used study designs (n = 23), followed by studies using the WHO Health Impact Assessment model (n = 14), cross-sectional studies (n = 5) and cohort studies (n = 3). Furthermore, three studies used cost analysis (n = 1), ecological (n = 1), and comparative risk assessment (n = 1) designs. Of the 48 studies included in the review, the majority (31; 64.6%) were of good or average methodological quality, with the most common limitations being inadequate confounder adjustment and insufficient air pollution measurement quality.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow chart.</p></caption><alt-text>PRISMA flow diagram of study selection process</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gh-21-1-1545-g1.jpg"><?image-name gh-21-1-1545-g1.jpg?><?image-size 106958?><?image-md5 c63b21f5b2c19307128ce1a1b1ec0717?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2218?><?image-original-width 1200?><?image-scaled-height 1479?><?image-scaled-width 800?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/49c6/13045793/c63b21f5b2c1/gh-21-1-1545-g1.jpg?><?thumb-name gh-21-1-1545-g1.gif?><?thumb-size 3392?><?thumb-md5 d373e684066356fac4f7980966dad54e?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 185?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/49c6/13045793/d373e6840663/gh-21-1-1545-g1.gif?></graphic></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of included studies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><th colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUTHOR</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YEAR</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COUNTRY</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DATA SOURCE</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DURATION</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DESIGN</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OUTCOME</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POLLUTANTS</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EXPOSURE ASSESSMENT</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ROB ASSESSMENT</th></tr><tr><th colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran statistical centre</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, NO, NO<sub>x</sub>, CO, O<sub>3</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub>, NO, O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, O<sub>3</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vietnam</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vietnam</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical registry</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case crossover</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O<sub>3</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indonesia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey data</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Satellite monitoring</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bangladesh</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case crossover</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case crossover</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bangladesh</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality, admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case crossover</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub> CO, NO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France, Iran, Italy</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality, admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O<sub>3</sub>, CO, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission, mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO, O<sub>3</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub>, CO, NO</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vietnam</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case crossover</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, CO, NO</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipal records</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost analysis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mortality, admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecological</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, CO</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bangladesh</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Registry data</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Satellite monitoring</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort data</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Satellite monitoring</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National registry</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross-sectional</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O<sub>3</sub>, CO, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality, admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survey/registry data</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Registry data</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comparative risk assessment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nepal</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case crossover</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO, O<sub>3</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lebanon</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIA, WHO AirQ</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>) (*)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital database</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case crossover</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO, O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipal records</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short term</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time series</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground monitoring stations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: (*) studies included in the meta-analysis, Air quality modelling software (WHO AirQ). WHO, World Health Organization; HIA, Health Impact Assessment; AirQ, Air Quality Health Impact Assessment tool.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>3.2 Meta-analysis</title><p>Overall CVD effects were obtained for four studies (<bold>Figure S3</bold>) through internal meta-analyses combining HF admission and MI admission for PM<sub>2.5</sub> (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>); ischemic heart disease (IHD) mortality and stroke mortality for PM<sub>2.5</sub> (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>); IHD admission and MI admission for CO, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, and SO<sub>2</sub> separately (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>); HF admission, IHD admission and stroke admission for CO (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Overall CVD admission was provided as an outcome and used instead of other CVD specific outcomes for two studies (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). <bold>Figure S3</bold> presents these combined within-study effect estimates that were subsequently used in our main meta-analysis.</p><p>The detailed pooled effect size RRs of pollutants for a 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increase along with p-values and heterogeneity are given in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The meta-analysis included a total of 22 studies and 101 data points investigating air pollutant-outcome pairs. Most of the studies (21; 88 estimates) examined the association between air pollutants and hospital admission for CVD, while only five studies (13 estimates) investigated associations with mortality.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Meta-Analysis results.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><th colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CATEGORY</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RR</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI LOWER</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI UPPER</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NUMBER OF STUDIES</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NUMBER OF DATA POINTS</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I<sup>2</sup></th></tr><tr><th colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CO</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality + admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NO<sub>2</sub></bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality + admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0066</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0036</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0097</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0062</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0026</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0099</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0108</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0008</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.021</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.0%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NO</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality + admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9987</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0053</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>O<sub>3</sub></bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality + admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9995</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9988</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0002</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.3%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9985</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9995</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.5%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0038</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0007</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0069</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.7%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PM<sub>10</sub></bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality + admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0168</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0321</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.1%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0191</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0017</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0368</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.2%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0032</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9984</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.008</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.1%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PM<sub>2.5</sub></bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality + admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0053</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0031</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0075</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.3%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0046</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0025</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0067</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.1%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0384</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9813</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0988</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.8%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SO<sub>2</sub></bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality + admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0015</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9986</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0044</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">admission</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9991</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0053</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9976</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9909</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0044</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.6%</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr></table></table-wrap><p>Daily exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> were both associated with increased combined hospital admission and CVD mortality with an RR of 1.0053 (95% Confidence Interval (CI): 1.0031–1.0075; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 74.3%) and 1.0168 (95% CI: 1.0017–1.0321; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 88.1%) per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increase in daily concentrations respectively (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). When stratified by outcome (admission or mortality), there was strong evidence of association between exposure to 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> of PM<sub>2.5</sub> and hospital admissions for CVD with an RR of 1.0046 (95% CI: 1.0025–1.0067; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 72.1%), while the same level of exposure to PM<sub>10</sub> showed strong evidence of association with an RR of 1.019 (95% CI: 1.0017–1.0368; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 87.2%) for hospital admission. The RR for mortality was larger for PM<sub>2.5</sub> (RR = 1.0384; 95% CI: 0.9813–1.0988; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 86.8%) compared to PM<sub>10</sub> (RR = 1.0032; 95% CI: 0.9984–1.008; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 95.1%), although neither were statistically significant due to the high variability of risk estimates, especially for PM<sub>2.5</sub> mortality.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Forest plot of pooled relative risks for cardiovascular outcomes (per 10 µg/m<sup>3</sup> increment).</p></caption><alt-text>Forest plot of pooled relative risks per 10 µg/m³ by pollutant</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gh-21-1-1545-g2.jpg"><?image-name gh-21-1-1545-g2.jpg?><?image-size 75651?><?image-md5 8bce5edbdd841a7656a91c730a0405f3?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1263?><?image-original-width 1200?><?image-scaled-height 842?><?image-scaled-width 800?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/49c6/13045793/8bce5edbdd84/gh-21-1-1545-g2.jpg?><?thumb-name gh-21-1-1545-g2.gif?><?thumb-size 2709?><?thumb-md5 f52d76b37cfc0f4d3253e5ec8aea030e?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 105?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/49c6/13045793/f52d76b37cfc/gh-21-1-1545-g2.gif?></graphic></fig><p>Exposure to gaseous pollutants was reported in approximately half of the studies included in the analysis. NO<sub>2</sub> generally had the strongest positive associations with an overall RR of cardiovascular outcomes of 1.0066 (95% CI: 1.0036–1.0097; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 56.1%), 1.0062 (95% CI: 1.0026–1.0099; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 51.0%) for admission alone and 1.0108 (95% CI: 1.0008–1.0210; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 85.0%) for mortality alone, per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increase in NO<sub>2</sub>. O<sub>3</sub> was associated with an increased RR of mortality of 1.0038 (95% CI: 1.0007–1.0069; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 47.7%) per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>, however there was no association with CVD admission or the overall CVD outcome. Increases in levels of CO were associated with an RR of 1.0001 (95% CI: 1.0001–1.0001; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>: 86%) in hospital admissions per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. No significant associations were detected for SO<sub>2</sub> or NO with either CVD mortality or admission.</p><p>Publication bias (Egger’s test for asymmetry p &lt; 0.05) was observed only for NO<sub>2</sub> (p = 0.0083) and CO (p &lt; 0.001) (<bold>Table S1</bold>). Adjustment for asymmetry with the trim and fill method did not alter the effect direction or effect size.</p></sec><sec><title>3.3 Sensitivity analysis</title><p>A sensitivity analysis was conducted excluding three studies (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref><xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) which reported OR for hospital admission rather than RR, to account for any bias introduced with the assumption OR approximation to RR. While the pattern of effects remained the same, the effect size for daily exposure to PM<sub>10</sub> and PM<sub>2.5</sub> were both associated with reductions in the RR of combined CVD mortality and hospital admissions in the sensitivity analysis, with an RR of 1.0065 (95% CI: 0.9941–1.0189; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 87.1%) and 1.0056 (95% CI: 1.0026–1.0087; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 48.8%) per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increase in daily concentrations, respectively (<bold>Figure S4</bold>). These changes were driven by reductions in the effect size for hospital admissions, bringing those associations closer to the null. For the gaseous pollutants, the only effect sizes impacted by this sensitivity analysis were related to NO<sub>2</sub>, where the RR for combined mortality and hospital admissions reduced slightly to 1.0065 (95% CI: 1.0037–1.0094; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 58.1%). No other effect sizes were impacted by this sensitivity analysis.</p><p>An additional analysis was performed to assess whether the predominance of Iranian studies (38 out of 48 studies) might have biassed our overall findings, and to determine if the observed associations were consistent across different geographical settings. This meta-analysis was conducted on five studies (28, 37–40) (17 data points) after excluding all data from Iran (<bold>Figure S5</bold>). PM<sub>10</sub> showed a smaller but less heterogeneous effect in the non-Iranian studies (RR = 1.0062; 95% CI: 1.0042–1.0081; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0%) versus Iranian studies (RR = 1.0221; 95% CI: 1.0022–1.0424; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 87.5%). For PM<sub>2.5</sub>, the non-Iranian studies had a lower but still significant effect estimate (RR = 1.0041; 95% CI: 1.0020–1.0061; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0%) compared to Iranian studies (RR = 1.0091; 95% CI: 1.0041–1.0142; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 81.5%). Notably, the non-Iranian studies demonstrated markedly lower heterogeneity (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0–6.4%) compared to the Iranian studies (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 79.5–87.5%). Due to the limited number of non-Iranian studies, separate analyses by outcomes were not feasible. In many cases, only one or two studies contributed data, although most of these individual study findings were consistent with the overall associations observed in the pooled analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>4. Discussion</title><p>This systematic review and meta-analysis find that short-term exposure to ambient air pollution, particularly for PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, and NO<sub>2</sub>, is associated with CVD outcomes in LICs and LMICs. These results complement global findings that air pollution is linked to cardiovascular morbidity and mortality, extending these findings beyond these data, which were predominantly from middle- to high-income countries, to lower income nations. While statistically significant associations were found, this review highlights the paucity of data from different countries that is needed to ascertain the true burden of air pollution in low-income nations.</p><p>Our findings build on the previous global meta-analysis by Shah et al. in 2013 and 2015 (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), which linked air pollution to HF and stroke, by focusing specifically on LICs and LMICs. For CVD hospital admissions, the pooled PM<sub>2.5</sub> effect observed here (0.46% increase per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>) is lower than the 1.01% increase reported by Shah et al., but slightly higher than 0.26–0.29% reported from studies using data from more than 180 cities in China, an upper-middle income country (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref><xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). By comparison, data from the USA, a high income country, found that a 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increase in PM<sub>10–2.5</sub> was associated with a 0.69% increase in same-day cardiovascular hospital admissions (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). When examining mortality outcomes, our estimates (3.84% increase per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>) exceed those reported in previous short-term exposure systematic reviews from global (0.84%) and China-specific (0.63%) settings (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref><xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>).</p><p>Larger effects are typically observed for long-term cohort studies in HICs. For instance, in a US cohort study (7.5 million person-years) there was a considerably higher increase (14%, 95% CI: 2–27%) in stroke mortality and in IHD mortality (16%, 95% CI: 9–22%) per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> PM<sub>2.5</sub> (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). This greater risk ratio in long-term studies reflects that admissions and mortality outcomes will likely capture any long-term effects of air pollution on disease progression as well as the acute effects of air pollution on exacerbation of CVD that leads to a cardiovascular event. Longitudinal cohort studies are more common in HICs due to factors that include the availability of long-term air pollution monitoring data from stationary monitoring networks, comprehensive medical records data systems, and the greater availability of resources required for prospective participant follow-up over many years. The limited number of long-term exposure studies in LICs/LMICs represents a critical research gap that needs to be addressed to establish the full burden of chronic air pollution exposure in these settings.</p><p>We observed that NO<sub>2</sub> generally had the strongest positive associations among gaseous pollutants. NO<sub>2</sub> is a gas with oxidative properties that induces pulmonary inflammation and oxidative stress; effects that can be transmitted to the circulation to impair cardiovascular function through multiple mechanisms, especially with long-term exposure (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). NO<sub>2</sub> is also a marker of traffic-related air pollution, emissions of which also include semi-volatile species and particulate matter, especially ultrafine particles, which are infrequently assessed in epidemiological studies; there may therefore be a degree of ‘effect transfer’ between closely correlated pollutants (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Nonetheless, rapidly urbanising LMIC settings will see increasing vehicle numbers and, frequently, an older vehicle fleet that generates significant emissions with less stringent emission controls. A greater commitment towards targeted interventions to reduce traffic emissions in LICs/LMICs could therefore lead to significant health benefits, not only for respiratory conditions but also for cardiovascular outcomes. Other gaseous pollutants, such as O<sub>3</sub> and CO, showed varying degrees of association with cardiovascular outcomes. The weaker associations observed for O<sub>3</sub> might reflect its different spatial distribution and atmospheric processes (including reactions that lead to an inverse relationship with NO<sub>2</sub>), in addition to the relatively limited monitoring of this pollutant. Nonetheless, O<sub>3</sub> should not be overlooked, as associations have been observed between O<sub>3</sub> and cardiovascular disease in other regions of the world (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Marked seasonal variations in this pollutant are observed and levels of this pollutant are likely to rise as global temperatures increase. For CO, our results here are consistent with previous meta-analyses linking short-term CO exposure to risk of myocardial infarction (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p><p>The effect of air pollutant exposure on mortality was stronger than that on hospital admissions. This pattern remained consistent across pollutants; mortality outcomes generally exceeded admission outcomes, especially for PM<sub>2.5</sub> (3.84% vs 0.46% increase in risk) and NO<sub>2</sub> (1.08% vs 0.62% increase in risk). Our observations may reflect several LIC and LMIC-specific challenges, including delayed healthcare-seeking behaviour driven by financial constraints and limited healthcare access (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), and the limited availability of advanced cardiac care facilities (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref><xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). However, the larger mortality effects observed in our analysis are based on considerably fewer studies (typically 2–3 studies per pollutant) compared with hospital admission outcomes (10–12 studies per pollutant), which could influence the reliability and precision of the mortality estimates. For PM<sub>2.5</sub> mortality in particular, high heterogeneity was largely driven by a single Iranian study that reported substantially larger effects than others, meaning the pooled estimate should be interpreted with caution until further studies are available. The higher mortality effects might also indicate that air pollution in LMICs has more severe cardiovascular consequences, possibly due to a more susceptible population or synergistic interactions with other risk factors such as household air pollution, occupational exposures, climate factors and co-morbidities (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>).</p><p>An interesting finding from our analysis was the differences in risk of hospital admissions between the two-size metrics of particulate matter, with PM<sub>10</sub> demonstrating stronger associations with cardiovascular admissions (RR: 1.0191; 95% CI: 1.0017–1.0368) compared to PM<sub>2.5</sub> (RR: 1.0046; 95% CI: 1.0025–1.0067) per 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increase. Typically, PM<sub>2.5</sub> shows stronger associations with cardiovascular outcomes than PM<sub>10</sub> (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>), in principle due to the greater penetration of these particles into the lung, their larger particle surface area and, in general, the higher content of harmful constituents of the sources that PM<sub>2.5</sub> arises from. A few factors might explain the pattern observed. First, when standardising to equivalent mass increments (10 μg/m<sup>3</sup>), the relative toxicity comparison is influenced by the typical concentration ranges of these pollutants. Given that PM<sub>10</sub> concentrations are generally higher and more variable in LMIC urban settings, a 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increment represents a smaller proportional change in exposure for PM<sub>10</sub> than for PM<sub>2.5</sub>, potentially making direct comparison of effect sizes challenging. Also, in many LMIC settings, the proportion of PM<sub>10</sub> derived from sources such as road dust, traffic and construction activities may be greater than in HICs, reflecting industrial emissions that are prevalent in rapidly urbanising environments, although it should be recognised that these sources will also contribute to particles in the PM<sub>2.5</sub> size range. The relative toxicity of the sources of PM in LICs are less well determined than that of urban PM in HIC settings and laboratory sources of combustion-derived PM (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Thus, there is a need for better attribution of different source contributions, and atmospheric reactions that affect the air pollution mixture people are exposed to, to link to health outcomes, and subsequently support targeted air quality interventions.</p><p>Studies performed in Iran constituted the majority of the dataset and were concentrated in urban areas. However, this dominance raises questions about generalisability. Non-Iranian studies, though fewer, showed similar directions of association but tended to report slightly weaker effects for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub>. Iran is also frequently affected by transboundary desert dust storms, which contribute substantially to ambient particulate matter and differ in toxicity from combustion-derived particles more typical of other urban environments (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). WHO has highlighted desert dust as a pollutant warranting separate long-term assessment (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). While the data from Iran is informative, it highlights the paucity of data from other regions. In particular, South Asia and sub-Saharan African regions, home to some of the world’s most polluted cities, are underrepresented. This geographic imbalance parallels gaps identified in the GBD study, which notes that 90% of air pollution-related deaths occur in LMICs, yet there is often a dearth of air pollution monitoring stations in low-income regions (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>), especially sub-Saharan Africa (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The few studies from these potentially high-burden regions, where air pollution characteristics and healthcare infrastructure could differ markedly, represent a critical data gap. Our review focused specifically on LICs and lower-middle-income countries, excluding upper-middle-income countries such as China, South Africa, and Brazil, where much of the recent growth in air pollution–CVD research has occurred. This deliberate distinction means that the geographic distribution of studies observed here reflects evidence gaps specific to the lowest-income settings, which previous reviews combining all low and middle-income countries may not have revealed. Also, our review focused on incident (hospitalisation and mortality) rather than prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors such as hypertension and diabetes. Since these risk factors are themselves influenced by air pollution, through both shared and independent mechanisms, including them alongside incident CVD events would risk double-counting of effects in a pooled analysis. Our focus on incident events also reflects a stronger causal inference framework, with clear temporal associations between air pollutant exposure and cardiovascular outcomes, and reduced potential for confounding.</p><p>The observed associations between air pollution and cardiovascular disease are supported by mechanistic studies (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). All the criteria air pollutants investigated can induce oxidative stress and inflammation in the lung, both of which can be propagated to the systemic circulation (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)<sub>.</sub> Several pollutants, but most notably PM, induce a range of cardiovascular impairments including endothelial dysfunction, increased blood pressure, changes to heart rhythm, increased cardiac susceptibility to ischaemia, enhanced blood clotting, impaired fibrinolysis, to name but a few (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Exposure to air pollution also promotes lipid peroxidation, vascular inflammation and accelerates atherosclerosis, and ultrafine particles may promote atherothrombotic vascular disease by directly accessing the blood and accumulating at sites of vascular inflammation (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). All these mechanisms will increase the risk of developing CVD but also increase the risk of cardiovascular events that lead to the outcomes studied in the current review. CO, a product of incomplete combustion, binds to haemoglobin, reducing oxygen delivery and exacerbating cardiac ischemia (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref><xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>), a mechanism that may be particularly detrimental in populations with pre-existing anaemia, prevalent in LICs (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). Future studies should ascertain the extent to which these mechanisms contribute to differences in the profile of cardiovascular diseases between LICs, LMICs and HICs, and if this may engender differences in susceptibility to specific air pollutants.</p><sec><title>4.1 Limitations</title><sec><title>4.1.1 Limitations of meta-analysis</title><p>While our study provides much needed insights from LICs and LMICs, several limitations warrant consideration. First, significant heterogeneity among the included studies owing to varying methodologies contributes substantially to the variability of pooled estimates and suggests the need for caution in generalising findings. Second, we assumed many of the included studies used generalised linear models, which assume a linear relationship between exposure and outcome. This assumption may not always hold true, as the exposure-response relationship is often reported to be supralinear (less steep at very high pollution levels). Third, our standardisation to a 10 μg/m<sup>3</sup> increment for all pollutants, while facilitating comparisons, may not optimally represent the typical exposure contrasts for each pollutant in LMIC settings. Finally, the predominance of short-term exposure studies in our analysis prevents an adequate assessment of the long-term cardiovascular consequences of chronic air pollution in these settings.</p></sec><sec><title>4.1.2 Limitations of systematic review</title><p>Our systematic review also has limitations. Although we used comprehensive search strategies, we may have missed relevant studies published in non-English languages or in journals not indexed in the databases searched. The substantial geographic concentration of studies in Iran limits generalising of our findings to other LICs and LMICs with different pollution profiles, population characteristics, and healthcare systems. The relatively small number of studies reporting certain outcomes (particularly mortality) resulted in less precise pooled estimates for these endpoints. This review is limited to incident events (hospitalisation and mortality) rather than prevalence and risk factors to ensure results reflect a causal inference framework (as from study protocol).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>4.2 Future research directions</title><p>Advancing research on air pollution and cardiovascular disease in LICs and LMICs requires a paradigm shift toward longitudinal, context-specific, and interdisciplinary approaches. Prioritising longitudinal cohort studies in regions with a high pollution burden will help to clarify the cumulative risks of chronic exposure in settings with a different socioeconomic status and healthcare disparities. It is highly likely that air pollution sources and PM composition will differ from HICs, yet assessment of this in LICs and LMICs (and between locations with different degrees of urbanisation) has been minimal. Source apportionment methodologies would help disentangle region-specific contributors such as industrial emissions, traffic, or agricultural burning, although such studies would require sufficient support to perform adequately. Not only would this information provide insight into which air pollutants are most harmful, but it would help in the design of targeted mitigation strategies to maximise potential health benefits for given resources. Population characteristics will differ between nations, including demographics that may be more vulnerable to air pollution exposure and health statuses that incur biological susceptibility to air pollutants. Mapping population demographics, even as far as profiling of gene variants that confer greater susceptibility, would contextualise air pollutant-outcome risk scores by clarifying the extent to which certain populations or individuals are biologically more susceptible to air pollution, thus enabling targeted public health interventions and more precise risk assessments.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>This systematic review and meta-analysis found significant associations between ambient air pollution and CVD in LICs and LMICs, complementing the findings of studies in higher income regions. High variability was observed for risk ratios due to the relatively limited number of studies identified and the different approaches used within them. However, given the overall positive associations between several air pollutants and cardiovascular mortality and hospital admission for CVD, the high levels of air pollution, as well as the structural and health inequities observed in many LICs and LMICs, suggest that the burden of air pollution on cardiovascular health is likely to be substantial. While a growing body of evidence on air pollution and cardiometabolic risk factors exists in broader LMIC settings, substantial gaps remain in studies reporting clinical CVD events in the LIC. Thus, there is a clear need for action on air pollution in LICs and LMICs, in terms of providing the evidence base to establish the risks of different sources of air pollution that exert the greatest effect on health. Doing so would greatly aid the justification of resources to improve air quality through policies that will provide a concerted approach of ground-level intervention, public awareness and appropriate health care provision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Accessibility Statement</title><p>Data extracted for this meta-analysis, including summary estimates and data dictionary, will be available upon request to the corresponding author following publication. Requests should be accompanied by a research proposal detailing the intended use and require approval from the study authors, along with a signed data-access agreement. The study protocol is publicly available via PROSPERO (registration number: CRD42023484929).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional File</title><p>The additional file for this article can be found as follows:</p><supplementary-material id="supp1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5334/gh.1545.s1</object-id><label>Supplementary Materials.</label><caption><p>Full search strategy, supplementary figures (S1–S5), supplementary table (S1), and risk of bias assessment details.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="gh-21-1-1545-s1.pdf" id="d67e3064" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name gh-21-1-1545-s1.pdf?><?suppdata-size 657612?><?suppdata-md5 f66346594d71503438c742b5e18fc3fd?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type pdf?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:49c6/13045793/f66346594d71/gh-21-1-1545-s1.pdf?></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was funded by a Clean Air Fund grant awarded to the World Heart Federation. The funder had no role in study design, data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, or manuscript preparation. For the purpose of open access, the author has applied a Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) licence to any Author Accepted Manuscript version arising from this submission.</p></ack><sec><title>Ethics and Consent</title><p>Ethical approval was not required for this study as it is a systematic review and meta-analysis of previously published data. No individual participant data were collected or used.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>Pablo Perel is Executive Editor of Global Heart. We confirm that all other authors are not current or former (within the past three years) members of the Global Heart editorial team or board. All authors have no competing interests to declare.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MA, MRM, and MDC conceived and designed the study. MA and SR performed the literature searches and independently screened studies, with discrepancies resolved by SS. MA, NE, SR and SS extracted data, conducted the statistical analysis, and drafted the initial manuscript. NE, SR, ST, SS, PP, AS, MDC, and MRM contributed substantially to interpreting results, critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content, and provided methodological guidance. No authors were prohibited from accessing the data. All authors reviewed and approved the final manuscript, and MRM and MDC had final responsibility for the decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p><p>Natalie Evans, Shadi Rahimzadeh had the same contribution.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boogaard</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Air pollution: the emergence of a major global health risk factor</article-title>. <source>Int Health</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Nov</month>
<day>13</day>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/inthealth/ihz078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31613318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>State of Global Air Report 2024</collab>. [cited 2025 Feb 18]. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.stateofglobalair.org/resources/report/state-global-air-report-2024">https://www.stateofglobalair.org/resources/report/state-global-air-report-2024</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>GBD 2021 Risk Factors Collaborators</collab>. <article-title>Global burden and strength of evidence for 88 risk factors in 204 countries and 811 subnational locations, 1990–2021: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>May</month>
<day>18</day>;<volume>403</volume>(<issue>10440</issue>):<fpage>2162</fpage>–<lpage>203</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)00933-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38762324</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11120204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Ambient (outdoor) air pollution</collab>. <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>; <year>2024</year> [cited 2025 Jan 2]. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/ambient-(outdoor)-air-quality-and-health">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/ambient-(outdoor)-air-quality-and-health</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Health Effects Institute</collab>. <article-title>Traffic-Related Air Pollution: A Critical Review of the Literature on Emissions, Exposure, and Health Effects</article-title>; <year>2010</year> [cited 2025 Feb 19]. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.healtheffects.org/publication/traffic-related-air-pollution-critical-review-literature-emissions-exposure-and-health">https://www.healtheffects.org/publication/traffic-related-air-pollution-critical-review-literature-emissions-exposure-and-health</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Interactive short-term effects of meteorological factors and air pollution on hospital admissions for cardiovascular diseases</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Sept</month>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>45</issue>):<fpage>68103</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-022-20592-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35532824</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Bont</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jaganathan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dahlquist</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Persson</surname>
<given-names>Å</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stafoggia</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ljungman</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ambient air pollution and cardiovascular diseases: An umbrella review of systematic reviews and meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>June</month>;<volume>291</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>779</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joim.13467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35138681</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9310863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vaičiulis</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Venclovienė</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miškinytė</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ustinavičienė</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dėdelė</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kalinienė</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between Outdoor Air Pollution and Fatal Acute Myocardial Infarction in Lithuania between 2006 and 2015: A Time Series Design</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Mar</month>
<day>3</day>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>). DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph20054549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10002310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36901560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mustafic</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jabre</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Caussin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Murad</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Escolano</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tafflet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Main air pollutants and myocardial infarction: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2012</year>
<month>Feb</month>
<day>15</day>;<volume>307</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2012.126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22337682</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jørgensen</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loft</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bräuner</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-Term Exposure to Air Pollution and Incidence of Myocardial Infarction: A Danish Nurse Cohort Study</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. <year>2020</year> May;<volume>128</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>57003</fpage>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32438827/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32438827/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32438827</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1289/EHP5818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7263451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Toubasi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Sayegh</surname>
<given-names>TN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short-term Exposure to Air Pollution and Ischemic Stroke: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Nov</month>
<day>7</day>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>e1922</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000207856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37758483</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10662999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>ASV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McAllister</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Whiteley</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short term exposure to air pollution and stroke: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2015</year>
<month>Mar</month>
<day>24</day>;<volume>350</volume>:<fpage>h1295</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.h1295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25810496</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4373601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of Air Pollution on Heart Failure: Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>July</month>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>76001</fpage>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37399145/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37399145/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37399145</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1289/EHP11506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10317211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>ASV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Langrish</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McAllister</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Donaldson</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Global association of air pollution and heart failure: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2013</year>
<month>Sept</month>
<day>21</day>;<volume>382</volume>(<issue>9897</issue>):<fpage>1039</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60898-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23849322</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3809511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Langrish</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>From particles to patients: oxidative stress and the cardiovascular effects of air pollution</article-title>. <source>Future Cardiol</source>. <year>2012</year>
<month>July</month>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>577</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fca.12.43</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22871197</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Franchini</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mannucci</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short-term effects of air pollution on cardiovascular diseases: outcomes and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>J Thromb Haemost</source>. <year>2007</year>
<month>Nov</month>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2169</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1538-7836.2007.02750.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17958737</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jaganathan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jaacks</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Magsumbol</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walia</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sieber</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shivasankar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of long-term exposure to fine particulate matter and cardio-metabolic diseases in low- and middle-income countries: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>July</month>
<day>16</day> [cited 2025 Mar 10];<volume>16</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>2541</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph16142541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31315297</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6679147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term exposure to particulate matter on cardiovascular and respiratory diseases in low- and middle-income countries: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Public Health</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Mar</month>
<day>28</day> [cited 2025 Mar 10];<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1134341</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1134341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37056647</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10089304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkinson</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garshick</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taub</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevention and Treatment of Cardiovascular Disease: Nutritional and Dietary Approaches</article-title>. <source>Springer Nature</source>. <year>2021</year>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://play.google.com/store/books/details?id=_Xs9EAAAQBAJ">https://play.google.com/store/books/details?id=_Xs9EAAAQBAJ</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rippe</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Lifestyle strategies for risk factor reduction, prevention, and treatment of cardiovascular disease</article-title>. <source>Am J Lifestyle Med</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Mar</month>-Apr;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1559827618812395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30800027</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6378495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Minja</surname>
<given-names>NW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nakagaayi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aliku</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ssinabulya</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nabaale</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cardiovascular diseases in Africa in the twenty-first century: Gaps and priorities going forward</article-title>. <source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Nov</month>
<day>10</day>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1008335</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2022.1008335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36440012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9686438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Adeoye</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimzadeh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shrikhande</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perel</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The impact of air pollution on cardiovascular health outcomes in African populations: A scoping review</article-title>. <source>JACC Adv</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>Dec</month>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>101371</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacadv.2024.101371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39817083</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11733974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newell</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kartsonaki</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>KBH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kurmi</surname>
<given-names>OP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiorespiratory health effects of particulate ambient air pollution exposure in low-income and middle-income countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>Dec</month>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e368</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(17)30166-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29851649</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boutron</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mulrow</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>BMJ (Clinical research ed)</source>. <year>2021</year>
<month>Mar</month>
<day>29</day> [cited 2025 Feb 19];<fpage>372</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8005924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33782057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A systematic review and meta-analysis of intraday effects of ambient air pollution and temperature on cardiorespiratory morbidities: First few hours of exposure matters to life</article-title>. <source>EBioMedicine</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Dec</month>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>104327</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2022.104327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36323182</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9626385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs</collab>. <article-title>UK AIR Air Information Resource [Internet]</article-title>. [cited 2025 Feb 19]. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://uk-air.defra.gov.uk/reports/cat06/0502160851_Conversion_Factors_Between_ppb_and.pdf">https://uk-air.defra.gov.uk/reports/cat06/0502160851_Conversion_Factors_Between_ppb_and.pdf</uri></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Duval</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tweedie</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Trim and fill: A simple funnel-plot-based method of testing and adjusting for publication bias in meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. <year>2000</year>
<month>June</month>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>455</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0006-341x.2000.00455.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10877304</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sicard</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khaniabadi</surname>
<given-names>YO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gualtieri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Marco</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effect of O, PM and PM on cardiovascular and respiratory diseases in cities of France, Iran and Italy</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Nov</month>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>31</issue>):<fpage>32645</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-019-06445-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31576506</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leili</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nadali</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karami</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bahrami</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Afkhami</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short-term effect of multi-pollutant air quality indexes and PM2.5 on cardiovascular hospitalization in Hamadan, Iran: a time-series analysis</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2021</year>
<month>Oct</month>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>38</issue>):<fpage>53653</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11356-021-14386-4">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11356-021-14386-4</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34036506</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-021-14386-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moradi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mokhtari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hadei</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vosoughi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Estimation of long-term and short-term health effects attributed to PM standard pollutants in the air of Ardabil (using Air Q + model)</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Mar</month>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>21508</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-17303-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34761318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soleimani</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Darvishi Boloorani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khalifeh</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mesdaghinia</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short-term effects of ambient air pollution and cardiovascular events in Shiraz, Iran, 2009 to 2015</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Mar</month>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>6359</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-3952-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30617889</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taheri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nouri</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ziaddini</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rabiei</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pourmoghaddas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shariful Islam</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ambient carbon monoxide and cardiovascular-related hospital admissions: A time-series analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Mar</month>
<day>8</day>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1126977</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2023.1126977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36969582</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10031048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dastoorpoor</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sekhavatpour</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Masoumi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aghababaeian</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khanjani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Air pollution and hospital admissions for cardiovascular diseases in Ahvaz, Iran</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Feb</month>
<day>20</day>;<volume>652</volume>:<fpage>1318</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.10.285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30586817</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Saifipour</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Azhari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pourmoghaddas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jafari-Koshki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between ambient air pollution and hospitalization caused by atrial fibrillation</article-title>. <source>ARYA Atheroscler</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>May</month>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>106</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31452658/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31452658/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31452658</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.22122/arya.v15i3.1843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6698081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tabaghi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sheibani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khaheshi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miri</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Haji Aghajani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Safi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Associations between short-term exposure to fine particulate matter and acute myocardial infarction: A case-crossover study</article-title>. <source>Clin Cardiol</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Nov</month>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1319</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/clc.24111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37501642</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10642339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Davoodabadi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soleimani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pourmoghaddas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jafari-Koshki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Correlation between air pollution and hospitalization due to myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>ARYA Atheroscler</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>July</month>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31819749/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31819749/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31819749</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.22122/arya.v15i4.1834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6884733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phung</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hien</surname>
<given-names>TT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Linh</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luong</surname>
<given-names>LMT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morawska</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Air pollution and risk of respiratory and cardiovascular hospitalizations in the most populous city in Vietnam</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. <year>2016</year>
<month>July</month>
<day>1</day>;<volume>557-558</volume>:<fpage>322</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.03.070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27016680</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Konishi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>CFS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Umezaki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kabir</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tasmin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between short-term exposure to fine particulate matter and daily emergency room visits at a cardiovascular hospital in Dhaka, Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Jan</month>
<day>1</day>;<volume>646</volume>:<fpage>1030</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.07.288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30235588</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Begum</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hopke</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nahar</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thurston</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular morbidity and mortality associations with biomass- and fossil-fuel-combustion fine-particulate-matter exposures in Dhaka, Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2021</year>
<month>Aug</month>
<day>30</day>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1172</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyab037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33822936</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8633660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nakhlé</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farah</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ziadé</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abboud</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Salameh</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Annesi-Maesano</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short-term relationships between emergency hospital admissions for respiratory and cardiovascular diseases and fine particulate air pollution in Beirut, Lebanon</article-title>. <source>Environ Monit Assess</source>. <year>2015</year>
<month>Apr</month>;<volume>187</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>196</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-015-4409-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25792024</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Juan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Ambient air pollution and daily hospital admissions: A nationwide study in 218 Chinese cities</article-title>. <source>Environmental pollution (Barking, Essex: 1987)</source>. <year>2018</year>
<month>Nov</month> [cited 2025 Mar 17];<volume>242</volume>(<issue>Pt B</issue>). DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2018.07.116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30096542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between ambient fine particulate pollution and hospital admissions for cause specific cardiovascular disease: time series study in 184 major Chinese cities</article-title>. <source>BMJ (Clinical research ed)</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Dec</month>
<day>30</day> [cited 2025 Mar 17];<fpage>367</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.l6572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7190041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31888884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Krall</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ambient coarse particulate matter and hospital admissions in the Medicare cohort air pollution study, 1999–2010</article-title>. <source>Environmental health perspectives</source>. <year>2015</year>
<month>Nov</month> [cited 2025 Mar 17];<volume>123</volume>(<issue>11</issue>). DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.1408720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4629736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25872223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>IC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiological time series studies of PM<sub>2.5</sub> and daily mortality and hospital admissions: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source>. <year>2014</year>
<month>July</month> [cited 2025 Mar 17];<volume>69</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>665</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2013-204492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24706041</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4078677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis of the adverse health effects of ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> pollution in the Chinese population</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. <year>2015</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2014.06.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25460637</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cromar</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>PM<sub>2.5</sub> air pollution and cause-specific cardiovascular disease mortality</article-title>. <source>International journal of epidemiology</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>Feb</month>
<day>1</day> [cited 2025 Mar 17];<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyz114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7124502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31289812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Newby</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Air pollution and cardiovascular disease: car sick</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Res</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>Feb</month>
<day>1</day>;<volume>116</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cvr/cvz228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31583404</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sagheer</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Kindi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abohashem</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rajagopalan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kalra</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Environmental pollution and cardiovascular disease: Part 1 of 2: Air pollution</article-title>. <source>JACC: Advances</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>Feb</month>
<day>1</day> [cited 2025 Apr 14]; DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacadv.2023.100805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11198409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38939391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of long-term exposure to ozone with cardiovascular mortality and its metabolic mediators: evidence from a nationwide, population-based, prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Reg Health West Pac</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>Nov</month>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>101222</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2024.101222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39444716</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11497431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Spath</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>ASV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Short-term exposure to carbon monoxide and myocardial infarction: A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Environment international</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>Oct</month> [cited 2025 Apr 11];<fpage>143</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2020.105901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32634667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bloom</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brieger</surname>
<given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Poverty and access to health care in developing countries</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>1136</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1196/annals.1425.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17954679</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mocumbi</surname>
<given-names>AO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular Health Care in Low- and Middle-Income Countries</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>Feb</month>
<day>20</day> [cited 2025 Feb 19]. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.123.065717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38377254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ragupathi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stribling</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yakunina</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fuster</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McLaughlin</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vedanthan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Availability, use, and barriers to cardiac rehabilitation in LMIC</article-title>. <source>Global Heart</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>Dec</month>
<day>1</day> [cited 2025 Feb 19];<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gheart.2016.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28302548</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhury</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pillarisetti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oberholzer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jetter</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cappuccilli</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A global review of the state of the evidence of household air pollution’s contribution to ambient fine particulate matter and their related health impacts</article-title>. <source>Environ Int</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Mar</month>;<volume>173</volume>:<fpage>107835</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2023.107835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36857905</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10378453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Air particulate matter and cardiovascular disease: the epidemiological, biomedical and clinical evidence</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Dis</source>. <year>2016</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>E8</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3978/j.issn.2072-1439.2015.11.37</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26904258</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4740122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shahsavani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tobías</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Querol</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Stafoggia</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdolshahnejad</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mayvaneh</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Short-term effects of particulate matter during desert and non-desert dust days on mortality in Iran</article-title>. <source>Environ Int</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>105299</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2019.105299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31751828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lwin</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tobias</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chua</surname>
<given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Thawonmas</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ith</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of desert dust and sandstorms on human health: A scoping review</article-title>. <source>GeoHealth</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Mar</month>
<day>1</day> [cited 2025 Sept 23];<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<elocation-id>e2022GH000728</elocation-id>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2022GH000728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9976568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36874170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fuller</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Landrigan</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Balakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bathan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bose-O’Reilly</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brauer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Pollution and health: a progress update</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>June</month>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e535</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00090-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35594895</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11995256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Oxidative stress and the cardiovascular effects of air pollution</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>May</month>
<day>1</day>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2020.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31923583</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7322534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Raftis</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Langrish</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McLean</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Samutrtai</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Connell</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Inhaled nanoparticles accumulate at sites of vascular disease</article-title>. <source>ACS nano</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>May</month>
<day>23</day> [cited 2025 Apr 11];<volume>11</volume>(<issue>5</issue>). DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.6b08551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5444047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28443337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ambient carbon monoxide and the risk of cardiovascular disease emergency room visits: a time-series study in Lanzhou, China</article-title>. <source>Environ Geochem Health</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Nov</month>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>7621</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-023-01653-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37395909</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>GBD 2021 Anaemia Collaborators</collab>. <article-title>Prevalence, years lived with disability, and trends in anaemia burden by severity and cause, 1990–2021: findings from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021</article-title>. <source>Lancet Haematol</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Sept</month>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e713</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3026(23)00160-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37536353</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10465717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khaniabadi</surname>
<given-names>YO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Daryanoosh</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hopke</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrante</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Marco</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sicard</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Acute myocardial infarction and COPD attributed to ambient SO2 in Iran</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>July</month>;<volume>156</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2017.04.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28477578</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaffari</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hajizadeh</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pourafkari</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shokouhi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tajlil</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mazani</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Air pollution and admissions due to ST elevation myocardial infarction-a time-series study from northwest of Iran</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>Dec</month>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>35</issue>):<fpage>27469</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2017.04.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28980195</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseinpoor</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Forouzanfar</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yunesian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Asghari</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naieni</surname>
<given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farhood</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Air pollution and hospitalization due to angina pectoris in Tehran, Iran: a time-series study</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. <year>2005</year>
<month>Sept</month>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2004.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16053936</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>HAP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ngoc</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname>
<given-names>THT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ton</surname>
<given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Van Le</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Air pollution and risk of respiratory and cardiovascular hospitalizations in a large city of the Mekong Delta Region</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Dec</month>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>60</issue>):<fpage>91165</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-022-22022-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35881281</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vahedian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khanjani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzaee</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Koolivand</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ambient air pollution and daily hospital admissions for cardiovascular diseases in Arak, Iran</article-title>. <source>ARYA Atheroscler</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>May</month>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29147121">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29147121</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29147121</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5677328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siregar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Idiawati</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Association between satellite-based estimates of long-term PM exposure and cardiovascular disease: evidence from the Indonesian Family Life Survey</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Mar</month>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>21156</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-17318-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34750763</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khaniabadi</surname>
<given-names>YO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hopke</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Daryanoosh</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jourvand</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Basiri</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiopulmonary mortality and COPD attributed to ambient ozone</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>152</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2016.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27842286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Geravandi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Foruozandeh</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Babaei</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alavi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Niri</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Cardiovascular and respiratory mortality attributed to ground-level ozone in Ahvaz, Iran</article-title>. <source>Environ Monit Assess</source>. <year>2015</year>
<month>Aug</month>;<volume>187</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>487</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-015-4674-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26141926</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdolahnejad</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jafari</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hajizadeh</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nikoonahad</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular, respiratory, and total mortality ascribed to PM and PM exposure in Isfahan, Iran</article-title>. <source>J Educ Health Promot</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>Dec</month>
<day>4</day>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jehp.jehp_166_16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29296610</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5747222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonyadi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrampoush</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaneian</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mokhtari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Cardiovascular, respiratory, and total mortality attributed to PM<sub>2.5</sub> in Mashhad, Iran</article-title>. <source>Environ Monit Assess</source>. <year>2016</year>
<month>Oct</month>;<volume>188</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>570</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-016-5574-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27640165</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hajizadeh</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jafari</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Momtaz</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fanaei</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abdolahnejad</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Concentrations and mortality due to short- and long-term exposure to PM in a megacity of Iran (2014-2019)</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>Oct</month>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>38004</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09695-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32617810</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadian-Khoshnoud</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Habibi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Manafi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Safarpour</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Soltanian</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Effects of air pollutant exposure on acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Heart Lung Circ</source>. <year>2023</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hlc.2022.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36428180</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Motesaddi Zarandi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hadei</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hashemi</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shahhosseini</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hopke</surname>
<given-names>PK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Namvar</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of ambient air pollutants on hospital admissions and deaths for cardiovascular diseases: a time series analysis in Tehran</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Mar</month>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>17997</fpage>–<lpage>8009</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-17051-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34677770</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sepandi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Akbari</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naseri</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alimohamadi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emergency hospital admissions for cardiovascular diseases attributed to air pollution in Tehran during 2016–2019</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2021</year>
<month>July</month>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>28</issue>):<fpage>38426</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-021-13377-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33733401</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nabavi</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jafari</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jalali</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nedjat</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashrafi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Salahesh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Environmental air pollution and acute cerebrovascular complications: an ecologic study in tehran, iran</article-title>. <source>Int J Prev Med</source>. <year>2012</year>
<month>Oct</month>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>723</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23112900">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23112900</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112900</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3483001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kermani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shahsavani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dowlati</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Asl</surname>
<given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karimzadeh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Estimation of short-term mortality and morbidity attributed to fine particulate matter in the ambient air of eight Iranian cities</article-title>. <source>Ann Glob Health</source>. <year>2018</year>
<month>Aug</month>
<day>31</day>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.29024/aogh.2308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30835377</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6748288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nhung</surname>
<given-names>NTT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schindler</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chau</surname>
<given-names>NQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hanh</surname>
<given-names>PT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hoang</surname>
<given-names>LT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dien</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Exposure to air pollution and risk of hospitalization for cardiovascular diseases amongst Vietnamese adults: Case-crossover study</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>Feb</month>
<day>10</day>;<volume>703</volume>:<fpage>134637</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31731158</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khaniabadi</surname>
<given-names>YO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Daryanoosh</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Borgini</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tittarelli</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Marco</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Exposure to PM<sub>10</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and O<sub>3</sub> and impacts on human health</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>2781</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-016-8038-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27837472</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bayat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ashrafi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shafiepour Motlagh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hassanvand</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Daroudi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Health impact and related cost of ambient air pollution in Tehran</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Sept</month>;<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>108547</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2019.108547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31247432</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gharehchahi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mahvi</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amini</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nabizadeh</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Akhlaghi</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shamsipour</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Health impact assessment of air pollution in Shiraz, Iran: a two-part study</article-title>. <source>J Environ Health Sci Eng</source>. <year>2013</year>
<month>June</month>
<day>28</day>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2052-336X-11-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24499576</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3776287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Toolabi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bonyadi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ramavandi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Health impacts quantification attributed to ambient particulate matter in the nearest Iranian city to the main dust source</article-title>. <source>Environ Monit Assess</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Aug</month>
<day>12</day>;<volume>194</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>666</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-022-10329-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35962291</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ebrahimi Aval</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrampoush</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Toolabi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nikonahad</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Human health impact assessment of exposure to particulate matter: an AirQ software modeling</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>July</month>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>16513</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-017-9189-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28555396</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dastoorpoor</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khanjani</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Idani</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aghababaeian</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bahrampour</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Lag time structure of cardiovascular deaths attributed to ambient air pollutants in Ahvaz, Iran, 2008–2015</article-title>. <source>Int J Occup Med Environ Health</source>. <year>2018</year>
<month>July</month>
<day>4</day>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13075/ijomeh.1896.01104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29546882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Downward</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hystad</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tasmin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Abe</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term exposure to particulate matter and all-cause and cause-specific mortality in an analysis of multiple Asian cohorts</article-title>. <source>Environ Int</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>July</month>;<volume>189</volume>(<issue>108803</issue>):<fpage>108803</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2024.108803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38870578</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jalali</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karbakhsh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Momeni</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Taheri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amini</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mansourian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Long-term exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub> and cardiovascular disease incidence and mortality in an Eastern Mediterranean country: findings based on a 15-year cohort study</article-title>. <source>Environ Health</source>. <year>2021</year>
<month>Oct</month>
<day>28</day>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>112</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12940-021-00797-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34711250</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8555193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baradaran</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Masoudipoor</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Frouzandeh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Modeling of the relationship between the environmental air pollution, clinical risk factors, and hospital mortality due to myocardial infarction in Isfahan, Iran</article-title>. <source>J Res Med Sci</source>. <year>2015</year>
<month>Aug</month>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1735-1995.168382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26664423</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4652309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Javanmardi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Morovati</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Farhadi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Geravandi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khaniabadi</surname>
<given-names>YO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Angali</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Monitoring the impact of ambient ozone on human health using time series analysis and air quality model approaches</article-title>. <source>Fresenius Environ Bull</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Miri</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Derakhshan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Allahabadi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveri Conti</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrante</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mortality and morbidity due to exposure to outdoor air pollution in Mashhad metropolis, Iran. The AirQ model approach</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. <year>2016</year>
<month>Nov</month>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>451</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2016.07.039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27565880</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Izawa</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Balakrishnan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chakma</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Menon</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Mortality associated with ambient PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure in India: Results from the Million Death Study</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. <year>2022</year>
<month>Sept</month>;<volume>130</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>97004</fpage>. <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9472672/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9472672/</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36102642</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1289/EHP9538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9472672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shamsipour</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hassanvand</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gohari</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yunesian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fotouhi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naddafi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>National and sub-national exposure to ambient fine particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub>) and its attributable burden of disease in Iran from 1990 to 2016</article-title>. <source>Environ Pollut</source>. <year>2019</year>
<month>Dec</month>;<volume>255</volume>(<issue>Pt 1</issue>):<fpage>113173</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.113173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31521993</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gurung</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname>
<given-names>JY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Particulate matter and risk of hospital admission in the Kathmandu Valley, Nepal: A case-crossover study</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2017</year>
<month>Sept</month>
<day>1</day>;<volume>186</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwx135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28911012</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sarizadeh</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jaafarzadeh</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roozbehani</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tahmasebi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moattar</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Relationship between the number of hospitalized cardiovascular and respiratory disease and the average concentration of criteria air pollutants (CAP) in Ahvaz</article-title>. <source>Environ Geochem Health</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>Oct</month>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3317</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00577-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32367271</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Azimi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hafezi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaderpoori</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kamarehie</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Karami</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sorooshian</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Temporal characteristics and health effects related to NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, and SO<sub>2</sub> in an urban area of Iran</article-title>. <source>Environ Pollut</source>. <year>2024</year>
<month>May</month>
<day>15</day>;<volume>349</volume>(<issue>123975</issue>):<fpage>123975</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.123975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38615834</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Akbarzadeh</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khaheshi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yousefi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Naderian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Namazi</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The association between exposure to air pollutants including PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, ozone, carbon monoxide, sulfur dioxide, and nitrogen dioxide concentration and the relative risk of developing STEMI: A case-crossover design</article-title>. <source>Environ Res</source>. <year>2018</year>
<month>Feb</month>;<volume>161</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>303</lpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2017.11.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29178978</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mayvaneh</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Baaghideh</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Entezari</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Utilizing daily excessive concentration hours to estimate cardiovascular mortality and years of life lost attributable to fine particulate matter in Tehran, Iran</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. <year>2020</year>
<month>Feb</month>
<day>10</day>;<volume>703</volume>(<issue>134909</issue>):<fpage>134909</fpage>. DOI: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31757557</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>