<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Sci Rep</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12528717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12528717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12528717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41093900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-19748-3</article-id><title-group><article-title>FLPSO-AMPS: an optimized WSN model for air quality monitoring in tier-2 smart cities</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>K</surname><given-names initials="L">Lingaraj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Malghan</surname><given-names initials="RL">Rashmi Laxmikant</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Rao M C</surname><given-names initials="K">Karthik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names initials="L">Lalit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>R H M</surname><given-names initials="SS">Somanath Swamy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>H M</surname><given-names initials="V">Vishwanatha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Rao Bahadur Y Mahabaleswarappa Engineering College, Ballari, 583104 Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Manipal Institute of Technology, Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal, 576104 Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Mechatronics, Manipal Institute of Technology, Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal, 576104 Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Computer Information System, University of Malta,  Msida, 2080 Malta </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Mechanical Engineering, Rao Bahadur Y Mahabaleswarappa Engineering College, Ballari, 583104 Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Mechanical and Industrial Engineering, Manipal Institute of Technology, Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal, 576104 Karnataka India </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label>Faculty of Information Technology, Industrial University of Ho Chi Minh, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>35989</fpage><page-range>35989</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_Article_19748.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path c52c/12528717/ec916af2200e/41598_2025_Article_19748.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 6333321?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Wireless Sensor Networks (WSNs) are composed of small, cost-effective sensing nodes that are primarily employed for the collection of environmental data. These networks are integral to various applications including industrial pollution monitoring, disaster management, and air quality regulation. However, WSNs encounter significant challenges, such as energy efficiency, end-to-end delay, and packet loss during data transmission. Existing methodologies often fall short in optimizing the network lifespan while ensuring reliable data delivery. To address these limitations, this study introduces FLPSO-AMPS, a novel Fuzzy Logic-based Particle Swarm Optimization (FLPSO) approach aimed at enhancing energy-efficient routing in WSN-based Air Pollution Monitoring Systems (APMS) for Tier-2 smart cities. The proposed approach leverages fuzzy logic principles combined with PSO to intelligently select optimal routing paths, thereby ensuring minimal energy consumption and enhanced network longevity. Unlike conventional methodologies, FLPSO-AMPS incorporates real-time pollutant data collection and mobility-aware optimization to improve network performance. The effectiveness of FLPSO-AMPS was validated through extensive simulations, demonstrating superior performance over existing approaches, particularly with improvements of 10% in energy efficiency, 15% in task delay, 24.5% in packet delivery ratio (PDR), 11.5% in packet loss ratio (PLR), and 20.1% in throughput. These findings underscore the potential of FLPSO-AMPS in establishing an intelligent, resource-efficient air quality monitoring framework for smart cities. Future research will explore security enhancements to safeguard data transmissions in APMS networks.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Energy science and technology, Engineering, Environmental sciences, Mathematics and computing</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 Jul 31; Accepted 2025 Sep 10; Collection date 2025.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The use of Wireless Sensor Networks (WSNs) is gaining global popularity. There is an immense need for significant improvement in flood disaster monitoring<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. The use of WSN for disaster monitoring presents certain benefits including cost-effectiveness, ease of management, and the ability to expand networks<sup><xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the capricious characteristics of natural calamities impede the dissemination of pertinent data to related sensor nodes, with minimal latency. A WSN is composed of several wirelessly linked sensor nodes. The proper functioning of software and hardware is contingent on their ability to adapt to new circumstances and meet evolving demands. These sensors exhibit diminutive size and restricted storage and processing capabilities. Owing to limited transmission energy, WSNs can communicate within a restricted range with specific neighboring nodes. According to<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>, nodes are dependent on cooperation to carry out various tasks, such as sensing, signal processing, routing, localization, and security<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">An air pollution monitoring system (APMS) is a crucial factor that impacts the standards of living, human well-being, and the ecosystem<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Typically, oversight of an air pollution monitoring program falls under the purview of the pollution control department and entails significant expenses. The use of wireless methodology is deemed a viable option for air pollution monitoring schemes owing to progress in communication technology. The implementation of an APMS involves the utilization of technologies, such as GSM and GPRS, which are associated with significant expenses in terms of both maintenance and installation. The implementation of an APMS offers benefits for monitoring various high-risk regions within a country<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. This is achieved through the provision of real-time data and alerts in the event of significant air quality degradation. Organizations have the potential to utilize these data to swiftly implement measures such as, evacuating specific areas or dispatching emergency response teams. The implementation of a wireless APMS involves the use of an air quality index(AQI) to categorize the distinct air pollution locations. The advancement of technology, particularly WSN, has transformed air pollution monitoring (APM) into a sophisticated smart air pollution monitoring system (SAPMS). This has facilitated monitoring of environmental parameters with greater precision and efficacy, thereby mitigating pollution and other undesirable environmental effects<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">To address these challenges, this study introduces FLPSO-AMPS, a fuzzy logic-based particle swarm optimization (FLPSO) approach aimed at enhancing energy-efficient routing in air pollution monitoring systems (APMS) for tier-2 smart cities. Traditional routing methods for WSN often exhibit limited adaptability to dynamic network conditions, resulting in suboptimal energy utilization and compromised data reliability<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. The proposed FLPSO-AMPS algorithm employs fuzzy logic principles and particle swarm optimization (PSO) to intelligently determine optimal network routes, thereby ensuring reduced energy consumption, enhanced data transmission reliability, and a prolonged network lifespan<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.This study provides an area for combining WSN technology with advanced efficiency approaches, effectively addressing the limitations of existing air pollution monitoring systems. The key contributions of this study include the development of an optimized routing scheme that improves data transmission efficiency in a WSN-based APMS. The implementation of a real-time air pollution monitoring system utilizing WSN nodes to track pollutants, such as AQI, PM2.5, PM10, CO, <inline-formula id="IEq1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e425" xlink:href="d33e425.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/08b41c90f37c/d33e425.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq2"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e431" xlink:href="d33e431.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fef4bf79bdd1/d33e431.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, and a comparative evaluation of the proposed method against existing state-of-the-art approaches in terms of PDR, EDP, PLR, and throughput<sup><xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. By providing a scalable and resource-efficient framework, FLPSO-AMPS offers a cost-effective solution for real-time pollution detection and monitoring, making a valuable contribution to smart city development. This study underscores the necessity for intelligent and adaptive routing strategies in WSN-based APMS and presents a novel approach that enhances network efficiency while ensuring reliable environmental monitoring. The proposed method bridges the gap between traditional energy-intensive routing protocols and modern optimization techniques, enabling smart cities to deploy sustainable and high-performance air quality monitoring systems<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. The findings of this study have the potential to improve urban air-quality monitoring, thereby contributing to environmental sustainability and public health protection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Related work</title><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title> Air pollution monitoring system</title><p id="Par5">This section outlines various techniques utilized for ineffective routing within the WSN and highlights the constraints of the study. Divya et al.<sup><xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> - designed a technique for monitoring AQI in WSN environments, highlighting the need for further research in this critical field. The proposed study advocates the development of a smart city that focuses on mitigating pollution and addressing environmental issues. Maurya et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>, implemented an APMS that was both cost-effective and reliable for use in developing countries. The scheme for monitoring pollutants in the atmosphere quantified the concentrations of CO and other toxic gases. The methodology relies on the use of the GPS and PRS. Furthermore, the analog information collected by the sensor was transmitted to the microcontroller unit, where it was converted into digital information and sent to a remote server in the cloud via a GPRS scheme, along with the corresponding positional information. The proposed methodology exhibited enhanced reliability owing to its reliance on the global positioning system. Siregar et al.<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> conducted air pollution monitoring and analysis at a specific location. The results were communicated to the administrator through a graphical user interface (GUI) utilizing an internet network. The protocol employed air pollution investigation approach based on the index standard panacea urara (ISPU), which has been previously utilized in indonesia. The research site has undergone an analysis of the concentrations of several gases, including CO2 and NO2, according to the results of the conducted tests. Handayani et al.<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> focused on the automation of air monitoring in enclosed parking areas by evaluating the exhaust emissions from motor vehicles. The present research focused on the development of a real-time operating system that is precise, resource-efficient, portable, reliable, cost-effective and compatible with interconnected networks that rely on internet protocols. The study presented herein offers pertinent information to the general populace, particularly individuals who frequently live in densely populated areas, with the aim of mitigating atmospheric contamination.</p><p id="Par6">Agnihotri et al.<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> extensively reviewed various studies and presented comprehensive insights into the components and constituents involved in the development of WSN. Wireless sensor network monitoring strategies have the potential to be expanded to encompass additional forms of pollution detection, such as those related to water, soil, and radioactive contamination. Moreover, the utilization of a communication protocol with high efficiency can facilitate the acquisition of information in a real-time setting, whereas the acquisition of information processing may be explored in future endeavors. Marques et al.<sup><xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> conducted a study on a stand-alone robot equipped with an air boot that demonstrated the ability to monitor indoor air quality. The study focused on corporations’ robotic systems that possess application programming interfaces to facilitate the dissemination of data on social media platforms and enable inter-connectivity with indoor monitoring systems. Guanochanga et al.<sup><xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> outlined the initial steps taken to implement a WSN to monitor air quality metrics in intelligent urban services. The main aim of this research was to design a wireless framework with minimal cost. IoT facilitates the visualization of a highly interconnected network of web applications with a GUI at an advanced level. The researchers investigated the feasibility of utilizing tangible instruments for gathering APM data in real-time and generating behavioral models of air pollution scenarios in urban areas. Naik et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> proposed the implementation of smart cities, particularly in terms of environmental monitoring, vehicular maintenance, and traffic management<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. Hojaiji et al.<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> presented a framework for APMS schemes that enabled real-time data collaboration.</p><p id="Par7">Laskar et al.<sup><xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> developed a surveillance system that focuse on air pollution. The system utilities an optimization technique to identify the global minimum based on real-time pollution data obtained from a wireless sensor network. A supplementary tool was activated to delineate pollution boundaries and suggest alternative pathways within a vast urban network, thereby assisting operators in determining the most efficient route to mitigate the spread of illness. Adumanu<sup><xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> utilized various WSN to assess real-time water quality, resulting in an optimized data communication schedule that conserves energy. In additionally, solar panels were used to improve the duration of the sensor hop. Gazis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> proposed the use of WSN to monitor underground routes that are covered and box-shaped to protect wildlife. The fundamental goal of this research was to implement commonly positioned routes and techniques and employ information synthesis to develop inexpensive and efficient tiny sensors that align with typical animal movement patterns. Luo et al.<sup><xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> performed studies on sensors and pollution monitoring network schemes, as well as different techniques for pollution recognition. Subsequently, a thorough examination of the models pertaining to the identification of contaminated resources was provided and interconnected. This study expounded upon certain constraints associated with the utilization of sensor systems in the context of the APM. The aforementioned survey revealed that the monitoring process incurred significant costs, owing to notable spatial and temporal inconsistencies. They employed a hybrid approach to schedule and deploy distinct features of the air pollution approach. Subsequently, a real-time air quality model was generated based on sensor readings. In addition, optimization techniques are utilized to assess the physical characteristics of the dispersion of air pollutants and to incorporate factual data obtained from contemporary pollution detection systems. Pavani et al.<sup><xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> devised a practical pollution monitoring system that utilizes a WSN to track the concentration levels of CO in a real-time setting. The experimental setup consisted of a testbed while five sequential hops, wherein CO sensors were calibrated to account for variations in the CO concentration levels<sup><xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. Furthermore, an alert system dispatches emails and messages to inform the system administrator of increasing CO levels at the earliest opportunity s<sup><xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–<xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">Recent works further enrich this landscape. Singh et al.<sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> introduced a hybrid genetic algorithm with greedy mutation for heterogeneous IoT-enabled WSNs, achieving over 30% improvement in lifetime compared to GA-based baselines . Complementarily, Del-Valle-Soto et al.<sup><xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> provided a systematic survey of clustering routing protocols using metaheuristic techniques, categorizing original, modified, and hybrid strategies, and highlighting bio-inspired methods as promising directions for energy-efficient routing. In the development of an optimized Wireless Sensor Network (WSN) model for air quality monitoring in tier-2 smart cities, several advanced technologies and frameworks play a crucial role<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–<xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> . One way to solve these environmental monitoring issues is by using IoT sensors, data processing algorithms and communication infrastructures<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Advanced communication technologies like 5g is that it enabled the use of IoT devices with real-time monitoring. This new implementation would help in live data collection and analysis to solve urban problems like network overload and security<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the IoT framework uses artificial intelligence and data analytics for efficient data management and rapid response to environmental changes<sup><xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>. It is imperative to also address data quality issues when monitoring air quality. To enhance the quality of time series data, a two-phase framework was proposed to detect outliers and to deal with the missing value utilizing machine learning algorithms and interpolation techniques<sup><xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>. The methodologies here ensure that air quality data is consistent and reliable, which is important for smart city applications. AI is not limited to just processing data; they are used in generative spatial AI models for urban planning and analysis. This makes predicting much easier and taking decisions easier and it also makes urban environment sustainable and resilient<sup><xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. At the same time, another important feature to have in place are privacy-preserving authentication schemes so as to secure the data which is gleaned from IoT sensors. It is important so as to prevent unauthorized access while ensuring that data integrity is maintained<sup><xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>. In smart cities tier-2, scalable and sustainable solutions with the combination of smart grids and renewable energy solutions are also essential. This integration solves sustainability, security, and affordability trilemma and enhances the efficiency of using resources<sup><xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">The WSNs were used to illustrate the effectiveness of multi mobile agent (MMA) based on data collection and aggregation. The installation of these agents must be carefully planned and tailored to the unique characteristics of WSN in order to guarantee their effectiveness<sup><xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>–<xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup>. Prior studies primarily focused on ascertaining the number of mobile agent (MA) to be implemented and the configuration of SNs for each MA<sup><xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>. This study involved tracing the origin nodes of each MA to map their respective journeys. These algorithms were employed to evaluate the effectiveness of the aggregation. The present research introduces a methodology for consolidating network nodes to determine the optimal route, considering multiple agents, energy conservation, and aggregation effectiveness within a minimal time-frame. This study also highlights the constraints of these techniques when applied to extensive networks.</p><p id="Par10">The predominant focus of contemporary research in the domain of WSN pertains to the minimization of energy consumption in the course of route design. The migration approach of an MA can have a substantial impact on energy usage and network durability, as indicated by previous studies<sup><xref rid="CR53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>–<xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup>. Determining the optimal configuration of SNs for traversal using MAs can present a formidable task.The purpose of this investigation was to find a solution to the challenges associated with IP in networks by applying MMA methodology. The innovative methodology for WSN consider the requirements of a satisfactory quantity of MA, an effective clustering of nodes, and ultimately the criterion of optimal route selection for each MA to cover all of its assigned SNs.</p><p id="Par11">Therefore, a centralized planning model was suggested, wherein the sink node determines the entire route schedule instead of being limited by energy consumption, as observed in previous systems. The current methodology presents certain concerns pertaining to data aggregation, specifically regarding the consolidation of all sensor nodes into a singular cluster, which warrants careful consideration. The selection of an appropriate sensor node to serve as a cluster head is a crucial consideration in the context of data aggregation, as it has implications for the extension of the network’s operational duration. Optimal itinerary planning pertaining to the extension of the sensor network lifespan and the concomitant reduction of data collection time warrants significant attention. The CM-FFA algorithm is suggested as a means of selecting an appropriate sensor node to serve as the cluster head. The BM-FPA algorithm<sup><xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> fails to address hot-spot issues, as per experimental studies.Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> demonstrates different air polloution monitoring systems</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of different air polloution monitoring system.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Refs</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Approach</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Advantages</bold></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Research gap</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Handayani et al.<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monitoring in enclosed parking areas</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Real-time, cost-effective, and portable</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hardware design and power-related attributes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Agnihotri et al.<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Review on WSN in pollution detection</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Comprehensive insights on WSN components</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Expansion to other forms of pollution detection</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marques et al.<sup><xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Robot equipped with air boot</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indoor air quality, API for data sharing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High computational complexity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Guanochanga et al.<sup><xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WSN for air quality in intelligent urban services</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cost-effective, real-time data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Potential for broader application</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Naik et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gas-sensing components</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Implementation in smart cities, multiple applications</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Potential for broader application</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dixit al.<sup><xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">E2R2D2: Energy-Efficient Robust Routing and Data Distribution Protocol for WSN-based Air Pollution Monitoring</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Enhanced energy efficiency and robust data routing in dynamic WSN environments</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lack of integration with mobile agents and fuzzy optimization for real-time adaptability</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abdul kareem et al.<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WSN-based air pollution monitoring system for university workstation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cost-effective monitoring for small-scale and localized environments</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited scalability, lacks advanced routing and optimization mechanisms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shi et al.<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mechanism model combined with deep learning for indoor air pollution prediction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accurate prediction using hybrid models in residential/commercial spaces</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indoor-focused; no real-time outdoor deployment or routing optimization</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Berniak-Woźny et al.<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Start-up–driven sustainability framework for incubator–city collaboration in smart cities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Encourages innovation ecosystems and stakeholder partnerships for sustainable growth</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lacks integration with IoT/AI-driven environmental monitoring and technical deployment</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Madan et al.<sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IoT with Elman neural network for smart waste management &amp; pollution forecasting</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Enables predictive waste/air-quality analysis with neural forecasting</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited scalability tests; energy efficiency and sensor reliability not addressed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sahu et al.<sup><xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Multi-objective optimization (digital twin + MDP + PSO) for smart parking</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Optimizes parking with Pareto fronts, enhancing urban mobility</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Focused on parking; does not extend to environmental sensing or WSN scalability</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Huo et al.<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AI-based quasi-natural experiment for green resilience in smart cities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shows AI benefits in sustainability and adaptive resilience</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Primarily policy-level; lacks detailed IoT/WSN-level deployment</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mahomed &amp; Saha<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Real-time digital twin integration with 5G</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Achieves real-time responsiveness and reduced latency in smart city monitoring</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Security, energy cost, and interoperability with low-cost WSN nodes remain gaps</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Salih et al.<sup><xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IoT in urban development: applications, case studies, challenges</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Provides a comprehensive landscape of IoT-enabled smart city implementations</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Broad overview; limited quantitative validation for air-quality monitoring</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alsalehy &amp; Bailey<sup><xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Two-phase ML framework for outlier detection and missing value imputation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Improves reliability of time-series gas/weather data</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Focused on data preprocessing; no routing/energy-efficiency integration for WSNs</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Huang et al.<sup><xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Generative spatial AI models for urban digital twin</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Facilitates predictive urban planning with spatial AI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited to planning; lacks integration with sensor reliability or real-time routing</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kim et al.<sup><xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Privacy-preserving authentication using PUF + biometrics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ensures data integrity and prevents unauthorized IoT access</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overheads on constrained WSN nodes not fully studied; deployment feasibility unclear</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Silva et al.<sup><xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Literature review on smart grids within smart cities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Identifies sustainability and resource efficiency gains through grid–IoT integration</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mainly grid-focused; limited discussion on environmental sensing and low-cost sensor networks</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="2"><title> Differences between the existing and proposed work</title><p id="Par12">Existing air pollution monitoring systems within Wireless Sensor Networks (WSNs) predominantly utilize conventional routing techniques, which are frequently constrained by high energy consumption, inefficient data transmission, and limited scalability. These methodologies often lack intelligent decision-making mechanisms, resulting in suboptimal network performance and diminished sensor longevity. Furthermore, many existing methods do not adequately address the real-time dynamic nature of environmental monitoring, thereby reducing their efficacy in urban environments where pollutant levels fluctuate rapidly due to industrial and vehicular emissions. In contrast to traditional methodologies, the FLPSO-AMPS approach to enhance routing and data transmission in WSN-based APMS. The primary distinctions between existing techniques and the proposed approach are as follows: </p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par13">Incorporation of Advanced Pollutant Detection : Unlike previous approaches that primarily monitor a limited set of pollutants such as CO, <inline-formula id="IEq3"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e889" xlink:href="d33e889.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fef4bf79bdd1/d33e889.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq4"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e895" xlink:href="d33e895.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/08b41c90f37c/d33e895.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, FLPSO-AMPS encompasses a broader spectrum of environmental contaminants, including ethane, acetylene, methanol, formaldehyde, formic acid, ammonia, naphthalene, and lead, thereby ensuring a more comprehensive assessment of air quality.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par14">Intelligent and Adaptive Routing Mechanism : Existing systems typically employ fixed or heuristic-based routing algorithms that do not dynamically adapt to network conditions. In contrast, FLPSO-AMPS utilizes fuzzy logic and PSO, facilitating real-time adaptation to changes in network topology, optimizing energy consumption, and enhancing data transmission reliability.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par15">Enhanced Scalability and Real-Time Performance: Traditional methods encounter challenges in real-time data collection due to limited computing resources and high communication overhead. The FLPSO-AMPS framework optimizes the energy efficiency of multi-mobile agent routing, enabling scalable deployment in Tier-2 smart cities, where cost-effective and efficient solutions are imperative.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par16">Comparison with SOTA Techniques : The proposed method is rigorously evaluated against well-established PSO-based routing techniques such as ELDC and IEESEP. Simulation results demonstrate that FLPSO-AMPS consistently outperforms these methods, achieving 10% better energy efficiency, a 15% reduction in task delay, a 24.5% higher PDR, an 11.5% lower PLR, and a 20.1% increase in throughput.</p></list-item></list><p>By integrating fuzzy logic with PSO-based optimization, the FLPSO-AMPS framework offers a more energy-efficient, adaptive, and scalable solution for real-time APM. The suggested technology is designed to support smart city applications, enabling policymakers and environmental agencies to make data-driven decisions for pollution control and urban planning.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="1"><title>Fuzzy logic-based particle swarm optimization in air quality monitoring system</title><p id="Par17">The main objective of this research is to investigate the effects of air pollution on human health. Numerous health disorders that cause a wide range of illnesses, have been associated with air pollution. Air pollution is a crucial determinant of both human health and environmental concerns and encompasses a diverse array of hazardous gases, chemicals, and minute particulate matter. The primary sources of these pollutants are vehicle and industrial emissions as well as volatile organic compounds. Air pollution is a significant peril to human health; therefore, it is imperative to eradicate air pollution as a fundamental requirement for achieving optimal health. Researchers conducted an investigation utilizing mobile sensors to explore the feasibility of implementing a mobile sensor network for environmental monitoring in smart cities. Additionally, they examined the impact of mobility on the measurement accuracy. Diverse data sources, encompassing both objective (derived from sensors) and subjective (reported by PCD), are integrated to generate significant indicators and facilitate discourse between the wider populace and municipal authorities.</p><p id="Par18">AQI indicators are derived exclusively from objective data. The sensor array gathered various environmental indicators, including but not limited to <inline-formula id="IEq5"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e923" xlink:href="d33e923.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f937e0388203/d33e923.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, hydrocarbons, <inline-formula id="IEq6"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e929" xlink:href="d33e929.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/2778c35b8a7c/d33e929.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, and PM pollutants. The metrics, which rely exclusively on empirical data, are subsequently disseminated to diverse stakeholders, such as the general population, researchers, and local government officials. The level of air quality (LAQ) is used to determine the concentration of pollutants in the air :</p><disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e935" xlink:href="d33e935.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/583224db7d53/d33e935.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>As demonstrated by Eq.(<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>), there exists a discernible disparity between the maximum and minimum LAQ values, denoted as <inline-formula id="IEq7"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e945" xlink:href="d33e945.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/047497b953d5/d33e945.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e952" xlink:href="d33e952.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f51061db21d4/d33e952.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, respectively. The sensor denoted as <inline-formula id="IEq9"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e958" xlink:href="d33e958.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f35516de8faf/d33e958.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> exhibited the lowest level of pollution, while the sensor designated as <inline-formula id="IEq10"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e964" xlink:href="d33e964.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/0be0e90790c9/d33e964.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> demonstrated the highest degree of pollution. The results indicate that the sensor with the least amount of pollution exhibits the lowest LAQ values, whereas the sensor with the highest level of pollution displays the highest LAQ values, as demonstrated in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>) The acquisition of reliable information regarding pollution in a specific area can be achieved using sensors and the subsequent indicators they offer.</p><p id="Par19">The air quality of a specific region m was determined as follows:</p><disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e975" xlink:href="d33e975.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/356e4d882b37/d33e975.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>The accuracy of model <inline-formula id="IEq11"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e982" xlink:href="d33e982.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/acd9286ea8d7/d33e982.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> compared to the actual truth of model z, as given in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>), in accordance with the RE.</p><p id="Par20">Surveillance of the surroundings in which collections are stored is of utmost importance in order to obtain an understanding of and assess the conditions under which they are maintained. The use of a time-series model enables the simulation of the prospective behavior of a system, thereby providing short-term predictions denoted as <inline-formula id="IEq12"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e993" xlink:href="d33e993.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ed1fe6f12a59/d33e993.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and prediction ranges p and E for the stressors in question.</p><disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e999" xlink:href="d33e999.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/6d84cf82473b/d33e999.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>Eq. (<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>) demonstrates that (x; <inline-formula id="IEq13"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1009" xlink:href="d33e1009.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cab6347f1d8d/d33e1009.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) denotes the estimate error, <inline-formula id="IEq14"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1015" xlink:href="d33e1015.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/11527d006279/d33e1015.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the nonlinear regression, and <inline-formula id="IEq15"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1022" xlink:href="d33e1022.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/26b760a1eae5/d33e1022.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes the parameter vector. Pollution has an impact on land, air, and water on earth by releasing contaminants into these three environments. Some types of pollutant released into the atmosphere include smog, contaminated air, and toxic gas emissions. In addition to natural sources, human activities can lead to pollution.</p><p id="Par21">The architecture of an APMS is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The mobile agent in wsn is responsible for gathering data from multiple interconnected devices. MA emphasizes the collection of data from sensors located at each observation point for air pollution. The two primary tasks involved in this process are the retrieval of data from sensors and the creation of middleware that utilities mobile agents to transmit the data to the sink node. This middleware is known as Eagilla<sup><xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> and is agent-based in nature. The process of collecting and aggregating data occurs in this domain because of the abundance of available data sources. The sink node is responsible for pre-processing and filtering tasks because it contains superfluous data. The transmission of data from the sink node to the cloud requires the implementation of an intermediary communication layer. This layer comprises various communication technologies such as LTE and Wi-Fi. This is the location where all the sensor data are transmitted for cloud-based data processing. This cloud infrastructure can be utilized as gateways capable of real-time processing. Cloud computing has the potential to enhance the cloud latency. This location facilitates real-time decision making. Data management constitutes the fundamental layer responsible for information storage and analysis. The integration of multiple external technologies is feasible in this context, as expeditious data processing is imperative for analytical purposes<sup><xref rid="CR57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup> . The data acquisition stratum of a smart urban environment aggregates information from a multitude of interconnected devices such as sensors.</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Architecture of air pollution monitoring system.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO1" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/30d9d73f6c48/41598_2025_19748_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 999?><?original-width 1770?><?scaled-height 400?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/d1fc45b40a2e/41598_2025_19748_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par22">Bayesian regression produces additional instances DF(z;<inline-formula id="IEq16"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1050" xlink:href="d33e1050.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cab6347f1d8d/d33e1050.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) is given as</p><disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1056" xlink:href="d33e1056.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cbd44377c7b6/d33e1056.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>As demonstrated in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>), forecasts <inline-formula id="IEq17"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1066" xlink:href="d33e1066.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ed1fe6f12a59/d33e1066.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, the noise has a specific probability distribution N, the objective of signal z and m size of the population. Distributed data estimation methods can be employed using the distance measures DI(R) as follows:</p><disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1072" xlink:href="d33e1072.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/162763dcce06/d33e1072.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>As illustrated in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref>), a weighted average is employed, to estimate the g value for a given query point <inline-formula id="IEq18"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1083" xlink:href="d33e1083.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/5dd246941568/d33e1083.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, where a distance-based function <inline-formula id="IEq19"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1089" xlink:href="d33e1089.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e3dc061e1f2b/d33e1089.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> determines the weights. The observed function demonstrated a gradual decrease in the range between R and <inline-formula id="IEq20"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1095" xlink:href="d33e1095.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cc2a341634f5/d33e1095.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. This location serves as an educational resource for individuals seeking to expand their knowledge on pollution and determine actionable steps towards its mitigation. A web-based APM service (P) is designed to provide users with the ability to track various air pollution metrics.</p><disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1101" xlink:href="d33e1101.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/737a386be63e/d33e1101.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>The user interface is denoted by <inline-formula id="IEq21"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1108" xlink:href="d33e1108.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/417501517b1b/d33e1108.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, whereas the device status is indicated by <inline-formula id="IEq22"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1115" xlink:href="d33e1115.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/afcbc8f35212/d33e1115.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref>). In addition, the real-time data storage on the server is represented by variable j. Air pollution has no discernible effect on individuals who are in good health. Variable B (x; <inline-formula id="IEq23"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1124" xlink:href="d33e1124.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cab6347f1d8d/d33e1124.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) is defined as the air quality level during the test days given that it is at a sufficiently high level.</p><disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1130" xlink:href="d33e1130.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/77064a5ea070/d33e1130.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>As illustrated in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>), a current services C(x; <inline-formula id="IEq24"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1140" xlink:href="d33e1140.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cab6347f1d8d/d33e1140.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> ) s utilized in order to assess the strength of living organisms <inline-formula id="IEq25"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1147" xlink:href="d33e1147.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/b986aabc597c/d33e1147.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, and monitor weather conditions <inline-formula id="IEq26"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1153" xlink:href="d33e1153.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/d38693826c1b/d33e1153.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>.</p><p id="Par23">A comprehensive web-based platform has been developed to collect, organize, store, and retrieve data and knowledge from various sources in real time. This platform allows data modification, analysis, and visualization, utilizing online portals and SMS notifications. The GPS technology integrated into the 4G model enables real-time surveillance and seamless connectivity to LTE networks.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="1"><title>Methodology</title><p id="Par24">To address the limitations of existing routing algorithms, especially in terms of adaptiveness and energy efficiency in dynamic wsn environments. this study introduces the Fuzzy Logic-enhanced Particle Swarm Optimization (FLPSO). The proposed method aims to integrate fuzzy rule-based intelligence with swarm optimization to enhance real-time decision-making, minimize energy usage, and reduce latency. The following section elaborates on the structural and algorithmic design of FLPSO.</p><p id="Par25">As noted earlier, the proposed FLPSO method utilizes three input parameters. To mitigate the problem of fuzzy rule explosion, the number of input variables was limited to three. This is because increasing the number of inputs in the fuzzy logic model (FLM) leads to a more complex rule base. Alternatively, approaches like the Hierarchical Fuzzy System (HFS)<sup><xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup> have been developed to reduce the size of the rule base without compromising the system’s accuracy.</p><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="2"><title>Initialization</title><p id="Par26">The FLPSO framework incorporates a diverse set of swarm sensor particles. Each sensor particle, denoted as <inline-formula id="IEq27"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1175" xlink:href="d33e1175.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e97501081eff/d33e1175.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, operates within a physical coordinate system, where D represents the set of varying positional dimensions<sup><xref rid="CR68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup>. The <inline-formula id="IEq28"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1185" xlink:href="d33e1185.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/62776ed5b376/d33e1185.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> sensor particle <inline-formula id="IEq29"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1191" xlink:href="d33e1191.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e97501081eff/d33e1191.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> distinct position is illustrated in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="disp-formula">8</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1201" xlink:href="d33e1201.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/2bd0f2eef810/d33e1201.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>Each sensor particle <inline-formula id="IEq30"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1208" xlink:href="d33e1208.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/3eca6a02cc6c/d33e1208.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> occupies a position in the network space, represented by the coordinates (<inline-formula id="IEq31"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1214" xlink:href="d33e1214.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/90c990058147/d33e1214.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) as illustration in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1223" xlink:href="d33e1223.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/05a97ed71164/d33e1223.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>where i represents the number of sensors.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="2"><title>Fuzzy logic input metrics</title><p id="Par27">Normalization across deployments. To ensure portability across cities, RE, DC, and NN are normalized using a short calibration run to estimate deployment percentiles. All membership functions are then defined on the [0,1] scale, enabling the same rule base (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>) to operate without change while only rescaling breakpoints to local operating ranges.</p><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="3"><title>Node’s remaining energy</title><p id="Par28">Represents the residual power of a node, computed in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ10" ref-type="disp-formula">10</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1244" xlink:href="d33e1244.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fc6158afcc2e/d33e1244.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="3"><title>Distance to the source node</title><p id="Par29">Denotes the Euclidean distance between a candidate node and the source node<sup><xref rid="CR69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></sup> is provided in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ11" ref-type="disp-formula">11</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1261" xlink:href="d33e1261.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/29218cf6b8df/d33e1261.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>where (<inline-formula id="IEq32"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1268" xlink:href="d33e1268.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/d9c118a3755c/d33e1268.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq33"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1274" xlink:href="d33e1274.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cde039b0b902/d33e1274.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> ) denote the coordinates of the next source node and (<inline-formula id="IEq34"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1281" xlink:href="d33e1281.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e4c1fc177e7f/d33e1281.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> ) represent the coordinates of each CN.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="3"><title>Number of neighbors</title><p id="Par30">Reflects nearby nodes within transmission range, influencing route redundancy and stability. A higher neighbor count reduces risk of node isolation and enhances routing efficiency<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="2"><title>FLM design in PSO</title><p id="Par31">The main goal of this investigation is to find the best possible routing path for mobile agents by applying the Particle Swarm Optimization(PSO). At every next-hop decision, the proposed FLPSO method considers three significant parameters of the path the mobile agent is moving along that need to be evaluated. The fuzzy logic model (FLM) displayed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> . FLPSO considers the conditional probabilities relevant to each possible node to decide the best next hop for the movement of the agents<sup><xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,<xref rid="CR71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup>. Each of these four phases is described further below.</p><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>FLPSO inference system.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO2" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/a61d22e6a204/41598_2025_19748_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1212?><?original-width 1770?><?scaled-height 485?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/be9e63f88860/41598_2025_19748_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="3"><title>Fuzzification</title><p id="Par32">At this time specific input variables for each candidate node such as residual energy, distance and number of neighbor are collected as reported in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. In a fuzzy set, the role of membership function and linguistic parameters is important to represent the real conditions as well as possible. While traditional sets contain only numerical values, fuzzy sets are represented using language or expressions to carry their meaning. Linguistic inputs were interpreted using triangular and trapezoidal membership functions within the FLPSO approach in this analysis. Regarding Eq. (<xref rid="Equ12" ref-type="disp-formula">12</xref>) and Eq. (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="disp-formula">13</xref>), triangular and trapezoidal membership functions were chosen for their computational simplicity and good performance in real time applications, being applicable to both input and output fuzzy variables<sup><xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,<xref rid="CR73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></sup>.</p><disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1336" xlink:href="d33e1336.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/531ec71eefeb/d33e1336.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p><italic>d</italic>1, <italic>e</italic>1 and <italic>f</italic>1 are parameters that define the geometry and placement of the triangular shape. Eq. (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="disp-formula">13</xref>) represents the standard form of the trapezoidal membership function.</p><disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1355" xlink:href="d33e1355.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/9b43c38769e7/d33e1355.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>The parameters <italic>d</italic>2, <italic>e</italic>2, <italic>f</italic>2 and <italic>d</italic>2 characterize the structure and location of the trapezoidal function.</p><p id="Par33">This is graphically depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, which presents the membership function associated to the residual energy parameter. The linguistic variables considered in this setting are A, B, and C. Membership values for these linguistic categories are defined within the following intervals: A from 0 to 0.1, B is 0.5, and C: 0.9 – 1.</p><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>RE degree of membership function.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO3" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/c5e0522a6fe7/41598_2025_19748_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 801?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 401?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/5d8c20044ceb/41598_2025_19748_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par34">The linguistic variables P, Q and R are modeled using triangular membership functions, each with a membership value ranging from 0 to 1. As illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, the P variable spans values from 0 to 0.5, while R ranges from 0.6 to 1. The Q variable is centered at 0.5.</p><fig id="Fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Distance degree of membership function.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO4" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/d639ad5359dd/41598_2025_19748_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 640?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 320?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig4_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/1bcde1b4ef15/41598_2025_19748_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par35">Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> presents the membership function corresponding to the number of neighbors. The linguistic variables used in this context are X, Y, and Z. The X variable covers the range from 0 to 0.1, Z spans from 0.3 to 1, and Y is centered around 0.2.</p><fig id="Fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Node neighbor degree of membership function.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO5" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e4713edf1bc8/41598_2025_19748_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 677?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 339?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig5_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/60910b9a07cc/41598_2025_19748_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="3"><title>Rule evaluation</title><p id="Par36">The fuzzy output set is derived using a series of IF-THEN rules, which are formulated as conditional statements based on the membership values of the input variables. The fuzzy logical operator (AND) is employed to evaluate the conjunction of multiple input conditions within each rule. The complete set of IF-THEN rules is presented in table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Fuzzy IF-THEN rules in FLPSO approach.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Remaining Energy</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Distance</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Node Neighbor</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> probability</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">L-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Medium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">L-Medium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Medium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">L-Medium</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">L-Low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">L-High</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Q</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-High</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-High</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">C</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">R</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Z</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V-High</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec15" disp-level="3"><title>Fuzzy inference system and aggregation</title><p id="Par37">At this phase, input observations are used to combine fuzzy rules and generate a unified fuzzy result. The Mamdani inference technique<sup><xref rid="CR74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></sup> was selected for its ease of implementation in deriving output values across various possible nodes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" disp-level="3"><title>Defuzzification</title><p id="Par38">Once the outputs of all fuzzy rules have been aggregated, the defuzzification process is applied to generate a crisp output. In this study, the Center of Area (CoA) method<sup><xref rid="CR75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></sup>. The commonly used defuzzification technique–was employed to compute the final crisp value. The corresponding calculation is presented in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ14" ref-type="disp-formula">14</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1703" xlink:href="d33e1703.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/10e6a642840e/d33e1703.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>Here, w represents the output obtained after defuzzification and <inline-formula id="IEq35"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1710" xlink:href="d33e1710.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/0959eb62650f/d33e1710.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes the aggregated membership function. The probability range was partitioned into nine linguistic levels at intervals of 2.5 cm, as depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. For a CN, a higher defuzzified output value increases the likelihood of it being selected as the next migration hop for the mobile agent.</p><fig id="Fig6" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Membership of the probability value.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO6" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig6_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/1e2e77f6932b/41598_2025_19748_Fig6_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 825?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 413?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig6_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ba7eadb3e33f/41598_2025_19748_Fig6_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17" disp-level="2"><title>Velocity and practice position update</title><p id="Par39">In each iteration t, the sensor particles <inline-formula id="IEq36"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1731" xlink:href="d33e1731.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e97501081eff/d33e1731.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> update their individual best-known positions <inline-formula id="IEq37"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1737" xlink:href="d33e1737.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/bf365ef05ad4/d33e1737.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq38"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1743" xlink:href="d33e1743.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/b9edbc5b1293/d33e1743.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>.. Each particle moves toward <inline-formula id="IEq39"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1749" xlink:href="d33e1749.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/b9edbc5b1293/d33e1749.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, by updating its velocity <inline-formula id="IEq40"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1755" xlink:href="d33e1755.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/41de74de39cc/d33e1755.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and positions <inline-formula id="IEq41"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1762" xlink:href="d33e1762.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/6cb30f54d262/d33e1762.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> during each iteration. The calculation for the velocity <inline-formula id="IEq42"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1768" xlink:href="d33e1768.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/41de74de39cc/d33e1768.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is provided in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ15" ref-type="disp-formula">15</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>15</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1777" xlink:href="d33e1777.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f67e92444fd9/d33e1777.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>where <inline-formula id="IEq43"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1784" xlink:href="d33e1784.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/6857bed9aaba/d33e1784.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> represent the acceleration coefficients, which are constant values. w denotes the inertial weight. The<inline-formula id="IEq44"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1790" xlink:href="d33e1790.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/34887f620a32/d33e1790.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> are random values uniformly distributed between 0 and 1. The position update of <inline-formula id="IEq45"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1797" xlink:href="d33e1797.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e97501081eff/d33e1797.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is given by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ16" ref-type="disp-formula">16</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ16"><label>16</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1806" xlink:href="d33e1806.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e8bbf3feda6d/d33e1806.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></sec><sec id="Sec18" disp-level="2"><title>Fitness function evaluation</title><p id="Par40">After each iteration, the sensor particles update their positions, and the fitness function<sup><xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> is evaluated to determine whether a particle has achieved the global best position Gbest. The fitness function evaluation is conducted using the formulas provided in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ17" ref-type="disp-formula">17</xref>) and Eq. (<xref rid="Equ18" ref-type="disp-formula">18</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ17"><label>17</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1826" xlink:href="d33e1826.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f8bc12099a2d/d33e1826.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ18"><label>18</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1832" xlink:href="d33e1832.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/0ee478c45a78/d33e1832.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></sec><sec id="Sec19" disp-level="2"><title> Fuzzy logic based particle swarm optimization MIP</title><p id="Par42">The FLPSO technique, which is a sophisticated computational framework based on the FLM, employs decision-making instruments to enhance networks efficiency<sup><xref rid="CR58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup> . The FLPSO technique comprises three distinct stages. The initial phase functions in the following manner: selecting an optimal sink node and determining an accurate cluster size are crucial for achieving an equal load distribution during processing. The second step involves utilizing FLM to calculate the likelihood of nodes based on input parameters such as the remaining energy (RE) of the node, its distance from the source node (DC), and its number of neighbors. The resulting output characteristics are restricted by the probability of forming specifier paths to the MAs<sup><xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup>. Third, each MA traverse the network in accordance with predetermined paths prior to commencing the process of acquiring information, as depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>. The generated routes aim to encompass all nodes within the network. The sink node assumes the responsibility of allocating MAs to a specific group to gather the data. The MA individually gathers information from the assigned groups. To streamline local interactions and minimise reporting delays, we employed a variety of MAs. The methodology employed for determining the quantity of sensory data to be gathered by multi-agent systems is analogous to that outlined in references<sup><xref rid="CR60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="CR61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup>.The pseudocode of the FLPSOMIP algorithm tailored for WSNs is presented in <xref rid="Sec19" ref-type="sec">1</xref>. The fuzzy logic rule evaluation incurs a computational time complexity of O(<inline-formula id="IEq46"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1874" xlink:href="d33e1874.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/6551016c0d79/d33e1874.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) where m is the number of input metrics (e.g., residual energy, delay), k the number of membership functions per metric, and n the number of fuzzy rules. For our implementation, m=3, k=3, and n=27, leading to a lightweight inference process.</p><fig id="Fig7" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>FLPSOMIP in WSN.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO7" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig7_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/7efc2f2c4fd1/41598_2025_19748_Fig7_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 900?><?original-width 944?><?scaled-height 600?><?scaled-width 629?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig7_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/1cfd1c867d4b/41598_2025_19748_Fig7_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig>
<fig id="Figa" position="anchor"><?disp-level 3?><label>Algorithm 1</label><caption><p>FLPSO Algorithm for Optimized Routing in Air Pollution Monitoring Systems.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO8" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Figa_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/c390c1c7d1f5/41598_2025_19748_Figa_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2237?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 745?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Figa_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/a201a89587a2/41598_2025_19748_Figa_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig>
</sec><sec id="Sec20" disp-level="2"><title>Congestion-aware FLPSO and hierarchical scaling</title><p id="Par44">To extend FLPSO-AMPS beyond small deployments, we introduce scalability mechanisms. First, the fitness function is augmented with congestion-awareness, incorporating both queue length (q) and link utilization</p><disp-formula id="Equ19"><label>19</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1894" xlink:href="d33e1894.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/11c6e51b27d4/d33e1894.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>This ensures that next-hop decisions avoid overloaded nodes and links. Second, we adopt hierarchical clustering, with residual-energy-based cluster-head rotation and multiple sinks to reduce path length and contention. Third, mobile-agent itineraries are partitioned across clusters so that latency grows sublinearly with network size. These enhancements preserve energy efficiency while stabilizing throughput and packet delivery ratio in large-scale deployments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21" disp-level="2"><title>Tuning and sensitivity of fuzzy rules</title><p id="Par45">The FLPSO-AMPS fuzzy controller employs triangular/trapezoidal membership functions for three network-centric inputs: remaining energy (RE), distance to source (DC), and number of neighbors (NN) (see Section 3.2). To generalize across cities with different densities and traffic dynamics, inputs are first normalized via deployment statistics. Let <inline-formula id="IEq47"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1905" xlink:href="d33e1905.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/12e845d23bdb/d33e1905.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and let<inline-formula id="IEq48"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1911" xlink:href="d33e1911.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/c9f169510b4d/d33e1911.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denote the empirical 5th–95th percentiles measured during a short calibration phase. We then scale <inline-formula id="IEq49"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1917" xlink:href="d33e1917.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ce155fb91d35/d33e1917.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and clip values outside this range. Initial membership breakpoints ((<italic>d</italic>, <italic>e</italic>, <italic>f</italic>, <italic>g</italic>)) for each linguistic label are seeded from percentiles (e.g., 25%, 50%, 75%) of <inline-formula id="IEq50"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1936" xlink:href="d33e1936.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/0dd05881fc25/d33e1936.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>.</p><p id="Par46">We refine <inline-formula id="IEq51"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1944" xlink:href="d33e1944.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/28f1c5764d95/d33e1944.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> using a constrained lightweight optimizer (PSO/Bayesian search) that maximizes a cross-validated objective:</p><disp-formula id="Equ20"><label>20</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1950" xlink:href="d33e1950.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/354b92cd7d14/d33e1950.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>subject to monotonicity constraints that preserve interpretability: <inline-formula id="IEq52"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1957" xlink:href="d33e1957.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/38adc9866a5d/d33e1957.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula></p><p id="Par47">The fuzzy rule base remains fixed only membership parameters <inline-formula id="IEq53"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1964" xlink:href="d33e1964.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/90e04dd97594/d33e1964.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and input scalers are tuned, keeping per-hop inference complexity unchanged.</p><p id="Par48">Robustness is quantified by two complementary analyses: </p><list list-type="label"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p id="Par49">Local one-at-a-time (OAT) perturbations of each membership breakpoint by <inline-formula id="IEq54"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1978" xlink:href="d33e1978.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ac09a7836ac7/d33e1978.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, while tracking performance metrics <inline-formula id="IEq55"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1984" xlink:href="d33e1984.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cbaa81212d0a/d33e1984.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="Par50">Global variance-based sensitivity analysis (Sobol indices) over the joint space of <inline-formula id="IEq56"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1995" xlink:href="d33e1995.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/edd700580a15/d33e1995.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and traffic intensity <inline-formula id="IEq57"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2001" xlink:href="d33e2001.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/95c7c0c413ff/d33e2001.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list><p>We also evaluate context shifts (traffic-dominated vs. industrial-dominated vs. mixed corridors) by altering spatial load maps and link reliabilities. These studies show that the controller’s performance degrades gracefully under parameter drift and that the relative influence of RE, NN, and DC aligns with intuition across contexts.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22" disp-level="1"><title>Data collection, experimental setup, and APMS analysis</title><sec id="Sec23" disp-level="2"><title> Sensor deployment and data collection</title><p id="Par51">The ballari district is an excellent example of a neighborhood comprising detached homes, attached houses, and apartments. The air quality in this area is predominantly affected by factors such as the use of building components, industrial emissions of CFCs, trash burning, road dust,fine ash and agricultural waste. The high residential density in urban locations can lead to significant smoke nuisance for immediate neighbors<sup><xref rid="CR62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup>. Additionally, local air quality can deteriorate due to geographical and weather conditions, particularly on cold and windy days. Our campaign utilized sensory data collected between january 1, 2023, and april 30, 2023. We deployed thirty-three devices in various locations corresponding to the city ward shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>. The measurement analysis focused on an area of approximately 8 <inline-formula id="IEq58"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2021" xlink:href="d33e2021.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/72957f2cecc4/d33e2021.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. The experiment aimed to assess the performance and accuracy of these cost-effective devices in the target area. Further experiments were conducted in the winter and summer of 2023 to evaluate the effectiveness of using the generated data by comparing it with the information provided by the pollution board and specific contaminants in the region<sup><xref rid="CR63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup>.</p><fig id="Fig8" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Photo of the monitoring node. (<bold>b</bold>) low-cost sensors used in our Ballari campaign.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO9" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig8_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/6d64e4808ee0/41598_2025_19748_Fig8_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 942?><?original-width 1770?><?scaled-height 377?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig8_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/c7325804c9b3/41598_2025_19748_Fig8_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par52">To validate our sensor measurements, we used the AQM station as the primary reference station. The measurement campaign occurred in the ballari district, adjacent to the hospet neighborhood, where the vijayanagara air quality station is situated. This station, located in the northern hospet, is approximately 3 km away from the city center. Ballari is renowned for its thermal power plant, industries, and iron ore mining, resulting in pollution from waste burning, coal, and wood and transportation. This motivated us to install affordable sensors and conduct a measurement campaign in the ballari district. The vijayanagara station, with its sampling intake positioned approximately 8 m above the ground, is an urbanized sensing station that monitors various aspects, such as greenery, roads, parking lots, and buildings. We collected data from the vijayanagara station to assess readings from our compact sensors. We computed the average of our sensor data as 1-hour averages, aligning them with the information gathered from the Vijayanagara station. We conducted a comparison between the readings obtained from our experiment and the data collected from vijayanagara station, thereby validating the performance of our measurements. the deployment of 33 sensors effectively ensures comprehensive spatial coverage and facilitates the detection of pollution patterns, conducting a formal cost-benefit analysis is crucial, particularly for scalability in Tier-2 cities. The initial deployment costs encompass sensor procurement, communication modules, and integration into the FLPSO-AMPS framework. Long-term maintenance costs, including periodic battery replacement, data transmission infrastructure upkeep, and sensor recalibration, can substantially affect the feasibility. In Tier-2 urban environments with limited municipal budgets, these recurring expenses present significant sustainability challenges. Additionally, environmental factors, such as dust accumulation, temperature drift, and humidity fluctuations, can lead to calibration errors over time, thereby impacting data fidelity. Addressing these issues necessitates the integration of self-calibration algorithms and robust error-compensation techniques. To address calibration drift and environmental interference common in low-cost sensors, each node incorporates a self-calibration routine. This includes periodic zero-point resets and offset estimation based on environmental baselines. Calibration flags are raised when deviations exceed thresholds, prompting remote updates or technician checks.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24" disp-level="2"><title> Low-cost sensors</title><p id="Par53">To detect and monitor microparticle densities, we installed the Wisen ZH06-III laser dust sensor. This device provides accurate PM 2.5 and PM 10 particle mass readings, representing the proportion of nanoparticles with aerodynamics diameters less than 2.5 <inline-formula id="IEq59"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2051" xlink:href="d33e2051.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/355db155d4f0/d33e2051.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and 10 <inline-formula id="IEq60"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2057" xlink:href="d33e2057.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/355db155d4f0/d33e2057.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> , respectively. It is accurate and highly reliable within a range of 0 - 10,000 particles/ <inline-formula id="IEq61"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2063" xlink:href="d33e2063.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ece75a12d25e/d33e2063.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> . For the detection of VOCs, which are HC based substances with high vapor pressure, we utilized the Ogam Technology GSBT11-P110 VOC sensor module. This module can detect various VOCs, including formaldehyde, toluene, benzene, xylene, and organic solvents. Ammonia (<inline-formula id="IEq62"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2069" xlink:href="d33e2069.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/3fb7e463963e/d33e2069.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) pollution is caused by the release of ammonia gas, a byproduct of both agriculture and industry. Common sources of ammonia pollution include decomposing agricultural slurry, fertilizer plants, and natural occurrences such as coal mine fires. To identify ammonia gas, we incorporated a Wisen ZP01-MP503 air quality detection module. This sensor module demonstrates sensitivity to ammonia as well as other substances, such as cigarette smoke, alcohol, and specific gases.</p><p id="Par54">Carbon monoxide (CO) is a harmful by-product of the incomplete combustion of carbon-based fuels such as gas, oil, and coal. Inhalation of CO leads to its binding with hemoglobin in the bloodstream, thereby reducing oxygen transport and causing hypoxia. To monitor CO gas, we employed the Wisen ZE03 air quality electrochemical detection module, which is capable of detecting gases such as <inline-formula id="IEq63"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2077" xlink:href="d33e2077.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f937e0388203/d33e2077.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq64"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2083" xlink:href="d33e2083.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/7ba7a6b581b5/d33e2083.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>S, <inline-formula id="IEq65"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2089" xlink:href="d33e2089.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fef4bf79bdd1/d33e2089.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq66"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2095" xlink:href="d33e2095.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/2778c35b8a7c/d33e2095.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq67"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2101" xlink:href="d33e2101.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/08b41c90f37c/d33e2101.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq68"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2108" xlink:href="d33e2108.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ec263f3cb574/d33e2108.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, HF, <inline-formula id="IEq69"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2114" xlink:href="d33e2114.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/387476e25b54/d33e2114.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>,<inline-formula id="IEq70"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2120" xlink:href="d33e2120.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/aca647e4fe9a/d33e2120.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, HCL, and other gases. For the detection of flammable gases, such as ethane, acetylene, and methanol, we utilized MQ-6 and ME4-ETO semiconductor sensors. A PAH500 Digital PAH sensor was employed to detect polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons. Although <inline-formula id="IEq71"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2126" xlink:href="d33e2126.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f937e0388203/d33e2126.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is not typically classified as an air contaminant, elevated levels of <inline-formula id="IEq72"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2132" xlink:href="d33e2132.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f937e0388203/d33e2132.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> in enclosed environments can lead to oxygen depletion and are considered pollutants. To measure and track <inline-formula id="IEq73"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2138" xlink:href="d33e2138.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f937e0388203/d33e2138.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> concentrations, we installed the MH-411D NDIR infrared <inline-formula id="IEq74"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2145" xlink:href="d33e2145.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f937e0388203/d33e2145.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> sensor module. Toxic metals, such as lead and mercury were measured using the Pb-023 lead sensor and the KY-017 mercury sensor module, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25" disp-level="2"><title>Cost–benefit and maintenance at scale</title><p id="Par55">A deployment cost–benefit analysis is essential for Tier-2 cities. The bill of materials for each sensor (dust, VOC, gas, metal modules, microcontroller, communication) is approximately USD 50–70 per node, making a 1,000-node deployment feasible under municipal budgets as shown in table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Maintenance overhead primarily arises from calibration drift and periodic battery replacement, which scale linearly with the number of nodes. To mitigate this, cluster-head rotation balances energy use, while over-the-air updates and self-calibration flags reduce technician visits. At scale, the combination of in-network aggregation and duty-cycling reduces data transmission costs by 30–40%, ensuring sustainability for long-term monitoring.</p><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Cost benefit analysis of FLPSO-AMPS deployment in tier-2 smart cities.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Item</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Per-Node Cost (USD)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1k-Node Deployment (USD)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maintenance Notes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM2.5/PM10 sensor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low-cost laser-based dust sensors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VOC sensor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Detects benzene, toluene, xylene</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gas sensors (CO, NH<inline-formula id="IEq75"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2201" xlink:href="d33e2201.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/b71c17129ef4/d33e2201.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, SO<inline-formula id="IEq76"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2207" xlink:href="d33e2207.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e00f5e278321/d33e2207.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Electrochemical, cross-sensitive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metal sensors (Pb, Hg)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Toxic metal detection modules</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Microcontroller (ESP32)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low-power dual-core MCU</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Communication module</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WiFi/LoRa modules</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Annual calibration</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Annual recalibration required</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Battery replacement</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Replaceable every 18–24 months</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec26" disp-level="2"><title>Reliability mechanisms for low-cost sensors</title><p id="Par56">Ensuring long-term reliability requires compensating for the inherent limitations of low-cost sensor modules. Three mechanisms are integrated into FLPSO-AMPS deployments: </p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par57">Self-calibration: Each node performs scheduled baseline checks against ambient conditions and, when available, co-located reference monitors. Drift is quantified and offsets are corrected in-situ.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par58">Sensor fusion: Measurements from multiple pollutant modules (e.g., particulate, VOC, and gas sensors) are aggregated using weighted averaging and correlation checks, which help detect anomalies and reduce cross-sensitivity.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par59">ML-based error correction: Lightweight regression models, trained during initial collocation campaigns with reference stations, correct systematic biases. The corrected values are applied in-field with negligible computational overhead on ESP32-class MCUs. These measures significantly improve consistency over extended deployments, reducing the mean absolute error by  15–20% compared with uncorrected readings.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="Sec27" disp-level="2"><title> Analysis of AQI using recorded data</title><p id="Par60">To track the state of air in ballari city, 33 APMS instruments were placed. After installing The FLPSO-APMS, a cloud-based web portal was activated to analyze the gathered information and provide visual representations of air quality on the application<sup><xref rid="CR64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,<xref rid="CR65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup>. The data from each device were categorized by the area and device ID. The cloud produced reports that could be extracted for analysis for the current set of saved data with measured times. The data were colour-coded and visualised depending on the air quality at the time. The device’s hue turned yellow or red whenever air quality was medium or poor, and the warning feature was activated. A mobile application was made available for remote air quality monitoring<sup><xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28" disp-level="2"><title> Data integration and visualization</title><p id="Par61">The critical aspect of our research lies in providing a daily air pollution profile specifically for ballari. This achievement is made possible by the use of portable and affordable sensors<sup><xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="CR68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup> . Likewise, the identification and analysis of air pollution hotspot profiles holds significant importance in the development of intervention strategies within a given region. Indeed, these findings have the potential to inform decisions pertaining to adjustments in road traffic infrastructure or the development of new green spaces<sup><xref rid="CR69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>. The variables of primary interest for the detection of air pollution include AQI, PM2.5, PM10, CO, <inline-formula id="IEq77"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2317" xlink:href="d33e2317.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fef4bf79bdd1/d33e2317.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq78"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2323" xlink:href="d33e2323.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/08b41c90f37c/d33e2323.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq79"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2329" xlink:href="d33e2329.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/2778c35b8a7c/d33e2329.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. The emission of the air quality index tended to rise during peak traffic hours, specifically from 8:00 a.m. to 10:30 a.m. in the morning and from 4:30 p.m. to 7:00 p.m. in the afternoon Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>. This increase can be attributed to the heightened use of vehicles by individuals commuting to and from their workplaces<sup><xref rid="CR71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>–<xref rid="CR73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></sup>. An increase in the AQI to 101 specifically due to the presence of PM10 particles, is attributed to the emission of dust particles from sources such as heavy traffic, smoke, and construction sites. These particulate matter pollutants have the potential to induce various health effects, including eye irritation, respiratory tract infections, and lung cancer, as reported by the CDC. Similarly, fine particulate matter, specifically PM2.5, was predominantly generated as a result of combustion emissions. These particles pose an even greater risk as they possess dimensions smaller than 2.5 <inline-formula id="IEq80"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2346" xlink:href="d33e2346.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/522dcb2e5063/d33e2346.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>m, enabling them to penetrate the respiratory system and potentially enter the bloodstream.</p><fig id="Fig9" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>AQI values of a day.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO10" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig9_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/b6eaded22877/41598_2025_19748_Fig9_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1177?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 589?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig9_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/cd3f1bf137cc/41598_2025_19748_Fig9_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par62">For the time period from january 1, 2023, to april 1, 2023, the provided data represent the reference and measured air quality parameters. The characteristics are presented in Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> and comprise the AQI, CO levels, PM2.5, PM10, <inline-formula id="IEq81"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2364" xlink:href="d33e2364.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/08b41c90f37c/d33e2364.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> levels, <inline-formula id="IEq82"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2370" xlink:href="d33e2370.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fef4bf79bdd1/d33e2370.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> levels, and ozone levels. The measured data represent the actual values recorded during the specified period, whereas the reference data served as a baseline for comparison. The data were displayed daily.</p><fig id="Fig10" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Reference data v/s measured value of AQI, CO levels, PM2.5, PM10, <inline-formula id="IEq90"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2446" xlink:href="d33e2446.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/08b41c90f37c/d33e2446.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> levels, <inline-formula id="IEq91"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2452" xlink:href="d33e2452.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fef4bf79bdd1/d33e2452.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> levels, and Ozone levels.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO11" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig10_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/2b4ad301de83/41598_2025_19748_Fig10_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2480?><?original-width 1966?><?scaled-height 991?><?scaled-width 786?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig10_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/00d74e53a7c9/41598_2025_19748_Fig10_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par63">The AQI values of the measured data, which range from 27 to 189, showed a range of air quality from healthy to unhealthy. Carbon monoxide concentrations ranged from 352 to 1017 parts per million (ppm), with higher values indicating higher levels of CO pollution. PM2.5 concentrations vary from 13 to 30 g/<inline-formula id="IEq83"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2378" xlink:href="d33e2378.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ece75a12d25e/d33e2378.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, whereas PM10 concentrations range from 8 to 161 g/<inline-formula id="IEq84"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2384" xlink:href="d33e2384.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ece75a12d25e/d33e2384.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. While <inline-formula id="IEq85"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2390" xlink:href="d33e2390.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fef4bf79bdd1/d33e2390.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> levels vary from 4 to 26 g/<inline-formula id="IEq86"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2396" xlink:href="d33e2396.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ece75a12d25e/d33e2396.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq87"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2402" xlink:href="d33e2402.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/08b41c90f37c/d33e2402.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> levels are between 2 and 10 g/<inline-formula id="IEq88"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2409" xlink:href="d33e2409.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ece75a12d25e/d33e2409.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. The ozone concentration varied from 10 to 49 g/<inline-formula id="IEq89"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2415" xlink:href="d33e2415.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/ece75a12d25e/d33e2415.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. Overall, the information points to variations in air quality metrics over the course of the time period, with some days having higher pollution levels than others. A more thorough analysis of the data can reveal insights into certain trends or patterns and assist in identifying times when air quality has improved or declined<sup><xref rid="CR74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="CR75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par64">Information on air quality is gathered and examined using FLPSO-AMPS system. For the demonstration, only data from January 1, 2023, through April 30, 2023, is used. Figure <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref> displays statistics on the air quality, including the VOC, POP, PAH, flammable gas, and dangerous metals<sup><xref rid="CR76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>–<xref rid="CR82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></sup>.</p><fig id="Fig11" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>AQI parameters like VOC, POP, PAH, flammable gas, and toxic metals.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO12" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig11_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/29bce0b6cb73/41598_2025_19748_Fig11_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2479?><?original-width 1928?><?scaled-height 991?><?scaled-width 771?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig11_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/50b4bfaa2bc6/41598_2025_19748_Fig11_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec29" disp-level="2"><title>Security considerations for FLPSO-AMPS</title><p id="Par65">Environmental monitoring networks are highly sensitive because falsified data can distort public health responses. In FLPSO-AMPS, three classes of attacks are particularly relevant data spoofing (injecting false pollutant levels), packet tampering/replay (altering or re-using old measurements) and routing disruption (sinkhole or selective forwarding). To counter these threats on resource-constrained sensor nodes, several lightweight protocols are viable: </p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par66">Symmetric cryptography with integrity checks: AES-CCM and HMAC-SHA-256 provide confidentiality and authenticity with &lt;1 ms processing overhead on ESP32-class devices.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par67">Reputation-based filtering: cluster-heads monitor packet consistency and penalize anomalous nodes, limiting insider threats.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par68">Blockchain-inspired edge logging: sinks maintain an append-only ledger of received values and routing itineraries, ensuring auditability and preventing retroactive tampering.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par69">Elliptic curve key management: ECC-based key refresh schemes provide forward secrecy with minimal key size overhead compared to RSA.</p></list-item></list><p>These mechanisms can be integrated incrementally, balancing energy cost against resilience, and collectively strengthen the trustworthiness of pollutant data.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec30" disp-level="1"><title>Simulation, results and discussion</title><p id="Par70">This section outlines the simulation environment, the benchmarks employed, the state-of-the-art methods used for performance comparison, and the statistical analysis conducted.</p><sec id="Sec31" disp-level="2"><title> Simulation setup</title><p id="Par71">The simulations were conducted using MATLAB R2019a. The proposed FLPSO method was validated by deploying 100 wireless sensor nodes in a landscape measuring 1000 x 1000 m using MATLAB. The simulation parameters are presented in table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Simulation setup details.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Deployment Area</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula id="IEq92"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2524" xlink:href="d33e2524.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/95ac4ab6d1b2/d33e2524.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> m<sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Input Data Type</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Air pollution metrics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Sensor Nodes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Initial Energy per Node</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 J</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range of Source Nodes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10–100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Communication Range</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60 m</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Raw Data Volume</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2048 bits</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mobile Agent (MA) Code Size</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1024 bits</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MA Access Latency</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 ms</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Data Compression Ratio</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Aggregation Efficiency</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Processing Speed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 Mbps</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Simulation Duration</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 rounds</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Performance Metrics</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TE, PDR, EDP, PLR, Throughput</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Swarm Size</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Acceleration Coefficients <inline-formula id="IEq93"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2606" xlink:href="d33e2606.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/1fd521127f42/d33e2606.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq94"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2612" xlink:href="d33e2612.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/dca386c9b503/d33e2612.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.4495 each</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inertia Weight Range (<italic>w</italic>)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4 to 0.9</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec32" disp-level="2"><title> Performance metrics</title><p id="Par72">The efficacy associated with the suggested approach is assessed by utilizing commonly used network indicators such as task energy, PDR, EDP, PLR, and throughput.All reported metrics were averaged over 30 independent Monte Carlo runs with randomized node placement and traffic generation seeds. To strengthen reproducibility, 95% confidence intervals were computed for each metric. Error bars representing these intervals are now included in Figs. <xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>, <xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>, <xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>, <xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig">15</xref>, <xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig">16</xref>. This ensures that performance improvements, such as the +24.5% increase in PDR, are statistically significant rather than dataset-specific artifacts.</p><fig id="Fig12" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>The impact of source node on task energy.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO13" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig12_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/d8fc9bd5d818/41598_2025_19748_Fig12_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 714?><?original-width 944?><?scaled-height 476?><?scaled-width 629?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig12_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/5c2196266218/41598_2025_19748_Fig12_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="Fig13" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>The impact of source node on PDR.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO14" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig13_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/47d73b863307/41598_2025_19748_Fig13_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 726?><?original-width 943?><?scaled-height 483?><?scaled-width 628?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig13_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/c5ca444d9adf/41598_2025_19748_Fig13_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="Fig14" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>The impact of source node on EDP.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO15" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig14_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/8dbba05b209c/41598_2025_19748_Fig14_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 718?><?original-width 944?><?scaled-height 478?><?scaled-width 629?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig14_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/84d7192501e4/41598_2025_19748_Fig14_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="Fig15" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>The impact of source node on PLR.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO16" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig15_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fd7a6e9626d8/41598_2025_19748_Fig15_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 720?><?original-width 943?><?scaled-height 479?><?scaled-width 628?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig15_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/9afad1de186a/41598_2025_19748_Fig15_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="Fig16" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 16</label><caption><p>The impact of source node on Throughput.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO17" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig16_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/4c2b706a61f2/41598_2025_19748_Fig16_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 709?><?original-width 944?><?scaled-height 472?><?scaled-width 629?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig16_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/7d1fc65665d4/41598_2025_19748_Fig16_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><sec id="Sec33" disp-level="3"><title>Task energy</title><p id="Par73">The task energy of the sensor is directly linked to the energy required for transmitting generated data messages and relaying congestion in the network. The energy consumed in WSN is typically quantified as:</p><disp-formula id="Equ21"><label>21</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2651" xlink:href="d33e2651.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/3e72b029da5a/d33e2651.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>Here, <inline-formula id="IEq95"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2658" xlink:href="d33e2658.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/48d5e0996dca/d33e2658.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> indicates the average amount of energy used by each hop while sleeping. Where R indicates the total number of records transmitted by each sensor hop. The energy required by hop(u) for transmitting a packet from hop(v) down route(r) to sink hop(p) is expressed as T(u,p).</p></sec><sec id="Sec34" disp-level="3"><title>Packet delivery ratio</title><p id="Par74">Packet Delivery Ratio (PDR) is the percentage of data packets successfully received at the sink node.</p><disp-formula id="Equ22"><label>22</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2668" xlink:href="d33e2668.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/6c1c9e90a4c6/d33e2668.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>where <inline-formula id="IEq96"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2675" xlink:href="d33e2675.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/726830d7f278/d33e2675.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes the number of data packets accepted by the target node. <inline-formula id="IEq97"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2681" xlink:href="d33e2681.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/063a5a389dfd/d33e2681.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes the number of packets sent by the original node<sup><xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec35" disp-level="3"><title>EDP</title><p id="Par75">EDP quantifies energy efficiency and responsiveness.</p><disp-formula id="Equ23"><label>23</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2695" xlink:href="d33e2695.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/a6d33654145e/d33e2695.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></sec><sec id="Sec36" disp-level="3"><title>PLR</title><p id="Par76">Packet Loss Ratio (PLR) represents the percentage of lost packets during transmission.</p><disp-formula id="Equ24"><label>24</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2705" xlink:href="d33e2705.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/23b0e8f8303a/d33e2705.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></sec><sec id="Sec37" disp-level="3"><title>Throughput</title><p id="Par77">Network throughput refers to the number of packets that reach their final destination within a second. It measures the speed at which data are transmitted over at network channel and is usually expressed in bits per second (bps).</p><disp-formula id="Equ25"><label>25</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2715" xlink:href="d33e2715.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/a1f23806b00d/d33e2715.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p>Here, <inline-formula id="IEq98"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2722" xlink:href="d33e2722.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/726830d7f278/d33e2722.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes data packets accepted by the target node, and t is the time in seconds.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec38" disp-level="2"><title> Benchmark on low-power microcontrollers (MCUs)</title><p id="Par78">To evaluate the scalability and feasibility of deploying the proposed FLPSO-AMPS model in real-world Internet of Things (IoT) environments, we bench-marked its computational performance on low-power microcontrollers, specifically the Arduino Uno and ESP32 platforms. These platforms are representative of the constrained hardware typically deployed in mobile ad hoc networks (MANETs) and sensor-based systems.</p><sec id="Sec39" disp-level="3"><title>Implementation setup</title><p id="Par79">The FLPSO-AMPS algorithm was implemented in lightweight C/C++ code with embedded fuzzy inference logic tailored for memory-constrained devices. We ported the fuzzy rule evaluation engine and the particle update routines to run on both Arduino Uno (ATmega328P, 16 MHz, 2 KB SRAM) and ESP32 (dual-core Xtensa 240 MHz, 520 KB SRAM). Key modules included : </p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par80">Fuzzification: Triangular and trapezoidal membership functions.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par81">Inference Engine: Mamdani-based fuzzy rule evaluation.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par82">Defuzzification: Centroid method and Swarm Update: Inertia weight and cognitive-social velocity adjustment routines.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="Sec40" disp-level="3"><title>Benchmark metrics</title><p id="Par83">We profiled the execution using the following metrics: </p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par84">Execution Latency: Time taken to evaluate all fuzzy rules and update a single particle position</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par85">Memory Footprint: Static and dynamic memory used during rule storage, swarm updates, and fitness evaluation</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par86">CPU Load: Measured via clock cycle profiling for critical sections</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="Sec41" disp-level="3"><title>Observations</title><p id="Par87">To evaluate the practical feasibility of deploying FLPSO-AMPS in resource-constrained environments, we benchmarked the computational performance on two representative low-power microcontrollers: Arduino Uno (ATmega328P) and ESP32 (Xtensa dual-core).</p><p id="Par88">The FLPSO fuzzy rule evaluation module was implemented in matlab, and the PSO update mechanism was ported using fixed-point arithmetic to optimize runtime on MCU hardware. Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> reports the average latency and memory footprint for 50 FLPSO iterations.</p><table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Computation latency and memory usage on low-power MCUs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MCU Platform</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Avg. Time/Iter(ms)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RAM Usage(KB)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Flash Usage(KB)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Arduino Uno (16 MHz)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ESP32 (240 MHz)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par89">As evident, FLPSO-AMPS remains lightweight enough to run within real-time routing constraints, especially on ESP32-class devices. However, on Arduino Uno, although feasible, the latency may approach upper bounds for high-mobility sensors, necessitating hybrid delegation to cluster heads or border routers.</p><p id="Par90">These results validate that the proposed FLPSO-based mechanism is deployable on edge devices with limited computation and memory resources, confirming its scalability for practical sensor applications.</p></sec><sec id="Sec42" disp-level="3"><title>Feasibility assessment</title><p id="Par91">These results confirm that FLPSO-AMPS is lightweight enough to be deployed on modern microcontrollers such as ESP32, making it suitable for distributed WSN routing and fuzzy decision-making in IoT environments. Nonetheless, for ultra-low-power MCUs (e.g., STM32L0), additional code optimization or rule simplification may be necessary.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec43" disp-level="2"><title> Results and analysis</title><sec id="Sec44" disp-level="3"><title>Task energy</title><p id="Par92">Figure <xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref> represents the task energy of all hops for SEP, ELDC, IEESEP, and the suggested approach, FLPSO. The proposed approach effectively governs the energy consumption of all the nodes within the air pollution monitoring system (APMS) and enhances the overall longevity of the network. Analysis of the simulation results reveals that the FLPSO protocol exhibits the lowest energy consumption, amounting to 84 J. This was followed by the IEESEP protocol, which consumes 95 J, the SEP protocol, which consumes 100 J, and ELDC protocol, which has the highest energy consumption of 149 J. The proposed model successfully addressed the prevailing challenges, particularly with regard to the task energy within the system, when compared with previous approaches.</p></sec><sec id="Sec45" disp-level="3"><title>PDR</title><p id="Par93">Based on the findings presented in Fig. <xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>, it can be observed that FLPSO exhibits a higher level of performance than other approaches of similar nature. To illustrate the efficacy of the suggested method, the range of the source node in the scenario was modified to 100. The consideration of sink nodes by FLPSO resulted in the observed outcomes. In addition, the Packet Delivery Ratio (PDR) of the fuzzy logic-based particle swarm optimisation (FLPSO) algorithm exhibits notable enhancements of approximately 24.15%, 92%, and 200% for IEESEP, SSEP, and ELDC, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec46" disp-level="3"><title>EDP</title><p id="Par94">The energy delay product (EDP) plays a crucial role in improving the network longevity of air pollution monitoring systems (APMS), as it exhibits a direct correlation with both energy consumption (EC) and lifetime parameters. The proposed model aims to minimize delays to the greatest extent possible. The performance evaluation of EDP is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>. In the simulated APMS environment, the EDP parameter of the ELDC protocol demonstrates a notably higher value of 273 s for a network comprising 100 nodes compared with other routing protocols. A comparative analysis of the ELDC protocol’s EDP with SEP and IEESEP reveals that the FLPSO protocol exhibits the lowest delays, especially at the 154-second mark.This phenomenon arises whenever a social networking service (SNS) seeks to transmit data. This process commences with the initiation of the route discovery procedure (RDP)is followed by the collection and gathering of data within the network.</p></sec><sec id="Sec47" disp-level="3"><title>PLR</title><p id="Par95">Compared with the other methods, FLPSO showed exceptional results, as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig">15</xref>. Compared with the other methods, FLPSO showed exceptional results, as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>. To verify the effectiveness of the proposed method, we changed the source node frequency of the scenario to 100. These findings were achieved because FLPSO considers packet transmissions. Additionally, for IEESEP, SEP, and ELDC, the PLR rate of the FLPSO increased by approximately 11.15%, 16.2%, and 24.96%, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec48" disp-level="3"><title>Throughput</title><p id="Par96">Throughput is the amount of data that successfully arrives to the sink node coming from the source node during a period of time . It is a measure of performance in that the lower it is the better the data across the network is being transported. The proposed FLPSO approach shows significantly improved throughput compared to known protocols, such as IEESEP, SEP, and ELDC. Figure <xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig">16</xref> illustrates how throughput is greatly increased as a result of efficient packet transmission. Comparing FLPSO to IEESEP, SEP, and ELDC, the throughput was much higher by approximately 20.1%, 24.35%, and 28.18%, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec49" disp-level="2"><title> Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par97">Statistical tests were performed to assess performance significance. For each method, samples for task Energy,PDR,EDP, PLR and throughput were chosen. The obtained sample was subjected to an Friedman test with a 5 % confidence level. The null hypothesis (<inline-formula id="IEq99"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2907" xlink:href="d33e2907.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/3b7adf45647f/d33e2907.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) and alternative hypothesis (<inline-formula id="IEq100"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2913" xlink:href="d33e2913.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/b29f29d1500e/d33e2913.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) are shown in table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref> .In addition to the Friedman and pairwise rank tests, we applied cross-validation to validate robustness. In the localized Ballari deployment, we divided the dataset into ten folds stratified by week (January–April 2023). Each fold was alternately used as a validation set while training/tuning was performed on the remaining nine. This procedure ensured that temporal variation (e.g., weekday vs. weekend traffic, seasonal changes) did not bias the reported results. Across folds, performance differences between FLPSO-AMPS and the baselines (SEP, ELDC, IEESEP) remained consistent, with standard deviations below 2% for PDR and below 1.5 J for task energy.</p><table-wrap id="Tab6" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Hypotheses test.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Null hypothesis(<inline-formula id="IEq101"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2935" xlink:href="d33e2935.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/3b7adf45647f/d33e2935.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alternative hypothesis(<inline-formula id="IEq102"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2944" xlink:href="d33e2944.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/b29f29d1500e/d33e2944.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">There is no difference between the</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">There is a difference between the</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dependent variables FLPSO, IEESEP,</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">dependent variables FLPSO, IEESEP,</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP and ELDC.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP and ELDC.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par98">Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>, present descriptive statistics, respectively for task energy,PDR,EDP, PLR and throughput pertaining to the approaches. These outcome statistics were obtained using 30 samples from each approach<sup><xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup>. Results show that FLPSO has done better compared to all the other methods, including IEESEP, SEP and ELDC. All parameters were subjected to the friedman test, which revealed a p-value of less than 0.05 ((p = 0.000 &lt; 0.05) as shown in table <xref rid="Tab8" ref-type="table">8</xref> . Hence, (<inline-formula id="IEq103"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2978" xlink:href="d33e2978.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/3b7adf45647f/d33e2978.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) is rejected. Further results also demonstrated that one sample was superior to the other. However, it was difficult to determine which method was superior in this group. The friedman rank sum difference test or pairwise comparison tests were performed to assess the outcomes of each assigned sample or pair. Pairwise Comparisons were performed. It is less susceptible to type-1 errors and works well with a similar samples ( N = 30). The results of pairwise comparison tests on all variable showed that FLPSO outperformed all other parameters to a substantial extent.</p><table-wrap id="Tab7" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Descriptive analysis of parameters with respect to algorithms.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sl.No</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paramaters</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Algorithms</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ranks</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">N</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Media</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><inline-formula id="IEq104"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e3020" xlink:href="d33e3020.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/eafd768f32b5/d33e3020.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">df</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Task Energy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.75</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">90</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">PDR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">89.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">EDP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">90</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154.43</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">193.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">193.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">211</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">121.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">PLR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">71.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Throughput</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">89.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.98</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab8" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Statistics analysis of parameters with respect to algorithms.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Sl</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Paramater</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Pairwise</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Test</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Std Error</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Std.test</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> p</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Adj.p</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Task Energy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO - SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">PDR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO - SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.004</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">EDP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.003</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">PLR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.42</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.82</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.921</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-0.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-2.85</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.004</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.017</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Throughput</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-IEESEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FLPSO-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-SEP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.004</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IEESEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SEP-ELDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.002</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">.009</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec50" disp-level="2"><title>Ablation and sensitivity results</title><p id="Par99">We ablated the fuzzy controller to isolate the effect of tuning and to assess robustness. First, we compared fixed (percentile-seeded) versus tuned membership parameters and observed consistent improvements in <italic>PDR</italic> and throughput under high load, with no increase in inference time. Second, one-at-a-time (OAT) perturbations of membership breakpoints by <inline-formula id="IEq105"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e3751" xlink:href="d33e3751.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/3ced28a899fc/d33e3751.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> yielded only modest changes in aggregate performance, indicating local robustness. Third, global sensitivity analysis using Sobol indices revealed that RE contributes the most output variance in low-battery regimes, NN becomes dominant in dense subgraphs with bursty traffic, and DC grows in importance at the network edge—consistent with the semantics encoded in the rules. Finally, we stress-tested three urban profiles (traffic-corridor, industrial-belt, mixed) by altering spatial load and link reliability; the same rule base with rescaled memberships maintained high delivery ratios and bounded delays, supporting cross-city portability.</p></sec><sec id="Sec51" disp-level="2"><title>Scalability experiments (N = 1k–10k)</title><p id="Par100">To evaluate the scalability of FLPSO-AMPS beyond the initial 33-node deployment, we conducted extended simulations with network sizes ranging from 1,000 to 10,000 sensor nodes. The experiments were designed to assess performance under conditions of increasing traffic load, varying sink configurations, and different routing protocols. In these large-scale settings, congestion, latency, and throughput are critical factors that directly impact the feasibility of real-world deployments in Tier-2 cities.</p><p id="Par101">The first set of results focuses on end-to-end latency as the number of deployed nodes increases. As illustrated in <xref rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig">17</xref>, the baseline FLPSO-AMPS protocol exhibits significantly lower delays compared to conventional protocols such as SEP, ELDC, and IEESEP. While delay grows with node count for all protocols, FLPSO-AMPS maintains a sublinear increase due to its adaptive fuzzy–PSO routing and multi-agent partitioning strategies. At 10,000 nodes, FLPSO-AMPS still delivers data within 720 ms, whereas ELDC and SEP exhibit delays exceeding 1,000 ms. These results confirm that the proposed approach effectively mitigates congestion even under dense deployment scenarios.</p><fig id="Fig17" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 17</label><caption><p>End-to-end delay vs. number of nodes.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO18" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig17_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/fb347f3e68b1/41598_2025_19748_Fig17_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 594?><?original-width 944?><?scaled-height 396?><?scaled-width 629?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig17_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/81da57783ded/41598_2025_19748_Fig17_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par102">Packet delivery ratio (PDR) was analyzed under varying traffic loads ranging from 0.1 to 1 packet per second per node. As shown in <xref rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig">18</xref>, FLPSO-AMPS sustains high delivery rates above 90% across the entire load spectrum, outperforming SEP, ELDC, and IEESEP. In contrast, traditional protocols experience sharp degradation beyond 0.5 packets/s/node, with ELDC dropping to nearly 35% at full load. The integration of congestion-aware fitness in FLPSO-AMPS enables the algorithm to reroute packets away from overloaded paths, ensuring robustness in high-traffic environments.</p><fig id="Fig18" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 18</label><caption><p>Packet delivery ratio vs. traffic load.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO19" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig18_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/66233723f49f/41598_2025_19748_Fig18_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 603?><?original-width 944?><?scaled-height 402?><?scaled-width 629?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig18_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/8823687e9c78/41598_2025_19748_Fig18_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par103">Throughput performance under different sink configurations is presented in <xref rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig">19</xref>. For a 10,000-node network, throughput was measured with 1, 2, and 4 sinks. Results indicate that while all protocols benefit from multi-sink deployments, FLPSO-AMPS demonstrates the steepest gains, scaling from 150 kbps with a single sink to 520 kbps with four sinks. In comparison, SEP and ELDC plateau at much lower values, highlighting their inefficiency in leveraging additional infrastructure. This result underlines the adaptability of FLPSO-AMPS to heterogeneous topologies, where adding sinks can be a practical intervention to handle surges in data volume.</p><fig id="Fig19" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 19</label><caption><p>Throughput gains from multi-sink deployment in different routing approaches.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO20" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig19_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/3a086848df62/41598_2025_19748_Fig19_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 599?><?original-width 944?><?scaled-height 399?><?scaled-width 629?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig19_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e99000f9f54e/41598_2025_19748_Fig19_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par104">Overall, the scalability experiments validate the effectiveness of FLPSO-AMPS in handling large-scale deployments with thousands of nodes. The integration of fuzzy logic, PSO-based optimization, congestion awareness, and hierarchical clustering ensures that latency, packet delivery, and throughput remain within acceptable bounds, even under demanding traffic loads. These findings demonstrate that FLPSO-AMPS is well-suited for Tier-2 smart cities planning cost-effective, citywide deployments of air quality monitoring networks.</p></sec><sec id="Sec52" disp-level="2"><title>Robustness across urban profiles</title><p id="Par105">To further validate the adaptability of FLPSO-AMPS, we evaluated its performance across three representative urban deployment profiles: (i) traffic-corridor, characterized by high diurnal packet bursts along major roadways with fluctuating link reliability; (ii) industrial-belt, dominated by persistent pollutant loads, stable background traffic, and interference from heavy machinery; and (iii) mixed-corridor, combining residential traffic peaks with episodic industrial activity. In all cases, the fuzzy rule base remained unchanged, with only membership breakpoints rescaled according to percentile distributions of the new deployment. Results demonstrated that FLPSO-AMPS consistently sustained packet delivery above 90% and bounded end-to-end delay within acceptable thresholds, even under heavy load variations. Importantly, the sensitivity analysis revealed that Remaining Energy was the dominant factor in traffic-corridor scenarios, Neighbor Density gained higher influence in mixed-corridor conditions, and Distance to Sink became critical in industrial-belt settings where interference disrupted longer links. These findings highlight the robustness of the fuzzy-augmented design, confirming that the same rule base can generalize across diverse Tier-2 urban contexts without extensive retuning. Table <xref rid="Tab9" ref-type="table">9</xref> summarizes the comparative results for FLPSO-AMPS across the three urban profiles. Despite differences in traffic intensity, interference, and node density, the protocol consistently maintained high packet delivery ratios and bounded delay. The variations observed highlight which input metric becomes most influential under each profile, yet overall performance demonstrates robustness and portability of the fuzzy rule base.</p><table-wrap id="Tab9" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Comparative performance of FLPSO-AMPS across urban profiles.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urban Profile</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PDR (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">End-to-End Delay (ms)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Energy Consumption (J)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Traffic-Corridor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">245</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Industrial-Belt</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">268</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mixed-Corridor</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">252</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec53" disp-level="2"><title>FLPSO vs. PSO ablation study</title><p id="Par106">To directly validate the benefit of integrating fuzzy inference into the particle swarm optimization framework, we conducted an ablation study where the fuzzy component was removed, resulting in a pure PSO-based routing scheme. Both algorithms were evaluated under identical conditions with node counts ranging from 500 to 2,000 and traffic loads between 0.2 and 0.8 packets/s per node. Figures X1–X3 illustrate the comparative outcomes for packet delivery ratio, end-to-end delay, and energy consumption/lifetime.</p><p id="Par107">As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig20" ref-type="fig">20</xref> , FLPSO consistently outperformed standard PSO in terms of reliability. At 500 nodes, FLPSO achieved a PDR of approximately 93% compared to 84% for PSO, representing a 9% gain. This advantage widened with increasing network size, where congestion and link contention become more significant. At 2,000 nodes, FLPSO maintained a PDR of 85%, while PSO dropped to 76%. The improvement is attributed to fuzzy rule–driven prioritization of nodes with higher residual energy and better connectivity, which pure PSO lacks.</p><fig id="Fig20" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 20</label><caption><p>PDR: FLPSO vs PSO.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO21" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig20_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/8513d8721fdf/41598_2025_19748_Fig20_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 832?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 416?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig20_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/d037bf67e6c3/41598_2025_19748_Fig20_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par108">Delay trends are presented in Fig. <xref rid="Fig21" ref-type="fig">21</xref>. FLPSO achieved lower average delays across all scales, reducing latency by roughly 8–10% compared to PSO. For instance, at 1,500 nodes, average delay under PSO was 410 ms, whereas FLPSO reduced it to 370 ms. The reduction results from congestion-aware decision making introduced by the fuzzy rules, which helps reroute packets away from overloaded nodes and balances traffic across the network.</p><fig id="Fig21" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 21</label><caption><p>Delay: FLPSO vs PSO.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO22" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig21_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/c044046d4a42/41598_2025_19748_Fig21_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 832?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 416?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig21_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/f981d130968d/41598_2025_19748_Fig21_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par109">Figure <xref rid="Fig22" ref-type="fig">22</xref> highlights differences in energy consumption and network lifetime. Under PSO, the first node death occurred around 780 rounds in the 1,000-node scenario, whereas FLPSO extended this to 835 rounds, a  7% improvement. The balanced load distribution, achieved by avoiding overuse of nodes with high connectivity but low residual energy, directly contributes to this gain. This demonstrates that fuzzy-enhanced PSO not only improves short-term performance (PDR and delay) but also sustains network longevity by distributing energy expenditure more evenly.</p><fig id="Fig22" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 22</label><caption><p>Lifetime: FLPSO vs PSO.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO23" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig22_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/5a39abdb6307/41598_2025_19748_Fig22_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 832?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 416?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig22_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/2350cd345a68/41598_2025_19748_Fig22_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par110">FLPSO consistently consumes less energy per round than standard PSO across all network sizes. This reduction ( 8–10%) comes from fuzzy-aware routing that balances load and avoids overusing specific nodes.As a result, FLPSO achieves greater efficiency compared with PSO as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig23" ref-type="fig">23</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig23" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 23</label><caption><p>Energy consumption: FLPSO vs PSO.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO24" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig23_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/e0171822b74e/41598_2025_19748_Fig23_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 864?><?original-width 1416?><?scaled-height 432?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_19748_Fig23_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/c52c/12528717/55433afcffc0/41598_2025_19748_Fig23_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par111">Overall, the ablation study confirms that fuzzy logic enhances PSO by embedding contextual awareness of energy, distance, and neighborhood density into routing decisions. This results in higher packet delivery reliability, lower latency, energy consumption and extended network lifetime, validating the design choice behind FLPSO-AMPS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec54" disp-level="2"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par112">Despite the demonstrated efficiency of the FLPSO-AMPS framework, our original field trial was limited to 33 sensors in one Tier-2 city. Large-scale scalability was subsequently validated in extended simulations (1k–10k nodes) with multi-sink and hierarchical routing. However, real-world multi-city deployments remain untested and may face additional latency, congestion, and calibration challenges. The computational overhead introduced by fuzzy rule evaluation poses a challenge, particularly for resource-constrained IoT devices. While the tuning procedure requires a short calibration phase to estimate percentiles, this step is lightweight (minutes to hours of passive observation) and does not alter the rule base. Future multi-city pilots will further validate the global sensitivity results using real traffic patterns and seasonal pollution shifts. Moreover, the framework currently lacks built-in security mechanisms, rendering it susceptible to malicious attacks in untrusted or hostile environments. To address these concerns, future work will explore the integration of lightweight, blockchain-based authentication protocols<sup><xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>, which can enhance both the trustworthiness and security of route selection. This enhancement is expected to mitigate the limitation of ineffective malicious node detection and contribute to the framework’s overall resilience. </p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par113">Firstly, the integration of fuzzy logic and PSO-based optimization introduces additional computational complexity, which may pose challenges for low-power sensor nodes with limited processing capabilities. Though fuzzy logic introduces rule evaluation overhead, our benchmarks on Arduino Uno and ESP32 indicate execution times under 5 ms and memory under 2 KB. Therefore, the model is scalable even for embedded MCUs, mitigating previous limitations.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par114">Secondly, while the system has been validated for a Tier-2 smart city, its performance in large-scale deployments with thousands of nodes remains uncertain, as high-density sensor networks may experience increased latency and network congestion.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par115">Thirdly, the current model lacks data encryption or security mechanisms to safeguard against malicious attacks, data tampering, or unauthorized access, which are crucial for secure data transmission in real-world applications.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par116">Fourth, the air quality sensors employed in this study are prone to calibration drift and environmental interference, potentially resulting in data inaccuracies during extended deployment. Although periodic manual recalibration was conducted during testing, such measures may not be practical for large-scale or long-term implementation, particularly in Tier-2 cities with limited technical personnel. Future research should prioritize the integration of low-cost, self-calibrating sensors or the implementation of machine learning-based error correction mechanisms to ensure measurement accuracy without increasing the operational burden.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par117">Sixth, the current deployment, which is confined to a single Tier-2 city with 33 sensors, limits the generalizability of our findings. Urban morphology, pollution sources, and climatic variations differed significantly across Tier-2 cities. For example, industrial towns may exhibit heavy metal pollution, whereas hilly regions may experience topographic trapping effects. Consequently, the conclusions derived from this localized deployment may not be applicable to diverse urban ecosystems. A broader multi-city deployment incorporating region-specific calibration and validation is essential to ensure the scalability and robustness of the FLPSO-AMPS system across the national Tier-2 landscape.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par118">Seventh, the statistical analysis in this study was constrained by the limited sample size and absence of rigorous significance testing. Although performance metrics, such as PDR, latency, and energy consumption, were compared across models, the lack of confidence intervals, standard deviation analysis, and hypothesis testing (e.g., federman, t-tests) undermined the statistical validity of the findings. Additionally, the deployment of only 33 nodes restricts the representativeness of the dataset, potentially affecting the generalizability of the observed trends. In future research, we intend to incorporate larger sample sizes and employ formal statistical methods to enhance the robustness and reliability of the performance comparisons.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par119">At the eighth point, the existing system architecture is deficient in integrated security mechanisms, rendering it susceptible to data tampering, spoofing, or unauthorized access. This limitation is particularly critical for real-time pollution-monitoring applications, where data integrity and authentication are imperative. Furthermore, the scalability of the system has not been validated for extensive deployment across multiple Tier-2 cities. The current testbed, which is limited to 33 sensors, does not provide adequate evidence regarding the network’s capacity to manage high node densities or sudden environmental changes such as abrupt increases in pollution due to industrial discharge or traffic congestion. These aspects of scalability and responsiveness remain unexplored and require targeted simulations and field-based validation.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par120">Additionally, although the FLPSO-AMPS model dynamically optimizes network routes, it does not account for sudden environmental changes, such as natural disasters or unexpected surges in pollution levels, which may necessitate instantaneous rerouting strategies.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par121">Lastly, the system’s efficiency is contingent upon the quality and accuracy of the deployed sensors, as low-cost sensors may introduce calibration errors and inconsistent pollutant readings, thereby affecting the reliability of the monitoring framework.”</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="Sec55" disp-level="2"><title>Scope for further work</title><p id="Par122">Future work will prioritize multi-city pilots involving thousands of nodes to validate scalability beyond simulations. We also plan to integrate reinforcement-learning-based adaptive routing, lightweight blockchain authentication, and energy-harvesting WSN nodes to further enhance resilience, security, and sustainability at scale. To enhance the effectiveness and applicability of the FLPSO-AMPS model, future research should focus on several key areas. </p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par123">First, the integration of edge computing is recommended to address computational overhead, enabling faster decision-making without overloading sensor nodes.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par124">Second, scalability optimization should be pursued by testing FLPSO-AMPS on large-scale sensor networks across multiple cities to evaluate its performance, latency, and energy efficiency under increased data loads.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par125">Third, the incorporation of security measures, such as a lightweight encryption protocol or blockchain-based data security mechanism, could enhance data integrity, confidentiality, and protection against cyber threats.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par126">Fourth, adaptive machine learning-based routing could be achieved by incorporating deep learning models or reinforcement learning algorithms, allowing the system to predict environmental changes and dynamically adjust routing decisions in real-time.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par127">Fifth, hybrid optimization techniques should be explored, such as combining Genetic Algorithm (GA) with PSO or Ant Colony Optimization (ACO) with Fuzzy Logic, to improve network lifetime and route stability.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par128">Sixth, integration with IoT and smart city infrastructure is essential, aligning FLPSO-AMPS with IoT cloud platforms to facilitate real-time monitoring, visualization, and data sharing for policymakers and environmental agencies.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par129">Seventh, sensor calibration and error correction mechanisms, such as self-calibrating algorithms or sensor fusion techniques, could enhance the accuracy and reliability of air pollution readings in diverse environmental conditions.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par130">Finally, energy harvesting for sustainable operations should be investigated, exploring solar-powered or energy-harvesting WSN nodes to prolong network lifespan and reduce reliance on battery-powered sensors.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="Sec56" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par131">This study discusses the use of the FLPSO Algorithm in the development of air pollution monitoring devices for tier-2 smart cities. The system encompasses various components, namely, the FLPSO-AMPS module, database, and online monitoring. These elements are integral to the system’s overall architecture, which incorporates air-detecting sensors, a microcontroller, and cloud and database management systems (DBMS). The feasibility of air pollution monitoring stations is hindered by their high cost. In areas where monitoring stations are not feasible, the deployment of affordable sensors capable of monitoring crucial factors that affect air contamination, such as climatic conditions and vehicular traffic, can serve as a viable alternative. Therefore, the suggested methodology should be applied to assess the air quality of any ward within the city for various tasks that require an accurate and immediate evaluation, with minimal investment in infrastructure. In our study, we utilized dedicated sensors specifically designed for the detection and quantification of various substances, including VOCs, ammonia, CFCs, POP, PAH, and toxic metals, such as lead and mercury. This paper presents the development of a sophisticated multisensor detection system that uses the FLPSO APMS algorithm. The motivation behind this research stems from the significance of air pollution in tier-2 cities. The empirical results of the suggested approach had a positive impact on the environment. Surveillance and examination of atmospheric contamination in regions where the implementation of air pollution monitoring stations is economically impractical because of their exorbitant costs, and low-cost sensors are a viable alternative for monitoring the crucial factors that contribute to air pollution, including weather conditions and traffic patterns. //In this study, we demonstrate the utilization of affordable sensor technology to deliver personalized data pertaining to an individual’s exposure to a specific pollutant. Empirical findings and acquired knowledge suggest that air quality monitors offer valuable insights into individual exposure to pollution and localized climatic conditions in urban areas. The proposed investigation aims to identify the initial stages of APMS by employing cost-effective and easily obtainable components.The proposed model enhances the accuracy of the APM system’s effectiveness in transmitting time-sensitive signals. Furthermore, the proposed system was evaluated in terms of both detection accuracy and energy efficiency, in addition to considering execution and modelling environments. The cost-effective FLPSO-AMPS has the potential to positively impact a multitude of individuals by providing timely alerts and facilitating message transmission.</p><p id="Par132">In the future, it will be possible to implement an encryption technique that safeguards sensitive information. The current scheme lacks the ability to defend against external malicious attacks by incorporating a classification tool within the source nodes (SNs). This study aims to design and implement a robust encryption technique that prioritizes security.In summary, while the initial deployment involved 33 nodes, the extended simulation results and architectural modifications demonstrate that FLPSO-AMPS can maintain efficiency and reliability in networks of up to 10,000 nodes, making it a scalable solution for smart city air-quality monitoring.</p></sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge the support from Manipal Institute of Technology, Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal, Rao Bahadur Y Mahabaleswarappa Engineering College, Bellary, University of Malta, Msidal, Malta, and Industrial University of Ho Chi Minh City, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam for the facilities provided to carry out this research.</p></sec><sec id="glossary1" sec-type="glossary" disp-level="1"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>MA</term><def><p>Mobile Agent</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CN</term><def><p>Candidate node</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IP</term><def><p>Itinerary Planning</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SIP</term><def><p>Single Mobile Agent Itinerary Planning</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIP</term><def><p>Multi Mobile Agent Itinerary Planning</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FLM</term><def><p>Fuzzy Logic model</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSO</term><def><p>Particle Swarm Optimization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SN</term><def><p>Source Nodes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MMA</term><def><p>Multi-mobile agents</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAMS</term><def><p>Mobile Agent Mobile Server</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MST</term><def><p>Minimum Spanning Tree</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CH</term><def><p>Cluster Head</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BS</term><def><p>Base Station</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>APMS</term><def><p>Air pollution monitoring system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSM</term><def><p>Global System for Mobile Communications</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPRS</term><def><p>General Packet Radio Services</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GUI</term><def><p>Graphical user interface</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RE</term><def><p>Remaining Energy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DC</term><def><p>Distance from Source Node</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCD</term><def><p>Pollution Control Department</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LQA</term><def><p>Level of air quality</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VOC</term><def><p>Volatile organic compounds</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HC</term><def><p>Hydrocarbon</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFC</term><def><p>chlorofluorocarbons</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>POP</term><def><p>Persistent organic pollutants</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAH</term><def><p>Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDC</term><def><p>Centres for Disease Control and Prevention</p></def></def-item></def-list></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Lingaraj K:Initial problem identification, writeup, analysis, comparison, sections identification, Literature survey and technicalimprovement. Rashmi Laxmikant Malghan:Drafting of the initial manuscript and Helped in Complexity analysis of the review work, andevaluation of the review work. KarthiK Rao M C: Drafting of the final manuscript, helped in the initial review process, Final English correction, and finalimages drawing using the draw.io tool, applied to the journal. Lalit Garg: Sections Identification, Final English correction, original draft, Software, Data curation. Somanath Swamy R H M: Comaprison, Final English correction. Vishwanatha H M:Drafting of the final manuscript, helped in the initial review process, Visualization,Final English correction.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by Manipal Academy of Higher Education, Manipal. No Funding is available.</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>The dataset and code supporting the conclusion of this article is available in the github repository. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/lingarajpower/FLPSO-MATLAB" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/lingarajpower/FLPSO-MATLAB</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par138">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="_ci93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="contrib-info" disp-level="1"><title>Contributor Information</title><p>Rashmi Laxmikant Malghan, Email: rashmi.malghan@manipal.edu.</p><p>Karthik Rao M. C., Email: rao.karthik@manipal.edu.</p></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rawat, P., Singh, K. D., Chaouchi, H. &amp; Bonnin, J. M. Wireless sensor networks: A survey on recent developments and potential synergies. <italic>J. Supercomput.</italic><bold>68</bold>(1), 1–48. 10.1007/s11227-013-1021-9 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rawat, P., Singh, K. D., Chaouchi, H. &amp; Bonnin, J. M. Wireless sensor networks: A survey on recent developments and potential synergies. J. Supercomput.68(1), 1–48. 10.1007/s11227-013-1021-9 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yong-Min, L., Shu-Ci, W. &amp; Xiao-Hong, N. The architecture and characteristics of wireless sensor network, In <italic>2009 International Conference on Computer Technology and Development</italic>, Vol. 1, pp. 561–565. 10.1109/ICCTD.2009.44 (2009).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh, M. K., Amin, S. I., Imam, S. A., Sachan, V. K. &amp; Choudhary, A. A survey of wireless sensor network and its types. In <italic>2018 International Conference on Advances in Computing, Communication Control and Networking (ICACCCN)</italic> pp. 326–330. 10.1109/ICACCCN.2018.8748710 (2018).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kulaib, A. R., Shubair, R. M., Al-Qutayri, M. A. &amp; Ng, J. W. P. An overview of localization techniques for wireless sensor networks. <italic>Int. Conf., Innov. Inf. Technol.</italic><bold>2011</bold>, 167–172. 10.1109/INNOVATIONS.2011.5893810 (2011).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kulaib, A. R., Shubair, R. M., Al-Qutayri, M. A. &amp; Ng, J. W. P. An overview of localization techniques for wireless sensor networks. Int. Conf., Innov. Inf. Technol.2011, 167–172. 10.1109/INNOVATIONS.2011.5893810 (2011)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Arroyo, P., Lozano, J., Su’arez, J., Herrero, J. &amp; Carmona, P. Wireless sensor network for air quality monitoring and control. <italic>Chem. Eng. Trans.</italic><bold>54</bold>, 217–222. 10.3303/CET1654037 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Arroyo, P., Lozano, J., Su’arez, J., Herrero, J. &amp; Carmona, P. Wireless sensor network for air quality monitoring and control. Chem. Eng. Trans.54, 217–222. 10.3303/CET1654037 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Amol, D. S. K., Kasar, R. &amp; Tembhurnikar, N. P. WSN based air pollution monitoring system. <italic>Int. J. Sci. Eng. Appl. (IJSEA)</italic><bold>2</bold>, 55 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Amol, D. S. K., Kasar, R. &amp; Tembhurnikar, N. P. WSN based air pollution monitoring system. Int. J. Sci. Eng. Appl. (IJSEA)2, 55 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bibri, S. A novel model for data-driven smart sustainable cities of the future: The institutional transformations required for balancing and advancing the three goals of sustainability. <italic>Energy Inform.</italic>10.1186/s42162-021-00138-8 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bibri, S. A novel model for data-driven smart sustainable cities of the future: The institutional transformations required for balancing and advancing the three goals of sustainability. Energy Inform.10.1186/s42162-021-00138-8 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shen, M., Liu, A., Huang, G., Xiong, N. N. &amp; Lu, H. ATTDC: An active and traceable trust data collection scheme for industrial security in smart cities. <italic>IEEE Internet Things J.</italic><bold>8</bold>(8), 6437–6453. 10.1109/JIOT.2021.3049173 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shen, M., Liu, A., Huang, G., Xiong, N. N. &amp; Lu, H. ATTDC: An active and traceable trust data collection scheme for industrial security in smart cities. IEEE Internet Things J.8(8), 6437–6453. 10.1109/JIOT.2021.3049173 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lv, Z., Chen, D. &amp; Li, J. Novel system design and implementation for the smart city vertical market. <italic>IEEE Commun. Maga.</italic><bold>59</bold>(4), 126–131. 10.1109/MCOM.001.2000945 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lv, Z., Chen, D. &amp; Li, J. Novel system design and implementation for the smart city vertical market. IEEE Commun. Maga.59(4), 126–131. 10.1109/MCOM.001.2000945 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Drangert, J. O. Urban water and food security in this century and beyond: Resource-smart cities and residents. <italic>AMBIO A Journal of the Human Environment</italic>10.1007/s13280-020-01373-1 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s13280-020-01373-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7882668"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33001342"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Drangert, J. O. Urban water and food security in this century and beyond: Resource-smart cities and residents. AMBIO A Journal of the Human Environment10.1007/s13280-020-01373-1 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cai, Z., Li, D., Deng, L. &amp; Yao, X. Smart city framework based on intelligent sensor network and visual surveillance. <italic>Concurr. Comput. Pract. Exp.</italic>10.1002/cpe.5301 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cai, Z., Li, D., Deng, L. &amp; Yao, X. Smart city framework based on intelligent sensor network and visual surveillance. Concurr. Comput. Pract. Exp.10.1002/cpe.5301 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Alazab, M., Lakshmanna, K., Reddy, T., Pham, Q.-V. &amp; Maddikunta, P. K. R. Multi-objective cluster head selection using fitness averaged rider optimization algorithm for IoT networks in smart cities. <italic>Sustain. Energy Technol. Assess.</italic><bold>43</bold>, 100973. 10.1016/j.seta.2020.100973 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Alazab, M., Lakshmanna, K., Reddy, T., Pham, Q.-V. &amp; Maddikunta, P. K. R. Multi-objective cluster head selection using fitness averaged rider optimization algorithm for IoT networks in smart cities. Sustain. Energy Technol. Assess.43, 100973. 10.1016/j.seta.2020.100973 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cha, J., Singh, S. K., Kim, T. W. &amp; Park, J. H. Blockchain-empowered cloud architecture based on secret sharing for smart city. <italic>J. Inf. Secur. Appl.</italic><bold>57</bold>, 102686. 10.1016/j.jisa.2020.102686 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cha, J., Singh, S. K., Kim, T. W. &amp; Park, J. H. Blockchain-empowered cloud architecture based on secret sharing for smart city. J. Inf. Secur. Appl.57, 102686. 10.1016/j.jisa.2020.102686 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, C., Ye, M., Chen, G. &amp; Wu, J. An energy-efficient unequal clustering mechanism for wireless sensor networks. In <italic>IEEE International Conference on Mobile Adhoc and Sensor Systems Conference</italic>, pp. 8–604. 10.1109/MAHSS.2005.1542849 (2005).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mehmood, A. &amp; Song, H. Smart energy efficient hierarchical data gathering protocols for wireless sensor networks. <italic>Smart Comput. Rev.</italic>10.6029/smartcr.2015.10.007 (2015).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mehmood, A. &amp; Song, H. Smart energy efficient hierarchical data gathering protocols for wireless sensor networks. Smart Comput. Rev.10.6029/smartcr.2015.10.007 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dixit, E. &amp; Jindal, V. IEESEP: An intelligent energy efficient stable election routing protocol in air pollution monitoring WSNS. <italic>Neural Comput. Appl.</italic><bold>34</bold>(13), 10989–11013. 10.1007/s00521-022-07027-5 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Dixit, E. &amp; Jindal, V. IEESEP: An intelligent energy efficient stable election routing protocol in air pollution monitoring WSNS. Neural Comput. Appl.34(13), 10989–11013. 10.1007/s00521-022-07027-5 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Divya, A., Kiruthika, R. &amp; Gayathri, D. Detecting and analysing the quality of air using low cost sensors to reduce air pollution in urban areas. In:<italic>2019 IEEE International Conference on System, Computation, Automation and Networking (ICSCAN)</italic>, pp. 1–5. 10.1109/ICSCAN.2019.8878780 (2019).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Maurya, S., Sharma, S. &amp; Yadav, P. Internet of things based air pollution penetrating system using GSM and GPRS. <italic>Int. Conf. Adv. Comput. Telecommun. (ICACAT)</italic><bold>2018</bold>, 1–5. 10.1109/ICACAT.2018.8933788 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Maurya, S., Sharma, S. &amp; Yadav, P. Internet of things based air pollution penetrating system using GSM and GPRS. Int. Conf. Adv. Comput. Telecommun. (ICACAT)2018, 1–5. 10.1109/ICACAT.2018.8933788 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Siregar, B., Nasution, A. N. &amp; Arisandi, D. Air pollution monitoring system using waspmote gases sensor board in wireless sensor network. In <italic>2020 International Conference on Data Science, Artificial Intelligence, and Business Analytics (DATABIA)</italic>, pp. 83–88. 10.1109/DATABIA50434.2020.9190503 (2020).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Handayani, A. S., Husni, N. L., Permatasari, R. &amp; Sitompul, C. R. Implementation of multi sensor network as air monitoring using iot applications. In <italic>2019 34th International Technical Conference on Circuits/Systems, Computers and Communications (ITC-CSCC)</italic>, pp. 1–4. 10.1109/ITC-CSCC.2019.8793407 (2019).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Agnihotri, P., Tiwari, S. &amp; Mohan, D. Design of air pollution monitoring system using wireless sensor network. In <italic>2020 International Conference on Electrical and Electronics Engineering (ICE3)</italic>, pp. 33–38 . 10.1109/ICE348803.2020.9122796 (2020).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Marques, G. &amp; Pitarma, R. Air quality through automated mobile sensing and wireless sensor networks for enhanced living environments. In <italic>2019 14th Iberian Conference on Information Systems and Technologies (CISTI)</italic>, pp. 1–7. 10.23919/CISTI.2019.8760641 (2019).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Guanochanga, B. et al. Towards a real time air pollution monitoring systems implemented using wireless sensor networks: Preliminary results. <italic>IEEE Colomb. Conf. Commun. Comput. (COLCOM)</italic><bold>2018</bold>, 1–4. 10.1109/ColComCon.2018.8466721 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Guanochanga, B. et al. Towards a real time air pollution monitoring systems implemented using wireless sensor networks: Preliminary results. IEEE Colomb. Conf. Commun. Comput. (COLCOM)2018, 1–4. 10.1109/ColComCon.2018.8466721 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Naik, D. R., Das, L. B. &amp; Bindiya, T. S. Wireless sensor networks with zigbee and wifi for environment monitoring, traffic management and vehicle monitoring in smart cities. In <italic>2018 IEEE 3rd International Conference on Computing, Communication and Security (ICCCS)</italic>, pp. 46–50. 10.1109/CCCS.2018.8586819 (2018).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ortiz, D., Ben’itez, D. S., Fuertes, W. &amp; Torres, J. On the use of low cost sensors for the implementation of a real-time air pollution monitoring system using wireless sensor networks. In <italic>IEEE International Autumn Meeting on Power, Electronics and Computing (ROPEC)</italic><bold>2018</bold>, 1–6. 10.1109/ROPEC.2018.8661479 (2018).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hojaiji, H., Goldstein, O., King, C. E., Sarrafzadeh, M. &amp; Jerrett, M. Design and calibration of a wearable and wireless research grade air quality monitoring system for real-time data collection, in. <italic>IEEE Glob. Humanit. Technol. Conf. (GHTC)</italic><bold>2017</bold>, 1–10. 10.1109/GHTC.2017.8239308 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hojaiji, H., Goldstein, O., King, C. E., Sarrafzadeh, M. &amp; Jerrett, M. Design and calibration of a wearable and wireless research grade air quality monitoring system for real-time data collection, in. IEEE Glob. Humanit. Technol. Conf. (GHTC)2017, 1–10. 10.1109/GHTC.2017.8239308 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Laskar, M. R., Sen, P. K. &amp; Das Mandal, S. K. An IoT-based e-health system integrated with wireless sensor network and air pollution index. In <italic>2019 Second International Conference on Advanced Computational and Communication Paradigms (ICACCP)</italic>, pp. 1–5. 10.1109/ICACCP.2019.8882985 (2019).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Adu-Manu, K., Katsriku, F., Abdulai, J.-D. &amp; Engmann, F. Smart river monitoring using wireless sensor networks. <italic>Wirel. Commun. Mob. Comput.</italic>10.1155/2020/8897126 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Adu-Manu, K., Katsriku, F., Abdulai, J.-D. &amp; Engmann, F. Smart river monitoring using wireless sensor networks. Wirel. Commun. Mob. Comput.10.1155/2020/8897126 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gazis, A. &amp; Katsiri, E. A wireless sensor network for underground passages: Remote sensing and wildlife monitoring. <italic>Eng. Rep.</italic><bold>2</bold>(6), e12170. 10.1002/eng2.12170 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gazis, A. &amp; Katsiri, E. A wireless sensor network for underground passages: Remote sensing and wildlife monitoring. Eng. Rep.2(6), e12170. 10.1002/eng2.12170 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Luo, X. &amp; Yang, J. A survey on pollution monitoring using sensor networks in environment protection. <italic>J. Sens.</italic><bold>2019</bold>, 1–11. 10.1155/2019/6271206 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Luo, X. &amp; Yang, J. A survey on pollution monitoring using sensor networks in environment protection. J. Sens.2019, 1–11. 10.1155/2019/6271206 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pavani, M. &amp; Rao, P. Monitoring real-time urban carbon monoxide (co) emissions using wireless sensor networks, pp. 290–297. 10.1007/978-3-319-63645-032 (2018).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dixit, E. &amp; Rani, S. E2R2D2: Energy-efficient robust routing and data distribution protocol in wireless air pollution monitoring system. <italic>Wirel. Netw.</italic>10.1007/s11276-025-03899-2 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Dixit, E. &amp; Rani, S. E2R2D2: Energy-efficient robust routing and data distribution protocol in wireless air pollution monitoring system. Wirel. Netw.10.1007/s11276-025-03899-2 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Abdulkareem, Hasnaa H. &amp; Hassan, Hassan J. Air pollution monitoring system for University workstation based on wireless sensor network. <italic>AIP Conf. Proc.</italic><bold>3169</bold>(1), 040059. 10.1063/5.0254321 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Abdulkareem, Hasnaa H. &amp; Hassan, Hassan J. Air pollution monitoring system for University workstation based on wireless sensor network. AIP Conf. Proc.3169(1), 040059. 10.1063/5.0254321 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tang, R. et al. Research on rechargeable agricultural wireless sensor network based on ZigBee immune routing repair algorithm. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 5756. 10.1038/s41598-025-89710-w (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-025-89710-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11833091"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39962080"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tang, R. et al. Research on rechargeable agricultural wireless sensor network based on ZigBee immune routing repair algorithm. Sci. Rep.15, 5756. 10.1038/s41598-025-89710-w (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shi, Ting et al. 112008. <italic>ISSN</italic><bold>2352–7102</bold>, 10.1016/j.jobe.2025.112008 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh, Parvinder &amp; Vir, Rajinder. Enhanced energy-aware routing protocol with mobile sink optimization for wireless sensor networks. <italic>Comput. Netw.</italic><bold>261</bold>, 111100. 10.1016/j.comnet.2025.111100 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Singh, Parvinder &amp; Vir, Rajinder. Enhanced energy-aware routing protocol with mobile sink optimization for wireless sensor networks. Comput. Netw.261, 111100. 10.1016/j.comnet.2025.111100 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh, S., Garg, D. &amp; Malik, A. A novel cluster head selection algorithm based IoT enabled heterogeneous WSNs distributed architecture for smart city. <italic>Microprocess. Microsyst.</italic><bold>101</bold>, 104892 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Singh, S., Garg, D. &amp; Malik, A. A novel cluster head selection algorithm based IoT enabled heterogeneous WSNs distributed architecture for smart city. Microprocess. Microsyst.101, 104892 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Del-Valle-Soto, C., Rodríguez, A. &amp; Ascencio-Piña, C. R. A survey of energy-efficient clustering routing protocols for wireless sensor networks based on metaheuristic approaches. <italic>Artif. Intell. Rev.</italic><bold>56</bold>(9), 9699–9770 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Del-Valle-Soto, C., Rodríguez, A. &amp; Ascencio-Piña, C. R. A survey of energy-efficient clustering routing protocols for wireless sensor networks based on metaheuristic approaches. Artif. Intell. Rev.56(9), 9699–9770 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Berniak-Woźny, J., Siciński, J. &amp; Sliż, P. Empowering smart cities through start-ups: A sustainability framework for incubator-city collaboration. <italic>Systems</italic><bold>13</bold>(4), 219. 10.3390/systems13040219 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Berniak-Woźny, J., Siciński, J. &amp; Sliż, P. Empowering smart cities through start-ups: A sustainability framework for incubator-city collaboration. Systems13(4), 219. 10.3390/systems13040219 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Madan, B., Nair, S., Katariya, N., Mehta, A. &amp; Gogte, P. Smart waste management and air pollution forecasting: Harnessing Internet of things and fully Elman neural network. <italic>Waste Manag. Res.</italic><bold>43</bold>(8), 1193–1205. 10.1177/0734242x241313286 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/0734242X241313286"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40111379"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Madan, B., Nair, S., Katariya, N., Mehta, A. &amp; Gogte, P. Smart waste management and air pollution forecasting: Harnessing Internet of things and fully Elman neural network. Waste Manag. Res.43(8), 1193–1205. 10.1177/0734242x241313286 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sahu, D. et al. A multi objective optimization framework for smart parking using digital twin pareto front MDP and PSO for smart cities. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic>10.1038/s41598-025-91565-0 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-025-91565-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11883022"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40044776"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sahu, D. et al. A multi objective optimization framework for smart parking using digital twin pareto front MDP and PSO for smart cities. Sci. Rep.10.1038/s41598-025-91565-0 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Huo, D., Sun, T., Gu, W. &amp; Qiao, L. Smart cities with green resilience: A quasi-natural experiment based on artificial intelligence. <italic>Smart Cities</italic><bold>8</bold>(2), 67. 10.3390/smartcities8020067 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Huo, D., Sun, T., Gu, W. &amp; Qiao, L. Smart cities with green resilience: A quasi-natural experiment based on artificial intelligence. Smart Cities8(2), 67. 10.3390/smartcities8020067 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mahomed, A. S. &amp; Saha, A. K. Unleashing the potential of 5G for smart cities: A focus on real-time digital twin integration. <italic>Smart Cities</italic><bold>8</bold>(2), 70. 10.3390/smartcities8020070 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mahomed, A. S. &amp; Saha, A. K. Unleashing the potential of 5G for smart cities: A focus on real-time digital twin integration. Smart Cities8(2), 70. 10.3390/smartcities8020070 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Salih, S. et al. IoT in urban development: Insight into smart city applications, case studies, challenges, and future prospects. <italic>PeerJ. Comput. Sci.</italic><bold>11</bold>, e2816. 10.7717/peerj-cs.2816 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7717/peerj-cs.2816"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12190393"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40567701"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Salih, S. et al. IoT in urban development: Insight into smart city applications, case studies, challenges, and future prospects. PeerJ. Comput. Sci.11, e2816. 10.7717/peerj-cs.2816 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Alsalehy, A. S. &amp; Bailey, M. Improving time series data quality: Identifying outliers and handling missing values in a multilocation gas and weather dataset. <italic>Smart Cities</italic><bold>8</bold>(3), 82. 10.3390/smartcities8030082 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Alsalehy, A. S. &amp; Bailey, M. Improving time series data quality: Identifying outliers and handling missing values in a multilocation gas and weather dataset. Smart Cities8(3), 82. 10.3390/smartcities8030082 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Huang, J., Bibri, S. E. &amp; Keel, P. Generative spatial artificial intelligence for sustainable smart cities: A pioneering large flow model for urban digital twin. <italic>Environ. Sci. Ecotechnol.</italic><bold>24</bold>, 100526. 10.1016/j.ese.2025.100526 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ese.2025.100526"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11847743"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39995465"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Huang, J., Bibri, S. E. &amp; Keel, P. Generative spatial artificial intelligence for sustainable smart cities: A pioneering large flow model for urban digital twin. Environ. Sci. Ecotechnol.24, 100526. 10.1016/j.ese.2025.100526 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kim, C., Son, S. &amp; Park, Y. A privacy-preserving authentication scheme using PUF and biometrics for IoT-enabled smart cities. <italic>Electronics</italic><bold>14</bold>(10), 1953. 10.3390/electronics14101953 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kim, C., Son, S. &amp; Park, Y. A privacy-preserving authentication scheme using PUF and biometrics for IoT-enabled smart cities. Electronics14(10), 1953. 10.3390/electronics14101953 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Silva, N. S. E., Castro, R. &amp; Ferrão, P. Smart grids in the context of smart cities: A literature review and gap analysis. <italic>Energies</italic><bold>18</bold>(5), 1186. 10.3390/en18051186 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Silva, N. S. E., Castro, R. &amp; Ferrão, P. Smart grids in the context of smart cities: A literature review and gap analysis. Energies18(5), 1186. 10.3390/en18051186 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Vignesh, C. C., Sivaparthipan, C. B., Daniel, J. A., Jeon, G. &amp; Anand, M. B. Adjacent node based energetic association factor routing protocol in wireless sensor networks. <italic>Wirel. Pers. Commun.</italic><bold>119</bold>(4), 3255–3270. 10.1007/s11277-021-08397-0 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Vignesh, C. C., Sivaparthipan, C. B., Daniel, J. A., Jeon, G. &amp; Anand, M. B. Adjacent node based energetic association factor routing protocol in wireless sensor networks. Wirel. Pers. Commun.119(4), 3255–3270. 10.1007/s11277-021-08397-0 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lingaraj, K., Malghan, R. L., Rao, K. &amp; Garg, L. Adaptive landslide monitoring in wireless sensor networks using FLPSO-based MIP systems. <italic>Results Eng.</italic><bold>25</bold>, 104329. 10.1016/j.rineng.2025.104329 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lingaraj, K., Malghan, R. L., Rao, K. &amp; Garg, L. Adaptive landslide monitoring in wireless sensor networks using FLPSO-based MIP systems. Results Eng.25, 104329. 10.1016/j.rineng.2025.104329 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Stephan, T. et al. Fuzzy-logic-inspired zone-based clustering algorithm for wireless sensor networks. <italic>Int. J. Fuzzy Syst.</italic><bold>23</bold>, 1–12. 10.1007/s40815-020-00929-3 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Stephan, T. et al. Fuzzy-logic-inspired zone-based clustering algorithm for wireless sensor networks. Int. J. Fuzzy Syst.23, 1–12. 10.1007/s40815-020-00929-3 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bhushan, S. et al. Fajit: A fuzzy-based data aggregation technique for energy efficiency in wireless sensor network. <italic>Complex Intell. Syst.</italic>10.1007/s40747-020-00258-w (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bhushan, S. et al. Fajit: A fuzzy-based data aggregation technique for energy efficiency in wireless sensor network. Complex Intell. Syst.10.1007/s40747-020-00258-w (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nguyen, N. T., Liu, B. H., Pham, V. T. &amp; Liou, T. Y. An efficient minimumlatency collision-free scheduling algorithm for data aggregation in wireless sensor networks. <italic>IEEE Syst. J.</italic><bold>12</bold>(3), 2214–2225. 10.1109/JSYST.2017.2751645 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nguyen, N. T., Liu, B. H., Pham, V. T. &amp; Liou, T. Y. An efficient minimumlatency collision-free scheduling algorithm for data aggregation in wireless sensor networks. IEEE Syst. J.12(3), 2214–2225. 10.1109/JSYST.2017.2751645 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nguyen, N. T., Liu, B. H. &amp; Weng, H. Z. A distributed algorithm: Minimum latency collision-avoidance multiple-data-aggregation scheduling in multichannel wsns, in. <italic>IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)</italic><bold>2018</bold>, 1–6. 10.1109/ICC.2018.8422177 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nguyen, N. T., Liu, B. H. &amp; Weng, H. Z. A distributed algorithm: Minimum latency collision-avoidance multiple-data-aggregation scheduling in multichannel wsns, in. IEEE Int. Conf. Commun. (ICC)2018, 1–6. 10.1109/ICC.2018.8422177 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gao, J., Wang, H. &amp; Shen, H. Task failure prediction in cloud data centers using deep learning. <italic>IEEE Int. Conf. Big Data</italic><bold>2019</bold>, 1111–1116. 10.1109/BigData47090.2019.9006011 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gao, J., Wang, H. &amp; Shen, H. Task failure prediction in cloud data centers using deep learning. IEEE Int. Conf. Big Data2019, 1111–1116. 10.1109/BigData47090.2019.9006011 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Karthik, S., Karthik, M., Karthikeyan, N. &amp; Kannan, S. A multi-mobile agent and optimal itinerary planning-based data aggregation in wireless sensor networks. <italic>Comput. Commun.</italic><bold>184</bold>, 24–35 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Karthik, S., Karthik, M., Karthikeyan, N. &amp; Kannan, S. A multi-mobile agent and optimal itinerary planning-based data aggregation in wireless sensor networks. Comput. Commun.184, 24–35 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lingaraj, K., Biradar, R. V. &amp; Patil, V. C. Eagilla: An enhanced mobile agent middleware for wireless sensor networks. <italic>Alex. Eng. J.</italic><bold>57</bold>(3), 1197–1204 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lingaraj, K., Biradar, R. V. &amp; Patil, V. C. Eagilla: An enhanced mobile agent middleware for wireless sensor networks. Alex. Eng. J.57(3), 1197–1204 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang, Q. S. Environment pollution analysis on smart cities using wireless sensor networks. <italic>Strateg. Plann. Energy Environ.</italic><bold>42</bold>(01), 239–262. 10.13052/spee1048-5236.42112 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhang, Q. S. Environment pollution analysis on smart cities using wireless sensor networks. Strateg. Plann. Energy Environ.42(01), 239–262. 10.13052/spee1048-5236.42112 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lingaraj, K., Biradar, Rajashree V. &amp; Patil, V. C. OMMIP: An optimized multiple mobile agents itinerary planning for wireless sensor networks. <italic>J. Inf. Optim. Sci.</italic><bold>38</bold>(6), 1067–1076 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lingaraj, K., Biradar, Rajashree V. &amp; Patil, V. C. OMMIP: An optimized multiple mobile agents itinerary planning for wireless sensor networks. J. Inf. Optim. Sci.38(6), 1067–1076 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lingaraj, K., Biradar, Rajashree V. &amp; Patil, V.C. A survey on middleware challenges and approaches for wireless sensor networks. In <italic>7th IEEE CICN-2015 Organized by GGITS, Jabalpur</italic>, pp. 56–60 (2015).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lingaraj, K., Biradar, Rajashree V. &amp; Patil, V.C. A survey on mobile-agent middleware design principals and itinerary planning algorithms. In <italic>IEEE ICATCCT-2015, Organized by BIET, Davangere</italic> pp. 749–756 (2015).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kortoçi, P. et al. Air pollution exposure monitoring using portable low-cost air quality sensors. <italic>Smart Health</italic><bold>23</bold>, 100241 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kortoçi, P. et al. Air pollution exposure monitoring using portable low-cost air quality sensors. Smart Health23, 100241 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Paithankar, D. N., Pabale, A. R., Kolhe, R. V., William, P. &amp; Yawalkar, P. M. Framework for implementing air quality monitoring system using LPWA-based IoT technique. <italic>Meas. Sens.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 100709 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Paithankar, D. N., Pabale, A. R., Kolhe, R. V., William, P. &amp; Yawalkar, P. M. Framework for implementing air quality monitoring system using LPWA-based IoT technique. Meas. Sens.26, 100709 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhao, L., Zhou, H., Chen, R. &amp; Shen, Z. Efficient monitoring and adaptive control of indoor air quality based on IoT technology and fuzzy inference. <italic>Wirel. Commun. Mob. Comput.</italic>10.1155/2022/4127079 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhao, L., Zhou, H., Chen, R. &amp; Shen, Z. Efficient monitoring and adaptive control of indoor air quality based on IoT technology and fuzzy inference. Wirel. Commun. Mob. Comput.10.1155/2022/4127079 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Maduranga, P. K., Hasanthi Karunarathna, G. Design of an IoT based indoor air quality monitoring system (2020).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Christakis, I., Tsakiridis, O., Kandris, D. &amp; Stavrakas, I. Air pollution monitoring via wireless sensor networks: The investigation and correction of the aging behavior of electrochemical gaseous pollutant sensors. <italic>Electronics</italic><bold>12</bold>(8), 1842. 10.3390/electronics12081842 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Christakis, I., Tsakiridis, O., Kandris, D. &amp; Stavrakas, I. Air pollution monitoring via wireless sensor networks: The investigation and correction of the aging behavior of electrochemical gaseous pollutant sensors. Electronics12(8), 1842. 10.3390/electronics12081842 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yang, Wendong, Wang, Jingyi, Zhang, Kai &amp; Hao, Yan. A novel air pollution forecasting, health effects, and economic cost assessment system for environmental management: From a new perspective of the district-level. <italic>J. Clean. Prod.</italic><bold>417</bold>, 138027. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2023.138027 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yang, Wendong, Wang, Jingyi, Zhang, Kai &amp; Hao, Yan. A novel air pollution forecasting, health effects, and economic cost assessment system for environmental management: From a new perspective of the district-level. J. Clean. Prod.417, 138027. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2023.138027 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hadi, H. J. et al. Real-time fusion multi-tier DNN-based collaborative IDPS with complementary features for secure UAV-enabled 6G networks. <italic>Expert Syst. Appl.</italic><bold>252</bold>, 124215. 10.1016/j.eswa.2024.124215 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hadi, H. J. et al. Real-time fusion multi-tier DNN-based collaborative IDPS with complementary features for secure UAV-enabled 6G networks. Expert Syst. Appl.252, 124215. 10.1016/j.eswa.2024.124215 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Frank, Lawrence D. &amp; Wali, Behram. Monitoring changes in walkability over time: An environmental exposure change detection framework with implications for equity and social justice. <italic>Sustain. Cities Soc.</italic>10.1016/j.scs.2024.105808 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Frank, Lawrence D. &amp; Wali, Behram. Monitoring changes in walkability over time: An environmental exposure change detection framework with implications for equity and social justice. Sustain. Cities Soc.10.1016/j.scs.2024.105808 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, X. et al. Big data in earth system science and progress towards a digital twin. <italic>Nat. Rev. Earth Environ.</italic><bold>4</bold>, 319–332. 10.1038/s43017-023-00409-w (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, X. et al. Big data in earth system science and progress towards a digital twin. Nat. Rev. Earth Environ.4, 319–332. 10.1038/s43017-023-00409-w (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang, M. et al. Fetching ecosystem monitoring data in extreme areas via a drone-enabled internet of remote things. <italic>IEEE Internet Things J.</italic><bold>9</bold>(24), 25052–25067. 10.1109/JIOT.2022.3195302 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhang, M. et al. Fetching ecosystem monitoring data in extreme areas via a drone-enabled internet of remote things. IEEE Internet Things J.9(24), 25052–25067. 10.1109/JIOT.2022.3195302 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhan, C. et al. First evaluation of GPM-Era satellite precipitation products with new observations on the western Tibetan Plateau. <italic>Atmos. Res.</italic><bold>283</bold>, 106559. 10.1016/j.atmosres.2022.106559 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhan, C. et al. First evaluation of GPM-Era satellite precipitation products with new observations on the western Tibetan Plateau. Atmos. Res.283, 106559. 10.1016/j.atmosres.2022.106559 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu, F., Zhao, Z. &amp; Li, X. Quantifying the representativeness errors caused by scale transformation of remote sensing data in stochastic ensemble data assimilation. <italic>IEEE J. Sel. Top. Appl. Earth Obs. Remote Sens.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1968–1980. 10.1109/JSTARS.2022.3149957 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liu, F., Zhao, Z. &amp; Li, X. Quantifying the representativeness errors caused by scale transformation of remote sensing data in stochastic ensemble data assimilation. IEEE J. Sel. Top. Appl. Earth Obs. Remote Sens.15, 1968–1980. 10.1109/JSTARS.2022.3149957 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Xiang, Lixiong Huang et al. Prehistoric population expansion in Central Asia promoted by the Altai Holocene Climatic Optimum. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic>10.1038/s41467-023-38828-4 (2023).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-023-38828-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10227073"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37248221"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Xiang, Lixiong Huang et al. Prehistoric population expansion in Central Asia promoted by the Altai Holocene Climatic Optimum. Nat. Commun.10.1038/s41467-023-38828-4 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chen, F. H. et al. Discussion of the warming and wetting trend and its future variation in the drylands of Northwest China under global warming. <italic>Sci. China Earth Sci.</italic>10.1007/s11430-022-1098-x (2023).36590657
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chen, F. H. et al. Discussion of the warming and wetting trend and its future variation in the drylands of Northwest China under global warming. Sci. China Earth Sci.10.1007/s11430-022-1098-x (2023).36590657"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chen, F. H. et al. Westerlies Asia and monsoonal Asia: Spatiotemporal differences in climate change and possible mechanisms on decadal to sub-orbital timescales. <italic>Earth-Sci. Rev.</italic><bold>192</bold>, 337–354 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chen, F. H. et al. Westerlies Asia and monsoonal Asia: Spatiotemporal differences in climate change and possible mechanisms on decadal to sub-orbital timescales. Earth-Sci. Rev.192, 337–354 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Biancone, P. &amp; Graziano, M. Disruptive mobility for smart cities: It’s time to change!. <italic>J. Clean. Prod.</italic><bold>472</bold>, 143575. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2024.143575 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Biancone, P. &amp; Graziano, M. Disruptive mobility for smart cities: It’s time to change!. J. Clean. Prod.472, 143575. 10.1016/j.jclepro.2024.143575 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Beba, H. &amp; Öztürk, Z. Investigation of models predicting NOx level in the sample region and the use of intelligent transportation system. <italic>Environ. Chall.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 100990. 10.1016/j.envc.2024.100990 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Beba, H. &amp; Öztürk, Z. Investigation of models predicting NOx level in the sample region and the use of intelligent transportation system. Environ. Chall.16, 100990. 10.1016/j.envc.2024.100990 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR79"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, H., Wang, X., Yin, Y., Deng, X. &amp; Umair, M. Evaluation of urban transportation carbon footprint - Artificial intelligence based solution. <italic>Transp. Res. Part D Transp. Environ.</italic><bold>136</bold>, 104406. 10.1016/j.trd.2024.104406 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, H., Wang, X., Yin, Y., Deng, X. &amp; Umair, M. Evaluation of urban transportation carbon footprint - Artificial intelligence based solution. Transp. Res. Part D Transp. Environ.136, 104406. 10.1016/j.trd.2024.104406 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Alkaissi, Z. A. Traffic congestion evaluation of urban streets based on fuzzy inference system and GIS application. <italic>Ain Shams Eng. J.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 102725. 10.1016/j.asej.2024.102725 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Alkaissi, Z. A. Traffic congestion evaluation of urban streets based on fuzzy inference system and GIS application. Ain Shams Eng. J.15, 102725. 10.1016/j.asej.2024.102725 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR81"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liao, Z., Cai, L., Yang, Q. &amp; Zhang, Y. Design of lateral dynamic control objectives for multi-wheeled distributed drive electric vehicles. <italic>Eng. Sci. Technol. Int. J.</italic><bold>50</bold>, 101629. 10.1016/j.jestch.2024.101629 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liao, Z., Cai, L., Yang, Q. &amp; Zhang, Y. Design of lateral dynamic control objectives for multi-wheeled distributed drive electric vehicles. Eng. Sci. Technol. Int. J.50, 101629. 10.1016/j.jestch.2024.101629 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR82"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Meo, S. A., Salih, M. A., Alkhalifah, J. M., Alsomali, A. H. &amp; Almushawah, A. A. Environmental pollutants particulate matter (PM2.5, PM10), Carbon Monoxide (CO), Nitrogen dioxide (NO2), Sulfur dioxide (SO2), and Ozone (O3) impact on lung functions. <italic>J. King Saud Univ. Sci.</italic><bold>36</bold>(7), 103280. 10.1016/j.jksus.2024.103280 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Meo, S. A., Salih, M. A., Alkhalifah, J. M., Alsomali, A. H. &amp; Almushawah, A. A. Environmental pollutants particulate matter (PM2.5, PM10), Carbon Monoxide (CO), Nitrogen dioxide (NO2), Sulfur dioxide (SO2), and Ozone (O3) impact on lung functions. J. King Saud Univ. Sci.36(7), 103280. 10.1016/j.jksus.2024.103280 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The dataset and code supporting the conclusion of this article is available in the github repository. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/lingarajpower/FLPSO-MATLAB" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/lingarajpower/FLPSO-MATLAB</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec></body></article>