<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="other"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">962</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ijcommed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Indian Journal of Community Medicine: Official Publication of Indian Association of Preventive &amp; Social Medicine</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Indian J Community Med</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer -- Medknow Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12815361</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12815361</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12815361</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41561726</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijcm.ijcm_663_24</article-id><title-group><article-title>Impact of Housing Conditions and Air Quality Awareness with Indoor PM2.5 Levels in Urban Jodhpur</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Huda</surname><given-names initials="RK">Ramesh Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="author-notes">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names initials="R">Rajnish</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names initials="P">Pankaj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names initials="J">Jayvardhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names initials="AK">Arun Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Toteja</surname><given-names initials="GS">GS</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Babu</surname><given-names initials="BV">Bontha V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Indian Council of Medical Research, National Institute for Implementation Research on Non-Communicable Diseases, Jodhpur, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Community Medicine, University College of Medical Sciences, Delhi, India</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Jodhpur City Knowledge and Innovation Foundation, Indian Institute of Technology, Jodhpur, India</aff><author-notes><fn id="cor1"><label>✉</label><p><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Ramesh Kumar Huda, Indian Council of Medical Research - National Institute for Implementation Research in Non-Communicable Diseases (ICMR-NIIRNCD), Jodhpur – 342 005, India. E-mail: <email>ramesh.hudda@gmail.com</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>50</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><fpage>S516</fpage><page-range>S516–S521</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: © 2025 Indian Journal of Community Medicine</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="IJCM-50-516.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 0e08/12815361/f99507fd76c4/IJCM-50-516.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 487562?></self-uri><abstract id="abstract1"><title>Abstract</title><p>Indoor air pollution poses a major public health concern in India, particularly among urban populations exposed to high levels of particulate matter. This study aimed to assess the influence of housing conditions and awareness on indoor particulate matter (PM2.5) levels in Jodhpur, Rajasthan. A cross-sectional study was conducted across 12 households representing slum, low-, middle-, and high-income groups, as well as commercial and industrial areas. Indoor PM2.5 concentrations were continuously monitored over a one-year period using pre-calibrated AirVisual Pro devices. Awareness regarding indoor air pollution and preventive measures was evaluated through structured questionnaires administered before and after an awareness intervention. The findings revealed that effective ventilation and good hygiene practices significantly contributed to reducing indoor PM2.5 levels. Poorly ventilated homes, such as House 1 (62 μg/m³) and House 4 (73 μg/m³), exhibited higher pollutant concentrations, while well-ventilated or air-conditioned homes, such as House 2 (46 μg/m³) and House 3 (40 μg/m³), maintained lower levels. The highest concentration (111 μg/m³) was recorded in House 5, which is located near a highway with inadequate ventilation. The awareness component showed a marked improvement in residents’ understanding of air pollution sources, health impacts, and mitigation strategies following real-time monitoring and education sessions. The study concludes that housing ventilation, seasonal behavioral factors, and real-time monitoring play a crucial role in determining indoor air quality. Strengthening building design standards and enhancing public awareness are vital for sustainable indoor air quality management in urban India.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Housing conditions, indoor air quality (IAQ), PM2.5, seasonal variations</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2024 Sep 6; Accepted 2025 Sep 9; Issue date 2025 Dec.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="sec1" disp-level="1"><title>I<sc>NTRODUCTION</sc></title><p>In India, exposure to ambient air pollution on the urban population is among the highest levels anywhere else in the world. Indoor air pollution is a critical public health concern, especially in developing countries. It is caused by harmful chemicals and materials that degrade air quality within enclosed spaces, making it up to 10 times worse than outdoor air pollution.[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] The urban landscape, comprising densely packed houses that have been built without any consideration for proper ventilation, combined with the use of biomass as cooking fuel and high atmospheric dust, contaminates the indoor air to very hazardous levels. These pollutants contribute to severe health outcomes, such as respiratory infections, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), lung cancer, and adverse perinatal outcomes. Incriminating evidence is gradually being generated about the role of pollutants in type-2 diabetes mellitus, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, and cognitive function disorders.[<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</p><p>Women and children are disproportionately affected due to their extended exposure to indoor pollutants, particularly from cooking with biomass fuels. These findings underscore the urgent need for interventions such as clean cooking technologies, improved building designs, and public education to mitigate the health impacts of indoor air pollution.[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</p><p>A study conducted in South India assessed the levels of PM2.5 in rural households, finding significant differences based on the type of housing and ventilation available. The study revealed that houses with poor ventilation and those using biomass fuels had higher concentrations of PM2.5, posing greater health risks to residents.[<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] In future, a significant proportion of households will use incense sticks, mosquito coils, and kerosene, which contribute to poor indoor air quality (IAQ). Additionally, overcrowding and inadequate ventilation were prevalent. Hence, it highlights the importance of improving housing conditions, increasing awareness about the health risks of indoor air pollution, and promoting the use of cleaner fuels to reduce the consequences may give more references to indoor air pollution.[<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</p><p>In India, cultural housing conditions, climate, and geographies vary from region to region. Hence, studies in specific geographies are needed to understand the nature and extent of indoor air pollution. Therefore, this study was conducted to determine the effect of housing conditions and people’s awareness about pollution on indoor air pollution in Jodhpur, western Rajasthan, India.</p></sec><sec id="sec2" disp-level="1"><title>S<sc>UBJECTS AND</sc> M<sc>ETHODS</sc></title><p>Study area: This community-based cross-sectional study was conducted in Jodhpur, a city in western Rajasthan located at 26°17’N and 73°01’E, spread over 233 km<sup>2</sup>, having a population of 9,21,476 (source: Jodhpur, India Population (2024) - Population Stat).[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] The study was conducted in residential premises, in slums, low-income, middle-income, and upper-income households, as well as commercial and industrial establishments.</p><sec id="sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Data collection procedure</title><sec id="sec4" disp-level="3"><title>Indoor air quality</title><p>Detailed methodology is provided elsewhere.[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] For IAQ assessment, two houses each were randomly selected from slums, low-income, middle-income, and upper-income households, as well as commercial and industrial establishments. Portable electricity/battery-operated pre-calibrated air quality monitors, AirVisual Pro Indoor Sensor (IQAir), were deployed in the selected households for one year. These houses were equipped with air quality monitors to measure PM2.5 levels.</p></sec><sec id="sec5" disp-level="3"><title>Awareness assessment</title><p>A survey was carried out using a structured, pre-tested questionnaire to assess the level of awareness about air pollution among the residents of all households selected for air quality monitoring (AQM), and devices were installed.</p><p>The housing conditions in these 12 houses were analyzed using a self-structured questionnaire and observation checklist, where higher scores indicated poorer air quality and lower scores suggested better air quality in the house.</p><p>This scoring system offers valuable insights into the current state of IAQ to identify specific areas for intervention and improvement. Scores of 0 typically indicate better practices or conditions that contribute to healthier indoor environments, while scores of 1 highlight areas where corrective actions are needed to mitigate potential health risks associated with indoor air pollution [<xref rid="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-T1" ref-type="table">Supplementary Table 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-T1" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><caption><p>Scoring criteria for indoor air quality measurement</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. No.,</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Criteria</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scoring</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ventilation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cross ventilation present<break/>Ventilators in living rooms<break/>Ventilators in the kitchen</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes=0, No=1<break/>Yes=0, No=1<break/>Yes=0, No=1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Appliance use</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Air conditioners<break/>Desert coolers<break/>Exhaust fans<break/>Air purifier</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes=0, No=1<break/>Yes=0, No=1<break/>Yes=0, No=1<break/>Yes=0, No=1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heating appliances</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Room heater<break/>Blower</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes=1, No=0<break/>Yes=1, No=0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dust and cleanliness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The presence of thick dust<break/>Mold/fungi presence</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes=1, No=0<break/>Yes=1, No=0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housing condition</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pakka house construction<break/>The kitchen is separated from the living room<break/>Dustbins covered</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes=0, No=1<break/>Yes=0, No=1<break/>Yes=0, No=1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Building and location factors</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proximity to the polluting establishment<break/>Located on a highway/expressway<break/>Located in an industrial/commercial area</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes=1, No=0<break/>Yes=1, No=0<break/>Yes=1, No=0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec6" disp-level="3"><title>Data management and analysis</title><p>All collected information was recorded digitally using an Excel sheet for further analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec7" disp-level="2"><title>Ethics and informed consent</title><p>Ethical clearance was obtained from the Institute Ethics Committee. Written consent was acquired from each participant after providing a comprehensive explanation of the study’s purpose and procedures. Participant confidentiality was strictly maintained throughout the study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec8" disp-level="1"><title>R<sc>ESULTS</sc></title><p><xref rid="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-T2" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows air pollution awareness among 12 participants in Jodhpur. At baseline, while 100% recognized air pollution and its health risks, specific knowledge was limited: Only 16.67% knew about the air quality index (AQI), and 8.33% were aware of pollution-related deaths in India. After the intervention, awareness improved significantly. AQI knowledge rose to 100%, and 75% knew about mortality due to air pollution. Recognition of specific health effects, such as breathing problems, reached 100%. All participants reported that AQM devices enhanced their understanding, with 58.33% committed to long-term use and 41.67% reporting direct benefits from the devices.</p><table-wrap id="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-T2" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Awareness of participants in selected areas of Jodhpur</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Questions</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-awareness yes (<italic>n</italic>=12)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-awareness yes (<italic>n</italic>=12)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you know about air pollution?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Is air pollution harmful to the health of humans and other living beings?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you know which air pollutants cause air pollution?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (50.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you know about the health effects of air pollution?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Which of the following is/are the health effects caused by air pollution?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breathing problem</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough up</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Watery eyes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All of the above</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (33.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Does air pollution cause disease?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Which of the following is/are the risk factor (s) caused by air pollution?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory infection</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (83.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPD</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung cancer</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All of the above</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you know about the sources of air pollution?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (83.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">What, according to you, is the main source of air pollution?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Industrial chimney</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (50.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traffic exit</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (66.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (75.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Open burning of garbage</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (83.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Building houses</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (75.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cigarette smoke</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (75.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other factors</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you know the number of deaths in India due to air pollution?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (75.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you know which city of Rajasthan is highly air-polluted?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (33.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you know about the air quality index?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Have you noticed air pollution in the area where you live?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (75.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (75.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">How do you rate the overall air quality in your area?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (66.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bad</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Don’t know</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">How severe is air pollution in the area where you live?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very less</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Less</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (33.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">More</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (16.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The most</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you think indoor air pollution can happen?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (75.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Where do you think pollution is more?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indoor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outdoor</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (91.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">How do you protect yourself when there is pollution in the air?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I wear a face mask</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.67)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cover my face with a handkerchief</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (25.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I do nothing</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (33.33)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Do you agree that every citizen’s responsibility is to improve the environment?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">What can you do to improve the environment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Planting trees</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Keeping surroundings clean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Planting trees and keeping the surroundings clean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (00.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Post-sensor installed</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have you benefited from having an air quality device installed in your home?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (41.67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">If the air quality device is installed in your home for a long time, will you take care of it?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you check the air quality instrument data regularly?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have you tried to work out pollution by looking at data from air quality instruments?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">If yes above question, which of the following have been attempted (Cleaning)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (58.33)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Has your air quality device increased your awareness?</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (100.00)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p><xref rid="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-T3" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows that indoor PM2.5 levels are closely linked to housing conditions. Poor ventilation and proximity to pollution sources led to higher PM2.5, as seen in House 5 (111 µg/m<sup>3</sup>, score 8) in a commercial area. In contrast, better-ventilated homes with lower housing condition scores had reduced PM2.5, such as House 3 (40 µg/m<sup>3</sup>, score 4) in an industrial area and House 12 (38 µg/m<sup>3</sup>, score 3) in a commercial area with good air conditioning and cleanliness. House 1 in a low-income area recorded 62 µg/m<sup>3</sup> (score 6) due to inadequate ventilation. Overall, lower scores of better housing conditions correlated with lower PM2.5, and seasonal increases were observed during winter.</p><table-wrap id="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-T3" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Household characteristics with PM2.5 indoor air quality measurement</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2">Area</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">LIG</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Industrial area</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Commercial area</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MIG</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">HIG</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="10" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Houses</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 1</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 2</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 3</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 4</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 5</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 6</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 9</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 10</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 11</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House 12</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Cross ventilation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Are there ventilators in living rooms</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Are the following gadgets used at home?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Air conditioners</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Desert coolers</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exhaust fan</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Room heater</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blower</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Air purifier</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Thick layer of dust</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Are dustbins covered with a lid</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Are there mold/fungi in the household</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Pakka house construction</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Is the house located on a highway/expressway</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Is the house located in an industrial area/commercial area</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Are there any polluting establishments in the neighborhood (within 50 meters)? (Restaurant/automobile workshop/waste disposal site/other specify)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Is kitchen separate from living room</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Source of ventilation in kitchen</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Avg. PM 2.5 (1 yr)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Score</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1-1"><p>Note: House 7 and House 8 were not analyzed due to their poor structural conditions in slum areas, which made it difficult to determine a proper correlation with PM2.5 levels and other variables. HIG: High-income group, LIG: Low-income group, MIG: Middle-income group</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> presents a strong positive linear correlation. This suggests that as the score for housing characteristics increases, the average PM2.5 levels also tend to increase. The <italic>P</italic> value for this correlation is 0.002, which is statistically significant [<xref rid="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-T4" ref-type="table">Supplementary Table 2</xref>].</p><fig id="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-F1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Linear correlation depicting housing characteristics with PM2.5</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="IJCM-50-516-g001.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/0e08/12815361/e12b065cd454/IJCM-50-516-g001.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 767?><?original-width 1108?><?scaled-height 511?><?scaled-width 738?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="IJCM-50-516-g001.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/0e08/12815361/c527f11e693a/IJCM-50-516-g001.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><table-wrap id="ijcm.ijcm_663_24-T4" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Supplementary Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlation of housing characteristics with PM2.5</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avg. PM2.5 (1 yr)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Person correlation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="10" colspan="1">0.845</td><td align="center" rowspan="10" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>PM2.5 levels vary by area: the industrial area fluctuated 52.36–110.72 µg/m<sup>3</sup>, slum areas had consistently high peaks up to 177.68 µg/m<sup>3</sup>, high-income group (HIG) colonies had lower levels, max 79.02 µg/m<sup>3</sup>, and middle-income group (MIG) colonies showed moderate levels up to 91.64 µg/m<sup>3</sup>. All areas experienced higher PM2.5 in winter [<inline-supplementary-material xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="IJCM-50-516_Suppl1.tif" id="d67e1311">Supplementary Figure 1<?cloudpmc-path 0e08/12815361/135901163cee/IJCM-50-516_Suppl1.tif?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1862260?></inline-supplementary-material>].</p></sec><sec id="sec9" disp-level="1"><title>D<sc>ISCUSSION</sc></title><p>This study examines the relationship between housing conditions, awareness, and indoor PM2.5 levels in urban Jodhpur, building on existing research on IAQ. These findings extend the work of Huda <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] who mapped ambient air quality in Jodhpur using low-cost sensors. While their study focused on outdoor pollution, the present research demonstrates that indoor air is significantly affected by both external emissions and internal housing deficiencies, highlighting the need for integrated indoor-outdoor AQM.</p><p>A positive correlation was found between housing condition scores, indicating structural and hygienic inadequacies and higher PM2.5 levels. This aligns with Vijay <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] who reported spatial and temporal variations in indoor PM2.5 across Indian urban homes, attributing higher concentrations to poor ventilation and household density. Similarly, Anand and Phuleria[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] found elevated indoor PM2.5 in Delhi’s slums due to structural constraints.</p><p>Proximity to traffic significantly impacted IAQ, as seen in a house near a highway with the highest. This supports Alhajeri <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] who identified traffic-related emissions as a major indoor pollutant in Kuwaiti homes. In contrast, a well-maintained commercial-area home with air conditioning recorded low PM2.5, indicating that mechanical ventilation and cleanliness can reduce outdoor infiltration. This contrasts with Ścibor <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] whose study in Poland found high indoor PM2.5 despite moderate outdoor levels, due to aging buildings and lack of filtration—highlighting that both building quality and behavioral practices are critical in urban Indian contexts.</p><p>Seasonal variation was evident, with PM2.5 rising in winter due to reduced ventilation and increased heating. This is consistent with Vijay <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] but this study adds a behavioral insight: residents restricted airflow to retain warmth, worsening indoor pollution. This thermal comfort–air quality trade-off is also noted by Niculita-Hirzel <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] in studies on urban environments and respiratory health.</p><p>Although cooking with biomass was not reported, findings from Karaca <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] show that even clean fuels like Liquefied Petroleum Gas (LPG) can generate PM2.5 spikes if kitchens lack proper ventilation. This underscores the need for kitchen-specific interventions such as exhaust fans. Papagiannis <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] identified traffic, construction, and industrial emissions as major PM2.5 sources in Dushanbe, Tajikistan, a pattern mirrored in Jodhpur’s industrial and commercial zones, especially when combined with poor housing infrastructure.</p><p>Awareness improved dramatically after installing air quality monitors. Awareness of the AQI rose from 16.67% to 100%, supporting Hou <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] who found that real-time data improves health literacy in Taiwan. Al-Shidi <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] reported similar gains in Oman through structured campaigns, but this study shows that device feedback alone can drive awareness, suggesting a low-effort, high-impact educational strategy. However, baseline knowledge of pollution-related mortality was very low, a gap also found by Gabel <italic>et al</italic>.[<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] in Greenland, indicating a global shortfall in communicating pollution’s health burden.</p><p>A clear socioeconomic gradient was observed higher-income households having better ventilation and lower PM2.5. This reflects findings by Dwivedi <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] who noted disproportionate exposure among women in low-income homes, and Ronita Bardhan <italic>et al</italic>.,[<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] who linked urban re-densification in Mumbai to deteriorated housing conditions. This study reaffirms that structural inequities place the greatest pollution burden on slum and low-income residents, who lack resources to improve their living environments.</p><sec id="sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Strengths and Limitations</title><p>The study used real-time, pre-calibrated air quality monitors (AirVisual Pro) over a 12-month period, ensuring reliable longitudinal data. The inclusion of diverse housing types—slum, low-, middle-, and high-income, as well as commercial and industrial areas—enhances the representativeness of findings for urban Jodhpur.</p><p>However, the small sample size limited statistical power and generalizability. Findings are specific to Jodhpur and may not apply to other climatic or urban settings. Only PM2.5 was measured, excluding other health-relevant pollutants such as NO₂, CO, and VOCs.</p></sec><sec id="sec11" disp-level="2"><title>Recommendations</title><p>Public education campaigns should expand to include information on the AQI, pollution-related mortality, and health risks, using schools, health centers, and local media. Urban planning policies must enforce ventilation standards in housing, particularly in low-income settlements, to reduce indoor pollution exposure.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec12" disp-level="1"><title>C<sc>ONCLUSION</sc></title><p>This study highlights that housing conditions and awareness significantly influence indoor PM2.5 levels in Jodhpur. Poor ventilation and proximity to pollution sources were linked to higher PM2.5, while better ventilation and air conditioning reduced levels. Seasonal spikes, especially in winter, worsened IAQ. Although general awareness of air pollution was high, knowledge of specific indicators like the AQI and pollution-related mortality was low. Installing air quality monitors significantly improved awareness and encouraged long-term engagement in air quality management.</p><sec id="sec13" disp-level="2"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec14" disp-level="1"><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Supplementary Figure 1</label><caption><p>Temporal distribution of PM2.5 levels in indoor areas of all colonies</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d67e1435" xlink:href="IJCM-50-516_Suppl1.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><?cloudpmc-path 0e08/12815361/135901163cee/IJCM-50-516_Suppl1.tif?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1862260?></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>We thank our study participants and their families for their patience and kind support throughout the study.</p></sec><sec id="funding-statement1" xml:lang="en" disp-level="1"><title>Funding Statement</title><p>The study was funded by the Jodhpur City Knowledge and Innovation Foundation (JCKIF), Indian Institute of Technology, Jodhpur, Rajasthan, India (No. JCKIF/IITJ/OM/2022-23) dated March 30, 2022.</p></sec><sec id="ref-list1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>R<sc>EFERENCES</sc></title><sec id="ref-list1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kankaria A, Nongkynrih B, Gupta SK. Indoor air pollution in India: Implications on health and its control. Indian J Community Med. 2014;39:203–7. doi: 10.4103/0970-0218.143019.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4103/0970-0218.143019"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4215499"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25364142"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Indian J Community Med&amp;title=Indoor air pollution in India: Implications on health and its control&amp;author=A Kankaria&amp;author=B Nongkynrih&amp;author=SK Gupta&amp;volume=39&amp;publication_year=2014&amp;pages=203-7&amp;pmid=25364142&amp;doi=10.4103/0970-0218.143019&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sasi AP, Udgiri RS. A study on indoor air pollution and its impact on health in urban field practice area: A community-based study. Int J Community Med Public Health. 2024;11:1246–51.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Int J Community Med Public Health&amp;title=A study on indoor air pollution and its impact on health in urban field practice area: A community-based study&amp;author=AP Sasi&amp;author=RS Udgiri&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=1246-51&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Neelakanta RR, Jagadeesan AR, Goudhaman L, Athisayaraj MS. Factors influencing particulate matter 2.5 levels in indoor areas of rural houses: A Cross-sectional Study. J Clin Diagn Res. 2022 doi: 10.7860/JCDR/2022/58657.16877.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Clin Diagn Res&amp;title=Factors influencing particulate matter 2.5 levels in indoor areas of rural houses: A Cross-sectional Study&amp;author=RR Neelakanta&amp;author=AR Jagadeesan&amp;author=L Goudhaman&amp;author=MS Athisayaraj&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Priyadarsini SP, Ibrahim RM, Somasundaram VM, Nayeem RA, Balasubramanian R. A cross-sectional study on determinants of indoor air pollution and its perceived impact among the residents of urban field practice area of AMCH, Salem, Tamil Nadu. J Family Med Prim Care. 2022;11:948–54. doi: 10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_780_21.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_780_21"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9051708"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35495797"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Family Med Prim Care&amp;title=A cross-sectional study on determinants of indoor air pollution and its perceived impact among the residents of urban field practice area of AMCH, Salem, Tamil Nadu&amp;author=SP Priyadarsini&amp;author=RM Ibrahim&amp;author=VM Somasundaram&amp;author=RA Nayeem&amp;author=R Balasubramanian&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=948-54&amp;pmid=35495797&amp;doi=10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_780_21&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Huda RK, Kumar P, Gupta R, Sharma AK, Toteja GS, Babu BV. Air quality monitoring using low-cost sensors in urban areas of Jodhpur, Rajasthan. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2024;21:623. doi: 10.3390/ijerph21050623.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijerph21050623"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11120845"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38791837"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Int J Environ Res Public Health&amp;title=Air quality monitoring using low-cost sensors in urban areas of Jodhpur, Rajasthan&amp;author=RK Huda&amp;author=P Kumar&amp;author=R Gupta&amp;author=AK Sharma&amp;author=GS Toteja&amp;volume=21&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=623&amp;pmid=38791837&amp;doi=10.3390/ijerph21050623&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Vijay P, Anand A, Singh N, Schikowski T, Phuleria HC. Examining the spatial and temporal variations in the indoor gaseous, PM2.5, BC concentrations in urban homes in India. Atmospheric Environment. 2024;319:120287.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmospheric Environment&amp;title=Examining the spatial and temporal variations in the indoor gaseous, PM2.5, BC concentrations in urban homes in India&amp;author=P Vijay&amp;author=A Anand&amp;author=N Singh&amp;author=T Schikowski&amp;author=HC Phuleria&amp;volume=319&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=120287&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Anand A, Phuleria HC. Assessment of indoor air quality and housing, household and health characteristics in densely populated urban slums. Environment, Development and Sustainability. 2022;24:11929–52.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environment, Development and Sustainability&amp;title=Assessment of indoor air quality and housing, household and health characteristics in densely populated urban slums&amp;author=A Anand&amp;author=HC Phuleria&amp;volume=24&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=11929-52&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Alhajeri NS, Alrashidi AM, Yassin MF, Al‐Awadi L. Optimizing indoor air quality: Investigating particulate matter exposure in household kitchens and source identification. Environ Qual Manag. 2024;34:e22198.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ Qual Manag&amp;title=Optimizing indoor air quality: Investigating particulate matter exposure in household kitchens and source identification&amp;author=NS Alhajeri&amp;author=AM Alrashidi&amp;author=MF Yassin&amp;author=L Al‐Awadi&amp;volume=34&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=e22198&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ścibor M, Balcerzak B, Galbarczyk A, Targosz N, Jasienska G. Are we safe inside? Indoor air quality in relation to outdoor concentration of PM10 and PM2. 5 and to characteristics of homes. Sustainable Cities and Society. 2019;48:101537.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Sustainable Cities and Society&amp;title=Are we safe inside? Indoor air quality in relation to outdoor concentration of PM10 and PM2. 5 and to characteristics of homes&amp;author=M Ścibor&amp;author=B Balcerzak&amp;author=A Galbarczyk&amp;author=N Targosz&amp;author=G Jasienska&amp;volume=48&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=101537&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Niculita-Hirzel H, Hirzel AH, Wild P. A GIS-based approach to assess the influence of the urban built environment on cardiac and respiratory outcomes in older adults. Building and Environment. 2024;253:111362.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Building and Environment&amp;title=A GIS-based approach to assess the influence of the urban built environment on cardiac and respiratory outcomes in older adults&amp;author=H Niculita-Hirzel&amp;author=AH Hirzel&amp;author=P Wild&amp;volume=253&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=111362&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Karaca F, Guney M, Agibayeva A, Otesh N, Kulimbet M, Glushkova N, et al.  Indoor air quality in Kazakh households: Evaluating PM2.5 levels generated by cooking activities. Engineering Reports. 2024;6:e12845.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Engineering Reports&amp;title=Indoor air quality in Kazakh households: Evaluating PM2.5 levels generated by cooking activities&amp;author=F Karaca&amp;author=M Guney&amp;author=A Agibayeva&amp;author=N Otesh&amp;author=M Kulimbet&amp;volume=6&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=e12845&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Papagiannis S, Abdullaev SF, Vasilatou V, Manousakas MI, Eleftheriadis K, Diapouli E. Air quality challenges in Central Asian urban areas: A PM2.5 source apportionment analysis in Dushanbe, Tajikistan. Environ Sci Pollut Res Int. 2024;31:39588–601. doi: 10.1007/s11356-024-33833-6.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s11356-024-33833-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38822961"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ Sci Pollut Res Int&amp;title=Air quality challenges in Central Asian urban areas: A PM2.5 source apportionment analysis in Dushanbe, Tajikistan&amp;author=S Papagiannis&amp;author=SF Abdullaev&amp;author=V Vasilatou&amp;author=MI Manousakas&amp;author=K Eleftheriadis&amp;volume=31&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=39588-601&amp;pmid=38822961&amp;doi=10.1007/s11356-024-33833-6&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hou WH, Huang YC, Lu CY, Chen IC, Lee PC, Lin MY, et al.  A national survey of ambient air pollution health literacy among adult residents of Taiwan. BMC Public Health. 2021;21:1604. doi: 10.1186/s12889-021-11658-z.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12889-021-11658-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8406719"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34465329"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMC Public Health&amp;title=A national survey of ambient air pollution health literacy among adult residents of Taiwan&amp;author=WH Hou&amp;author=YC Huang&amp;author=CY Lu&amp;author=IC Chen&amp;author=PC Lee&amp;volume=21&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=1604&amp;pmid=34465329&amp;doi=10.1186/s12889-021-11658-z&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Al-Shidi HK, Ambusaidi AK, Sulaiman H. Public awareness, perceptions and attitudes on air pollution and its health effects in Muscat, Oman. J Air Waste Manag Assoc. 2021;71:1159–74. doi: 10.1080/10962247.2021.1930287.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/10962247.2021.1930287"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33989134"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Air Waste Manag Assoc&amp;title=Public awareness, perceptions and attitudes on air pollution and its health effects in Muscat, Oman&amp;author=HK Al-Shidi&amp;author=AK Ambusaidi&amp;author=H Sulaiman&amp;volume=71&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=1159-74&amp;pmid=33989134&amp;doi=10.1080/10962247.2021.1930287&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gabel C, Sigsgaard T, Petersen S, Elholm G. The prevalence and association of measured and perceived indoor air quality, housing characteristics, and residents’ behavior and health. Front Environ Health. 2024;3:1358546.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Front Environ Health&amp;title=The prevalence and association of measured and perceived indoor air quality, housing characteristics, and residents’ behavior and health&amp;author=C Gabel&amp;author=T Sigsgaard&amp;author=S Petersen&amp;author=G Elholm&amp;volume=3&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=1358546&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dwivedi S, Taushiba A, Zehra F, Gupta SK, Lawrence A. Revelations to indoor air pollutants and health risk assessment on women: A case study. Hygiene and Environmental Health Advances. 2023;5:100038.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Hygiene and Environmental Health Advances&amp;title=Revelations to indoor air pollutants and health risk assessment on women: A case study&amp;author=S Dwivedi&amp;author=A Taushiba&amp;author=F Zehra&amp;author=SK Gupta&amp;author=A Lawrence&amp;volume=5&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=100038&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bardhan R, Pan J, Chen S, Cho TY. Breathing space in a compact city: Impacts of urban re-densification on Mumbai’s low-income housing environment. Habitat International. 2024;149:103098.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Habitat International&amp;title=Breathing space in a compact city: Impacts of urban re-densification on Mumbai’s low-income housing environment&amp;author=R Bardhan&amp;author=J Pan&amp;author=S Chen&amp;author=TY Cho&amp;volume=149&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=103098&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Supplementary Figure 1</label><caption><p>Temporal distribution of PM2.5 levels in indoor areas of all colonies</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="IJCM-50-516_Suppl1.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><?cloudpmc-path 0e08/12815361/135901163cee/IJCM-50-516_Suppl1.tif?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1862260?></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body></article>