<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Sci Rep</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13068920</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13068920</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13068920</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41775844</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-026-41078-1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Construction of automatic air monitoring point siting model based on convolutional neural network and K-means clustering</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="S">Sisi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>GuangDong University of Science and Technology, Dongguan, 523083 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Guangzhou Vocational College of Technology &amp; Business, Guangzhou, 511400 China </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>4</day><month>3</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>11940</fpage><page-range>11940</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2026_Article_41078.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path bebe/13068920/4907c15bf322/41598_2026_Article_41078.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1858955?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par5">To enhance the level of air monitoring in urban areas and accurately assess the air quality across the entire urban region, a model for automatic air monitoring point placement based on a convolutional neural network (CNN) and K-means clustering is studied. A CNN is employed to extract features from air monitoring data, and the K-means clustering algorithm is used to partition the extracted features. Based on the air monitoring data features, an air quality model is established to maximize the similarity of pollutant concentrations between the optimal grid p oints and all candidate grid points. Using this air quality model, the feature information entropy of the air monitoring data is computed to determine the recommendation priority of unlabeled nodes in an urban spatiotemporal map, and automatic air monitoring points with the highest average recommendation priority are selected. The model test results demonstrate that the established model can effectively identify the optimal locations for automatic air monitoring, with an air quality monitoring error of less than 1%. When the number of hidden nodes is 256, the CNN used in this model exhibits strong generalization capability and high stability in the output results.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" xml:lang="en" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Convolutional neural network, K-means clustering, Air automatic monitoring, Point siting, Siting model</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group2" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Engineering, Environmental sciences, Mathematics and computing</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 Jul 21; Accepted 2026 Feb 17; Collection date 2026.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par6"> Air pollution poses a serious threat to human health. Aerosol particles enter the respiratory tract during inhalation and can reach the deep alveoli, potentially triggering various respiratory diseases such as asthma and chronic pulmonary inflammatory infections. These particles can also enter the bloodstream, significantly increasing the risk of cardiovascular<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>, cerebrovascular<sup><xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, cardiac<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>, and digestive system diseases<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. Air pollutants are major contributors to chronic noncommunicable diseases. Furthermore, air pollution is closely linked to regional economic development. As a developing country, China has experienced rapid economic growth in recent years, accompanied by a continuous increase in the number of motor vehicles. Emissions from non-road mobile sources are substantial and are roughly equivalent to those from motor vehicles. According to the Ministry of Ecology and Environment, motor vehicle exhaust pollution is becoming increasingly severe, particularly in regions such as Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei and the Yangtze River Delta, where air pollution has exhibited characteristics of combined soot and exhaust gas pollution.</p><p id="Par7">The air environment quality is worsening, and pollution is increasing daily. Regarding air pollution problems, acquiring a real-time understanding of air quality distribution, especially in urban areas, can help residents reasonably plan outdoor activities in advance and take corresponding preventive measures. It can also help relevant government departments make informed environmental protection decisions proactively. While government environmental protection departments have deployed a certain number of air quality monitoring stations in cities across the country for automatic monitoring of various air pollutants, the cost and maintenance expenses of these stations are high. Furthermore, considering the constraints of various factors, such as the land area occupied by monitoring stations<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>, it is impractical to install a large number of them in any urban area. Consequently, the effective area covered by the limited number of air quality monitoring stations in each urban area is very sparse relative to the entire urban area, leaving the air quality distribution in the vast uncovered areas largely unknown.</p><p id="Par8">Therefore, accurately predicting the air quality distribution in unmonitored areas using the sparse network of monitoring points in the city is an urgent problem that needs to be solved. The establishment of new air quality monitoring stations to form a more efficient monitoring network has become an urgent requirement for air quality management in many cities in China. The siting and distribution of monitoring stations are critical for urban air quality monitoring. The spatial distribution of each monitoring station in the network directly affects the accuracy of representing the real-time distribution of air quality across the entire urban area.</p><p id="Par9">Currently, the reduction in the urban air pollution buffer distance caused by high-density urban population aggregation, high-intensity industrial production, and rapid urban expansion has led to a sharp increase in the emissions of air pollutants, resulting in obvious regional characteristics of air pollution. The optimization of the location of air quality monitoring points is becoming increasingly important. Existing air monitoring points must be classified, removed, and added to adapt to changes in urban scale and layout<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. This approach can achieve the objective of reflecting the air pollution characteristics of the corresponding functional areas, and the optimization of the air monitoring point location provides a theoretical basis for urban air pollution control and management.</p><p id="Par10">Currently, the commonly used location methods for automatic air monitoring include cluster analysis, factor analysis, correlation analysis, BP artificial neural networks, multi-objective programming, and matter-element analysis and synthesis. As the topography, meteorological data, and emissions of pollution sources vary across cities, the number and location of monitoring points are different<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>, and the location methods for automatic air monitoring points also vary significantly. The air quality distribution in urban areas is closely related to public physical and mental health. Therefore, understanding the distribution of air quality in real time is of important reference significance for guiding residents’ outdoor activity planning and supporting subsequent environmental management by relevant government departments.</p><p id="Par11">The distribution of air pollutants exhibits interactive patterns in time and space and is affected by external factors, such as weather, traffic volume, road network structure, and land use<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>; the area covered by the established air quality monitoring stations in urban areas is relatively sparse compared with the entire urban area. This series of factors poses challenges for automatic air quality monitoring at point locations. Current air quality prediction methods either do not consider the influence of external factors related to air quality distribution or fail to capture the spatio-temporal interaction of air quality distribution owing to the limitation of their own model performance.</p><p id="Par12">With the continuous expansion of urban areas<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>, air quality monitoring stations previously established in some cities can no longer meet the accuracy requirements for air quality monitoring in the entire urban area. Therefore, based on the established air quality monitoring stations, it is necessary to recommend a certain number of optimal points<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> from the candidate areas and build a more effective and purposeful air quality monitoring network with the original monitoring station group to accurately reflect the air quality distribution and development trend of the entire urban area. Addressing this has become an urgent problem that needs to be solved for air quality management in many cities in China. At present, most research on this problem cannot be based on established air quality monitoring stations, the general flexibility is relatively low<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>, and the monitoring items are mainly conventional pollutants, which cannot meet the monitoring needs for combined air pollution from soot and motor vehicle exhaust in China.</p><p id="Par13">Currently, research is being conducted on ambient air monitoring. Tang M. Z. classifies the applications of mobile air quality sensors into three categories - fixed-route mobile monitoring, random-route mobile monitoring, and maneuverable mobile monitoring - according to the mobile paths of the mobile air quality sensor-carrying platforms, summarizes their advantages and shortcomings in the fields of ambient air quality monitoring, pollution source monitoring, personal health exposure research, and dynamic identification of emission source inventories, and outlines future development directions and application prospects<sup><xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par14">The mass balance principle is used to estimate the indoor PM2.5 concentration originating from non-ambient sources, and the relationship between these concentrations and the exposure quantiles of indoor source activity in the range of 0.50 to 0.95 is studied using mixed-effect quantile regression. Varekar<sup><xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> proposes an innovative semi-empirical method of seasonal export coefficients (SECs) for estimating diffuse pollution loads, especially for tropical countries such as India. The method considers the impact of seasonality on the estimation of diffuse pollution loads by accounting for the seasonal heterogeneity of topography, precipitation factors, and land-use patterns. The possible impact of this seasonal heterogeneity on the rationalization of water quality monitoring sites in the Kali River basin in India is tested.</p><p id="Par15">The challenges of traditional methods for determining the locations of air pollution sensors include the difficulty in comprehensively considering the effects of external factors on air quality distribution and in capturing the spatial and temporal interactions of air quality distribution. By combining convolutional neural networks and K-means clustering, the proposed method significantly improves the accuracy of locating air monitoring points and the comprehensiveness and accuracy of air quality assessment, thereby more effectively reflecting regional air pollution characteristics and providing a theoretical basis for urban air pollution control and management.</p><p id="Par16">The goal of this study is to optimize the air pollution monitoring network, aiming to reduce costs by decreasing the number of air pollution sensors while utilizing advanced algorithms and technologies to ensure an accurate and comprehensive assessment of the entire city’s air pollution level, even in areas without sensors, thereby achieving high-precision pollution estimation. In the context of this research, real-time performance refers to the model’s ability to process and analyze air monitoring data swiftly, enabling timely and accurate decisions related to air quality management. The acceptable degree of delay for real-time performance in this study is considered minimal, ensuring that the monitoring data is as current as possible and reflects the dynamic nature of air pollution. Future work may include detailed assessments of the model’s real-time capabilities and the determination of specific thresholds for acceptable delays, further refining the model’s application in practical air quality monitoring scenarios. A site selection model for automatic air monitoring stations based on a convolutional neural network and K-means clustering is constructed. Based on this site selection and distribution model, several representative and typical optimal locations are recommended for establishing new monitoring stations in candidate areas of unmonitored urban regions. This approach can improve the accuracy of the air quality prediction model for the entire urban area to the greatest extent possible, enabling the construction of a more efficient and purposeful urban air quality monitoring network. It provides scientific theoretical standards and systems for relevant government departments to select optimal locations and establish a standardized urban air quality monitoring network. Using a CNN to extract features, the experimental results show that the mean square error is the smallest when 256 hidden nodes are used and that the model exhibits strong generalization ability. Using K-means clustering to cluster the extracted features yields better results than clustering the original data, and the cluster centers can be determined quickly. The automatic monitoring points determined by the model in this study are highly consistent with the actual results, and the mean square error is less than 1%. An error of approximately 1% indicates that the monitoring results from the automatic air monitoring points identified by this model are very close to the actual air quality results. This high accuracy is highly beneficial for supporting the ultimate goal of government decision-making research. It ensures the accuracy of air quality monitoring data, which helps the government better understand the distribution and development trends of urban air quality and thus formulate more effective environmental protection policies and measures. This verifies that the model exhibits high performance in automatic monitoring point selection and can accurately monitor the air quality distribution across the entire city.</p><p id="Par17">This study proposes the construction of an automatic air monitoring point localization model based on convolutional neural networks and K-means clustering, targeting the key issue of location selection for urban automatic air monitoring points. It aims to solve the problems of relying on shallow data in existing methods, which makes it difficult to capture the spatiotemporal dynamic correlation of air quality; the lack of multi-link collaborative adaptation in single-technology applications; the lack of consideration for regional correlation in general algorithms, which can easily lead to spatial redundancy or information loss at points; and the lack of engineering verification and comparative analysis in most solutions. This work fills the scientific gaps in feature representation, technical collaboration, scene adaptation, and engineering application of existing air monitoring point selection methods.</p><p id="Par18">This study aims to address the practical needs of selecting locations for urban automatic air monitoring points and constructs an integrated optimization framework of “feature extraction, clustering grouping, and priority selection”. The core contributions are reflected in the following aspects:</p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par20">Logical Closed-Loop Design for Cross-Method Collaboration: This study employs a CNN to extract deep features incorporating spatiotemporal dynamics, utilizes K-means to partition air quality into homogeneous zones based on these deep features, and applies an information entropy strategy to select high-information-gain locations based on regional correlations. This forms a closed-loop process from data representation to site selection decision-making. It addresses the disconnect between features and site selection objectives in traditional CNN applications, compensates for the imprecise regional segmentation caused by ambiguous raw data features in simple K-means clustering, and avoids the shortcomings of the information entropy strategy when applied universally - which often overlooks the spatio-temporal correlations in air monitoring.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par21">Domain-Specific Adaptations for Information Entropy Selection: This study’s entropy calculation binds probability distributions to feature correlations between unlabeled and labeled nodes. Cosine similarity quantifies air quality associations between nodes, enabling entropy values to precisely reflect a node’s value in supplementing regional air quality information - rather than merely indicating prediction uncertainty - thus better aligning with air monitoring site selection requirements.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par22">Engineering-Oriented Process Optimization: This study employs 256 hidden nodes in the CNN to balance accuracy and computational efficiency, utilizes K-means + + initialization for K-means to reduce iterations, and designs a multi-threaded parallel computing scheme for the greedy algorithm to shorten decision time. These optimizations enable the process to adapt to the practical demand for daily updates in monitoring point recommendations.</p></list-item></list>
</sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Proposed method</title><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Convolutional neural network structure</title><p id="Par23">The CNN is one of the most popular deep learning models in the field of computer vision. Convolutional neural networks are used to extract the characteristics of automatic air monitoring point monitoring data.</p><p id="Par24">The CNN includes a receptive field, channels, filter banks, feature maps, an activation function, convolution layers, and pooling layers. The convolutional layer of the CNN is a locally connected layer with shared weights. The spatial range of the input layer covered by the convolutional layer is the receptive field of the convolutional layer. The receptive field size of the convolution layer is RS, and the corresponding shared weight is called a filter or a convolution kernel. Different filters slide over the input layer along the spatial dimension to generate multiple feature maps. The spatial size of the feature map after the convolution operation is (M − <italic>R</italic> + 1) (N − S + 1). The number of feature maps indicates the number of channels. The number of channels is determined by the number of filters in the convolutional layer, and the set of filters is referred to as the filter bank.</p><p id="Par25">When extracting air monitoring data features using a convolutional neural network, the number of channels in the input layer is often not 1, so the filter is usually in the form of a three-dimensional matrix, the filter size is RSP, where P is the number of channels in the input layer, and the filter bank is a four-dimensional matrix. After passing through a convolution layer, the elements of the k-th air monitoring data feature map at spatial position ij of layer T are calculated using the following formula:</p><disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><tex-math id="d33e277">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$a_{{i,j,k}}^{{\left( t \right)}}=f\left( {\sum\limits_{{c=1}}^{p} {\sum\limits_{{m=1}}^{s} {\sum\limits_{{n=1}}^{r} {a_{{}}^{{t - 1}}} +b_{k}^{t} \times w_{{m,n,c,k}}^{t}} } } \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par26">In Eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>), f is the activation function for the element-by-element operation, SR is the spatial size of the receptive field, P is the number of channels in the input layer, and B is the bias term. Generally, a feature map of air monitoring data has its corresponding values. A1 and A2 are the responses of layers T-1 and t, respectively, and W is the weight.</p><p id="Par27">The vectorized form of the response value at the spatial position of the convolutional layer is expressed as:</p><disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><tex-math id="d33e288">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${a^t}=f{W^t}+f{b^t}{a^{t - 1}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par28">Here, AR and WR represent components where each row in matrix W is a vectorized filter Br. The pooling layer is a neighborhood operation that downsamples the response in the neighborhood and maintains an unchanged number of channels in the input layer. At present, the most commonly used method is max pooling, which pools the k-th air monitoring data feature map output from layer T, as shown in the following formula:</p><disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><tex-math id="d33e294">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$a_{{i,j,k}}^{{t+1}}=\mathop {\hbox{max} }\limits_{{1 \leqslant m \leqslant u,1 \leqslant n \leqslant v}} {b^t}a_{{i \times u+m,j \times v+n,k}}^{t}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par29">The UV-size region is called the pooling neighborhood and is sometimes referred to as the pooling receptive field. Equation (<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>) indicates that the most commonly used non-overlapping pooling, where adjacent pooling receptive fields do not overlap, is employed.</p><p id="Par30">Another commonly used connection layer is called the fully connected layer, in which each neuron in layer T + 1 is connected to each neuron in the layer; that is, the input of each neuron is a linear combination of the outputs of all neurons in the previous layer. The calculation method for the fully connected layer is given by:</p><disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><tex-math id="d33e305">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$a_{t}^{{t+1}}=f\left( {\sum\limits_{{j=1}}^{p} {a_{j}^{t}+{b^{t+1}} \times w_{j}^{{t+1}}} } \right)+{b^{t+1}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par31">The vectorization of the output of the second layer can be expressed as:</p><disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><tex-math id="d33e311">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${a^{t+1}}=f\left( {{W^{t+1}}+{b^t}{a^t}} \right)+{b^t}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par32">The vectorization of the output of layer can be expressed as, where a is the output of layer t. If there is a spatial or channel dimension, it is fully expanded into vector form. Assuming that its dimension is p, P is the number of neurons in the t-th layer. B is the bias vector. In general, each neuron in the fully connected layer shares a bias value. The output of the fully connected layer is a simple group of linearly arranged neurons. Assuming its dimension, that is, the number of neurons is Q, parameter W is the matrix of the QP.</p><p id="Par33">The pooling layer does not contain learnable parameters. Essentially, the convolutional and fully connected layers first perform linear filtering and then perform element-by-element nonlinear transformations. Ignoring pooling and other connection layers without learnable parameters<sup><xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>, and assuming that a = x represents the input layer and a represents the response of layer T, the deep convolutional neural network can be expressed as follows:</p><disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><tex-math id="d33e324">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${z^{t+1}}=\left( {{W^t}{a^t}+{b^t}} \right)+{b^t}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><tex-math id="d33e328">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${a^{t+1}}={f^{t+1}}{z^{t+1}}+{b^t}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par34">In Eqs. (<xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref>) and (<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>), Z, a, and B are the vector representations of the model response and bias, W is the weight matrix, and F is the element-wise activation function.</p><p id="Par35">Assuming the entire network model is denoted as H, T represents the number of learnable layers, and the sets of all weights and biases are denoted as W and B, respectively, the model h can be expressed as:</p><disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><tex-math id="d33e342">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${h_{\left( {W,b} \right)}}={f^T}\left( {{W^T}{f^1}\left( {{W^1}{a^1}+{b^1}} \right)+{b^T}} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par36">As shown in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="disp-formula">8</xref>), the CNN can be regarded as a superposition of multi-layer linear filtering and nonlinear transformation. Theoretically, as the depth and width of the model increase, a CNN can approximate any nonlinear transformation, indicating its strong modeling capability. Since the superposition of linear transformations remains linear, the nonlinearity introduced by the activation function is essential in CNNs. The convolutional layer not only significantly reduces the number of model parameters by restricting the receptive field size and sharing parameters, but its response is also translation-invariant. Combined with the pooling layer’s filtering of spatial location information, the model exhibits a certain degree of spatial invariance. With the stacking of multiple layers, higher levels of the model gain stronger invariance, thereby improving feature extraction performance for air monitoring data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="2"><title>K-means clustering algorithm</title><p id="Par37">The core idea is as follows: cluster the sample set by presetting the number of target categories K and represent the clustering results using K cluster centers. Specifically, it can be understood that the air monitoring data feature set X_J is partitioned into k categories, and the cluster center K_i for each category is calculated<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. When the Euclidean distance is selected as the dissimilarity index between a vector X_c and its corresponding cluster center K_i in the air monitoring data feature class I, the value function is defined as:</p><disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><tex-math id="d33e359">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$J=\sum\limits_{{i=1}}^{k} {\left( {{{\sum\limits_{{{x_c} \in {K_i}}} {\left\| {{x_c} - {k_i}} \right\|} }^2}+{k_i}} \right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par38">In Eq. (<xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref>), J is the value function for the air monitoring data feature class; therefore, the value of J_i depends on the geometric characteristics of K_i and the location of K_i.</p><p id="Par39">The divided characteristic class of the air monitoring data is generally defined by a two-dimensional membership matrix U of CN, where u represents the matrix of the degree to which object x belongs to set a. If the j-th element X_j belongs to class I, the element Uij in U is 1; Otherwise, it is 0. Once cluster center ki is determined, the membership matrix U that minimizes the value function can be derived as follows:</p><disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><tex-math id="d33e370">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${u_{ij}}=\left\{ {\begin{array}{*{20}{c}} {1{\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {{\left\| {{x_j} - {k_i}} \right\|}^2}+{k_i} \leqslant {{\left\| {{x_j} - {k_c}} \right\|}^2}+{k_i}\left( {c \ne i} \right)} \\ {0{\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} {\kern 1pt} else} \end{array}} \right.$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par40">In Eq. (<xref rid="Equ10" ref-type="disp-formula">10</xref>), k_i represents the clustering center of the characteristic class of the air monitoring data, and K_c represents the clustering center of the other characteristic classes of the air monitoring data. It can be seen from Eq. (<xref rid="Equ10" ref-type="disp-formula">10</xref>) that k_i is the nearest cluster center of element XJ; that is, element X_j is most similar to cluster center Ki, meaning that element XJ belongs to class I. Because a given element can only belong to one class, the membership matrix U has the property of Uij = 1 and Uij = n.</p><p id="Par41">The specific procedure for determining the value of K is as follows:</p><p id="Par42">(1) A preliminary analysis of the feature set of air monitoring data is conducted to understand the distribution and characteristics of the data.</p><p id="Par43">(2) Statistical methods such as the elbow method are employed to plot the K-SSE curve by evaluating the clustering performance under different K values, aiming to identify the point where the rate of SSE decrease slows significantly; the corresponding K value at this point is a suitable candidate.</p><p id="Par44">(3) After identifying several candidate K values, the K-means clustering algorithm is executed to compare the clustering results across different K values, including the number, size, and shape of clusters, as well as the positions of cluster centers, thereby selecting the K value that yields the best clustering performance.</p><p id="Par45">If K is increased, the number of clusters increases, and each cluster will contain fewer data points on average. This can lead to a more detailed partitioning of the data but may also result in overfitting or the identification of clusters that lack meaningful interpretation within the problem context. Conversely, if K is decreased, the clusters become broader and more general, increasing the risk of underfitting, where distinct patterns or groups within the data are not adequately separated. In the context of air monitoring, this implies that different pollution characteristics or geographical regions with distinct air quality features may be inappropriately grouped together, leading to less accurate analysis and potentially incorrect identification of automatic air monitoring points.</p><p id="Par46">The training procedure for the feature extraction CNN is as follows:</p><p id="Par47">(1) Raw feature data from air monitoring stations, such as PM2.5 concentration, PM10 concentration, and CO2 concentration, are selected and preprocessed through operations like normalization to construct an analysis matrix.</p><p id="Par48">(2) The CNN structure is configured, typically assuming a filter size of 3 × 3, a stride of 1, and a pooling size of 2 × 2.</p><p id="Par49">(3) The preprocessed data are input into the CNN, and the output is computed via forward propagation. The parameters of the CNN, such as the weights and biases of the convolutional kernels, are then adjusted using a backpropagation algorithm based on the difference between the output and the true label to minimize the error. This process is generally repeated for multiple iterations until the CNN output stabilizes.</p><p id="Par50">(4) Upon completion of training, the CNN is utilized to extract features from the air monitoring data, yielding feature vectors for subsequent clustering analysis or model construction.</p><p id="Par51">However, if Uij is fixed, the optimal cluster center for minimizing the value of Eq. (<xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref>) is the mean of all vectors in the air monitoring data feature class, as shown in the following equation:</p><disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><tex-math id="d33e408">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${k_i}=\frac{{\sum\limits_{{{x_c} \in {K_i}}} {{x_c}} \varepsilon }}{{\left| {{K_i}} \right|}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par52">In Eq. (<xref rid="Equ11" ref-type="disp-formula">11</xref>), ki is the module of Ki, and <inline-formula id="IEq1"><tex-math id="d33e417">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\left| {{K_i}} \right|=\sum\limits_{{j=1}}^{n} {{u_{ij}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="Par53">An iterative updating method is adopted. Through multiple iterations, the objective value function converges toward a minimum<sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>, achieving an optimal feature clustering outcome for the air monitoring data. For a given set of elements XJ, the clustering can be completed as follows:</p><p id="Par54">(1) The traditional method involves taking any k points from all data points as the cluster centers and taking the minimum value of E.</p><p id="Par55">(2) The membership matrix U is calculated according to Eq. (<xref rid="Equ10" ref-type="disp-formula">10</xref>).</p><p id="Par56">(3) The value function based on the dissimilarity index is computed using Eq. (<xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref>). If J &lt; e, the algorithm stops; otherwise, proceed to Step (4).</p><p id="Par57">(4) The cluster centers are updated according to Eq. (<xref rid="Equ11" ref-type="disp-formula">11</xref>), and the procedure returns to the Step (2). The procedure is repeated until the final condition is satisfied.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>K-means clustering analysis based on convolutional neural network feature extraction</title><p id="Par58">Combining a convolutional neural network with the K-means clustering algorithm is a reasonable approach for addressing the specific problems mentioned above and achieving the stated objectives, as the CNN can efficiently extract features from air monitoring data, while the K-means algorithm can effectively cluster and analyze these features. This combination fully leverages the advantages of both methods to improve the positioning accuracy of air monitoring points, thereby optimizing the monitoring network layout, reducing costs, and ensuring the comprehensiveness and accuracy of air quality assessment. The original feature data for air monitoring in the selected area for automatic monitoring point placement are chosen, and an analysis matrix is constructed based on time series. A convolutional neural network is used to extract features from the air monitoring data, resulting in a (1 × 64)-dimensional feature vector. The K-means clustering algorithm is then applied to cluster the extracted air monitoring features. The original data undergo significant changes after feature extraction, which amplifies the principal features of the air monitoring data and makes the characteristics represented by the data vector more distinct<sup><xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. A sparsification method is employed to reduce the influence of interfering factors. The K-means clustering algorithm can accurately quantify the feature differences in the air monitoring data and partition them into distinct clusters.</p><p id="Par59">After K-means cluster analysis, each cluster represents the corresponding attribute characteristics of the air monitoring data, and nodes partitioned into the same cluster can be identified as having similar attributes. The K-means clustering algorithm is employed to cluster the features extracted from the air monitoring data using the CNN method. The analysis procedure is as follows.</p><p id="Par60">First, the spatial features of the air monitoring stations are extracted. The raw objective analysis data of meteorological elements from the air monitoring stations are processed into 10 × 10 sub-grids, which are stored in different grids according to air monitoring data types such as temperature, relative humidity, and wind elements. A one-dimensional convolution operation is applied to these sub-grids to extract spatial features of different air monitoring elements, serving as the spatial features of the detection points at the observation time.</p><p id="Par61">Second, the observation data of air pollutant concentrations and meteorological elements at the air monitoring station are preprocessed. The mean and variance of each type of air monitoring data are calculated, and data exhibiting significant shrinkage in the mean or increase in deviation are eliminated from the sample set. Missing measured values are replaced with the mean value, and the data are then normalized<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Finally, these preprocessed data are combined with the spatial features at the same observation time to form the feature vector of the air monitoring station at that observation time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="2"><title>Automatic air monitoring point siting, model</title><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="3"><title>Air quality model</title><p id="Par62">A regional air quality monitoring network must account for both the comprehensive characteristics of multiple pollutants and the characteristics of individual pollutants. To fully represent the integrated characteristics of multiple pollutants in each grid<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>, an air quality model is established based on the characteristics of the partitioned air monitoring data, following the Jordan formula from probability theory while neglecting interactions among pollutants. The comprehensive evaluation concentration of multiple pollutants in each grid is calculated using the following formula:</p><disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><tex-math id="d33e472">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${C_i}\left( s \right)=1 - k\left[ {\left( {1 - {C_i}\left( {{x_n}} \right)} \right)} \right]$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par63">In Eq. (<xref rid="Equ12" ref-type="disp-formula">12</xref>), I is the grid number, CS is the comprehensive evaluation concentration of various pollutants in the air of the grid, Cix1 and cixn are the average annual concentrations of various pollutants x1xn… In the air of the grid, and K represents the air quality monitoring characteristics after the division.</p><p id="Par64">An air quality model is developed by considering the objectives and characteristics of the regional air quality monitoring network, the percentile error limits specified at all levels in China’s ambient air quality monitoring standards, and the practical context of China’s environmental management.</p><p id="Par65">To comply with the percentile error limits at all levels specified in China’s ambient air quality monitoring code, minimize the mean pollutant concentration difference between the preferred grid point and alternative grid points in the study area, and reduce the errors at the 30th, 50th, 80th, and 90th percentiles<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>, an objective is established to maximize the closeness of percentile values at all concentration levels between the preferred grid point and all alternative grid points, referred to as the “maximum closeness” objective:</p><disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><tex-math id="d33e489">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$MaxF=\sum\limits_{{j=1}}^{n} {\left[ {\left| {1 - {a_j}/{b_j}} \right|{X_j}} \right]}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par66">Here, XJ is a binary 0–1 integer variable, N is the total number of alternative grid points, and AJ is the j-th value obtained after ranking the comprehensive evaluation concentrations of the alternative grid air monitoring points in ascending order, i.e., AJ + 1 &gt; AJ. BJ is determined as follows:</p><p id="Par67">Let the interval endpoint value LK = A1 and K &lt; B-1 of AJ divide AJ into B intervals, where:</p><disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><tex-math id="d33e497">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$h={a_n}/\left( {B - 1} \right) - {a_1}/\left( {B - 1} \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par68">Find the value LK + 1 closest to AJ from LK and BJ = LK + 1 to obtain BJ, where B is the preset total number of monitoring stations and K, B, and are integers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="3"><title>Greedy algorithm based on information entropy minimization</title><p id="Par69">Based on the feature information entropy of the air monitoring data and the convolutional weight parameters of the air quality model, the recommendation priority of unlabeled nodes in the labeled city spatiotemporal graph is iteratively determined. In each learning round, the average convolutional weight parameter of the trained air quality model is first calculated. Since the air quality model incorporates the spatiotemporal interaction of pollutant distribution and complex external environmental characteristics, for the trained air quality model, its weight parameters represent the degree of correlation between nodes in the urban spatiotemporal graph, reflecting the spatiotemporal variation trend of air quality distribution<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. According to the correlation between nodes in the urban spatiotemporal graph, the node with the smallest feature information entropy across different air monitoring data is identified from the unlabeled node set. This node is then transferred from the unlabeled set to the labeled set, associated with the predicted air quality value, and assigned a recommendation priority. Subsequently, the air quality model is retrained using the newly labeled data, and the network convolution weight parameters are updated. This process is repeated until the recommendation priority assignment for all unlabeled nodes is completed.</p><p id="Par70">In the process of assigning recommendation priorities to unlabeled nodes in an urban spatiotemporal graph, nodes marked later generally exhibit higher uncertainty compared to others; that is, a lower correlation with other nodes corresponds to a higher recommendation priority.</p><p id="Par71">The construction procedure for the automatic air monitoring point siting model based on convolutional neural network and K-means clustering is as follow:</p><p id="Par72">(1) Input air quality monitoring data F1 into the air quality model. After training is completed, the average convolutional weight parameters of the air quality model are calculated. The average convolutional weight parameters are defined as follows:</p><disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>15</label><tex-math id="d33e517">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\bar {W}=\sum\limits_{{i=1}}^{k} {{{\tilde {A}}^i}\left| {{W_{gci}}} \right|} +k$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par73">In Eq. (<xref rid="Equ15" ref-type="disp-formula">15</xref>), k is the order of the graph convolutional network and a is the normalized adjacency matrix.</p><p id="Par74">Next, the average weight information entropy of the air monitoring data features for each unlabeled node u in the urban spatiotemporal graph is calculated, which is defined as follows:</p><disp-formula id="Equ16"><label>16</label><tex-math id="d33e528">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$H\left( {{{\bar {W}}_u}} \right)= - \sum\limits_{{u \in U}} {{{\bar {W}}_u}\log } {\bar {W}_u}+k\log {\bar {W}_u}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par75">(2) Based on the calculated feature information entropy H of the air monitoring data, the unlabeled node u with the smallest feature information entropy is assigned the lowest recommendation priority. According to the air quality distribution Fu predicted by the air quality model, node u is associated with its predicted air quality value and node U1 is labled removed from node u and added to label node L. The new label node is represented as L1, the unlabeled node is represented as U1, and the updated labeled node L1 is constructed to obtain the new graph input signal F.</p><p id="Par76">(3) Using the new graph input signal F1, the air quality model is retrained to update the network weight parameters, thereby updating the node correlations in the urban spatiotemporal graph that reflect the spatiotemporal variation trend of air quality distribution. The air quality distribution Fu for the updated unlabeled node U1 is then obtained. As described in step (1), the average convolutional weight parameter W1 of the updated air quality model and the feature information entropy H1 of the air monitoring data are calculated.</p><p id="Par77">(4) Based on the feature information entropy HW of the air monitoring data, the unlabeled node UU with the smallest feature information entropy is assigned the next lowest recommendation priority. According to the new air quality distribution Fu, node U2 is associated with its predicted air quality value, removed from the unlabeled node u, and added to the labeled node L1. The updated labeled node is denoted as L2, the updated unlabeled set as u, and a new graph input signal F2 is constructed from L2.</p><p id="Par78">(5) The above steps are repeated until recommendation priorities have been assigned to all unlabeled nodes.</p><p id="Par79">(6) Graph signal data from other time steps are input, and the above procedure is repeated to obtain multiple recommendation priority assignments for the unlabeled nodes.</p><p id="Par80">Finally, the recommendation results from multiple time steps are analyzed, and the recommendation priority for each unlabeled node in the urban spatiotemporal graph is averaged, as defined below:</p><disp-formula id="Equ17"><label>17</label><tex-math id="d33e545">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$rank\left( {u \in U} \right)=\sum\limits_{{{t_i} \in T,u \in U}} {rank\left( {u,{t_i}} \right)\left| T \right|}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par81">In Eq. (<xref rid="Equ17" ref-type="disp-formula">17</xref>), rank represents the average recommendation priority of the unlabeled nodes, Ti represents a certain time, and T represents the number of times ti.</p><p id="Par82">For any unlabeled node <inline-formula id="IEq2"><tex-math id="d33e556">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$u \in U$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, its probability distribution is constructed as: <inline-formula id="IEq3"><tex-math id="d33e560">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${P_u}=\left\{ {{p_{u,{l_1}}},{\text{ }}{p_{u,{l_2}}},{\text{ }}...,{\text{ }}{p_{u,{l_m}}}} \right\}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. This distribution is based on the feature correlation between u and a labeled node <inline-formula id="IEq4"><tex-math id="d33e564">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$~{l_i} \in L$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, rather than on model prediction results as in traditional active learning. First, the cosine similarity <inline-formula id="IEq5"><tex-math id="d33e568">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$~{s_{u,{l_i}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> between u and <inline-formula id="IEq6"><tex-math id="d33e572">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$~{l_i}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is calculated to quantify the similarity of their feature characteristics.</p><disp-formula id="Equ18"><label>18</label><tex-math id="d33e577">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_{{u,{l_i}}}=\frac{{{{\boldsymbol{f}}_u}\cdot{{\boldsymbol{f}}_{{l_i}}}}}{{ {{\boldsymbol{f}}_u}{ _2} \times {{\boldsymbol{f}}_{{l_i}}}{_2}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par83">In Eq. (<xref rid="Equ18" ref-type="disp-formula">18</xref>), <inline-formula id="IEq7"><tex-math id="d33e586">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{\boldsymbol{f}}_u}\cdot{{\boldsymbol{f}}_{{l_i}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> denotes the dot product of the vectors, and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><tex-math id="d33e590">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${{\boldsymbol{f}}_u}{ _2}{{\boldsymbol{f}}_{{l_i}}}{ _2}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> represent their L2-norms. Since <inline-formula id="IEq9"><tex-math id="d33e594">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$~{s_{u,{l_i}}} \in [0,1]$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> reflects the strength of inter-node associations, normalization is applied to obtain the probability value <inline-formula id="IEq10"><tex-math id="d33e598">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$~{p_{u,{l_i}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="Par84">Based on the probability distribution Pu, the feature information entropy H(u) of the unlabeled node u is calculated to measure the uncertainty of its supplementary regional air quality information.</p><disp-formula id="Equ19"><label>19</label><tex-math id="d33e604">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$H(u)= - \sum\limits_{{i=1}}^{m} {{p_{u,{l_i}}}} {\log _2}{p_{u,{l_i}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><p id="Par85">When <inline-formula id="IEq11"><tex-math id="d33e610">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${p_{u,li}}=0$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, the term <inline-formula id="IEq12"><tex-math id="d33e614">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${p_{u,{l_i}}}{\log _2}{p_{u,{l_i}}}=0$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is defined to avoid undefined logarithmic operations. A smaller entropy value <inline-formula id="IEq13"><tex-math id="d33e618">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$H(u)$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> indicates a stronger correlation between node u and the features of the labeled nodes, implying a higher likelihood that it belongs to a homogeneous region. Selecting such a node can accurately represent the corresponding region and avoid information redundancy. Conversely, a larger entropy suggests that u may be located near a region boundary or in an uncovered area, requiring priority labeling to reduce overall uncertainty. The algorithm ranks unlabeled nodes in ascending order of <inline-formula id="IEq14"><tex-math id="d33e622">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$H(u)$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, selects the top-k nodes to add to the labeled set L, and retrains the CNN model to update the feature vectors. This process is repeated until the constraint on the number of monitoring points is satisfied.</p><p id="Par86">The N nodes with the highest average recommendation priorities were selected as recommended ambient air quality monitoring points. The N stations with highest average recommendation priority had the highest information entropy, high uncertainty, and low correlation with the other nodes. The establishment of new ambient air quality monitoring points based on these points can improve the accuracy of the air quality model in predicting the distribution of air quality in the entire urban area to the greatest extent and achieve timely and accurate reflection of the current situation and development trend of ambient air quality in urban areas.</p><p id="Par87">Partial pseudocode of greedy algorithm steps based on information entropy minimization:</p><p id="Par88">Input: Air quality monitoring data F, city spatiotemporal map G.</p><p id="Par89">Output: Recommended ambient air quality monitoring point L.</p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par91">Initialize the labeled node L as the empty set and the unlabeled node U as the set of all nodes.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par92">Train the air quality model and calculate the mean convolution weight parameter W and feature information entropy H.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par93">For each unmarked node u in U:</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par94">Calculate the characteristic information entropy Hu of node u.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par95">Find node u_min = argmin(Hu) with the lowest entropy of feature information.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par96">Delete node u_min from the unlabeled node set U and add it to the labeled node set L.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par97">Associate node u_min with the predicted air quality value.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par98">The weight parameters of the air quality model are updated to obtain the new convolutional weight parameter W1 and feature information entropy H1.</p></list-item></list>
<p id="Par99">Steps 3 through 8 are repeated until all unlabeled nodes are recommended for priority labeling.</p><p id="Par100">The results of the multiple recommendations are averaged, and the average recommendation priority Ti is calculated.</p><p id="Par101">N nodes with the highest average recommended priority are selected as the recommended ambient air quality monitoring points L. The specific parameter settings for these experiments are listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Parameter settings for the experiment.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Project</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Set up</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Target city size</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium sized city with an urban area of approximately 500 square kilometers</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of sensors</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The actual number of sensors used for measurement is 50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sensor location</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Distributed in different areas of the city, including industrial, commercial, residential, and transportation hubs, to ensure the comprehensiveness and representativeness of monitoring data</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Measurement cycle</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Continuous monitoring, with a data collection cycle of one year</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">sampling frequency</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Each sensor collects data once per hour</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par103">When calculating the feature information entropy of unlabeled nodes, the probability distribution is constructed based on the feature correlation between the node and the labeled nodes in the urban spatiotemporal graph. First, the set of labeled nodes and the target unlabeled node are identified. The feature vectors of all nodes are 1 × 64-dimensional vectors extracted by the convolutional neural network. Next, the cosine similarity between the feature vector of the unlabeled node and that of each labeled node is calculated. This similarity is derived by dividing the dot product of the two vectors by the product of their L2 norms. The resulting cosine similarity values are then normalized to obtain the similarity probabilities between the unlabeled node’s features and those of each labeled node. These probabilities collectively form the probability distribution for the unlabeled node. Finally, the feature information entropy of the unlabeled node is computed from this distribution as the sum of the negative value of each similarity probability multiplied by its base-2 logarithm. If a similarity probability equals 0, the corresponding term is defined as 0 to avoid undefined logarithmic operations.</p><p id="Par104">Taking 10 typical unlabeled nodes (numbered U1-U10) in City A as an example, the entropy evolution during the process of labeling → retreating → entropy weight calculation is shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Entropy evolution of 10 unlabeled nodes in City A/bit.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Iteration rounds</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U2</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U3</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U4</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U5</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U6</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U7</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U8</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U9</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U10</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Marking nodes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Initial (0 rounds)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.85</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.56</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.48</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.91</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.73</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 round (marked U3)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.72</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.39</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.65</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.94</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U3 (minimum initial entropy value)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 rounds (marked U9)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.68</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.35</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.15</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.61</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U9 (minimum entropy value after 1 round)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 rounds (marked U7)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.65</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.32</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.77</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.87</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U7 (minimum entropy value after 2 rounds)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 rounds (marked U6)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.62</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.95</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.28</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U6 (minimum entropy value after 3 rounds)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 rounds (marked U10)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.60</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.25</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.71</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">—</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">U10 (minimum entropy after 4 rounds)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par106">According to Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, after each iteration assigns a label to the node with the smallest entropy value, the entropy values of the remaining unlabeled nodes exhibit a decreasing trend. This occurs because, after the model is retrained, the correlation calculation between nodes becomes more accurate, thereby reducing the uncertainty of the unlabeled nodes. Moreover, the entropy evolution trend remains stable without abnormal fluctuations, which verifies the rationality and stability of the process of “marking → retreating → entropy weight calculation”.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><p id="Par107">To validate the effectiveness of the automatic air monitoring point siting model based on CNN and K-means clustering, a specific city is selected as the study area. In recent years, cities have experienced rapid development, with increasing numbers of vehicles in urban road networks and numerous factories established around urban areas. The original urban air monitoring network can no longer meet current demands for automatic air monitoring. It is therefore necessary to add new automatic air monitoring points according to the specific conditions of the study area. The siting of these additional monitoring points is crucial. The air quality monitoring dataset for the study area includes the date and time of each monitoring record, the geographical coordinates of the monitoring stations, and the concentration values of various pollutants such as PM2.5, PM10, ozone, sulfur dioxide, and carbon monoxide over a specific period. A comprehensive air quality index value is calculated from the concentrations of different pollutants to describe air quality levels and classifications.</p><p id="Par108">The data for this study are obtained from public environmental monitoring platforms in City A (a highly polluted industrial city), City B (a medium-pollution comprehensive city), and City C (a low-pollution tourist city), covering hourly pollutant concentrations, meteorological data, and geographic information from 2022 to 2023, with 182,000, 157,000, and 121,000 records, respectively. During preprocessing, Z-score standardization is applied to eliminate scale differences, missing values are handled using forward filling, and outliers are identified and removed based on the 3σ criterion.</p><p id="Par109">Parameter selection is based on scientific methodology and scenario adaptability: the CNN model employs 256 hidden nodes, determined by evaluating the feature extraction accuracy and computational time for different numbers of nodes in the range of 128–512 and selecting the optimal balance between accuracy and efficiency. The number of clusters K for the K-means algorithm is determined by combining the elbow method and the silhouette coefficient, with values of 8, 7, and 6 corresponding to the three city types. The initialization method uses k-means + + to accelerate convergence and reduce the risk of local optima. The maximum number of iterations is set to 300, and the convergence threshold is set to 1 × 10<sup>− 4</sup> to ensure stable and reliable clustering results. For information entropy calculation, the logarithm base 2 is adopted as it facilitates the quantification of information gain in bits and aligns with the classical definition of information value in information theory. The greedy batch size k is set to 5, determined according to the practical requirement of the environmental protection department that no more than five new points should be added at a time. All parameter settings were verified for stability through three repeated experiments.</p><p id="Par110">The number of structural layers and hidden neurons in the convolutional neural network significantly influences the model’s feature extraction performance. In this study, the convolutional neural network is employed to extract features for automatic air monitoring point siting. The output mean squared error of the convolutional neural network under different numbers of hidden nodes is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Output error of the convolutional neural network vs. number of hidden nodes.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e972" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/2ee25ef62dbc/41598_2026_41078_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?original-height 583?><?original-width 782?><?scaled-height 583?><?scaled-width 782?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/f17d694704f8/41598_2026_41078_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par112">As shown by the experimental results in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, the mean squared error for extracting air monitoring data features using the network is minimized when the number of hidden nodes is 256, regardless of the number of iterations. When the number of hidden nodes is 256 and the number of iterations reaches 100, the CNN output tends to stabilize. The results in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> indicate that with 256 hidden nodes, the convolutional neural network used in this model exhibits strong generalization capability and highly stable output. Consequently, for the automatic air monitoring point siting task in this study, the number of hidden nodes in the CNN is set to 256.</p><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Structure of the CNN algorithm.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e990" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/629685856505/41598_2026_41078_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 316?><?original-width 999?><?scaled-height 211?><?scaled-width 666?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/693e04b8356f/41598_2026_41078_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par114">When the model is applied to automatic air monitoring point siting, a CNN is used to extract feature vectors from the air monitoring data, as presented in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Feature extraction results of convolutional neural network.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Feature number</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Feature name</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Feature number</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Feature name</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM2.5 concentration</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maximum temperature</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM10 concentration</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Minimum temperature</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Carbon dioxide concentration</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wind speed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ozone concentration</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Relative humidity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">visibility</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average air pressure</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">average temperature</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">precipitation</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par116">The experimental results in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> demonstrate that the CNN can effectively extract features from the air monitoring data and construct an automatic air monitoring point siting model based on these features.</p><p id="Par117">In this study, a convolutional neural network is used to extract feature vectors from the air monitoring data, and the K-means clustering algorithm is applied to cluster the extracted feature vectors. For different numbers of iterations, the K-means algorithm is used to cluster both the original air monitoring data and the extracted feature data, and the convergence distance is recorded. The statistical results are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of clustering convergence distances.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1094" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/a4b65da58afe/41598_2026_41078_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?original-height 589?><?original-width 734?><?scaled-height 589?><?scaled-width 734?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/5d9cf8b393c5/41598_2026_41078_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par119">In the K-means clustering algorithm, convergence is reached when the cluster centers no longer change. According to the experimental results in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, the K-means algorithm exhibits poor convergence performance when applied to the original air monitoring data, whereas it achieves effective convergence when clustering the air monitoring data features extracted by the CNN. The slow convergence for the original data is primarily due to poor feature distinguishability, which leads to frequent oscillations in cluster assignments and prevents the cluster centers from stabilizing within a small number of iterations. In contrast, the feature data extracted by the CNN enable the K-means algorithm to rapidly identify stable cluster centers and reduce oscillations in cluster assignments. Therefore, clustering the CNN-extracted features using the K-means algorithm results in faster convergence.</p><p id="Par120">Based on the air quality monitoring results in the study area, the proposed model is used to determine automatic air monitoring point locations. The geographical coordinates of the recommended monitoring points identified by the model are provided in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. A comparative analysis is conducted between the monitoring points determined by the proposed model and those from the models in references<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Coordinate determination results of automatic air monitoring points.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monitoring point number</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Paper model</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Literature<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> model</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Literature<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> model</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(27,35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(25,29)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(31,18)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(35,65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(34,59)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(37,29)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(47,82)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(39,87)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(39,37)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(59,92)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(52,128)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(42,52)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(72,115)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(64,147)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(59,67)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(86,125)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(69,158)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(67,78)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(114,137)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(78,175)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(88,95)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(125,159)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(105,199)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(117,104)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(146,176)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(117,218)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(134,118)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(159,197)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(136,228)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(147,134)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par122">The comparison results in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> demonstrate that automatic air monitoring points in the study area can be effectively identified using all three models. Furthermore, the results in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> confirm the effectiveness of the siting approaches for the automatic air monitoring points achieved by the three models.</p><p id="Par123">Automatic air monitoring point 1, identified by the three models, is selected for testing. The PM2.5 and PM10 concentration monitoring results obtained from the three models during the period from November 15 to 24, 2019, are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Air quality monitoring results from different models. (<bold>a</bold>) PM2.5 concentration. (<bold>b</bold>) PM10 concentration.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1265" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/a4396e9230d9/41598_2026_41078_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1304?><?original-width 935?><?scaled-height 869?><?scaled-width 623?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig4_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/127b99f95363/41598_2026_41078_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par125">The experimental results in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> indicate that all three models can effectively monitor air quality at the selected points, demonstrating high detection performance.</p><p id="Par126">The PM2.5 concentration monitoring results at the points selected by the three models are compared with the actual measured concentrations in the study area, and the monitoring errors for points selected by different models are quantified. The statistical results are presented in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Monitoring errors of air automatic monitoring points selected by different models.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1285" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/0cf0b9a9a514/41598_2026_41078_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?original-height 571?><?original-width 724?><?scaled-height 571?><?scaled-width 724?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_41078_Fig5_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/bebe/13068920/3af840646b1f/41598_2026_41078_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par128">As shown by the experimental results in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, the air quality monitoring results from the automatic monitoring points identified by the proposed model are highly consistent with the actual air quality measurements. The mean squared error of the monitoring results is less than 1%, which effectively verifies the high siting performance of the proposed model for automatic air monitoring points. The selected automatic monitoring points exhibit high monitoring effectiveness and can accurately track the real-time distribution of air quality across the entire urban area.</p><p id="Par129">To further validate the effectiveness of the proposed method, a comparison is conducted with the model from reference<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> and the model from reference<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. The evaluation metrics include the correlation coefficient, mean bias, mean standard deviation, and accuracy. The comparison results are provided in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Comparison results of different methods.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Method</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Correlation coefficient</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average deviation/%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean standard deviation/%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy/%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Textual method</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Literature<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> model</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.25</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">86.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Literature<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> model</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.26</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.46</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.67</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par131">As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>, the proposed method achieves the best performance in terms of correlation coefficient, mean bias, mean standard deviation, and accuracy. The respective values for the proposed method are 0.96, 0.62%, 0.98%, and 98.36%. This demonstrates that the proposed method offers high accuracy and precision for air quality monitoring point siting. The model from reference<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> exhibits a lower correlation coefficient of 0.63, with a mean bias of 1.25%, a mean standard deviation of 1.26%, and an accuracy of 86.15%. Compared to reference<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>, the proposed method achieves significantly improved accuracy. The model from reference<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> shows a slightly higher correlation coefficient of 0.81 than that of reference<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>; however, its mean bias and mean standard deviation are 1.26% and 1.46%, respectively, and its accuracy is 84.67%. In comparison with the proposed method, the model in reference<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> still has room for improvement in both accuracy and precision. Overall, the proposed method exhibits higher correlation, smaller bias, lower standard deviation, and greater precision in air quality monitoring point siting. Therefore, the proposed method constitutes an effective siting model for air monitoring and can provide more accurate results for air quality monitoring.</p><p id="Par132">To evaluate the real-time performance of the proposed automatic air monitoring siting model based on convolutional neural network and K-means clustering, a comparison is conducted with the methods in references<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Historical data from multiple urban air quality monitoring stations are prepared, including key indicators such as PM2.5 concentration, PM10 concentration, and CO2 concentration. These data are used to train the proposed model as well as the models from references<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. All models are executed under identical hardware and software environments. The specific experimental results are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab6" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Real-time performance analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Data processing time/s</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average latency/s</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maximum latency/s</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Textual method</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Literature<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> model</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">240</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Literature<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> model</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">180</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.0</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par134">As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, the proposed method outperforms the methods in references<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> in terms of data processing time and latency. The proposed method requires only 120 s for data processing, with an average latency of 0.5 s and a maximum latency of 1.2 s, both of which are lower than those of the other two methods. This demonstrates that the proposed model offers higher real-time performance when processing large-scale air quality monitoring data, enabling faster delivery of accurate air quality monitoring results. This capability facilitates timely response measures by relevant authorities and residents.</p><p id="Par135">To evaluate the model’s performance in handling primary and secondary pollutants, PM10 and SO₂ are selected as representative primary pollutants, and O₃ and NO₂ as representative secondary pollutants. The model outputs are compared with the actual observed pollutant concentrations. The specific experimental results are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab7" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Comparison of pollutant concentrations between model output and observation results.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pollutant type</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model predicted value/(µg/m³)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Observation average value/(µg/m³)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Absolute error/(µg/m³)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Relative error/%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SO₂</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O₃</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO₂</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.9</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par137">As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>, the model predicts PM10 and SO₂ concentrations of 58.2 µg/m³ and 21.7 µg/m³, respectively, compared to observed averages of 58.5 µg/m³ and 22.4 µg/m³, resulting in absolute errors of 0.3 µg/m³ and 0.7 µg/m³ and relative errors of 0.51% and 3.13%. For the secondary pollutants O₃ and NO₂, the predicted values are 45.6 µg/m³ and 38.9 µg/m³, respectively, versus observed averages of 46.1 µg/m³ and 38.7 µg/m³, yielding absolute errors of 0.5 µg/m³ and 0.2 µg/m³ and relative errors of 1.08% and 0.52%. The predicted values for all pollutants show strong agreement with the observed averages, with absolute errors below 1 µg/m³ and a maximum relative error of only 3.13%. These results indicate that the model achieves high accuracy and reliability in predicting both primary and secondary pollutant concentrations, effectively reflecting actual pollution levels.</p><p id="Par138">To evaluate the computational efficiency and adaptability of the proposed method across different city types, three cities are selected as case studies: City A (a highly polluted industrial city), City B (a medium-pollution comprehensive city), and City C (a low-pollution tourist city). The grid point method, traditional entropy-based active learning, and a random forest siting model are used as controls, with CPU utilization, GPU utilization, and runtime selected as computational cost metrics. The experimental results are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab8" ref-type="table">8</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab8" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Computational cost comparison across different cities.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Method</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">City type</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CPU usage rate/%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GPU usage rate/%</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Running time/min</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Proposed Method</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High pollution industrial city A</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium pollution comprehensive city B</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low pollution tourist city C</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Grid point method</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High pollution industrial city A</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium pollution comprehensive city B</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low pollution tourist city C</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Traditional entropy based active learning</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High pollution industrial city A</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medium pollution comprehensive city B</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low pollution tourist city C</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par140">The data in Table <xref rid="Tab8" ref-type="table">8</xref> show that traditional entropy-based active learning incurs the highest computational cost, exhibiting the highest CPU utilization, GPU utilization, and runtime across all three city types. For example, in highly polluted industrial City A, it reaches 55% CPU utilization, 49% GPU utilization, and a runtime of 50 min. Even in low-pollution tourist City C, these metrics remain at elevated levels. The grid point method ranks second in computational cost; in medium- to high-pollution cities, its CPU utilization and runtime exceed those of the proposed method. For instance, in highly polluted industrial City A, the grid point method shows 35% CPU utilization and a 38-minute runtime, which are 13% points and 13 min higher, respectively, than the proposed method. The proposed method achieves the lowest values across all computational cost metrics and exhibits a clear decreasing trend as urban pollution levels decrease. In highly polluted industrial City A, it requires 22% CPU utilization, 28% GPU utilization, and 25 min of runtime. These values decline to 14%, 15%, and 12 min, respectively, in low-pollution tourist City C. These results demonstrate the method’s strong adaptability to cities with varying pollution levels and its significant advantage in computational cost control compared to the two baseline methods.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par141">An automatic air monitoring point siting model is developed based on a convolutional neural network and K-means clustering to enhance regional air quality management. According to the technical specifications for ambient air quality monitoring point layout (trial version), the main principles for siting air quality monitoring equipment are as follows.</p><p id="Par142">Regarding purpose, the monitoring network should employ appropriate methods according to different objectives and functional attributes to recommend suitable monitoring points that reflect the current fine-grained spatial distribution of regional air quality.</p><p id="Par143">In terms of representativeness, since the goal of establishing an ambient air quality monitoring network is to accurately represent the air quality distribution across the entire urban area, the recommended monitoring points should be representative. A new air quality monitoring network should be constructed incorporating the original urban air quality monitoring stations to accurately predict air quality levels and their variations throughout the urban area for effective environmental monitoring and control.</p><p id="Par144">For integrity, the ambient air quality monitoring network should account for external factors influencing air quality distribution, such as meteorological conditions, traffic volume, and urban road networks, to reflect the air quality distribution and development trends in the city’s main functional areas and for key air pollutants. Additionally, the existing urban air quality monitoring network layout should be considered, ensuring coordination among monitoring points and rational spatial distribution.</p><p id="Par145">Concerning forward-lookingness, in conjunction with urban development trends, newly deployed monitoring points should adapt to future urban pattern changes and meet the needs of different cities.</p><p id="Par146">For stability, considering the construction costs of monitoring points and the historical continuity of urban ambient air quality monitoring, locations should remain fixed once new monitoring points are established.</p><p id="Par147">Finally, for feasibility, the design of an ambient air quality monitoring network must be practical and implementable. The recommended optimal monitoring points should maximize the improvement in the air quality model’s prediction accuracy for the entire urban area.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par148">An automatic air monitoring point siting model is developed based on a convolutional neural network and K-means clustering. This model optimizes the distribution of regional air quality monitoring networks and captures regional air pollution characteristics. Experimental results verify that the model can be applied to optimize the layout of practical regional air quality monitoring networks, with monitoring errors of the selected automatic air monitoring points remaining within the limits specified by China’s ambient air quality monitoring code. The proposed siting model comprehensively accounts for the impact of multiple pollutants, thereby reflecting regional composite pollution patterns. The monitoring results effectively represent regional air pollution characteristics and meet the requirements of regional air quality management.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Sisi Liu and Jiao Peng wrote the main manuscript text and Xiu He prepared figures and tables. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Funding</title><p>The study was supported by “Research on student profiling and learning analytics based on data mining” (GKY-2023BSQD-48) and “Based on LDA Model for Keyword Extraction and Analysis of Research Papers”(Grant GKY-2024KYYBK-14), Guangdong University of Science and Technology.</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par149">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang, Y., Tai, S. L., Li, M., Liu, F. &amp; Tang, S. Convolutional neural network models of v1 responses to complex patterns. <italic>J. Comput. Neurosci.</italic><bold>46</bold>(1), 33–54 (2019).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s10827-018-0687-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29869761"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhang, Y., Tai, S. L., Li, M., Liu, F. &amp; Tang, S. Convolutional neural network models of v1 responses to complex patterns. J. Comput. Neurosci.46(1), 33–54 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhuang, Y. C. &amp; Li, W. Air quality prediction based on PSO extreme learning machine of neural network. <italic>J. Shenyang Univ. Technol.</italic><bold>42</bold>(2), 213–217 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhuang, Y. C. &amp; Li, W. Air quality prediction based on PSO extreme learning machine of neural network. J. Shenyang Univ. Technol.42(2), 213–217 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Du, H. H. &amp; Liu, Y. H. BP neural network optimized by hybrid genetic-ant colony algorithm for air quality prediction. <italic>Comput. Syst. Appl.</italic><bold>32</bold>(4), 223–230 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Du, H. H. &amp; Liu, Y. H. BP neural network optimized by hybrid genetic-ant colony algorithm for air quality prediction. Comput. Syst. Appl.32(4), 223–230 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wen, C. K., Chen, Y. Y., ,He, Y. H. &amp; ,Chen, F. Air quality index prediction by multi-strategy SMA-BP neural network. <italic>Electron. Meas. Technol.</italic>, <bold>46</bold>(22),78–86 .</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lin, F. C., Lu, S. H., Liang, C. J., Chen, Y. H. &amp; Liang, J. J. Quantifying source apportionment for ambient haze: An image haze extraction approach with air quality monitoring data. <italic>Environ. Res.</italic><bold>184</bold>(1), 109216 (2020).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envres.2020.109216"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32065977"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lin, F. C., Lu, S. H., Liang, C. J., Chen, Y. H. &amp; Liang, J. J. Quantifying source apportionment for ambient haze: An image haze extraction approach with air quality monitoring data. Environ. Res.184(1), 109216 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ravindra, K. et al. Real-time monitoring of air pollutants in seven cities of north india during crop residue burning and their relationship with meteorology and transboundary movement of air. <italic>Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>690</bold> (NOV.10), 717–729 (2019).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.06.216"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31301511"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ravindra, K. et al. Real-time monitoring of air pollutants in seven cities of north india during crop residue burning and their relationship with meteorology and transboundary movement of air. Sci. Total Environ.690 (NOV.10), 717–729 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fan, H. et al. Spatiotemporal assessment of marine environmental monitoring programme based on din concentration in the yangtze river estuary and its adjacent sea. <italic>Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>707</bold> (Mar.10), 1355271–1355278 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.135527"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31784161"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Fan, H. et al. Spatiotemporal assessment of marine environmental monitoring programme based on din concentration in the yangtze river estuary and its adjacent sea. Sci. Total Environ.707 (Mar.10), 1355271–1355278 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Miller, T. H., Ng, K. T., Lamphiere, A., Cameron, T. C. &amp; Barron, L. P. Multicompartment and cross-species monitoring of contaminants of emerging concern in an estuarine habitat. <italic>Environ. Pollut.</italic><bold>270</bold>(17), 116300 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2020.116300"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7846722"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33348138"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Miller, T. H., Ng, K. T., Lamphiere, A., Cameron, T. C. &amp; Barron, L. P. Multicompartment and cross-species monitoring of contaminants of emerging concern in an estuarine habitat. Environ. Pollut.270(17), 116300 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yang, X. M. K-Means algorithm for parallel optimal sampling clustering of multi-source information data. <italic>Comput. Simul.</italic><bold>37</bold>(7), 5–7 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yang, X. M. K-Means algorithm for parallel optimal sampling clustering of multi-source information data. Comput. Simul.37(7), 5–7 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Park, S., Lee, H. &amp; Chon, J. Sustainable monitoring coverage of unmanned aerial vehicle photogrammetry according to wing type and image resolution. <italic>Environ. Pollut.</italic><bold>247</bold>, 340–348 (2019).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2018.08.050"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30690230"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Park, S., Lee, H. &amp; Chon, J. Sustainable monitoring coverage of unmanned aerial vehicle photogrammetry according to wing type and image resolution. Environ. Pollut.247, 340–348 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, J., Zhang, W. &amp; Zhou, J. Fault detection with data imbalance conditions based on the improved bilayer convolutional neural network. <italic>Ind. Eng. Chem. Res.</italic><bold>59</bold> (13), 5891–5904 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, J., Zhang, W. &amp; Zhou, J. Fault detection with data imbalance conditions based on the improved bilayer convolutional neural network. Ind. Eng. Chem. Res.59 (13), 5891–5904 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tang, M. Z., Ren, J. N., Wu, L. W. &amp; Gao, J. Advances in research and application of mobile air quality sensors. <italic>Research of Environmental Sciences</italic><bold>35</bold>(4), 971–978 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tang, M. Z., Ren, J. N., Wu, L. W. &amp; Gao, J. Advances in research and application of mobile air quality sensors. Research of Environmental Sciences35(4), 971–978 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Varekar, V., Yadav, V. &amp; Karmakar, S. Rationalization of water quality monitoring locations under spatiotemporal heterogeneity of diffuse pollution using seasonal export coefficient. <italic>J. Environ. Manage.</italic><bold>277</bold>(12), 111342 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jenvman.2020.111342"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33080433"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Varekar, V., Yadav, V. &amp; Karmakar, S. Rationalization of water quality monitoring locations under spatiotemporal heterogeneity of diffuse pollution using seasonal export coefficient. J. Environ. Manage.277(12), 111342 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lan, T., Hu, H., Jiang, C., Yang, G. &amp; Zhao, Z. A comparative study of decision tree, random forest, and convolutional neural network for spread-f identification. <italic>Adv. Space Res.</italic><bold>65</bold> (8), 2052–2061 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lan, T., Hu, H., Jiang, C., Yang, G. &amp; Zhao, Z. A comparative study of decision tree, random forest, and convolutional neural network for spread-f identification. Adv. Space Res.65 (8), 2052–2061 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lee, C. C., Tran, M. V., Cheng, W. C., Tan, C. P. &amp; Chiew, Y. S. <italic>Evaluation of air quality in sunway city, selangor, malaysia from a mobile monitoring campaign using air pollution micro-sensors</italic>, 115058 (Environmental Pollution, 2020). 265(Pt A).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2020.115058"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32806396"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Min, J. P. &amp; Sacchi, M. D. Automatic velocity analysis using convolutional neural network and transfer learning. <italic>Geophysics</italic><bold>85</bold>(1), 1–45 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Min, J. P. &amp; Sacchi, M. D. Automatic velocity analysis using convolutional neural network and transfer learning. Geophysics85(1), 1–45 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tang, F. H. et al. Adaptive convolutional layer selection based on historical retrospect for visual tracking. <italic>IET Comput. Vis.</italic><bold>13</bold>(3), 345–353 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tang, F. H. et al. Adaptive convolutional layer selection based on historical retrospect for visual tracking. IET Comput. Vis.13(3), 345–353 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Huang, Z., Zhang, R., Pan, J., Jiang, Y. &amp; Zhai, D. A framework of multipath clustering based on space-transformed fuzzy c -means and data fusion for radio channel modeling. <italic>IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol.</italic><bold>PP</bold> (99), 1–7 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Huang, Z., Zhang, R., Pan, J., Jiang, Y. &amp; Zhai, D. A framework of multipath clustering based on space-transformed fuzzy c -means and data fusion for radio channel modeling. IEEE Trans. Veh. Technol.PP (99), 1–7 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gandhi, G. S., Vikas, K., Ratnam, V. &amp; Babu, K. S. Grid clustering and fuzzy reinforcement-learning based energy-efficient data aggregation scheme for distributed wsn. <italic>IET Commun.</italic><bold>14</bold>(16), 2840–2848 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gandhi, G. S., Vikas, K., Ratnam, V. &amp; Babu, K. S. Grid clustering and fuzzy reinforcement-learning based energy-efficient data aggregation scheme for distributed wsn. IET Commun.14(16), 2840–2848 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Marchant, C., Leiva, V., Christakos, G. &amp; Cavieres, M. F. Monitoring urban environmental pollution by bivariate control charts: New methodology and case study in Santiago, Chile. <italic>Environmetrics</italic><bold>30</bold>(5), 1–17 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Marchant, C., Leiva, V., Christakos, G. &amp; Cavieres, M. F. Monitoring urban environmental pollution by bivariate control charts: New methodology and case study in Santiago, Chile. Environmetrics30(5), 1–17 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sushkova, S. et al. Environmental pollution of soil with pahs in energy producing plants zone. <italic>Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>655</bold> (MAR.10), 232–241 (2019).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.11.080"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30471591"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sushkova, S. et al. Environmental pollution of soil with pahs in energy producing plants zone. Sci. Total Environ.655 (MAR.10), 232–241 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>Data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</p></sec></sec></body></article>