
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><?da-xref-anchor-style superscripted?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12368213</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12368213.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12368213</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12368213</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40835637</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-11472-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">11472</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Source dynamics and environmental risk of street dust as a vector of human exposure to potentially toxic elements in Istanbul, Türkiye</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Öncü</surname><given-names initials="T">Tuna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazman</surname><given-names initials="MM">Mehmet Metin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustaoğlu</surname><given-names initials="F">Fikret</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hristova</surname><given-names initials="E">Elena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7686-8648</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names initials="B">Bayram</given-names></name><address><email>bayram.yuksel@giresun.edu.tr</email><email>bayramyuksel83@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05szaq822</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411709.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0399 3319</institution-id><institution>Department of Biology, </institution><institution>Giresun University, </institution></institution-wrap>Gure Campus, Giresun, 28200 Türkiye Turkey </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05szaq822</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411709.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0399 3319</institution-id><institution>Department of Food Processing, </institution><institution>Giresun University, </institution></institution-wrap>28600 Espiye, Giresun Türkiye </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/021vn9c61</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.425472.2</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Meteorology and Hydrology, </institution></institution-wrap>Sofia, Bulgaria </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05szaq822</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411709.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0399 3319</institution-id><institution>Department of Property Protection and Security, </institution><institution>Giresun University, </institution></institution-wrap>28600 Espiye, Giresun Türkiye </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478255</issue-id><elocation-id>30550</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-08-22 00:25:22.283"><day>22</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2025_Article_11472.pdf"><?pdf-name 41598_2025_Article_11472.pdf?><?pdf-size 9986195?><?pdf-md5 24319344abf4ffa7d381f3c8e7c55f5c?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:0057/12368213/24319344abf4/41598_2025_Article_11472.pdf?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par10">Urban street dust acts as both a sink and a secondary source of potentially toxic elements (PTEs), contributing to environmental contamination and air quality degradation. Using geochemical and statistical methods, this study aimed to investigate the concentrations, spatial distribution, ecological risks, sources, and associated health risks of selected PTEs (Al, As, Cd, Co, Cr, Cu, Fe, Mn, Ni, Pb, Zn) in &lt; 63 μm street dust samples collected from 29 locations across Istanbul, Türkiye. Elemental concentrations were determined using ICP-MS, and contamination was evaluated using geo-accumulation (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub>), enrichment (EF), contamination (CF), potential ecological risk (PERI), and Nemerow’s pollution indices (NPI). Positive Matrix Factorization (PMF) identified three dominant sources: industrial runoff (39.4%), traffic emissions (31.3%), and natural/soil inputs (29.4%). Health risk assessments indicated ingestion as the primary exposure pathway. Monte Carlo simulation revealed that the 95th percentiles of THI (3.57) and TCR (2.61 × 10⁻⁴) exceeded recommended thresholds for children, indicating potential non-carcinogenic and carcinogenic risks, while adult risks largely remained within acceptable limits. Traffic-related elements such as Pb, Cu, and Zn were the major contributors to non-carcinogenic risks, with additional implications for inhalation exposure through dust resuspension. Although the Air Quality Index (AQI) remained below 50, suggesting generally good atmospheric conditions during the study period, localized dust contamination was found to pose significant health risks. These findings emphasize the need for integrated mitigation strategies, including traffic emission controls, dust suppression, and urban greening, to minimize PTE exposure and enhance urban environmental health.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-11472-2.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Street dust</kwd><kwd>Potentially toxic elements</kwd><kwd>Istanbul</kwd><kwd>Source identification</kwd><kwd>Health risk assessment</kwd><kwd>Environmental protection strategies</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Environmental sciences</kwd><kwd>Solid Earth sciences</kwd><kwd>Chemistry</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100017218</institution-id><institution>Giresun Üniversitesi</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>FEN-BAP-A-290224-43</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>Bayram</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par11">The rapid growth of urban populations and infrastructure has intensified environmental pressures in metropolitan areas, where restricted air circulation due to dense building layouts contributes to pollutant accumulation. These conditions have led to elevated human exposure to airborne contaminants, reflected in increasing levels of traffic congestion, noise pollution, and declining air quality, thereby posing significant risks to public health and urban sustainability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. In other words, urban environments are increasingly challenged by contamination with potentially toxic elements (PTEs), such as arsenic, cadmium, lead, chromium, and nickel These elements originate from both natural sources and anthropogenic activities, including rapid urbanization, industrial processes, and vehicular emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Among various environmental matrices, street dust acts as a major reservoir and transport medium for these contaminants. It also represents a critical source of particulate matter (PM) in urban atmospheres, significantly influencing pollution dynamics and posing substantial public health risks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par12">Human exposure to PTEs, including arsenic, lead, nickel, chromium, and cadmium, primarily arises through ingestion, inhalation, and dermal penetration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. These contaminants, introduced into urban environments via industrial discharges, construction activities, vehicular emissions, and atmospheric deposition, often accumulate in urban street dust. Once deposited, PTEs can be resuspended into the air or migrate into water and soil systems, thereby amplifying exposure risks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Arsenic, a recognized carcinogen, is associated with bladder, skin, and lung cancers, as well as developmental disorders and cardiovascular problems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Chromium, particularly in its hexavalent form, exhibits high carcinogenicity and mutagenic toxicity, while nickel exposure is linked to respiratory diseases and allergic reactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Lead primarily affect neurological and renal systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Cadmium toxicity is a serious health concern, primarily damaging the kidneys, lungs, and bones, and is classified as a human carcinogen with severe acute and chronic effects dependent on exposure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Prolonged exposure to these elements has been further correlated with increased risks of cardiovascular disease and cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Children represent a particularly vulnerable group due to their frequent ground-level activities and greater physiological sensitivity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The co-existence of multiple PTEs in street dust exacerbates health hazards, underscoring the urgent need for specific actions designed to limit exposure and protect community health. Implementing effective strategies is essential to minimize the adverse health and ecological impacts of urban street dust contamination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par13">Air quality refers to the degree to which the ambient atmosphere is clean or polluted, typically measured by the concentrations of key pollutants such as particulate matter (PM<sub>10</sub> and PM<sub>2.5</sub>), ozone (O<sub>3</sub>), nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>), sulfur dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub>), and carbon monoxide (CO), and is often expressed using composite indices like the Air Quality Index (AQI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Therefore, air quality plays a critical role in safeguarding human health and promoting environmental sustainability. Comprehensive understanding of pollutant concentrations and their impacts provides essential insights for regulatory compliance and public health protection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Istanbul, a transcontinental megacity characterized by a combination of historical heritage and rapid urbanization, faces a complex and evolving pollution landscape. High population density, extensive transportation networks, significant industrial activities, and ongoing urban development projects contribute substantially to the contamination of the city’s environmental media<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Meteorological dynamics, including the interaction of local wind patterns and seasonal precipitation, further influence the transport, dispersion, and deposition of street dust contaminants, emphasizing the necessity for integrated assessments of pollution sources and environmental drivers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Although previous studies have addressed soil and water contamination in Istanbul<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> comprehensive investigations focusing specifically on the source identification, spatial distribution, and health risks of PTEs in urban street dust, along with their relationship to meteorological factors, remain limited.</p><p id="Par14">PM not only acts as a vector for potentially toxic elements in urban environments but also plays a crucial role in atmospheric processes related to climate change. Fine particles can influence radiative forcing, urban heat island effects, and cloud formation dynamics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Additionally, the increasing frequency of extreme weather events and prolonged dry periods associated with climate change may enhance the resuspension and deposition of contaminated dust, thereby intensifying human exposure in densely populated areas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The AQI is a standardized system used to assess air pollution levels based on key atmospheric pollutants. In this study, the monitored parameters included PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SO<sub>2</sub>, each with distinct environmental and health implications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. PM<sub>2.5</sub> (particulate matter ≤ 2.5 μm) consists of fine particles primarily emitted from combustion sources, such as vehicle exhaust, industrial activities, and biomass burning. Due to their small size, PM<sub>2.5</sub> particles can penetrate deep into the respiratory tract and are associated with cardiovascular and pulmonary health risks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. PM<sub>10</sub> (particulate matter ≤ 10 μm) is coarser, originating from sources such as road dust, construction activities, and industrial emissions. Although less harmful than PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub> can cause respiratory irritation and contribute to overall reductions in air quality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. NO<sub>2</sub>, a gaseous pollutant generated mainly from vehicular emissions and industrial processes, can exacerbate respiratory diseases, particularly in vulnerable groups such as individuals with asthma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. SO<sub>2</sub> is primarily emitted from fossil fuel combustion, industrial processes, and volcanic eruptions and is known to cause respiratory ailments while contributing to acid rain formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Both the United States Environmental Protection Agency Air Quality Index Scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and the World Health Organization Air Quality Guidelines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> provide standardized frameworks for evaluating air quality and associated health risks. These guidelines set critical thresholds for pollutants such as PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, Pb, and As, which are essential for contextualizing exposure risks in urban environments.</p><p id="Par15">Thus, analyzing urban street dust’s geochemical composition and associated human health risks is crucial for sustainable urban planning and environmental management, aligning with UN Sustainable Development Goals 3 (Good Health and Well-Being) and 11 (Sustainable Cities and Communities) by identifying pollution sources and evaluating exposure risks to minimize environmental degradation and protect public health in metropolitan areas. Recent studies have applied machine learning and optimization methods to environmental pollution modeling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. However, this study aims to address these knowledge gaps by systematically investigating street dust contamination in Istanbul, with an emphasis on the quantification, source identification, and health risk assessment of PTEs. The specific objectives of the study are as follows: (i) to quantify the concentrations of key PTEs, including arsenic, chromium, lead, cadmium, and nickel, in urban street dust collected from diverse districts of Istanbul and to analyze their spatial distribution patterns; (ii) to identify the major sources of PTE contamination through advanced statistical techniques, including Positive Matrix Factorization (PMF) and hierarchical cluster analysis (HCA), while evaluating the influence of meteorological factors such as wind patterns, precipitation, and temperature on contaminant dispersion and deposition; (iii) to assess ecological risks using multiple contamination indices, namely the geo-accumulation index (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub>), contamination factor (CF), enrichment factor (EF), ecological risk index (E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup>), pollution load index (PLI), potential ecological risk index (PERI), and Nemerow’s pollution index (NPI); (iv) to evaluate non-carcinogenic and carcinogenic health risks associated with PTE exposure, refined through Monte Carlo Simulation to enhance the accuracy and robustness of risk estimations; and (v) to propose targeted mitigation strategies aimed at reducing PTE contamination and associated health risks, with particular consideration of the role of meteorological dynamics in shaping urban contamination patterns.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study area</title><p id="Par16">Istanbul, the largest city in Türkiye, is home to over 15 million people as of 2025, accounting for approximately 19% of the country’s total population. This transcontinental metropolis spans Europe and Asia, connected by the Bosphorus Strait, making it a vital cultural, economic, and industrial hub<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The city’s population density varies significantly, with central urban districts such as Kadıköy, Beşiktaş, and Şişli being highly concentrated, while suburban and peripheral areas are less densely populated but experiencing rapid growth. Urban expansion fueled by migration and economic development has heightened urban stressors, leading to increased construction, industrial activity, and vehicular traffic, which significantly contribute to street dust pollution. Furthermore, Istanbul experiences a transitional climate between the Mediterranean and oceanic types, with some humid subtropical characteristics in specific areas. Winters are mild, with average temperatures ranging from 4 °C to 8 °C in January, while summers are warm to hot, with temperatures averaging between 23 °C and 30 °C in July. The city receives moderate annual precipitation of 850–1,200 mm, predominantly during autumn and winter, while occasional snowfall occurs in winter. Humidity levels are generally high, ranging from 70 to 85%, due to the influence of the surrounding Black Sea and Marmara Sea. Istanbul enjoys approximately 2,500 h of sunshine annually, primarily in summer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Street dust samples were collected in February 2024 from 29 locations across Istanbul (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). At each site, five samples were obtained to represent industrial zones, residential areas, and high-traffic regions, ensuring comprehensive coverage of spatial variability. Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, created using ArcGIS Desktop version 10.8.2 (Esri, Redlands, CA, USA), illustrates the spatial distribution of the sampling sites and key geographic features within the study area. All spatial data were processed and visualized following standard cartographic principles to ensure clarity and accuracy.</p><p id="Par17">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Spatial distribution of the 29 street dust sampling locations across the European and Asian sides of Istanbul, Türkiye.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e456" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 137575?><?image-md5 b70f519c2d86735704b7344c6403a61c?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1427?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 475?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/b70f519c2d86/41598_2025_11472_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 6033?><?thumb-md5 42f100fe8af586f5dfb751137162fb09?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 112?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/42f100fe8af5/41598_2025_11472_Fig1_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Sampling protocols and analytical approaches</title><p id="Par18">Once collected, the dust samples were initially treated at 40 °C for 24 h to ensure proper drying. Afterward, they were sieved through a 63 μm mesh to separate finer particles from larger debris. The fine fractions were then stored at 4 °C to maintain their integrity and prevent contamination until further analysis. Sample preparation involved microwave-assisted acid digestion. For each sample, 100.00 mg of dust was placed in Teflon<sup>®</sup> vessels and treated with 12 mL of an acidic mixture consisting of concentrated nitric acid (HNO<sub>3</sub>) and hydrochloric acid (HCl) in a 3:1 ratio. The digestion was performed under controlled conditions to ensure the complete dissolution of target elements. Following digestion, the solution was diluted to a final volume of 50 mL using ultrapure water, which was used exclusively throughout the process to ensure consistency and eliminate potential contamination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par19">The levels of PTEs in street dust subjects were determined using a Shimadzu ICP-MS 2050 (Kyoto, Japan), renowned for its sensitivity and precision in trace metal detection. To achieve reliable and valid analytical outcomes, stringent quality assurance and quality control (QA/QC) protocols were implemented in accordance with ISO/IEC 17,025 standards for laboratory competence and analytical accuracy. Certified reference materials (CRMs) were used to validate the analytical method, and triplicate analyses of each sample were performed to assess precision and reproducibility. The ICP-MS method was confirmed by analyzing NIST 2702 (Gaithersburg, Maryland, USA) six times, evaluating parameters such as the precision, accuracy, recovery and limit of detection. Blank samples and spiked recoveries were included in the workflow to monitor potential contamination and assess method recovery efficiency. Internal standards were also employed to track instrumental consistency and correct for potential signal drift during analysis. Herewith, the elements such as<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>Li (low mass)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref></sup>, Y (medium mass), and <sup>205</sup>Tl (high mass) were used, providing optimal signal intensities across the mass range during the ICP-MS analysis. Calibration was performed using multi-element standard solutions, with calibration curves achieving high correlation coefficients (R² &gt; 0.99) throughout the analytical process, ensuring robust and reliable quantification of potentially toxic elements. The results demonstrated satisfactory analytical performance across all evaluated parameters. Recoveries for the quantified PTEs ranged from 96.34% (As) to 100.50% (Cu), reflecting high analytical accuracy and method reliability. The relative bias remained within ± 5% for all elements, indicating minimal systematic error. Moreover, the method exhibited excellent sensitivity, as evidenced by the low limits of detection (LOD) and limits of quantification (LOQ) across all analytes. The calculated uncertainties were within acceptable ranges, and precision was confirmed by low %RSD values (&lt; 2%), demonstrating robust repeatability. Collectively, these results confirm that the applied method is sufficiently accurate, precise, and sensitive for the determination of PTEs in complex environmental matrices such as street dust. Hence, the validation results presented in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> confirm that the analytical procedure is precise and accurate, ensuring the reliability and robustness of the measurements.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Meteorological and air quality data</title><p id="Par20">Meteorological and air pollutant data in Istanbul during the study period (10–20 February 2024) were obtained from the Turkish State Meteorological Service (TSMS) and the National Air Quality Monitoring Network (NAQMN)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. During this period, temperatures ranged from 6 °C to 10 °C, with wind speeds of 4–6 m/s predominantly from the north-northeast, and no precipitation was recorded. These stable conditions likely contributed to the persistence of street dust and reduced variability in pollutant deposition.</p><p id="Par21">As detailed in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>, the air quality categories defined by the USEPA Air Quality Index Scale<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and WHO Air Quality Guidelines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> are presented. The AQI is a standardized measure used to evaluate the concentration of key air pollutants and their potential impact on human health. The AQI is calculated using the formula (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>) established by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e514"><?equation-image-name d33e514.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 f402007dc1a032b4484c7f6eb1605de0?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/f402007dc1a0/d33e514.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:AQIp=\:\frac{(IH-IL)}{(CH-CL)}\:X\:\left(C-CL\right)+IL$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ1.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ1.gif?><?image-size 1719?><?image-md5 b5a3be1fd869aeabff0b2e974fb1e497?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 29?><?image-scaled-width 200?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/b5a3be1fd869/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ1.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ1.gif?><?thumb-size 1719?><?thumb-md5 b5a3be1fd869aeabff0b2e974fb1e497?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 29?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/b5a3be1fd869/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ1.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par22">where AQI<sub>p</sub> represents the computed AQI for a specific pollutant, C is the measured pollutant concentration (in µg/m³), C<sub>L</sub> and C<sub>H</sub> are the lower and upper concentration breakpoints respectively, and I<sub>L</sub> and I<sub>H</sub> are the corresponding AQI values.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Ecological indices employed for street dust</title><p id="Par23">In this research, certain ecological indices (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub>, CF, EF, E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup>, PLI, PERI, and NPI) were applied to assess contamination levels, pollution sources, and ecological risks linked with PTEs in urban street dust. The indices were calculated based on the concentrations of selected metals, including Pb, Cd, Zn, Cu, Ni, Cr, and As, using standardized formulas provided in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>.</p><p id="Par24">The <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub> was employed to assess the extent of metal enrichment relative to background values by comparing current metal concentrations to pre-industrial reference levels. It classifies contamination into different categories, ranging from uncontaminated to extremely contaminated, helping to determine the severity of metal accumulation. The CF and EF were applied to distinguish anthropogenic influences from natural sources. CF is computed as the ratio of the measured metal concentration to its background value, providing insights into the degree of contamination, while EF normalizes metal concentrations against a reference element (such as Al or Fe) to assess the extent of enrichment due to human activities. The E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup> was conducted to estimate the potential risks posed by individual elements as it quantifies the potential ecological hazard by incorporating metal toxicity factors, offering a risk classification ranging from low to very high ecological risk<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">To assess overall contamination and ecological risks, the PLI, PERI, E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup>, and NPI were computed. PLI provides an integrated assessment of pollution across multiple elements, indicating whether an area is polluted or unpolluted. PERI is a comprehensive index that aggregates individual E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup> values to predict the overall ecological risk of heavy metals in a given environment. NPI standardizes contamination levels across different elements to facilitate comparison<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Health risk assessment</title><p id="Par26">The health risk assessment followed the guidelines of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> and previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. The assessment estimated non-carcinogenic risks using the hazard quotient (HQ) and hazard index (HI) and evaluated total cancer risk (TCR) for carcinogenic elements. Separate assessments were conducted for children and adults based on age-specific exposure factors. The hazard index (HI) was calculated by summing the HQ values across all metals. The hazard index (HI), which represents the cumulative non-carcinogenic risk for a given metal across all exposure pathways, was calculated using the formulas (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>–<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>):<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e592"><?equation-image-name d33e592.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 84c83d6ca6c355f91006f5fa2f2d51eb?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/84c83d6ca6c3/d33e592.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:HQ=\frac{ADD}{RfD}\:$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ2.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ2.gif?><?image-size 1498?><?image-md5 498c882b7f3f3959c896a3602dba6f8f?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 80?><?image-scaled-width 194?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/498c882b7f3f/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ2.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ2.gif?><?thumb-size 1498?><?thumb-md5 498c882b7f3f3959c896a3602dba6f8f?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 194?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/498c882b7f3f/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ2.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e598"><?equation-image-name d33e598.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 fddf57604ef6cf8526b5f452dd106301?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/fddf57604ef6/d33e598.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:HI=\sum\:\:HQ\:\frac{{ADD}_{inh}}{{RfD}_{inh}}+\frac{{ADD}_{ing}}{{RfD}_{ing}}+\frac{{ADD}_{derm}}{{RfD}_{derm}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ3.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ3.gif?><?image-size 1920?><?image-md5 cfa1de5d94349247176e1fdade7a5f77?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 25?><?image-scaled-width 200?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/cfa1de5d9434/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ3.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ3.gif?><?thumb-size 1920?><?thumb-md5 cfa1de5d94349247176e1fdade7a5f77?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 25?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/cfa1de5d9434/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ3.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e605"><?equation-image-name d33e605.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 26fbd2caab73b66fe53a474b26ccc7b1?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/26fbd2caab73/d33e605.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:THI=\sum\:\:HI$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ4.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ4.gif?><?image-size 523?><?image-md5 c09d095e00c427cb500da7dc002fd17a?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 29?><?image-scaled-width 121?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/c09d095e00c4/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ4.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ4.gif?><?thumb-size 523?><?thumb-md5 c09d095e00c427cb500da7dc002fd17a?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 29?><?thumb-scaled-width 121?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/c09d095e00c4/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ4.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par27">where ADD is the average daily dose (mg/kg-day) and RfD is the reference dose (mg/kg-day). The following formulas (<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref>, <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref>) were used to calculate ADD<sub>ingestion</sub>, ADD<sub>inhalation</sub>, and ADD<sub>dermal</sub>.<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e626"><?equation-image-name d33e626.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 147036495f8e509a5be55ade16d82d32?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/147036495f8e/d33e626.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{ADD}_{ingestion}=\frac{MC\:x\:{IR}_{ingestion}\:x\:EF\:x\:ED\:}{BW\:x\:AT}\:x\:CF$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ5.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ5.gif?><?image-size 1594?><?image-md5 6c12000600a75bd098789dfd61105a3b?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 20?><?image-scaled-width 200?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/6c12000600a7/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ5.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ5.gif?><?thumb-size 1594?><?thumb-md5 6c12000600a75bd098789dfd61105a3b?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 20?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/6c12000600a7/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ5.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par28">where C represents the metal concentration in dust (mg/kg), IR<sub>ing</sub> is the dust ingestion rate (200 mg/day for children and 100 mg/day for adults), EF is the exposure frequency (350 days/year), ED is the exposure duration (6 years for children and 24 years for adults), BW is the body weight (15 kg for children and 70 kg for adults), and AT is the average time for non-cancer risk (2190 days for children and 8760 days for adults). For inhalation exposure, the ADD was calculated using the formula (<xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref>) below:<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e639"><?equation-image-name d33e639.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 b60be91344112ee73fd2f2c4b7084159?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/b60be9134411/d33e639.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{ADD}_{inhalation}=\frac{MC\:x\:{IR}_{inhalation}\:x\:EF\:x\:ED}{BW\:x\:AT\:x\:PEF}\:$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ6.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ6.gif?><?image-size 1805?><?image-md5 969d1dce4af3b39b98c45e4b89c611fe?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 22?><?image-scaled-width 200?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/969d1dce4af3/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ6.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ6.gif?><?thumb-size 1805?><?thumb-md5 969d1dce4af3b39b98c45e4b89c611fe?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 22?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/969d1dce4af3/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ6.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par29">where IR<sub>inh</sub> is the dust inhalation rate (7.6 m³/day for children and 20 m³/day for adults), and PEF is the particle emission factor (1.36 × 10⁹ m³/kg). For dermal contact, the ADD was determined using formula (<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>) below:<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e652"><?equation-image-name d33e652.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 30710d53f7f9e57ff5b2da4c8810660b?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/30710d53f7f9/d33e652.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{ADD}_{dermal}=\frac{MC\:x\:SA\:x\:ABS\:x\:EF\:x\:ED\:x\:AF\:}{BW\:x\:AT}\:x\:CF$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ7.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ7.gif?><?image-size 1057?><?image-md5 eb62d20578682d71813e802a5003fbbf?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 18?><?image-scaled-width 200?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/eb62d2057868/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ7.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ7.gif?><?thumb-size 1057?><?thumb-md5 eb62d20578682d71813e802a5003fbbf?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 18?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/eb62d2057868/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ7.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par30">where SA is the exposed skin area (2800 cm² for children and 5700 cm² for adults), AF is the skin adherence factor (0.2 mg/cm²-day for children and 0.07 mg/cm²-day for adults), and ABS is the dermal absorption factor (0.001, unitless).</p><p id="Par31">Carcinogenic risk was assessed using the cancer risk (CR) formula (<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="disp-formula">8</xref>):<disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e665"><?equation-image-name d33e665.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 1e76acc754a6e6102d78451c91fec46f?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/1e76acc754a6/d33e665.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:CR=\sum\:\:CR={ADD}_{inh}\:x\:{SF}_{inh}+{ADD}_{ing}\:x\:{SF}_{ing}+{ADD}_{derm}\:x\:{SF}_{derm}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ8.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ8.gif?><?image-size 800?><?image-md5 704ef01bbb036b90cff3ca511445ec63?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 11?><?image-scaled-width 200?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/704ef01bbb03/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ8.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ8.gif?><?thumb-size 800?><?thumb-md5 704ef01bbb036b90cff3ca511445ec63?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 11?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/704ef01bbb03/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ8.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par32">where CSF is the cancer slope factor (kg-day/mg). The total cancer risk (TCR) was calculated by summing the cancer risks from ingestion, inhalation, and dermal contact:<disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e673"><?equation-image-name d33e673.gif?><?equation-image-status READY?><?equation-image-md5 04278f3e71afcdf82b2e15a6f1abd1a9?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/04278f3e71af/d33e673.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:TCR=\sum\:\:CR$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ9.gif"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ9.gif?><?image-size 580?><?image-md5 ced3ae26d0180f3222f9e1573a3289ee?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-scaled-height 29?><?image-scaled-width 126?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/ced3ae26d018/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ9.gif?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ9.gif?><?thumb-size 580?><?thumb-md5 ced3ae26d0180f3222f9e1573a3289ee?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 29?><?thumb-scaled-width 126?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/ced3ae26d018/41598_2025_11472_Article_Equ9.gif?></graphic></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par33">The average time for cancer risk assessment (AT<sub>cancer</sub>) was set at 25,550 days for both children and adults<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. The exposure parameters and their probability distributions are provided in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>, while Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref> presents the reference dose (RfD) and cancer slope factors (CSF) used in the assessment. The metal concentrations were assumed to follow a lognormal distribution, while exposure factors followed triangular, uniform, normal, and beta-PERT distributions. This methodology provides a comprehensive risk evaluation, allowing for the assessment of potential health hazards due to heavy metal exposure in urban dust.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Source identification and statistical analysis</title><p id="Par34">To analyze the relationships among PTEs in street dust collected from Istanbul, Türkiye, statistical evaluations were performed using OriginPro 2022 and SPSS<sup>®</sup> version 27. Pearson correlation coefficients PCC helped determine the strength of pairwise associations between elements, while HCA was applied to group elements exhibiting similar behaviors or origins. Additionally, PCA was utilized to identify key influencing factors and distinguish possible contamination sources. To further investigate the origins of PTEs in street dust, PMF analysis was employed using the US EPA PMF 5.0 software. The analysis was based on elemental concentration data, and the extracted factor profiles provided insights into contamination sources across the study area. In addition, a Monte Carlo Simulation (MCS) was carried out using Crystal Ball software (Oracle, USA) to estimate the potential health risks linked with human exposure to PTEs in street dust. Model performance and reliability were validated through diagnostic tools integrated within the software, applying a 95% confidence interval and 10,000 iterations. The health risks linked to PTEs exposure via ingestion, inhalation, and dermal routes of administration were assessed using a Monte Carlo Simulation conducted with Crystal Ball software (Oracle, USA). A comprehensive overview of the distribution settings values and input parameters used in the MCS-based health risk assessment is presented in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>PTE concentrations</title><p id="Par35">This study investigated the levels of PTEs in urban street dust samples collected from 29 locations across Istanbul, providing insights into their spatial distribution and potential environmental and health risks (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). The descriptive statistics for the analyzed elements are summarized in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>. The elemental concentrations (mg/kg) were quantified in the following increasing order: Cd (0.9) &lt; Co (10.9) &lt; As (11.8) &lt; Ni (63.1) &lt; Pb (67.8) &lt; Cr (135.1) &lt; Cu (333.3) &lt; Mn (459.2) &lt; Zn (477.2) &lt; Fe (27,252) &lt; Al (29,916).</p><p id="Par36">In this study, the mean concentrations of Al and Fe were the highest among all elements, reflecting their natural abundance in the Earth’s crust. These elements exhibited relatively low variability, suggesting a dominant geogenic origin influenced by local soil composition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. In contrast, elements such as Cr, Cu, Zn, and Pb displayed considerable variability, indicating mixed sources likely from anthropogenic activities, including industrial emissions, vehicular wear, and urban pollution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Similarly, Co and Ni exhibited localized concentration elevations, indicating potential industrial contributions, particularly from activities such as metal processing, electroplating, and combustion-related emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. The presence of As and Cd at moderate levels necessitates further investigation due to their toxicological significance.</p><p id="Par37">The spatial distribution maps of PTEs across Istanbul reveal significant heterogeneity, reflecting diverse pollution sources and environmental influences (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Al and Fe exhibit relatively uniform distributions, with slightly higher concentrations in northern and central areas, consistent with their geogenic origin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Elevated concentrations of Ni and Cr were observed in the northern European side of the study region and along major transportation corridors, indicating contributions from industrial activities and vehicular sources. Existing literature supports the finding that vehicular traffic is a significant source of these metals in urban environments. A study in Toronto found that Ni levels were higher in sweepings from major roads than in urban soils, indicating a vehicular emission source. Additionally, Cr and Ni concentrations increased with road hierarchy, peaking on high-traffic routes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Manganese exhibited a more dispersed spatial distribution, suggesting the influence of both natural soil composition and anthropogenic contributions. Mn is naturally abundant in the Earth’s crust, yet its dispersed distribution in the study area suggests mixed geogenic and anthropogenic origins. Industrial emissions, vehicular traffic, and Mn-based fuel additives contribute to elevated levels in urban environments, particularly through steel manufacturing and atmospheric deposition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Co displayed localized hotspots on the European side, potentially indicating site-specific industrial activities or areas affected by historical contamination sources, such as past metallurgical operations or waste disposal practices<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Cu and Zn exhibited elevated concentrations in the central and northern urban areas, closely associated with traffic-related emissions, including brake and tire wear, as well as urban runoff. These patterns are consistent with their widespread use in automotive components and their known mobility in urban environments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. As and Cd exhibited moderate concentrations with localized peaks, indicating the presence of point sources, potentially related to industrial discharges, waste disposal sites, or legacy contamination from metallurgical activities and urban landfills<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. Pb distribution reveals pronounced hotspots in densely populated urban areas, indicating the impact of historical pollution from formerly used leaded gasoline, along with ongoing contributions from industrial emissions and lead-containing construction materials. These legacy sources have resulted in long-term accumulation of lead in urban soils despite regulatory phase-outs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Hg exhibited significant spatial variability, with localized hotspots likely associated with industrial sources, such as combustion processes, waste incineration, or historical contamination. These patterns stress the importance of implementing targeted pollution management strategies to mitigate mercury-related environmental and health risks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par38">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Spatial distribution maps of PTEs across sampling stations in Istanbul, Türkiye.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e777" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 239700?><?image-md5 f077827ef274d3a50d0d66e6b725f1b4?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2363?><?image-original-width 1798?><?image-scaled-height 945?><?image-scaled-width 719?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/f077827ef274/41598_2025_11472_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 7521?><?thumb-md5 37784754a3e5658dcb1207c95191682b?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 131?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/37784754a3e5/41598_2025_11472_Fig2_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par39">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of the results obtained in this study with previously reported values in the global literature.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Location</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">As</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cd</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cr</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mn</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fe</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Co</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ni</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pb</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zn</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Istanbul, Türkiye</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">135.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">333.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">459.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27,252</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">477.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Abbottabad, Pakistan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">304</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15,540</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ankara, Türkiye</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jiaozuo, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">373.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">374.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Khulna City, Bangladesh</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">386</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25,648</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Xiangtan, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">549.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">536.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moscow, Russia</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">380</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">945</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46,506</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1389</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhengzhou, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">515</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Czeck Republic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">914</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36,692</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1023</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ilam, Iran</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">213</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kermanshah, Iran</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">181</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Taiwan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">304.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20,586</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">500.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recife, Brazil</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">315.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Al-Hillah, Iraq</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">480</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25,600</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lublin, Poland</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">120.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">296.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Monterrey, Mexico</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">653.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chhattisgarh, India</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">833.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">152.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">571.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">231.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">236.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jinan, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">517.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">492.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Warsaw, Poland</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">184.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">149.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Jiaozuo, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">473.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">374.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Izmir, Türkiye</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13,303</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Spain</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">173.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">109.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">258.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kerman, Iran</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">71.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">417.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.57</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">-</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">170.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par40">As can be evidenced in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, the content of PTEs in Istanbul’s street dust are generally moderate and comparable to those reported in other global urban areas. However, certain elements, particularly Cu (333.3 mg/kg), Zn (477.2 mg/kg), and Cr (135.1 mg/kg), exhibited elevated concentrations, suggesting the influence of anthropogenic activities such as traffic emissions and industrial processes. Copper and zinc, which are strongly associated with vehicular brake and tire wear, showed notably higher concentrations in Istanbul compared to cities like Abbottabad (Cu: 50.0, Zn: 139.0 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> and Ankara (Cu: 35.7, Zn: 0.9 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Istanbul’s Cu level is comparable to Moscow (380.0 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> and exceeded values reported in highly urbanized regions such as Jiaozuo, China (Cu: 49.9 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. The Zn concentration in Istanbul is also comparable to Taiwan (500.4 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> and Jinan (492.8 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>, indicating a significant contribution from traffic-related sources. Chromium concentrations in Istanbul were relatively high (135.1 mg/kg), aligning closely with levels in Jiaozuo (112.1 mg/kg) and Xiangtan (115.6 mg/kg), but lower than those reported in Kermanshah (181 mg/kg)<sup>3</sup> and Chhattisgarh (833 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>, where heavy industrial activity is prevalent. The elevated Cr levels may be attributed to metal alloy wear, industrial discharges, or construction-related activities. Lead (Pb: 67.8 mg/kg) showed moderate enrichment, consistent with findings from Al-Hillah (64.6 mg/kg)<sup>2</sup> and higher than those in Warsaw (17.1 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>, suggesting residual contamination from historical leaded fuel use and urban infrastructure. Nickel levels (63.1 mg/kg) in Istanbul also suggest mixed geogenic and anthropogenic origins, with values similar to those in Taiwan (64.1 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> and slightly lower than in Al-Hillah (75.4 mg/kg)<sup>2</sup>, yet elevated compared to Ankara (25.9 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> and Abbottabad (10.3 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. This distribution pattern implies possible influence from fossil fuel combustion, industrial sources, and soil background. Cadmium (0.9 mg/kg) and arsenic (11.8 mg/kg) concentrations were within ranges reported globally, with Cd comparable to levels found in Jiaozuo (1.3 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> and Xiangtan (0.4 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, and As matching those reported in Al-Hillah (11.8 mg/kg)<sup>2</sup> and Kerman (11.0 mg/kg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>. These findings indicate localized enrichment, possibly from point sources such as waste disposal or industrial emissions.</p><p id="Par41">Collectively, the elemental profiles observed in Istanbul’s street dust indicate a multifactorial origin, shaped by a combination of traffic-related emissions, industrial activities, residual historical contamination, and natural geochemical background levels. The spatial distribution and elevated concentrations of key elements, particularly Cu, Zn, and Cr, highlight the necessity for sustained environmental monitoring, as their levels frequently exceeded or closely approached the upper ranges reported in comparable urban environments worldwide. In comparison with other metropolitan areas, Istanbul exhibits a distinctly heterogeneous pattern of PTE distribution, reflecting the concurrent influence of both geogenic and anthropogenic sources.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Air quality</title><p id="Par42">Air pollution is a significant environmental concern affecting public health, ecosystems, and urban sustainability. Monitoring key air pollutants provides crucial insights into their concentration levels, sources, and potential impacts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>. This study evaluates the air quality in Istanbul during February 2024, using key atmospheric pollutants: NO, NO₂, NOx, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, and SO₂. Descriptive statistics due to these parameters are provided in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par43">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics of air quality parameters in istanbul, Türkiye.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Min</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Std Dev</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">263.30</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.61</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.21</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.50</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">204.80</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.89</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.49</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO<sub>X</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.88</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">934.61</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.01</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.81</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM <sub>2.5</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64.00</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.61</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.61</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">176.91</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.28</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.19</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.62</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.91</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.49</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are provided in µg/m<sup>3</sup>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par44">The interpretation of the air quality data for February 2024 in Istanbul reveals notable trends among the invesitigated pollutants. Nitrogen oxides (NO, NO₂, NOx) exhibited significant variability, with NOx reaching a maximum concentration of 934.61 µg/m³ and a mean of 83.81 µg/m³, suggesting substantial contributions from traffic emissions and industrial activities. The high standard deviation further indicates fluctuations due to varying traffic density and meteorological influences. Particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub>) levels remained relatively moderate, with PM<sub>2.5</sub> showing a low mean concentration of 9.61 µg/m³, while PM<sub>10</sub> displayed greater variability, peaking at 176.91 µg/m<sup>3</sup>, likely due to localized dust resuspension and construction activities. SO<sub>2</sub> concentrations remained low, with a mean of 3.49 µg/m<sup>3</sup>, suggesting minimal influence from coal combustion or heavy industrial sources. These findings indicate that while air quality was generally within acceptable limits, elevated NOx levels may pose a concern for respiratory health and ozone formation, particularly in high-traffic areas. Additionally, occasional PM<sub>10</sub> peaks warrant further investigation to mitigate exposure risks, especially for vulnerable populations. Overall, targeted measures, including improved traffic emission controls and dust management strategies, could further enhance Istanbul’s air quality.</p><p id="Par45">As evidenced in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, the overall AQI value calculated for Istanbul is 40, which falls under the “Good” (0–50) category according to the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and World Health Organization guidelines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. This suggests that the air quality is satisfactory and that air pollution poses minimal or no risk to the general population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. Among the individual pollutants, PM₂.₅ (AQI = 40) was identified as the primary contributing pollutant, which aligns with global concerns over fine particulate matter as a major air quality indicator. Despite being within the “Good” category, PM<sub>2.5</sub> should be continuously monitored due to its long-term health effects. PM<sub>10</sub> (AQI = 22) remains well below hazardous levels, indicating that coarse particulate pollution is not a significant issue in this assessment. NO<sub>2</sub> (AQI = 35), primarily from traffic emissions, is also within the acceptable range<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> implying that vehicular pollution is not currently at dangerous levels. SO<sub>2</sub> (AQI = 5) is extremely low, suggesting minimal industrial or fossil fuel-related emissions affecting the air quality.</p><p id="Par46">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>AQI results with USEPA Thresholds.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pollutant</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Measured AQI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">USEPA Category</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EPA description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Air quality is deemed acceptable, with pollutant levels posing minimal or no health risk<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub></td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall AQI</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par47">Although air quality data were obtained from 10 different monitoring stations of the NAQMN, most of which are located near the street dust sampling points, no direct air sampling was conducted at the same locations. Nevertheless, the AQI values, particularly those associated with PM<sub>10</sub> and PM<sub>2.5</sub>, provide context for atmospheric conditions that may influence the deposition of PTEs in street dust. The moderate levels of PM<sub>10</sub>, with occasional peaks, suggest that particulate matter from traffic and industrial sources could contribute to PTE accumulation in dust through atmospheric deposition. This potential relationship highlights the interaction between air quality and urban dust contamination, warranting further integrated investigations. These findings indicate that Istanbul’s air quality in the study period was safe, with PM<sub>2.5</sub> as the most notable pollutant. Given its potential impact on human health, efforts to reduce emissions from combustion sources (e.g., vehicle regulations, industrial emission controls) should continue to ensure sustained air quality improvements. Moreover, long-term exposure assessments should be conducted to determine seasonal and spatial variations in pollution levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par48">It should be noted that AQI data in this study was used solely as a complementary aid to contextualize ambient air conditions during the dust sampling period. Due to the spatial separation between monitoring stations and dust sampling sites, direct correlation analysis or spatial co-mapping was not feasible. However, a general consistency was observed between higher PM₁₀ levels and traffic-heavy zones with elevated dust concentrations of Cu, Zn, and Pb, suggesting a potential link through common emission sources. The interpretation of air quality and inhalation-related exposure risks in this study is informed by both WHO (2021)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> and USEPA (2016)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> thresholds, as summarized in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Ecological investigation</title><p id="Par49">Ecological health was evaluated employing a comprehensive set of indices, including <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub>, CF, EF, E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup>, PLI, PERI, and NPI.</p><p id="Par50">The geo-accumulation index is a widely used tool to evaluate the contamination levels of PTEs in environmental samples, such as street dust and sediments. It compares current concentrations to pre-industrial baseline values, accounting for natural variations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. In this study, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub> analysis revealed significant spatial variability of PTEs across 29 sampling sites in Istanbul. Cu exhibited the highest contamination levels, particularly at sites S15 and S19, indicating moderate to heavy pollution likely originating from anthropogenic sources, including traffic-related activities and industrial runoff. Zn and Pb also exhibited moderate contamination, reflecting urban influences. Conversely, Al, Fe, Mn, and Cr consistently showed low <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub> values, suggesting natural background levels. As evidenced in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, The violin plots further highlighted site-specific variability, with wider distributions in S15 and S19 indicating localized contamination events, while narrower distributions in S3, S4, and S26 suggested more uniform contamination patterns.</p><p id="Par51">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Heatmap and violin plot illustrating the spatial distribution of <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub> across sampling stations.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1973" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 174428?><?image-md5 87641bfa7d641627b26f3f4dc0283c6c?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1653?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 551?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/87641bfa7d64/41598_2025_11472_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 6550?><?thumb-md5 c8ae38e576774aaee604f832a382352a?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 82?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/c8ae38e57677/41598_2025_11472_Fig3_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par52">The CF is used to evaluate the extent of contamination by comparing the concentration of PTEs in environmental samples to background values<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Herewith, CF analysis revealed significant spatial variability in street dust across 29 sampling sites in Istanbul. Zn showed the highest CF values, particularly at sites S14 and S19, indicating considerable to very high contamination, likely originating from human activities such as vehicular traffic and industrial emissions. In contrast, Pb, Cd, As, Cu, Ni, Co, Fe, Mn, Cr, and Al exhibited consistently low CF values, suggesting natural background levels with minimal anthropogenic influence. As illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, The violin plots further illustrated site-specific variability, with wider distributions at S14 and S19 indicating localized contamination events, while narrower distributions at S3, S4, S26, and S29 suggested more uniform contamination patterns.</p><p id="Par53">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Heatmap and violin plot illustrating the spatial distribution of CF across sampling stations.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1992" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 153949?><?image-md5 67038b34f64e1bbeae5f5d0effc09669?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1656?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 552?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/67038b34f64e/41598_2025_11472_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 5413?><?thumb-md5 49b1fefe0c75ee629fa83e4363786d11?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 82?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/49b1fefe0c75/41598_2025_11472_Fig4_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par54">The enrichment factor is applied to evaluate the degree of anthropogenic influence on PTEs by normalizing the concentration of each element against a reference element, typically Al or Fe. EF values are categorized as minimal enrichment (EF &lt; 2), moderate enrichment (2 ≤ EF &lt; 5), significant enrichment (5 ≤ EF &lt; 20), very high enrichment (20 ≤ EF &lt; 40), and extremely high enrichment (EF ≥ 40)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>. In this study, EF analysis revealed that Zn exhibited the highest enrichment, particularly at sites S22, S24, and S26, indicating significant to very high enrichment levels likely due to anthropogenic sources such as vehicular traffic and industrial runoff. In contrast, Pb, Cd, As, Cu, Ni, Co, Fe, Mn, Cr, and Al showed minimal enrichment, suggesting natural background levels with negligible anthropogenic influence. As can be seen in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, The violin plots illustrated site-specific variability, with wider distributions at S22, S24, and S26 indicating localized contamination events, whereas narrower distributions at other sites suggested more uniform patterns.</p><p id="Par55">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Heatmap and violin plot illustrating the spatial distribution of EF across sampling stations.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2011" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 152488?><?image-md5 8929b8a574b89d0c1ca3e5a770bb115a?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1605?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 535?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/8929b8a574b8/41598_2025_11472_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 4937?><?thumb-md5 7a1522f6634e864caddd6f70e4280ae3?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/7a1522f6634e/41598_2025_11472_Fig5_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par56">The ecological risk index (E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup>) is used to assess the potential ecological risks posed by PTEs by integrating contamination levels with toxic response factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>. In this study, E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup> values for Cr, Mn, Ni, Cu, Zn, As, Cd, and Pb were evaluated across 29 sampling sites in Istanbul (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The results revealed that Cd consistently exhibited the highest E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup> values across all sites, particularly at S25, S22, and S16, indicating considerable to high ecological risks likely due to industrial and vehicular emissions. Cu also showed elevated E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup> values, particularly at sites S22 and S23, reflecting localized contamination likely linked to urban activities. In contrast, Mn, Zn, Cr, and Ni displayed relatively lower E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup> values, suggesting minimal ecological risks.</p><p id="Par57">Thus, the findings derived from <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub>, CF, EF, and E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup> indicate dominant influence of anthropogenic emissions to Zn and Cd contamination, emphasizing the need for targeted pollution control in high-enrichment urban hotspots to mitigate associated ecological and health risks.</p><p id="Par58">In addition, the PLI, PERI, NPI, and NRI are comprehensive indices used to evaluate the environmental pollution status and ecological risks of PTEs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>. In this study, spatial distribution maps of these indices were generated for the study area in Istanbul (Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The results indicate that the western region exhibits higher pollution and ecological risks, particularly around industrial and urban areas. High PLI and NPI values suggest significant pollution loads, mainly due to human activities known as vehicular traffic and industrial emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par59">
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Heatmap and violin plot illustrating the spatial distribution of E<sub>r</sub><sup>i</sup> across sampling stations.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2073" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig6_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig6_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 143275?><?image-md5 54ccc5b92809bd854aa297143c4f1105?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1674?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 558?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/54ccc5b92809/41598_2025_11472_Fig6_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig6_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 4972?><?thumb-md5 4d81acab1c197ac7a0fab9f14f9dd81c?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 83?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/4d81acab1c19/41598_2025_11472_Fig6_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par60">The elevated PERI values in these areas highlight potential ecological risks, emphasizing the need for targeted pollution management strategies. Conversely, the eastern region shows relatively lower pollution levels, reflecting a more natural background state. These findings provide crucial insights into spatial pollution patterns and can guide environmental protection and management policies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Source identification</title><p id="Par61">The identification of sources contributing to the contamination of street dust in Istanbul was performed using PMF, PCA, PCC, polar HCA. These methods collectively provide insights into the possible sources of PTEs, allowing for a more comprehensive understanding of the major contributors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par62">The performance of the PMF model was evaluated using standard diagnostic tools, including the Q-robust (15,328.2) and Q-true (15,742.5) statistics, as well as the distribution of residuals, which were symmetrically centered around zero for most metals, indicating acceptable model fit. The total R² between observed and predicted concentrations exceeded 0.85 for key elements such as Cu, Zn, Pb, and Cr, supporting the validity of the extracted factor profiles. As can be seen in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a, The PMF model identified three major sources contributing to PTE contamination in street dust: industrial runoff (39.4%), traffic emissions (31.3%), and natural and soil sources (29.4%). As can be seen in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b, the source profiles derived from PMF indicate that traffic emissions are characterized by high loadings of Cu (76.8%), Zn (62.6%), and Pb (58.2%), which are typically associated with vehicular sources such as brake and tire wear, engine wear, and fossil fuel combustion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup>. Industrial runoff shows a significant contribution from Cr (81.7%), Ni (84.3%), and Co (41.4%), suggesting emissions from industrial activities, particularly metal processing, electroplating, and manufacturing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup>. In addition, percent contribution of each metal is illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c. As a result, natural and soil sources are dominated by Fe (44.5%), Al (54.7%), Mn (46.4%), and As (47.0%), indicating contributions from geological background sources and soil resuspension<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>. These findings suggest that while industrial activities remain a significant contributor to PTE contamination, vehicular emissions also play a substantial role in metal accumulation in street dust. As shown in Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>, The rotated component matrix from PCA provides further insights into the association of PTEs with potential sources. PC1, explaining 52.4% of the total variance, shows strong loadings of Cr (0.959), Ni (0.956), Co (0.732), and As (0.726), confirming an industrial origin, particularly from metal-processing industries. PC2, accounting for 18.1% of the variance, has high correlations for Cu (0.904), Zn (0.903), and Pb (0.890), indicating vehicular emissions as the dominant contributor. PC3, explaining 10.5% of the variance, includes Mn (0.829), Al (0.683), and Fe (0.593), suggesting contributions from natural sources such as soil and rock weathering<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref></sup>. The correlation heatmap highlights significant relationships between specific PTEs, further confirming the source identification. Strong correlations between Cr, Ni, and Co (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> &gt; 0.9, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) suggest a common industrial source<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref></sup> while high positive correlations between Zn, Cu, and Pb (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> &gt; 0.8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) reinforce their association with traffic-related emissions. Fe, Al, and Mn show moderate correlations, supporting their natural geogenic origin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par63">
<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Graphical demonstration of PMF results (<bold>a</bold>), percent of contribution of factors (<bold>b</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2152" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig7_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig7_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 80743?><?image-md5 8b06c6f8885d346985e01ed8369bc517?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1270?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 423?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/8b06c6f8885d/41598_2025_11472_Fig7_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig7_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 4541?><?thumb-md5 f219fd59ecd04d52751a22510f647bb3?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 126?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/f219fd59ecd0/41598_2025_11472_Fig7_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par64">Cluster analysis further validates the identified sources by grouping similar elements together. The results indicate that Cr, Ni, and Co are primarily associated with industrial emissions, Zn, Cu, and Pb are closely linked to vehicular emissions, and Al, Mn, Fe, and As are indicative of natural soil-derived sources (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). The dominance of industrial runoff as the primary contributor to PTE contamination suggests the need for stricter environmental regulations targeting industrial waste management<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref></sup>. The substantial influence of traffic emissions stresses the necessity for improved urban air quality measures, such as promoting public transportation and cleaner vehicle technologies. Additionally, the contribution of natural sources highlights the importance of controlling dust resuspension through urban greening initiatives<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref></sup>. The integrated approach utilizing PMF, PCA, PCC, and cluster analysis has provided a comprehensive understanding of the sources of PTEs in Istanbul’s street dust. The findings emphasize the need for targeted mitigation strategies addressing industrial, vehicular, and natural contributions to urban metal contamination.</p><p id="Par65">
<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Graphical demonstration of PCC (<bold>a</bold>), and polar heatmap HCA (<bold>b</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2182" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig8_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig8_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 173799?><?image-md5 99364cbb9c7f77d7116eea4e0b37607d?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2125?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 708?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/99364cbb9c7f/41598_2025_11472_Fig8_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig8_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 6632?><?thumb-md5 2b049bf615374581b1d88c081d923c44?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 106?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/2b049bf61537/41598_2025_11472_Fig8_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par66">Additionaly, the spatial variability of air quality parameters, especially PM₁₀, aligns with regions showing higher concentrations of traffic-related metals such as Cu, Zn, and Pb. The proximity of air quality monitoring stations to dust sampling sites and the moderate AQI levels observed suggest that airborne particulates may play a supplementary role in the deposition of these elements. Although the overall AQI was classified as ‘Good’, particulate matter remains a critical vector for metal transport. Previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> have shown that road transport significantly contributes to particulate matter and NO₂ emissions in urban environments, further supporting the notion that vehicular activities influence both air quality and metal accumulation in street dust.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Health risk assessment</title><p id="Par67">The noncarcinogenic health risks linked with exposure to PTEs in street dust were evaluated using HQ and the HI. HQ values were computed for ingestion, dermal contact, and inhalation pathways, with the HI representing the sum of these exposures for each element<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref></sup>. The results indicate that for adults, the THI is 0.345, which remains below the acceptable risk threshold of 1.0, suggesting that noncarcinogenic risks are not significant for this group. However, for children, the THI is 3.13, exceeding the acceptable limit, indicating potential adverse health effects due to exposure to street dust (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par68">Among the analyzed elements, Pb presents the highest noncarcinogenic risk for children, with an HI value of 0.618, followed by As (0.551) and Cr (0.635). These elements are known to cause neurological, developmental, and systemic health effects, particularly in children, who are more vulnerable due to higher ingestion rates and lower body weight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. For adults, Pb and As also show the highest HI values at 0.0665 and 0.0612, respectively, but remain below the risk threshold. The elevated HQ<sub>ing</sub> values for Pb, Cr, and As indicate that ingestion is the primary exposure route contributing to health risks, which is consistent with previous studies highlighting the ingestion of contaminated dust as a major pathway for metal exposure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Nickel, zinc, and cadmium exhibit the lowest HI values for both age groups, suggesting minimal noncarcinogenic risks from these elements. However, manganese, cobalt, and aluminum contribute moderately to the total HI, particularly in children.</p><p id="Par69">
<table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Estimated non-carcinogenic risk values for adults and children based on exposure ptes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Noncarcinogenic risks for adult</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Noncarcinogenic risks for child</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HQ <sub>ing</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HQ<sub>derm</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HQ <sub>inh</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HQ <sub>ing</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HQ<sub>derm</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HQ <sub>inh</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Al</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.09E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.16E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.29E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.82E-01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.35E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.13E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.89E-01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cr</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.11E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.76E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.70E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.12E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.71E-01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.39E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.78E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.35E-01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mn</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.63E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.62E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.86E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.08E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.45E-01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.29E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.66E-01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Co</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.00E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.98E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.68E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.14E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.67E-01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.54E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.52E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.74E-01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ni</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.28E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.27E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.40E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.85E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.80E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.48E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.30E-02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cu</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.13E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.25E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.65E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.15E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05E-01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.47E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.92E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07E-01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zn</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.16E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.30E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.17E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.20E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.01E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.82E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.62E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.04E-02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">As</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.42E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.83E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.12E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.06E-01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.48E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.83E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.51E-01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cd</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.55E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.04E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.88E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.77E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.33E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.33E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.52E-02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pb</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.57E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.73E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.86E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.65E-02</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.13E-01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.72E-03</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.85E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.18E-01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">THI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.45E-01</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">THI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.13E + 00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par70">The Monte Carlo simulation results indicate a considerable non-carcinogenic health risk associated with exposure to PTEs in street dust, particularly for children. The HI values for certain metals, including Al, Mn, Cr, Ni, Cd, Cu, and Pb, exceed the safe threshold (HI &gt; 1), suggesting potential adverse health effects. Children exhibit significantly higher HI values than adults, which is expected due to their increased dust ingestion rates, lower body weight, and heightened physiological susceptibility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref></sup>. Notably, Cr and Mn demonstrate the highest HI values, with their 95th percentile levels exceeding the acceptable range, indicating potential neurotoxic and systemic health risks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the cumulative non-carcinogenic hazard index further emphasizes that a portion of the exposed population may experience health effects, warranting immediate attention (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). The moderate temperatures and wind conditions, along with the absence of rainfall during the sampling period, favored the accumulation and limited dispersion of street dust contaminants. The consistent meteorological conditions likely enhanced the representativeness of the sampled PTE concentrations, as dust resuspension was not heavily influenced by sudden weather shifts. The elevated PM<sub>10</sub> values in some locations further support the role of dry conditions in particulate mobilization.</p><p id="Par71">
<table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Estimated carcinogenic risk values for adults and children based on exposure ptes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Carcinogenic risks for adult</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Carcinogenic risks for child</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CR <sub>ing</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CR <sub>derm</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CR <sub>inh</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CR <sub>ing</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CR <sub>derm</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CR <sub>inh</sub></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cr</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.14E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.02E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.88E-08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.20E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.34E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.22E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72E-08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.42E-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ni</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.99E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.98E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.63E-09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.04E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17E-04</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.16E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.61E-09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17E-04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">As</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.37E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.44E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.24E-09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.08E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.95E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.00E-06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.49E-10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.35E-05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cd</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.66E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.10E-08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.05E-10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.78E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.88E-07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.80E-10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.80E-10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.06E-07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pb</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.68E-08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.28E-09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.95E-10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.23E-08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.25E-08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.65E-09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.63E-11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.12E-08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.34E-05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.16E-04</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par72">The carcinogenic risks related with exposure to PTEs in street dust were evaluated for ingestion (CR<sub>ing</sub>), dermal contact (CR<sub>derm</sub>), and inhalation (CR<sub>inh</sub>) exposure pathways. The total carcinogenic risk (TCR) represents the cumulative risk from all pathways for each element. The results indicate that for adults, the TCR is 9.34 × 10⁻⁵, while for children, the TCR is 2.16 × 10⁻⁴. Both values exceed the acceptable carcinogenic risk threshold of 1 × 10⁻⁶, indicating potential long-term health concerns by reason of chronic exposure to carcinogenic metals in street dust. The risk level for children was found to be more than twice that of adults, reflecting their greater vulnerability stemming from higher ingestion rates, frequent hand-to-mouth activity, and lower body weight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref></sup> which collectively increase their susceptibility to PTE exposure (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par73">Among the analyzed elements, nickel and chromium contribute the most to carcinogenic risk, highlighting their potential threat to long-term human health. For adults, the highest carcinogenic risk is associated with Ni (5.04 × 10⁻⁵), followed by Cr (3.20 × 10⁻⁵) and As (1.08 × 10⁻⁵). A similar trend is observed in children, where Ni (1.17 × 10⁻⁴) and Cr (7.42 × 10⁻⁵) present the highest risks, with As (2.35 × 10⁻⁵) contributing moderately. Although Ni and Cr contributed most to the estimated TCR values, it is critical to recognize that the carcinogenic risk related with nickel is primarily linked to inhalation exposure. According to recent EFSA evaluations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref></sup> there is insufficient evidence to classify nickel as carcinogenic via the oral route. Therefore, while the modeled TCR values for Ni appear elevated, they do not necessarily represent a realistic cancer risk through ingestion. The elevated risk levels for these elements generally align with their known carcinogenic profiles, with Ni and Cr linked to lung and nasal cancers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>and As associated with bladder, lung, and skin cancers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref></sup>. The ingestion pathway (CR<sub>ing</sub>) is the predominant exposure route for carcinogenic risk, suggesting that accidental ingestion of contaminated dust poses the greatest health concern.</p><p id="Par74">The carcinogenic risks associated with cadmium and lead are relatively low in comparison but still contribute to the overall risk profile. In other words, the health risks are negligible<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup> with TCR values well below the acceptable threshold of 1 × 10⁻⁶. Specifically, Cd poses a minimal risk, with TCRs of 1.78 × 10⁻⁷ for adults and 4.06 × 10⁻⁷ for children, while Pb shows even lower values of 3.23 × 10⁻⁸ and 7.12 × 10⁻⁸, respectively. Despite the low risk estimates, the toxicological relevance of these metals should not be overlooked. Cadmium is a recognized nephrotoxin and carcinogen, with a long biological half-life and bioaccumulative potential<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref></sup> while lead is associated with neurological, haematological, and renal toxicity, particularly in children<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref></sup>. These results support the continued need for environmental surveillance and exposure minimization plans in urban ecosystems.</p><p id="Par75">To more accurately characterize uncertainties in health risk estimates, MCS was applied. This stochastic modeling approach is commonly used in environmental health risk assessments to account for the uncertainty and variability inherent in input parameters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. In contrast to deterministic approaches that yield single-point estimates, MCS generates a probabilistic distribution of potential outcomes by repeatedly sampling from defined probability distributions assigned to each variable, such as metal concentrations, exposure duration, ingestion rate, and body weight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref></sup>. This probabilistic framework provides a more comprehensive and realistic evaluation of health risks under variable exposure scenarios, thereby enhancing the robustness of risk characterization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref></sup>. Further refinement of risk assessment has been conducted through Monte Carlo simulation. Herewith, the probabilistic analysis of carcinogenic risk highlights significant concerns regarding exposure to arsenic, chromium, cadmium, and lead through street dust (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). While the mean TCR remains within the acceptable limit of 1 × 10⁻⁴ for both adults and children, the 95th percentile estimates indicate that a fraction of the population, particularly children, is exposed to risk levels exceeding this threshold. Among the analyzed elements, Cr poses the highest carcinogenic threat, followed by As, with their upper-bound risk estimates exceeding the acceptable range for children. The high mobility and bioavailability of these metals in urban environments further exacerbate their potential impact<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref></sup>. The cumulative nature of these exposures suggests that prolonged contact with contaminated street dust may contribute to long-term health implications<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. To mitigate these risks, implementing strict emission control measures, enhancing street cleaning practices, and enforcing stringent industrial regulations are crucial steps toward reducing human exposure to carcinogenic metals in urban environments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Source contribution to health risks: linking pollution origins to human exposure</title><p id="Par76">Sankey diagrams serve as effective visualization tools for representing the proportional contributions of pollution sources to environmental contaminants and their associated health risks. In urban environments, they facilitate an extensive characterization of the relationships between emission sources and the distribution of PTEs in various environmental media<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par77">
<fig id="Fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Visualization of human health risk distributions derived from Monte Carlo simulation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2753" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig9_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig9_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 390564?><?image-md5 be871655eead1618ac76ae5b5db02318?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2363?><?image-original-width 1527?><?image-scaled-height 1181?><?image-scaled-width 763?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/be871655eead/41598_2025_11472_Fig9_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig9_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 9401?><?thumb-md5 bb77906439aeeac6bee5f0848b19ffae?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 155?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/bb77906439ae/41598_2025_11472_Fig9_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par78">Herewith, the Sankey diagram (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>) illustrates the proportional contributions of traffic emissions, natural/soil sources, and industrial runoff to the existence of PTEs in urban street dust and their subsequent impact on human health risks. Traffic emissions are identified as the dominant contributor to chromium (81.7%), copper (76.8%), lead (58.2%), and zinc (62.6%), highlighting vehicular activities such as fuel combustion, brake wear, and tire abrasion as key sources of metal contamination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Natural and soil sources contribute significantly to arsenic (47%), aluminium (29.7%), and nickel (24.4%), suggesting that geological composition and soil resuspension play a major role in metal dispersion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>. Meanwhile, industrial runoff is a notable source of cadmium (39.9%), manganese (46.4%), cobalt (41.4%), and iron (28.2%), reflecting the influence of industrial discharges and wastewater contamination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par79">
<fig id="Fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Sankey diagram demonstrating the flow from pollution sources to metal contaminants and their corresponding health risks.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e2780" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_Fig10_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig10_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 74206?><?image-md5 dddc7a94aa2ed5153f8406052b8a05f8?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 949?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 316?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/dddc7a94aa2e/41598_2025_11472_Fig10_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2025_11472_Fig10_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 8230?><?thumb-md5 056d09aa60d542f7aecfea4e6775a8e1?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 169?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0057/12368213/056d09aa60d5/41598_2025_11472_Fig10_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par80">From a health risk perspective, the THI results of this research indicate that traffic emissions play a substantial role in cumulative exposure, with children exhibiting slightly higher risk levels (20.29%) compared to adults (19.26%). This trend aligns with children’s increased susceptibility because of higher dust ingestion rates and lower body weight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref></sup>. The TCR further highlights the severity of industrial runoff, particularly in its contribution to cadmium and arsenic exposure. Notably, children face a significantly higher cancer risk (54.44%) compared to adults (34.23%), emphasizing their heightened vulnerability to long-term exposure effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Given these findings, targeted mitigation strategies are essential, including stricter vehicular emission controls, improved industrial waste management, and enhanced urban dust suppression measures. Addressing these pollution sources through policy interventions and public health initiatives is critical for reducing environmental health risks and safeguarding vulnerable populations, particularly children.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Policy implications</title><p id="Par81">The findings of this study have important implications for urban environmental management and public health protection in Istanbul and similar megacities. In line with the WHO Air Quality Guidelines reported in 2021<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref></sup> and the European Union’s urban pollution report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref></sup> our results highlight elevated non-carcinogenic and carcinogenic risks for children due to exposure to toxic elements such as Pb, Cr, and As through ingestion of street dust. The source apportionment results, particularly those derived from PMF, PCA, and cluster analysis, indicate that traffic emissions and industrial runoff are the primary contributors to PTE contamination in urban dust. These results support the need for targeted mitigation measures. In particular, the implementation of green or smart road cleaning technologies could help reduce dust resuspension and airborne exposure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. Restrictions on heavy-duty vehicles in densely populated or high-risk districts, alongside enhanced urban greening efforts, could further limit the circulation of contaminated particles in the environment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref></sup>. Additionally, land use policies and zoning regulations may be strengthened to limit industrial emissions near residential zones. Establishing regular monitoring programs focused on street dust composition could also provide an early warning system and help evaluate the effectiveness of interventions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref></sup>. These locally tailored measures would align with broader sustainability and public health goals while reinforcing Türkiye’s commitment to harmonizing urban environmental policies with EU standards. These findings not only inform local pollution control but also support Istanbul’s progress toward sustainable urban development and health-focused environmental governance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par82">This study provides a detailed evaluation of PTEs in urban street dust from Istanbul, integrating geochemical analysis, source apportionment, ecological risk indices, and health risk assessment. The findings reveal that street dust serves not only as a contaminant reservoir but also as a potential airborne vector for toxic metal exposure in urban settings. Through the application of Positive Matrix Factorization, Monte Carlo simulation, and multivariate statistics, the spatial patterns, sources, and health implications of heavy metal contamination were effectively characterized. Accordingly, the key findings include:</p><p id="Par83">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par84">Based on the PMF results, supported by PCA, HCA, and PCC analyses, industrial runoff (39.4%) was identified as the dominant source of PTEs, followed by traffic emissions (31.3%) and natural/soil sources (29.4%).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par85">Contamination indices (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>geo</sub>, EF, CF, PERI) indicated moderate to very high ecological risks at several locations, particularly for Cr, Cu, Zn, and Pb.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par86">MCS-enhanced health risk assessments showed that ingestion is the primary exposure route, with children facing a higher total hazard index (THI = 3.13) compared to adults (2.32).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par87">Although the TCR values numerically exceeded the USEPA threshold, the outcome was predominantly influenced by nickel ingestion, which is not classified as carcinogenic via the oral route. Therefore, the elevated TCR does not represent a significant health concern in this context.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par88">Traffic-related metals (Pb, Cu, Zn) were major contributors to health risks and also pose a concern for air quality due to their resuspension potential.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par89">Although the overall air quality during the study period was classified as ‘Good’, the findings suggest that localized dust contamination can still present significant health risks through inhalation and ingestion pathways.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par90">Stable meteorological conditions favored the persistence of dust-borne contaminants, which can contribute to long-term human exposure.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par91">Sankey diagram visualization confirmed the dominance of vehicular and industrial emissions in driving both ecological and human health burdens.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par92">Given these outcomes, a multifaceted mitigation approach is necessary. Regulatory control of industrial discharges, expansion of low-emission transport systems, street cleaning and dust suppression strategies, and urban vegetation initiatives are strongly recommended to reduce human exposure and environmental accumulation of PTEs.</p><p id="Par93">Importantly, the integration of Monte Carlo simulation enhanced the robustness of the health risk assessment by accounting for variability and uncertainty in exposure parameters, reinforcing the conclusion that no significant health risk exists under current exposure scenarios. Future studies should incorporate bioaccessibility and metal speciation analyses, and consider real-time monitoring of airborne particulate-bound metals to better evaluate inhalation risks. In conclusion, this work highlights the urgency of implementing integrated environmental and public health strategies in rapidly urbanizing areas to safeguard both ecological integrity and human well-being.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_11472_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name 41598_2025_11472_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?suppdata-size 495305?><?suppdata-md5 ce738786ad37025c66a4d0317d028673?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:0057/12368213/ce738786ad37/41598_2025_11472_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors express their sincere gratitude to the Directorate of Shimadzu Middle East, Istanbul Branch Office, for providing access to the Shimadzu ICP-MS 2050 instrument used in the elemental analysis.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>T. Ö: Sampling, Laboratory analysis; M. M. Y: Formal analysis, Visualization, Software (PMF, PCA, MCS), Writing – review &amp; editing; F. U: GIS mapping, Spatial interpretation, Ecological indices, Writing – review &amp; editing; E. H: Air Quality Data interpretation, Validation, Literature review; B. Y: Writing – original draft; Supervision, PMF, Methodology design, Health risk modeling, Final manuscript preparation, Project administration,</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by Giresun University Scientific Research Projects Coordination Unit under award number FEN-BAP-A-290224-43.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article [and its supplementary information files].</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par94">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dust pollution: its removal and effect on foliage physiology of urban trees</article-title><source>Sustain. Cities Soc.</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>101696</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scs.2019.101696</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Chaudhary, I. J. &amp; Rathore, D. Dust pollution: its removal and effect on foliage physiology of urban trees. <italic toggle="yes">Sustain. Cities Soc.</italic><bold>51</bold>, 101696. 10.1016/j.scs.2019.101696 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Rubaye</surname><given-names>RFF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kardel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dehbandi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological and human health risks of potentially toxic elements (PTEs) in street dust of Al-Hillah city, Iraq using Monte Carlo simulation</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2025</year><volume>966</volume><fpage>178722</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2025.178722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39919661</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Al-Rubaye, R. F. F., Kardel, F. &amp; Dehbandi, R. Ecological and human health risks of potentially toxic elements (PTEs) in street dust of Al-Hillah city, Iraq using Monte Carlo simulation. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>966</bold>, 178722. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2025.178722 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39919661</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2025.178722</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobhanardakani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheraghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorestani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiani Sadr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Source apportionment, ecological and health risks of potentially toxic elements in street dusts across different land uses in City of kermanshah, Iran</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2025</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2517</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-86677-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39833456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11746890</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Asgari, A., Sobhanardakani, S., Cheraghi, M., Lorestani, B. &amp; Kiani Sadr, M. Source apportionment, ecological and health risks of potentially toxic elements in street dusts across different land uses in City of kermanshah, Iran. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 2517. 10.1038/s41598-025-86677-6 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39833456</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-025-86677-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11746890</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karadeniz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustaoğlu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydın</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicological risk assessment using spring water quality indices in plateaus of Giresun province/türkiye: A holistic hydrogeochemical data analysis</article-title><source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>285</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-024-02054-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38967745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11226512</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Karadeniz, S., Ustaoğlu, F., Aydın, H. &amp; Yüksel, B. Toxicological risk assessment using spring water quality indices in plateaus of Giresun province/türkiye: A holistic hydrogeochemical data analysis. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Geochem. Health</italic>. <bold>46</bold>, 285. 10.1007/s10653-024-02054-8 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38967745</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10653-024-02054-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11226512</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sources and distribution of potentially toxic elements in urban road dust: A comparative insights and risk assessment of two polluted cities</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut</source><year>2025</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>125768</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2025.125768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39889943</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Khan, R. et al. Sources and distribution of potentially toxic elements in urban road dust: A comparative insights and risk assessment of two polluted cities. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Pollut</italic>. <bold>368</bold>, 125768. 10.1016/j.envpol.2025.125768 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39889943</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envpol.2025.125768</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganie</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Javaid</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajam</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reshi</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arsenic toxicity: sources, pathophysiology and mechanism</article-title><source>Toxicol. Res.</source><year>2024</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>tfad111</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxres/tfad111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10762673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38178998</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Ganie, S. Y., Javaid, D., Hajam, Y. A. &amp; Reshi, M. S. Arsenic toxicity: sources, pathophysiology and mechanism. <italic toggle="yes">Toxicol. Res.</italic><bold>13</bold> (1), tfad111. 10.1093/toxres/tfad111 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/toxres/tfad111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10762673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38178998</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ATSDR &amp; Registry <italic toggle="yes">Toxicological Profile for Arsenic. Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease</italic> (U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 2007). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxprofiles/tp2.pdf">https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxprofiles/tp2.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arıca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Söylemezoğlu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing reference levels of nickel and chromium in cord blood, maternal blood and placenta specimens from ankara, Turkey</article-title><source>J. Turk. Ger. Gynecol. Assoc.</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4274/jtgga.galenos.2021.2020.0202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33631873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8420753</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Yüksel, B., Arıca, E. &amp; Söylemezoğlu, T. Assessing reference levels of nickel and chromium in cord blood, maternal blood and placenta specimens from ankara, Turkey. <italic toggle="yes">J. Turk. Ger. Gynecol. Assoc.</italic><bold>22</bold>, 187–195. 10.4274/jtgga.galenos.2021.2020.0202 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33631873</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4274/jtgga.galenos.2021.2020.0202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8420753</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozalan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turksoy</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Güvendik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soylemezoglu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary assessment of lead levels in soft plastic toys by flame atomic absorption spectroscopy</article-title><source>Turk. Hij Den Biyol Derg</source><year>2019</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5505/TurkHijyen.2019.58234</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Bozalan, M., Turksoy, V. A., Yüksel, B., Güvendik, G. &amp; Soylemezoglu, T. Preliminary assessment of lead levels in soft plastic toys by flame atomic absorption spectroscopy. <italic toggle="yes">Turk. Hij Den Biyol Derg</italic>. <bold>76</bold>, 243–254. 10.5505/TurkHijyen.2019.58234 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ATSDR &amp; Registry <italic toggle="yes">Toxicological Profile for Lead. Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease</italic> (U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 2020). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxprofiles/tp13.pdf">https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxprofiles/tp13.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charkiewicz</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omeljaniuk</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikliński</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadmium toxicity and health effects – A brief summary</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2023</year><volume>28</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>6620</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules28186620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37764397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10537762</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Charkiewicz, A. E., Omeljaniuk, W. J., Nowak, K., Garley, M. &amp; Nikliński, J. Cadmium toxicity and health effects – A brief summary. <italic toggle="yes">Molecules</italic><bold>28</bold> (18), 6620. 10.3390/molecules28186620 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37764397</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules28186620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10537762</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustaoğlu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Şeker</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Öncü</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to potentially toxic elements through ingestion of canned non-alcoholic drinks sold in istanbul, türkiye: A health risk assessment study</article-title><source>J. Food Compos. Anal.</source><year>2023</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>105361</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2023.105361</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Yüksel, B., Ustaoğlu, F., Yazman, M. M., Şeker, M. E. &amp; Öncü, T. Exposure to potentially toxic elements through ingestion of canned non-alcoholic drinks sold in istanbul, türkiye: A health risk assessment study. <italic toggle="yes">J. Food Compos. Anal.</italic><bold>121</bold>, 105361. 10.1016/j.jfca.2023.105361 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breathing in danger: Understanding the multifaceted impact of air pollution on health impacts</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</source><year>2024</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>116532</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2024.116532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38850696</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Chen, F. et al. Breathing in danger: Understanding the multifaceted impact of air pollution on health impacts. <italic toggle="yes">Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</italic><bold>280</bold>, 116532. 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2024.116532 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38850696</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2024.116532</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlasov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosheleva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinkareva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasimov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contamination assessment and source identification of metals and metalloids in submicron road dust (PM1) in Moscow megacity</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</source><year>2025</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2085</fpage><lpage>2106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-024-35791-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39755863</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Vlasov, D., Kosheleva, N., Shinkareva, G. &amp; Kasimov, N. Contamination assessment and source identification of metals and metalloids in submicron road dust (PM1) in Moscow megacity. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 2085–2106. 10.1007/s11356-024-35791-5 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-024-35791-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39755863</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological and health risk assessment and anthropogenic sources analysis of heavy metals in different types of urban road dust</article-title><source>Process. Saf. Environ. Prot.</source><year>2025</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>106813</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psep.2025.106813</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Ma, Y., Zhang, Y. &amp; Song, L. Ecological and health risk assessment and anthropogenic sources analysis of heavy metals in different types of urban road dust. <italic toggle="yes">Process. Saf. Environ. Prot.</italic><bold>195</bold>, 106813. 10.1016/j.psep.2025.106813 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of multi-pollutant air quality in China using health-centric air pollution indices</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut</source><year>2025</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>126565</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2025.126565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40446898</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Wang, Y., Li, Z., Qian, F., Huang, C. &amp; Hu, J. Characterization of multi-pollutant air quality in China using health-centric air pollution indices. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Pollut</italic>. <bold>381</bold>, 126565. 10.1016/j.envpol.2025.126565 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40446898</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envpol.2025.126565</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manisalidis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavropoulou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavropoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bezirtzoglou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental and health impacts of air pollution: A review</article-title><source>Front. Public. Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2020.00014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32154200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7044178</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Manisalidis, I., Stavropoulou, E., Stavropoulos, A. &amp; Bezirtzoglou, E. Environmental and health impacts of air pollution: A review. <italic toggle="yes">Front. Public. Health</italic>. <bold>8</bold>, 14. 10.3389/fpubh.2020.00014 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32154200</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpubh.2020.00014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7044178</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. WHO global air quality guidelines: particulate matter (PM2.5 and PM10), ozone, nitrogen dioxide, sulfur dioxide, and carbon monoxide. World Health Organization. (2021). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240034228">https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240034228</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34662007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">USEPA. Technical assistance document for the reporting of daily air quality – The Air Quality Index (AQI). U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. (2016). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/air-trends/air-quality-index-report">https://www.epa.gov/air-trends/air-quality-index-report</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Canitez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alpkokin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topuz Kiremitci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable urban mobility in istanbul: challenges and prospects</article-title><source>Case Stud. Transp. Policy</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1148</fpage><lpage>1157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cstp.2020.07.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Canitez, F., Alpkokin, P. &amp; Topuz Kiremitci, S. Sustainable urban mobility in istanbul: challenges and prospects. <italic toggle="yes">Case Stud. Transp. Policy</italic>. <bold>8</bold>, 1148–1157. 10.1016/j.cstp.2020.07.005 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alver Şahin</surname><given-names>Ü</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of ambient particulate matter and trace gases in istanbul: insights from long-term and multi-monitoring stations</article-title><source>Atmos. Pollut Res.</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>102089</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apr.2024.102089</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Alver Şahin, Ü. et al. Assessment of ambient particulate matter and trace gases in istanbul: insights from long-term and multi-monitoring stations. <italic toggle="yes">Atmos. Pollut Res.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 102089. 10.1016/j.apr.2024.102089 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sezgin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozcan</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demir</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemlioglu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of heavy metal concentrations in street dusts in Istanbul E-5 highway</article-title><source>Environ. Int.</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>985</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0160-4120(03)00075-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592575</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Sezgin, N., Ozcan, H. K., Demir, G., Nemlioglu, S. &amp; Bayat, C. Determination of heavy metal concentrations in street dusts in Istanbul E-5 highway. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Int.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 979–985. 10.1016/S0160-4120(03)00075-8 (2004).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14592575</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0160-4120(03)00075-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sezgin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balkaya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahmurova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aysal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of heavy metal contamination in urban soil (Tuzla district, istanbul, Turkey)</article-title><source>Desalin. Water Treat.</source><year>2019</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5004/dwt.2019.25023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Sezgin, N., Balkaya, N., Sahmurova, A. &amp; Aysal, N. Assessment of heavy metal contamination in urban soil (Tuzla district, istanbul, Turkey). <italic toggle="yes">Desalin. Water Treat.</italic><bold>172</bold>, 167–176. 10.5004/dwt.2019.25023 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen, S. Y. et al. Urban fine particulate matter and elements associated with subclinical atherosclerosis in adolescents and young adults. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>56</bold> (11). 10.1021/acs.est.1c07322 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.est.1c06347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35138845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liew</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Maternal plasma perfluoroalkyl substances and miscarriage: A nested case–control study in the Danish National birth cohort</article-title><source>Environ. Health Perspect.</source><year>2020</year><volume>128</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>047007</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/EHP6202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32319790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7228130</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Liew, Z. et al. Maternal plasma perfluoroalkyl substances and miscarriage: A nested case–control study in the Danish National birth cohort. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Health Perspect.</italic><bold>128</bold> (4), 047007. 10.1289/EHP6202 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32319790</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1289/EHP6202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7228130</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meo</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alotaibi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between air pollutants particulate matter (PM2.5, PM10), nitrogen dioxide (NO2), sulfur dioxide (SO2), volatile organic compounds (VOCs), ground-level Ozone (O3) and hypertension</article-title><source>J. King Saud Univ. Sci.</source><year>2024</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>103531</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jksus.2024.103531</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Meo, S. A., Shaikh, N. &amp; Alotaibi, M. Association between air pollutants particulate matter (PM2.5, PM10), nitrogen dioxide (NO2), sulfur dioxide (SO2), volatile organic compounds (VOCs), ground-level Ozone (O3) and hypertension. <italic toggle="yes">J. King Saud Univ. Sci.</italic><bold>36</bold>, 103531. 10.1016/j.jksus.2024.103531 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henning</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Particulate matter air pollution is a significant risk factor for cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>Curr. Probl. Cardiol.</source><year>2024</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>102094</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2023.102094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37734693</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Henning, R. J. Particulate matter air pollution is a significant risk factor for cardiovascular disease. <italic toggle="yes">Curr. Probl. Cardiol.</italic><bold>49</bold>, 102094. 10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2023.102094 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37734693</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cpcardiol.2023.102094</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marín-Palma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PM10 promotes an inflammatory cytokine response that May impact SARS-CoV-2 replication in vitro</article-title><source>Front. Immunol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1161135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1161135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37180105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10166799</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Marín-Palma, D. et al. PM10 promotes an inflammatory cytokine response that May impact SARS-CoV-2 replication in vitro. <italic toggle="yes">Front. Immunol.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 1161135. 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1161135 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37180105</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1161135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10166799</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Velizarova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of emission factors for particulate matter and NO2 from road transport in Sofia</article-title><source>Bulgaria Atmos.</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>773</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/atmos15070773</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Velizarova, M. et al. Evaluation of emission factors for particulate matter and NO2 from road transport in Sofia. <italic toggle="yes">Bulgaria Atmos.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 773. 10.3390/atmos15070773 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarek</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alhussan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khafaga</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Kenawy</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elshewey</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A snake optimization algorithm-based feature selection framework for rapid detection of cardiovascular disease in its early stages</article-title><source>Biomed. Signal. Process. Control</source><year>2025</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>107417</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bspc.2024.107417</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Tarek, Z., Alhussan, A. A., Khafaga, D. S., El-Kenawy, E. M. &amp; Elshewey, A. M. A snake optimization algorithm-based feature selection framework for rapid detection of cardiovascular disease in its early stages. <italic toggle="yes">Biomed. Signal. Process. Control</italic>. <bold>102</bold>, 107417. 10.1016/j.bspc.2024.107417 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Rashidy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multitask multilayer-prediction model for predicting mechanical ventilation and the associated mortality rate</article-title><source>Neural Comput. Appl.</source><year>2025</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1321</fpage><lpage>1343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00521-024-10468-9</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">El-Rashidy, N. et al. Multitask multilayer-prediction model for predicting mechanical ventilation and the associated mortality rate. <italic toggle="yes">Neural Comput. Appl.</italic><bold>37</bold>, 1321–1343. 10.1007/s00521-024-10468-9 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gündoğdu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbir</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevating hourly PM2.5 forecasting in istanbul, türkiye: leveraging ERA5 reanalysis and genetic algorithms in a comparative machine learning model analysis</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2024</year><volume>364</volume><fpage>143096</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2024.143096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39146993</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Gündoğdu, S. &amp; Elbir, T. Elevating hourly PM2.5 forecasting in istanbul, türkiye: leveraging ERA5 reanalysis and genetic algorithms in a comparative machine learning model analysis. <italic toggle="yes">Chemosphere</italic><bold>364</bold>, 143096. 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2024.143096 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39146993</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2024.143096</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Özger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multi-method and multi-duration trend analysis of temperature and precipitation in istanbul, turkey, by using meteorological records, MERRA-2 reanalysis, and IMERG estimations</article-title><source>HydroResearch</source><year>2025</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hydres.2024.11.005</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Sam, S. &amp; Özger, M. A multi-method and multi-duration trend analysis of temperature and precipitation in istanbul, turkey, by using meteorological records, MERRA-2 reanalysis, and IMERG estimations. <italic toggle="yes">HydroResearch</italic><bold>8</bold>, 209–222. 10.1016/j.hydres.2024.11.005 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustaoğlu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pollution analysis of metals in the sediments of lagoon lakes in türkiye: toxicological risk assessment and source insights</article-title><source>Process. Saf. Environ. Prot.</source><year>2025</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psep.2024.11.085</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Yüksel, B. &amp; Ustaoğlu, F. Pollution analysis of metals in the sediments of lagoon lakes in türkiye: toxicological risk assessment and source insights. <italic toggle="yes">Process. Saf. Environ. Prot.</italic><bold>193</bold>, 665–682. 10.1016/j.psep.2024.11.085 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NAQMN. National Air Quality Monitoring Network. Republic of Türkiye Ministry of Environment, Urbanization, and Climate Change. (2025). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.havaizleme.gov.tr">https://www.havaizleme.gov.tr</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Topaldemir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taş</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustaoğlu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentially hazardous elements in sediments and Ceratophyllum demersum: an ecotoxicological risk assessment in miliç wetland, samsun, Türkiye</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>26397</fpage><lpage>26416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-022-23937-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36367653</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Topaldemir, H., Taş, B., Yüksel, B. &amp; Ustaoğlu, F. Potentially hazardous elements in sediments and Ceratophyllum demersum: an ecotoxicological risk assessment in miliç wetland, samsun, Türkiye. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 26397–26416. 10.1007/s11356-022-23937-2 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-022-23937-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36367653</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tokatlı, C. et al. Spatial-temporal variations of inorganic contaminants and associated risks for sediment of felent stream basin flowing along with silver mines in the Midwestern Türkiye. <italic toggle="yes">Soil. Sediment. Contam.</italic><bold>2025</bold>10.1080/15320383.2025.2464153 (2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">USEPA. Conducting a Human Health Risk Assessment. U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. (2025). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/risk/human-health-risk-assessment">https://www.epa.gov/risk/human-health-risk-assessment</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yesilkanat</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial characteristics of ecological and health risks of toxic heavy metal pollution from road dust in the black sea Coast of Turkey</article-title><source>Geoderma Reg.</source><year>2021</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>e00388</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geodrs.2021.e00388</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Yesilkanat, C. M. &amp; Kobya, Y. Spatial characteristics of ecological and health risks of toxic heavy metal pollution from road dust in the black sea Coast of Turkey. <italic toggle="yes">Geoderma Reg.</italic><bold>25</bold>, e00388. 10.1016/j.geodrs.2021.e00388 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A questionnaire based probabilistic risk assessment (PRA) of heavy metals in urban and suburban soils under different land uses and receptor populations</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2021</year><volume>793</volume><fpage>148525</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.148525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34175607</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Zhang, Y., Guo, Z., Peng, C., Deng, H. &amp; Xiao, X. A questionnaire based probabilistic risk assessment (PRA) of heavy metals in urban and suburban soils under different land uses and receptor populations. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>793</bold>, 148525. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.148525 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34175607</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.148525</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heidari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darijani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alipour</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metal pollution of road dust in a City and its highly polluted suburb; quantitative source apportionment and source-specific ecological and health risk assessment</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2021</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>129656</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33503525</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Heidari, M., Darijani, T. &amp; Alipour, V. Heavy metal pollution of road dust in a City and its highly polluted suburb; quantitative source apportionment and source-specific ecological and health risk assessment. <italic toggle="yes">Chemosphere</italic><bold>273</bold>, 129656. 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129656 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33503525</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2021.129656</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimation of children’s soil and dust ingestion rates and health risk at e-waste dismantling area</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>7332</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph19127332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35742584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9224165</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Yang, Y. et al. Estimation of children’s soil and dust ingestion rates and health risk at e-waste dismantling area. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health</italic>. <bold>19</bold>, 7332. 10.3390/ijerph19127332 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35742584</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph19127332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9224165</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Receptor model-based source-specific health risks of toxic metal(loid)s in coal basin-induced agricultural soil in Northwest Bangladesh</article-title><source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>8539</fpage><lpage>8564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-023-01740-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37646918</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Habib, M. A. et al. Receptor model-based source-specific health risks of toxic metal(loid)s in coal basin-induced agricultural soil in Northwest Bangladesh. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Geochem. Health</italic>. <bold>45</bold>, 8539–8564. 10.1007/s10653-023-01740-3 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37646918</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10653-023-01740-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determining priority control factors for heavy metal management in urban road dust based on source-oriented probabilistic ecological-health risk assessment: A study in xi’an during peak pollution season</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manag</source><year>2024</year><volume>369</volume><fpage>122105</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39213844</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Wang, X. et al. Determining priority control factors for heavy metal management in urban road dust based on source-oriented probabilistic ecological-health risk assessment: A study in xi’an during peak pollution season. <italic toggle="yes">J. Environ. Manag</italic>. <bold>369</bold>, 122105. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122105 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jenvman.2024.122105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39213844</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">USEPA. Risk Assessment Guidance for Superfund Volume I: Human Health Evaluation Manual (Part E, Supplemental Guidance for Dermal Risk Assessment). U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Office of Superfund Remediation and Technology Innovation, EPA/540/R/99/005. (2004). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/sites/default/files/2015-09/documents/part_e_final_revision_10-03-07.pdf">https://www.epa.gov/sites/default/files/2015-09/documents/part_e_final_revision_10-03-07.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hızlı</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karaoglu</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gören</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying Geogenic and anthropogenic aluminum pollution on different Spatial distributions and removal of natural waters and soil in çanakkale, Turkey</article-title><source>ACS Omega</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>8557</fpage><lpage>8568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.2c07707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36910959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9996766</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Hızlı, S., Karaoglu, A. G., Gören, A. Y. &amp; Kobya, M. Identifying Geogenic and anthropogenic aluminum pollution on different Spatial distributions and removal of natural waters and soil in çanakkale, Turkey. <italic toggle="yes">ACS Omega</italic>. <bold>8</bold>, 8557–8568. 10.1021/acsomega.2c07707 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36910959</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acsomega.2c07707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9996766</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heavy metal pollution of street dust in the largest City of mexico: sources and health risk assessment</article-title><source>Environ. Monit. Assess.</source><year>2021</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>193</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-021-08993-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33723965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7960608</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Aguilera, A. et al. Heavy metal pollution of street dust in the largest City of mexico: sources and health risk assessment. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Monit. Assess.</italic><bold>193</bold>, 193. 10.1007/s10661-021-08993-4 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33723965</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10661-021-08993-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7960608</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Genchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carocci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauria</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinicropi</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catalano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nickel: human health and environmental toxicology</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>679</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17030679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31973020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7037090</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Genchi, G., Carocci, A., Lauria, G., Sinicropi, M. S. &amp; Catalano, A. Nickel: human health and environmental toxicology. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health</italic>. <bold>17</bold>, 679. 10.3390/ijerph17030679 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31973020</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph17030679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7037090</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>CLS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the sources, concentrations, and resuspension potential of metals and metalloids in the thoracic fraction of urban road dust</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2021</year><volume>786</volume><fpage>147467</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.147467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33971596</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Wiseman, C. L. S., Levesque, C. &amp; Rasmussen, P. E. Characterizing the sources, concentrations, and resuspension potential of metals and metalloids in the thoracic fraction of urban road dust. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>786</bold>, 147467. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.147467 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33971596</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.147467</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brantley</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soils reveal widespread manganese enrichment from industrial inputs</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es102001w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21133425</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Herndon, E. M., Jin, L. &amp; Brantley, S. L. Soils reveal widespread manganese enrichment from industrial inputs. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>45</bold>, 241–247. 10.1021/es102001w (2011).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21133425</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/es102001w</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cobalt resources in Europe and the potential for new discoveries</article-title><source>Ore Geol. Rev.</source><year>2021</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>103915</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.oregeorev.2020.103915</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Horn, S. et al. Cobalt resources in Europe and the potential for new discoveries. <italic toggle="yes">Ore Geol. Rev.</italic><bold>130</bold>, 103915. 10.1016/j.oregeorev.2020.103915 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Österlund</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsalek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viklander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pollution conveyed by urban runoff: A review of sources</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2020</year><volume>709</volume><fpage>136125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.136125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31905584</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Müller, A., Österlund, H., Marsalek, J. &amp; Viklander, M. The pollution conveyed by urban runoff: A review of sources. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>709</bold>, 136125. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.136125 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31905584</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.136125</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR53" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mould</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouillon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental arsenic, cadmium and lead dust emissions from metal mine operations: implications for environmental management, monitoring and human health</article-title><source>Environ. Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2014.08.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25462679</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53" publication-type="journal">Taylor, M. P., Mould, S. A., Kristensen, L. J. &amp; Rouillon, M. Environmental arsenic, cadmium and lead dust emissions from metal mine operations: implications for environmental management, monitoring and human health. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Res.</italic><bold>135</bold>, 296–303. 10.1016/j.envres.2014.08.036 (2014).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25462679</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envres.2014.08.036</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The urban lead (Pb) burden in humans, animals and the natural environment</article-title><source>Environ. Res.</source><year>2021</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>110377</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33129862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8812512</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Levin, R. et al. The urban lead (Pb) burden in humans, animals and the natural environment. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Res.</italic><bold>193</bold>, 110377. 10.1016/j.envres.2020.110377 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33129862</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envres.2020.110377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8812512</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mercury abatement in the environment: insights from industrial emissions and fates in the environment</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e28253</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38571637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10987932</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Kung, H. C. et al. Mercury abatement in the environment: insights from industrial emissions and fates in the environment. <italic toggle="yes">Heliyon</italic><bold>10</bold>, e28253. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28253 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38571637</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e28253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10987932</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR56" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jadoon</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onjia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive analysis and risk assessment of fine road dust in Abbottabad City (Pakistan) with heavy traffic for potentially toxic elements</article-title><source>J. Hazard. Mater.</source><year>2025</year><volume>486</volume><fpage>136788</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2024.136788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39740543</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56" publication-type="journal">Jadoon, W. A., Khan, Y. A., Varol, M., Onjia, A. &amp; Mohany, M. Comprehensive analysis and risk assessment of fine road dust in Abbottabad City (Pakistan) with heavy traffic for potentially toxic elements. <italic toggle="yes">J. Hazard. Mater.</italic><bold>486</bold>, 136788. 10.1016/j.jhazmat.2024.136788 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39740543</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2024.136788</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Işınkaralar</surname><given-names>Ö</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Işınkaralar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayraktar</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring the Spatial distribution pattern according to urban land use and health risk assessment on potential toxic metal contamination via street dust in ankara, Türkiye</article-title><source>Environ. Monit. Assess.</source><year>2023</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>11705</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-023-11705-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37615782</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Işınkaralar, Ö., Işınkaralar, K. &amp; Bayraktar, E. P. Monitoring the Spatial distribution pattern according to urban land use and health risk assessment on potential toxic metal contamination via street dust in ankara, Türkiye. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Monit. Assess.</italic><bold>195</bold>, 11705. 10.1007/s10661-023-11705-9 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10661-023-11705-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37615782</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health risk assessment and bioaccessibilities of heavy metals for children in soil and dust from urban parks and schools of jiaozuo, China</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</source><year>2020</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>110157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.110157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31954218</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Han, Q. et al. Health risk assessment and bioaccessibilities of heavy metals for children in soil and dust from urban parks and schools of jiaozuo, China. <italic toggle="yes">Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</italic><bold>191</bold>, 110157. 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.110157 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31954218</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.110157</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Considering the bioavailability and bioaccessibility of heavy metals for risk assessment of street dust by typical transportation cities in China</article-title><source>Microchem J.</source><year>2025</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>112264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2024.112264</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Yu, F., Wang, P. &amp; Lv, H. Considering the bioavailability and bioaccessibility of heavy metals for risk assessment of street dust by typical transportation cities in China. <italic toggle="yes">Microchem J.</italic><bold>208</bold>, 112264. 10.1016/j.microc.2024.112264 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seibert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regional and seasonal drivers of metals and PAHs concentrations in road dust and their health implications in the Czech Republic</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e40725</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e40725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39691203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11650297</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Seibert, R. et al. Regional and seasonal drivers of metals and PAHs concentrations in road dust and their health implications in the Czech Republic. <italic toggle="yes">Heliyon</italic><bold>10</bold>, e40725. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e40725 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39691203</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e40725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11650297</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehtemae</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanavati</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazarpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babaeinejad</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Status, source, and risk assessment of heavy metal(loid)s and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in the street dust of ilam, Iran</article-title><source>Polycycl. Aromat. Compd.</source><year>2024</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>6475</fpage><lpage>6500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10406638.2023.2276864</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Ehtemae, N., Ghanavati, N., Nazarpour, A., Babaeinejad, T. &amp; Watts, M. J. Status, source, and risk assessment of heavy metal(loid)s and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in the street dust of ilam, Iran. <italic toggle="yes">Polycycl. Aromat. Compd.</italic><bold>44</bold>, 6475–6500. 10.1080/10406638.2023.2276864 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>TDH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accumulation degree and risk assessment of metals in street dust from a developing City in central Taiwan</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2023</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>139785</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.139785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37567257</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Lin, T. S., Wu, J. W., Vo, T. D. H., Nguyen, V. T. &amp; Ju, Y. R. Accumulation degree and risk assessment of metals in street dust from a developing City in central Taiwan. <italic toggle="yes">Chemosphere</italic><bold>339</bold>, 139785. 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.139785 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37567257</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2023.139785</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>LHV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>CWA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>FBV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araújo</surname><given-names>PRM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Baseline concentrations, source apportionment, and probabilistic risk assessment of heavy metals in urban street dust in Northeast Brazil</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2023</year><volume>858</volume><fpage>159750</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36309279</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Lima, L. H. V., Nascimento, C. W. A., Silva, F. B. V. &amp; Araújo, P. R. M. Baseline concentrations, source apportionment, and probabilistic risk assessment of heavy metals in urban street dust in Northeast Brazil. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>858</bold>, 159750. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159750 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36309279</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159750</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR64" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zgłobicki</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Telecka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metals in urban street dust: health risk assessment (Lublin city, E Poland)</article-title><source>Appl. Sci.</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4092</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app11094092</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64" publication-type="journal">Zgłobicki, W. &amp; Telecka, M. Heavy metals in urban street dust: health risk assessment (Lublin city, E Poland). <italic toggle="yes">Appl. Sci.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 4092. 10.3390/app11094092 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo-Nava</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heavy metals (lead, cadmium, and zinc) from street dust in monterrey, mexico: ecological risk index</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3231</fpage><lpage>3240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13762-020-02649-5</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Castillo-Nava, D. et al. Heavy metals (lead, cadmium, and zinc) from street dust in monterrey, mexico: ecological risk index. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 3231–3240. 10.1007/s13762-020-02649-5 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR66" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>CLS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining the effectiveness of municipal street sweeping in removing road-deposited particles and metal(loid)s of respiratory health concern</article-title><source>Environ. Int.</source><year>2024</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>108697</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2024.108697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38696979</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66" publication-type="journal">Das, S. &amp; Wiseman, C. L. S. Examining the effectiveness of municipal street sweeping in removing road-deposited particles and metal(loid)s of respiratory health concern. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Int.</italic><bold>187</bold>, 108697. 10.1016/j.envint.2024.108697 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38696979</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envint.2024.108697</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delibašić</surname><given-names>Š</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health risk assessment of heavy metal contamination in street dust of federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina</article-title><source>Hum. Ecol. Risk Assess.</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1296</fpage><lpage>1308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10807039.2020.1826290</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Delibašić, Š. et al. Health risk assessment of heavy metal contamination in street dust of federation of Bosnia and Herzegovina. <italic toggle="yes">Hum. Ecol. Risk Assess.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 1296–1308. 10.1080/10807039.2020.1826290 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR68" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Concentrations, speciation, and bioavailability of heavy metals in street dust as well as relationships with physiochemical properties: A case study of Jinan City in East China</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>35724</fpage><lpage>35737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09761-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32601863</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68" publication-type="journal">Dong, S. et al. Concentrations, speciation, and bioavailability of heavy metals in street dust as well as relationships with physiochemical properties: A case study of Jinan City in East China. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 35724–35737. 10.1007/s11356-020-09761-6 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-020-09761-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32601863</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR69" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dytłow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Górka-Kostrubiec</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concentration of heavy metals in street dust: an implication of using different geochemical background data in estimating the level of heavy metal pollution</article-title><source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00726-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33037955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7847877</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69" publication-type="journal">Dytłow, S. &amp; Górka-Kostrubiec, B. Concentration of heavy metals in street dust: an implication of using different geochemical background data in estimating the level of heavy metal pollution. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Geochem. Health</italic>. <bold>43</bold>, 521–535. 10.1007/s10653-020-00726-9 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33037955</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10653-020-00726-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7847877</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR70" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of sources and pollution state of trace and toxic elements in street dust in a metropolitan City</article-title><source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>3213</fpage><lpage>3229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00560-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32307635</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70" publication-type="journal">Kara, M. Assessment of sources and pollution state of trace and toxic elements in street dust in a metropolitan City. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Geochem. Health</italic>. <bold>42</bold>, 3213–3229. 10.1007/s10653-020-00560-z (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32307635</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10653-020-00560-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR71" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khademi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distribution of metal(loid)s in particle size fraction in urban soil and street dust: influence of population density</article-title><source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>4341</fpage><lpage>4354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00515-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31955288</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71" publication-type="journal">Khademi, H. et al. Distribution of metal(loid)s in particle size fraction in urban soil and street dust: influence of population density. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Geochem. Health</italic>. <bold>42</bold>, 4341–4354. 10.1007/s10653-020-00515-4 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31955288</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10653-020-00515-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR72" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malakootian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial distribution and correlations among elements in smaller than 75 µm street dust: ecological and probabilistic health risk assessment</article-title><source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source><year>2020</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00694-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33052509</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72" publication-type="journal">Malakootian, M. et al. Spatial distribution and correlations among elements in smaller than 75 µm street dust: ecological and probabilistic health risk assessment. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Geochem. Health</italic>. <bold>43</bold>, 567–583. 10.1007/s10653-020-00694-0 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33052509</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10653-020-00694-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR73" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erener</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal analysis and mapping of air pollution (PM10 and SO2) during COVID-19 lockdown in Kocaeli (Türkiye)</article-title><source>Int. J. Eng. Geosci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26833/ijeg.1111699</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73" publication-type="journal">Kotan, B. &amp; Erener, A. Seasonal analysis and mapping of air pollution (PM10 and SO2) during COVID-19 lockdown in Kocaeli (Türkiye). <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Eng. Geosci.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 173–187. 10.26833/ijeg.1111699 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR74" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dongre</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhoi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maltare</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An outlier detection framework for air quality index prediction using linear and ensemble models</article-title><source>Decis. Anal. J.</source><year>2025</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>100546</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dajour.2025.100546</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74" publication-type="journal">Dongre, P. K., Patel, V., Bhoi, U. &amp; Maltare, N. N. An outlier detection framework for air quality index prediction using linear and ensemble models. <italic toggle="yes">Decis. Anal. J.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 100546. 10.1016/j.dajour.2025.100546 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR75" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of particulate matter (PM10, PM2.5) on global horizontal irradiance and direct normal irradiance in urban areas</article-title><source>Build. Environ.</source><year>2025</year><volume>2025</volume><fpage>112610</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.buildenv.2025.112610</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75" publication-type="journal">Shim, J., Park, S. &amp; Song, D. Impact of particulate matter (PM10, PM2.5) on global horizontal irradiance and direct normal irradiance in urban areas. <italic toggle="yes">Build. Environ.</italic><bold>2025</bold>, 112610. 10.1016/j.buildenv.2025.112610 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR76" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roganović</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rare Earth elements and health risk assessment of road dust from the vicinity of coal fired thermal power plants</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2025</year><volume>377</volume><fpage>144329</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2025.144329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40132349</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76" publication-type="journal">Roganović, J. et al. Rare Earth elements and health risk assessment of road dust from the vicinity of coal fired thermal power plants. <italic toggle="yes">Chemosphere</italic><bold>377</bold>, 144329. 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2025.144329 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40132349</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2025.144329</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR77" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Özlü</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of bioaccessibility and sources of elements in road dust: implications for ecological and human health risks</article-title><source>Microchem J.</source><year>2024</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>111374</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.microc.2024.111374</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77" publication-type="journal">Özlü, E. Investigation of bioaccessibility and sources of elements in road dust: implications for ecological and human health risks. <italic toggle="yes">Microchem J.</italic><bold>205</bold>, 111374. 10.1016/j.microc.2024.111374 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR78" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaibur</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Application of pollution indices to determine pollution intensities in the groundwater of Gopalganj (south-central part), Bangladesh</article-title><source>Groundw. Sustain. Dev.</source><year>2024</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>101206</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gsd.2024.101206</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78" publication-type="journal">Shaibur, M. R. et al. Application of pollution indices to determine pollution intensities in the groundwater of Gopalganj (south-central part), Bangladesh. <italic toggle="yes">Groundw. Sustain. Dev.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 101206. 10.1016/j.gsd.2024.101206 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR79" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartkowiak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemanowicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rydlewska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sowiński</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of proximity to road traffic on heavy metal accumulation and enzyme activity in urban soils and dandelion</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>812</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su16020812</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR79" publication-type="journal">Bartkowiak, A., Lemanowicz, J., Rydlewska, M. &amp; Sowiński, P. The impact of proximity to road traffic on heavy metal accumulation and enzyme activity in urban soils and dandelion. <italic toggle="yes">Sustainability</italic><bold>16</bold>, 812. 10.3390/su16020812 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR80" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insight into PM2.5 sources by applying positive matrix factorization (PMF) at urban and rural sites of Beijing</article-title><source>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>14703</fpage><lpage>14724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/acp-21-14703-2021</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80" publication-type="journal">Srivastava, D. et al. Insight into PM2.5 sources by applying positive matrix factorization (PMF) at urban and rural sites of Beijing. <italic toggle="yes">Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 14703–14724. 10.5194/acp-21-14703-2021 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR81" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poznanović Spahić</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Natural and anthropogenic sources of chromium, nickel and Cobalt in soils impacted by agricultural and industrial activity (Vojvodina, Serbia)</article-title><source>J. Environ. Sci. Health A</source><year>2019</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10934529.2018.1544802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30587075</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR81" publication-type="journal">Poznanović Spahić, M. M. et al. Natural and anthropogenic sources of chromium, nickel and Cobalt in soils impacted by agricultural and industrial activity (Vojvodina, Serbia). <italic toggle="yes">J. Environ. Sci. Health A</italic>. <bold>54</bold>, 219–230. 10.1080/10934529.2018.1544802 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10934529.2018.1544802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30587075</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR82" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geochemical partitioning and Spatial distribution of heavy metals in soils contaminated by lead smelting</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut</source><year>2022</year><volume>307</volume><fpage>119486</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35595002</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR82" publication-type="journal">Ke, W. et al. Geochemical partitioning and Spatial distribution of heavy metals in soils contaminated by lead smelting. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Pollut</italic>. <bold>307</bold>, 119486. 10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119486 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35595002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envpol.2022.119486</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR83" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geochemical signatures and contamination levels of rare Earth elements in soil profiles controlled by parent rock and soil properties</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</source><year>2025</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2682</fpage><lpage>2697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-025-35925-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39810011</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR83" publication-type="journal">Wu, C. Y. et al. Geochemical signatures and contamination levels of rare Earth elements in soil profiles controlled by parent rock and soil properties. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 2682–2697. 10.1007/s11356-025-35925-3 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-025-35925-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39810011</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR84" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delina</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immobilization of chromium by iron oxides in nickel–cobalt laterite mine tailings</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2025</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>5683</fpage><lpage>5692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.4c05383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40084431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11948461</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR84" publication-type="journal">Delina, R. E. et al. Immobilization of chromium by iron oxides in nickel–cobalt laterite mine tailings. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>59</bold>, 5683–5692. 10.1021/acs.est.4c05383 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40084431</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.est.4c05383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11948461</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR85" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziyaee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geogenic and anthropogenic sources of potentially toxic elements in airborne dust in Northeastern Iran</article-title><source>Aeolian Res.</source><year>2019</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>100540</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aeolia.2019.100540</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR85" publication-type="journal">Ziyaee, A. et al. Geogenic and anthropogenic sources of potentially toxic elements in airborne dust in Northeastern Iran. <italic toggle="yes">Aeolian Res.</italic><bold>41</bold>, 100540. 10.1016/j.aeolia.2019.100540 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR86" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pathways to advancing sustainable practices in industrial solid waste management: unveiling Obstacles and implications</article-title><source>Next Res.</source><year>2025</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>100124</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nexres.2024.100124</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR86" publication-type="journal">Salman, S. et al. Pathways to advancing sustainable practices in industrial solid waste management: unveiling Obstacles and implications. <italic toggle="yes">Next Res.</italic><bold>2</bold>, 100124. 10.1016/j.nexres.2024.100124 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR87" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales Betancourt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toward cleaner transport alternatives: reduction in exposure to air pollutants in a mass public transport</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>7096</fpage><lpage>7106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.1c07004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35333524</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR87" publication-type="journal">Morales Betancourt, R. et al. Toward cleaner transport alternatives: reduction in exposure to air pollutants in a mass public transport. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>56</bold>, 7096–7106. 10.1021/acs.est.1c07004 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35333524</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/acs.est.1c07004</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR88" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ra</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pollution and health risk assessments of potentially toxic elements in the fine-grained particles (10–63 µm and &lt; 10 µm) in road dust from Apia City</article-title><source>Samoa Toxics</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>683</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxics10110683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36422891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9698250</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR88" publication-type="journal">Jeong, H. &amp; Ra, K. Pollution and health risk assessments of potentially toxic elements in the fine-grained particles (10–63 µm and &lt; 10 µm) in road dust from Apia City. <italic toggle="yes">Samoa Toxics</italic>. <bold>10</bold>, 683. 10.3390/toxics10110683 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36422891</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/toxics10110683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9698250</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR89" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Meta-analysis of soil and dust ingestion studies</article-title><source>Environ. Res.</source><year>2024</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>119649</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2024.119649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39048064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12694522</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR89" publication-type="journal">Cohen, J. et al. Meta-analysis of soil and dust ingestion studies. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Res.</italic><bold>261</bold>, 119649. 10.1016/j.envres.2024.119649 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39048064</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envres.2024.119649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12694522</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR90" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjørklund</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chartrand</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aaseth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manganese exposure and neurotoxic effects in children</article-title><source>Environ. Res.</source><year>2017</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2017.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28282629</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR90" publication-type="journal">Bjørklund, G., Chartrand, M. S. &amp; Aaseth, J. Manganese exposure and neurotoxic effects in children. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Res.</italic><bold>155</bold>, 380–384. 10.1016/j.envres.2017.03.003 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28282629</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envres.2017.03.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR91" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caparros-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Childhood chromium exposure and neuropsychological development in children living in two polluted areas in Southern Spain</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut</source><year>2019</year><volume>252</volume><fpage>1550</fpage><lpage>1560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31277024</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR91" publication-type="journal">Caparros-Gonzalez, R. A. et al. Childhood chromium exposure and neuropsychological development in children living in two polluted areas in Southern Spain. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Pollut</italic>. <bold>252</bold>, 1550–1560. 10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.084 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31277024</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.084</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR92" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pujalté</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arsenic and fifteen other metal(loid)s exposure of children living around old mines in the South of France</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</source><year>2025</year><volume>291</volume><fpage>117842</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2025.117842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39919591</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR92" publication-type="journal">Pujalté, I. et al. Arsenic and fifteen other metal(loid)s exposure of children living around old mines in the South of France. <italic toggle="yes">Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf.</italic><bold>291</bold>, 117842. 10.1016/j.ecoenv.2025.117842 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39919591</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2025.117842</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR93" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>EFSA</collab></person-group><article-title>Scientific opinion on the risk to human health related to the presence of nickel in food and drinking water</article-title><source>EFSA J.</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>6268</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2020.6268</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR93" publication-type="journal">EFSA. Scientific opinion on the risk to human health related to the presence of nickel in food and drinking water. <italic toggle="yes">EFSA J.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 6268. 10.2903/j.efsa.2020.6268 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR94" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative assessment of lung and bladder cancer risk and oral exposure to inorganic arsenic: Meta-regression analyses of epidemiological data</article-title><source>Environ. Int.</source><year>2017</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2017.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28625818</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR94" publication-type="journal">Lynch, H. N. et al. Quantitative assessment of lung and bladder cancer risk and oral exposure to inorganic arsenic: Meta-regression analyses of epidemiological data. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Int.</italic><bold>106</bold>, 178–206. 10.1016/j.envint.2017.04.008 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28625818</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envint.2017.04.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR95" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mergen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soylemezoglu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of arsenic levels in human hair by hydride generation atomic absorption spectrometry: A toxicological application</article-title><source>Spectrosc.</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR95" publication-type="journal">Yüksel, B., Mergen, G. &amp; Soylemezoglu, T. Assessment of arsenic levels in human hair by hydride generation atomic absorption spectrometry: A toxicological application. <italic toggle="yes">Spectrosc.</italic><bold>31</bold> (1), 1–5 (2010).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR96" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biological effects of human exposure to environmental cadmium</article-title><source>Biomolecules</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom13010036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36671421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9855641</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR96" publication-type="journal">Peana, M. et al. Biological effects of human exposure to environmental cadmium. <italic toggle="yes">Biomolecules</italic><bold>13</bold>, 36. 10.3390/biom13010036 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36671421</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biom13010036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9855641</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR97" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of lead and mercury levels in maternal blood, fetal cord blood and placenta in pregnancy with intrauterine growth restriction</article-title><source>J. Basic. Clin. Health Sci.</source><year>2022</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30621/jbachs.1008609</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR97" publication-type="journal">Yüksel, D. et al. Assessment of lead and mercury levels in maternal blood, fetal cord blood and placenta in pregnancy with intrauterine growth restriction. <italic toggle="yes">J. Basic. Clin. Health Sci.</italic><bold>6</bold>, 199–205. 10.30621/jbachs.1008609 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR98" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jafari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asadyari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moutab Sahihazar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajaghazadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monte Carlo-based probabilistic risk assessment for cement workers exposed to heavy metals in cement dust</article-title><source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>5961</fpage><lpage>5979</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-023-01611-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37195567</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR98" publication-type="journal">Jafari, A., Asadyari, S., Moutab Sahihazar, Z. &amp; Hajaghazadeh, M. Monte Carlo-based probabilistic risk assessment for cement workers exposed to heavy metals in cement dust. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Geochem. Health</italic>. <bold>45</bold>, 5961–5979. 10.1007/s10653-023-01611-x (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37195567</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10653-023-01611-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR99" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustaoğlu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topaldemir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokatlı</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unveiling the nutritional value and potentially toxic elements in fish species from miliç wetland, türkiye: A probabilistic human health risk assessment using Monte Carlo simulation</article-title><source>Mar. Pollut Bull.</source><year>2025</year><volume>211</volume><fpage>117417</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2024.117417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39642435</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR99" publication-type="journal">Yüksel, B., Ustaoğlu, F., Topaldemir, H., Yazman, M. M. &amp; Tokatlı, C. Unveiling the nutritional value and potentially toxic elements in fish species from miliç wetland, türkiye: A probabilistic human health risk assessment using Monte Carlo simulation. <italic toggle="yes">Mar. Pollut Bull.</italic><bold>211</bold>, 117417. 10.1016/j.marpolbul.2024.117417 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39642435</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2024.117417</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR100" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Speciation and migration of heavy metals in sediment cores of urban wetland: bioavailability and risks</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>23914</fpage><lpage>23925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-08719-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32297118</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR100" publication-type="journal">Shao, S. et al. Speciation and migration of heavy metals in sediment cores of urban wetland: bioavailability and risks. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Sci. Pollut Res.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 23914–23925. 10.1007/s11356-020-08719-y (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-020-08719-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32297118</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR101" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustaoğlu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yüksel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional profiling of Oncorhynchus mykiss from çamlıgöze dam, türkiye: health risk assessment through Monte Carlo simulation and elemental source attribution using positive matrix factorization</article-title><source>Process. Saf. Environ. Prot.</source><year>2025</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>107172</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psep.2025.107172</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR101" publication-type="journal">Yazman, M. M., Ustaoğlu, F. &amp; Yüksel, B. Nutritional profiling of Oncorhynchus mykiss from çamlıgöze dam, türkiye: health risk assessment through Monte Carlo simulation and elemental source attribution using positive matrix factorization. <italic toggle="yes">Process. Saf. Environ. Prot.</italic><bold>198</bold>, 107172. 10.1016/j.psep.2025.107172 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR102" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okoro</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health risk assessments of heavy metals in dust samples collected from classrooms in ilorin, Nigeria and its impact on public health</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2025</year><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e42769</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2025.e42769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40070952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11894315</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR102" publication-type="journal">Okoro, H. K. et al. Health risk assessments of heavy metals in dust samples collected from classrooms in ilorin, Nigeria and its impact on public health. <italic toggle="yes">Heliyon</italic><bold>11</bold> (4), e42769. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2025.e42769 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40070952</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.heliyon.2025.e42769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11894315</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR103" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WHO air quality guidelines 2021 – Aiming for healthier air for all: A joint statement by medical, public health, scientific societies and patient representative organisations</article-title><source>Int. J. Public. Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1604465</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/ijph.2021.1604465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34630006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8494774</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR103" publication-type="journal">Hoffmann, B. et al. WHO air quality guidelines 2021 – Aiming for healthier air for all: A joint statement by medical, public health, scientific societies and patient representative organisations. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Public. Health</italic>. <bold>66</bold>, 1604465. 10.3389/ijph.2021.1604465 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34630006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/ijph.2021.1604465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8494774</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Court of Auditors. Special report 02/2025: Urban pollution in the EU – Cities have cleaner air but are still too noisy. Publications Office of the European Union. (2025). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.eca.europa.eu/ECAPublications/SR-2025-02/SR-2025-02_EN.pdf">https://www.eca.europa.eu/ECAPublications/SR-2025-02/SR-2025-02_EN.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR105" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of urban green spaces on air quality: A study of PM10 reduction across diverse climates</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2024</year><volume>955</volume><fpage>176770</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.176770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39393695</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR105" publication-type="journal">Islam, A. et al. Impact of urban green spaces on air quality: A study of PM10 reduction across diverse climates. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>955</bold>, 176770. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.176770 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39393695</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.176770</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR106"><label>106.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR106" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A framework for assessing the impact of land use policy on community exposure to air toxics</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manage.</source><year>2007</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2006.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16842900</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR106" publication-type="journal">Willis, M. R. &amp; Keller, A. A. A framework for assessing the impact of land use policy on community exposure to air toxics. <italic toggle="yes">J. Environ. Manage.</italic><bold>83</bold>, 213–227. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2006.03.011 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16842900</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jenvman.2006.03.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR107"><label>107.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR107" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental regulation, land use efficiency and industrial structure upgrading: test analysis based on Spatial Durbin model and threshold effect</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e26508</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e26508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38486726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10938079</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR107" publication-type="journal">Hu, Y. &amp; Zheng, C. Environmental regulation, land use efficiency and industrial structure upgrading: test analysis based on Spatial Durbin model and threshold effect. <italic toggle="yes">Heliyon</italic><bold>10</bold> (5), e26508. 10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e26508 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38486726</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e26508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10938079</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>