
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Scand J Trauma Resusc Emerg Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Scand J Trauma Resusc Emerg Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">707</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">sjtrem</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scandinavian Journal of Trauma, Resuscitation and Emergency Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1757-7241</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12613902</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12613902.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12613902</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12613902</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41233838</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13049-025-01498-w</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1498</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Barriers to helicopter emergency medical services in a Haze-Prone, mountainous region of Northern Thailand</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutham</surname><given-names initials="K">Krongkarn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piamanan</surname><given-names initials="P">Prasan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamthip</surname><given-names initials="B">Boonyarit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaewpaengchan</surname><given-names initials="W">Weerapont</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meelarp</surname><given-names initials="N">Nattikarn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wongtanasarasin</surname><given-names initials="W">Wachira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wittayachamnankul</surname><given-names initials="B">Borwon</given-names></name><address><email>borwon.witt@cmu.ac.th</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05m2fqn25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7132.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9039 7662</institution-id><institution>Department of Emergency Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Chiang Mai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chiang Mai, Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05m2fqn25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7132.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9039 7662</institution-id><institution>Department of Emergency Medicine, Nakornping Hospital, </institution><institution>Chiang Mai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chiang Mai, Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05m2fqn25</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7132.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9039 7662</institution-id><institution>Sriphat Medical Center, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>Chiang Mai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Chiang Mai, Thailand </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>33</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478383</issue-id><elocation-id>182</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-15 16:25:14.500"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="13049_2025_Article_1498.pdf"><?pdf-name 13049_2025_Article_1498.pdf?><?pdf-size 1420095?><?pdf-md5 0d89a11391162c1b631948956a934a8b?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:c6ba/12613902/0d89a1139116/13049_2025_Article_1498.pdf?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Study objective</title><p id="Par1">To identify factors associated with the mission outcome (transport completed vs. not transported) of air medical transport (AMT), with particular attention to environmental and operational constraints such as haze-related air pollution.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We conducted a retrospective analysis of all requests to the Northern Thailand Sky Doctor program (SkyDoc) from Jan 1, 2020, to Sept 30, 2024. Patient demographics, mission characteristics, environmental conditions, and operational variables were extracted from program records and merged with daily PM2.5 and PM10 concentrations from the national air quality monitoring network. The primary outcome was mission outcome, defined as transport completed versus not transported. We analyzed factors associated with non-transport.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Among 656 mission requests, 412 (62.8%) were transport and 244 (37.2%) were not transported. Patients were predominantly male (57.2%) with a median age of 49 years (IQR 28–67). The most frequent diagnostic categories were ST-elevation myocardial infarction (32.3%), major trauma (21.2%), and stroke (11.7%). Non-transport was most often due to medical contraindications (25.8%), aircraft or landing-zone unavailability (23.8%), adverse weather (18.9%), and haze-related air pollution (12.7%). Seasonal peaks in not transport were observed from February through April, coinciding with regional surges in particulate matter. In multivariable analysis, twilight-hour requests (16:00–20:00) were associated with non-transport (adjusted OR 0.29; 95% CI 0.13–0.67; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), whereas secondary missions were more likely to be transport than primary missions (adjusted OR 3.51; 1.47–8.40; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Higher PM2.5 concentrations were independently associated with non-transport (adjusted OR 0.99; 0.97–0.99; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.018). PM10 was not associated with outcomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">AMT in northern Thailand is constrained by both medical and environmental factors. Twilight-hour requests, mission type, and PM2.5 concentrations independently influenced mission completion. These findings highlight the need for haze-adapted flight protocols, enhanced forecasting, and system-level strategies to safeguard patient access to aeromedical care during seasonal pollution surges.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s13049-025-01498-w.</p></sec></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="Key points"><title>Key points</title><sec><title>What is already known on this topic</title><p id="Par5">Air Medical Transport (AMT) services are essential for timely access to advanced care in remote and mountainous regions. Operational limitations such as weather, geography, and patient condition are recognized barriers, but the impact of environmental air pollution on aeromedical transport has been poorly studied.</p></sec><sec><title>What this study adds</title><p id="Par6">In northern Thailand, we found that twilight-hour requests, primary missions, and elevated PM2.5 concentrations were independently associated with air medical non-transport. Seasonal haze surges created critical access barriers during periods of heightened clinical demand.</p></sec><sec><title>How this is relevant to clinical practice</title><p id="Par7">These findings highlight the need for haze-adapted flight protocols, improved forecasting systems, and policy interventions to strengthen AMT resilience in environments affected by air pollution and complex terrain.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s13049-025-01498-w.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Air ambulances</kwd><kwd>Emergency medical services</kwd><kwd>Helicopters</kwd><kwd>Air pollution</kwd><kwd>Southeast asia</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Norwegian Air Ambulance Foundation 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par8">Air Medical Transport (AMT) is a crucial component of prehospital care, particularly in rural and remote areas where ground transportation may be delayed or unavailable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. AMT reduces time to definitive care and improves outcomes in time-sensitive emergencies such as trauma, acute coronary syndromes, and stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In Thailand, the Sky Doctor program delivers this essential service across various regions, including the mountainous areas of the north. The team oversees AMT operations in the northern region, coordinating both secondary missions (inter-hospital transfers) and primary missions (scene responses) using helicopter emergency medical services (HEMS) from government sectors. These missions often originate from rural health stations or are activated by village health volunteers, serving as a vital link to higher-level care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">Despite the essential role of air medical services, multiple barriers routinely limit the feasibility of flights [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Globally, these challenges can be categorized into four broad areas. First, resource constraints, such as the limited availability of aircraft and trained personnel, often reduce system responsiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Second, infrastructure barriers including inadequate helipad networks and difficult terrain can delay or prevent access to remote locations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Third, environmental and meteorological factors, including extreme weather [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], snowstorms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], and typhoons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], frequently lead to flight cancellations or delays, as reported in regions such as Alaska, India, and Taiwan. In Northern Thailand, seasonal haze often suppresses HEMS requests, as flight infeasibility is presumed, and patients are managed instead by ground transfer. Lastly, operational inefficiencies, including communication breakdowns and fragmented coordination between agencies, further complicate timely deployment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">In high-income settings, these challenges are often mitigated by robust systems and dedicated fleets. In contrast, Southeast Asia, Thailand specifically, faces unique regional challenges compounded by limited health system resources, fragmented inter-agency coordination, and an underdeveloped data infrastructure. Yet, there has been no systematic investigation into the factors contributing to AMT not completed in Southeast Asia. A clearer understanding of these barriers could inform policy and operational improvements, reduce preventable non-transport, and enhance equity in emergency care delivery. This study aims to identify factors associated with non-transport among requests for AMT in Northern Thailand.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study design and setting</title><p id="Par11">We conducted a retrospective observational study to evaluate factors associated with not-transport AMT requests in Region 1 of Northern Thailand, which encompasses mountainous provinces such as Chiang Mai, Chiang Rai, Mae Hong Son, Nan, and their surrounding areas. The study period spanned from January 1, 2020, to September 30, 2024, using data from the regional Sky Doctor program, an established AMT system. This study was conducted using de-identified retrospective data. Ethical approval by the Research Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, granted a waiver of informed consent (registration number EME-2568-0410). All methods were performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations, including the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study population and data source</title><p id="Par12">All AMT requests recorded through the SkyDoc system during the study period were reviewed. Each record included patient demographics, diagnosis, time and date of request, referring and receiving hospitals, transport outcome (whether transported or not), and stated reasons for non-transport (denial reasons) when applicable. All 656 mission requests recorded during the study period met inclusion criteria and were analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Variable definitions</title><p id="Par13">The age group was classified as follows: Infant (&lt; 1 year), Pediatric (1–15 years), Adult (&gt; 15 years), or Unknown. The province of origin was inferred from referring hospital names.</p><p id="Par14">Air Pollution Data, which were defined as daily PM2.5 and PM10 values, were retrieved from the Pollution Control Department, Thailand, via <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://air4thai.pcd.go.th">https://air4thai.pcd.go.th</ext-link>, and matched to each case by province and date of request. Monitoring station locations were geospatially matched to patient provinces. For each case, the average PM2.5 and PM10 value on the date and location of the request was linked to the patient record. When direct measurements were unavailable, values were imputed from the nearest available station on the same day.</p><p id="Par15">Non-transport cases reasons were categorized based on a structured text review. Each AMT request was evaluated by an on-call aviation medical director (AVD) who is an emergency medicine specialist with expertise in prehospital care. The AVD rendered a decision within 40 min using the CSTAT framework (Contraindications, Safety considerations, Transport team availability, Aircraft status and route feasibility, and Time efficiency compared to ground transport). In this framework, ‘C’ included considerations such as COVID-19 risk, while ‘S’ encompassed weather and air pollution risks. This structured approach, which serves as the standard protocol in this region, ensures consistent, timely, and safety-oriented decision-making.</p><p id="Par16">The reasons for non-transport were extracted from structured text and categorized as follows: Haze-related (high PM2.5/PM10 and visibility limitations), Weather-related (non-haze) (e.g., rain, storm), Lack of aircraft or landing constraints, Medical contraindication, Inappropriate timing (twilight hours (16:00–20:00), crew duty-time limits, overlapping missions, or local curfew restrictions), No time benefit over ground transport, Poor prognosis, Medical team issue and Unspecified. Each case with a non-transport outcome was assigned to a category based on manual review of the reason text. The primary outcome was mission outcome, defined as transport completed versus not transported.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par17">Descriptive statistics summarized patient characteristics. Categorical variables were summarized as counts (%) and continuous variables as medians (IQR). Univariate comparisons used chi-square or Fisher’s exact tests, as appropriate. Variables with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.10 or strong clinical plausibility entered a multivariable logistic regression model. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were reported. In the primary analyses, records were retained and missing values were coded as an explicit ‘Unknown’ category where feasible. To assess robustness, we also conducted sensitivity analyses, which yielded results consistent in direction and magnitude with the primary model. All analyses were performed using Python (Pandas, NumPy, Statsmodels, Seaborn, Matplotlib). A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><p id="Par18">From January 1, 2020, to September 30, 2024, 656 AMT requests were logged by the SkyDoc program; 412 (62.8%) were transport and 244 (37.2%) were non-transported. No cases were excluded (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) Patients were predominantly male (375, 57.2%) with a median age of 49 years (IQR 28–67). Most missions were secondary inter-hospital transfers (524, 79.9%). The most frequent diagnostic categories were ST-elevation myocardial infarction (212, 32.3%), major trauma (139, 21.2%), and stroke (77, 11.7%). The two most common origin provinces were Chiang Mai (377, 57.5%) and Mae Hong Son (265, 40.4%). Survival data are based on available cases only (&gt; 30% missing).</p><p id="Par19">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Case (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 656)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not Transported (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 244)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Transported (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 412)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender -</bold> <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> <bold>(%)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">375 (57.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (53.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">244 (59.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Female</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">197 (30.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">67 (27.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">130 (31.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84 (12.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (18.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (9.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Median age (IQR)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (28–67)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (27–65)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (28–66)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age group -</bold> <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> <bold>(%)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Infant (&lt; 1 year)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24 (3.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (3.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Pediatric (1–15 years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65 (9.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (9.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43 (10.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Adult (&gt; 15 years)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">438 (66.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 (53.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">307 (74.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">129 (19.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83 (34.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46 (11.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Year of Transport</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 2020</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (5.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (4.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 (6.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 2021</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63 (9.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (9.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41 (9.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 2022</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">145 (22.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (20.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96 (23.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 2023</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">252 (38.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97 (39.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">155 (37.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 2024</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">161 (24.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (27.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95 (23.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Type of mission</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Primary mission</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">132 (20.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (18.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87 (21.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Secondary mission</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">524 (79.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">199 (81.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">325 (78.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Time of Request</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 08:00–12:00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">224 (34.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">42 (17.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">182 (44.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 12:00–16:00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">246 (37.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (13.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">212 (51.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 16:00–20:00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39 (6.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21 (8.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18 (4.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147 (22.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">147 (60.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Particulate Matter -</bold> µg/m³, median (IQR)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> PM2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (14–41)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (19–49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (13–35)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> PM10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38 (24–56)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">40 (26–59)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36 (23–55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Origin</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Chiang Mai</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">377 (57.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">157 (64.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">220 (53.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Chiang Rai</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (1.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Lampang</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Lamphun</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Mae Hong Son</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">265 (40.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80 (32.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185 (44.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Nan</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Tak</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2 (0.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Disease</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> STEMI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">212 (32.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66 (27.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146 (35.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Major Trauma</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139 (21.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49 (20.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90 (21.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Stroke</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77 (11.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32 (13.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45 (10.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Respiratory illnesses</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">81 (12.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34 (13.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47 (11.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Cardiac emergencies</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 (3.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (4.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (3.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> GI emergencies</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (2.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (1.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11 (2.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> OB-Gyn emergencies</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (4.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (5.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15 (3.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Neonatal emergencies</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22 (3.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8 (3.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (3.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Aortic emergencies</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (2.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (1.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (2.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Sepsis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19 (2.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (1.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (3.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Neurology Emergencies</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (1.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7 (2.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Other</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (2.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13 (5.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Survival at 24 h</bold>
<sup>†</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">386 (58.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (2.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">380 (92.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Death</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30 (4.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1 (0.4)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29 (7.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">240 (36.6)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">237 (97.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3 (0.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Survival at 72 h</bold>
<sup>†</sup>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">373 (56.9)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (2.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">368 (89.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Death</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (6.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (10.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> unknown</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">244 (37.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">239 (98.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5 (1.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Abbreviations: IQR; Interquartile Range., Age group: Infant (&lt; 1 year), Pediatric (1–15 years), Adult (&gt; 15 years)., Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) are marked with an asterisk (*). Remark: 2024 data cover January–September, †Survival denominators are based on available cases only (&gt; 30% missing), data are exploratory and not part of the primary analysis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par20">Among non-transported requests, leading non-transport categories were medical contraindication (63, 25.8%), lack of aircraft or landing-zone feasibility (58, 23.8%), adverse weather (46, 18.9%), and haze-related air pollution (31/244, 12.7%); inappropriate timing accounted for a further 31 (12.7%) show in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Medical contraindications were further detailed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>.</p><p id="Par21">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Reasons for non-transport (Denial Reasons)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reason Category</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cases (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Percent (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical contraindication</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.82%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lack of aircraft / landing constraints</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.77%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Weather-related (Cloudy, storm, rain)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.85%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Haze-related</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.70%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inappropriate timing</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.70%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poor prognosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.51%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Medical Team Issue</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No time benefit over ground transport</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.41%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Remark: Haze-related and weather-related non-transport were mutually exclusive; in this dataset, days with precipitation/storms did not overlap with haze events; inappropriate timing includes twilight hours, crew duty-time limits, overlapping missions, or curfew</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par22">In multivariable logistic regression (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), three factors were independently associated with transport completion. Requests during twilight hours (16:00–20:00) were less likely to be transport (adjusted OR 0.29, 95% CI 0.13–0.67; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Secondary missions were more likely to be transport than primary missions (adjusted OR 3.51, 1.47–8.40; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Increasing PM2.5 concentration was associated with lower odds of transport (adjusted OR 0.99, 0.97–0.99; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.018). PM10 was not associated with transport (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.40). Sensitivity analyses excluding cases with missing values yielded results consistent with the primary model. Seasonal patterns were evident: non-transport rose between February and April, peaking in March, coincident with higher ambient PM2.5 and PM10 concentrations (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par23">
<table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Logistic regression analysis of factors associated with successful operation of air medical transport</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Univariable</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Multivariable</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OR</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Demographic</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Male (ref: Female)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.66–3.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Age group Child (ref: Adult)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05–2.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Age group Infant (ref: Adult)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05–2.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Diagnosis group</bold> (ref: other diagnoses)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Sepsis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15–1.37</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14–2.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> STEMI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36–1.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.96</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49–1.89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Secondary Mission</bold> (ref: Primary)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.72–4.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.51</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.47–8.40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Time of request</bold> (ref: 8:00–12:00)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> 16:00–20:00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10–0.40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.13–0.67</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt; 0.01*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Other reasons</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Poor prognosis</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05–1.16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02–2.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> PM2.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97–0.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97–0.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> PM10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94–1.17</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: OR = Odds Ratio; CI = Confidence Interval; PM2.5 = Particulate Matter ≤ 2.5 μm; PM10 = Particulate Matter ≤ 10 μm., Ref = Reference, Significant results (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) are marked with an asterisk (*)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par24">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Monthly distribution of air medical transport cases that were not transported due to weather or haze (bars, left y-axis), overlaid with the monthly average concentrations of PM2.5 <italic toggle="yes">(µg/m³)</italic> (red ×) and PM10 <italic toggle="yes">(µg/m³)</italic> (green ×) from 2020 to 2024 (right y-axis). A seasonal peak in non-transported cases is observed in March, coinciding with the highest average PM concentrations. This suggests a potential environmental impact on air medical transport availability; 2024 data represent January–September only</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1348" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="13049_2025_1498_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 13049_2025_1498_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 61618?><?image-md5 b4a095e66fde406a5e1cc21962af5613?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 762?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 254?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c6ba/12613902/b4a095e66fde/13049_2025_1498_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 13049_2025_1498_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 5388?><?thumb-md5 82a08e2cb2544db15cb804654fee36d9?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 76?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c6ba/12613902/82a08e2cb254/13049_2025_1498_Fig1_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par25">This study highlights the multifactorial challenges affecting AMS in a resource-constrained, mountainous region of Northern Thailand. Among all AMT requests approximately one-third were not transported. The leading causes included medical contraindications, limited aircraft or landing zone constraints, adverse weather, and air pollution, particularly seasonal haze. These findings reflect a broader pattern observed in rural and low-resource settings, where patient needs must be balanced against logistical readiness, infrastructure limitations, and environmental hazards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">One of the most striking findings was the high frequency of non-transport due to aircraft unavailability or landing zone. In Thailand, air medical missions are largely dependent on shared resources from the military, police, or governmental agencies, all of which may be unavailable at critical moments due to competing priorities. This contrasts with high-resource settings such as the United States, Germany, and parts of Japan, where dedicated, 24/7 HEMS fleets exist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Compounding this issue is the limited helipad infrastructure, particularly in remote or highland communities. While regional Aeromedical Dispatch Center have made progress by investing in new helipads, development remains slow due to challenges in terrain assessment, land-use negotiation, and first-responder training.</p><p id="Par27">Weather-related and visibility issues were also among the most common reasons for non-transport. Similar to studies conducted in Alaska [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], Australia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and Canada [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], our data confirm that poor weather, including storms, cloud cover, and low light conditions, can frequently prevent safe takeoff or landing, even when aircraft are available. A notable concentration of denied flights occurred between 16:00 and 20:00, corresponding with twilight hours when visual flight becomes increasingly hazardous [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In our cohort, adverse weather alone accounted for nearly one-fifth of denials, underscoring its importance alongside air pollution as a key environmental barrier. Moreover, this figure likely underestimates the true impact of weather, because during rainfall or storms, flight infeasibility is often presumed and requests for HEMS may not be initiated at all. This high frequency underscores that weather remains a major environmental barrier, second only to air pollution, in limiting air medical transport feasibility.</p><p id="Par28">PM2.5, or particulate matter with aerodynamic diameters less than 2.5 microns, poses a critical challenge to helicopter operations, especially in regions reliant on visual flight rules (VFR) such as Northern Thailand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Unlike PM10, PM2.5 particles scatter visible light more efficiently, remain airborne for longer durations, and readily interact with water vapor to form dense haze, thereby reducing visibility below safe operating thresholds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. These ultrafine particles primarily originate from biomass burning, vehicle emissions, and industrial processes, with seasonal surges driven by agricultural fires and transboundary pollution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. During haze seasons, visibility often drops below 3 km, and cloud ceilings fall beneath 1,000 feet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. These environmental conditions can restrict helicopter takeoffs, landings, and operations, especially in mountainous or urban terrain, increasing the likelihood of spatial disorientation and mission cancellations. In the SkyDoc program, AMT missions in this region are frequently withheld when the AQI exceeds 150, which is often a threshold communicated during morning briefings. This has led to some cases being excluded from coordination altogether due to the presumed infeasibility of flight. As a result, the impact of PM2.5 may be underreported in existing data, and its association with non-transport could be even stronger than shown. A particularly vivid incident occurred during the 2015 Southeast Asian haze crisis, when elevated PM2.5 levels grounded both commercial and emergency flights across the region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par29">Globally, AMT systems face a wide spectrum of operational and environmental barriers, though the specific factors vary by geography. For instance, in Latin America, Araiza et al. highlighted that high-altitude conditions and weather-induced risks, compounded by insufficient helipad infrastructure, often impair operational efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Similarly, in resource-limited settings, Johnson and Luscombe pointed to delays in dispatch and coordination gaps as major impediments to timely helicopter response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In India, Singh et al. noted that terrain and extreme altitude presented physical challenges to AMT, but did not report fine particulate air pollution as a significant factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Studies in Alaska and Taiwan also reflect this, identifying harsh weather conditions such as snow, wind, and typhoons as the principal causes of flight delays or cancellations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Our study, however, reveals an additional and largely underrepresented environmental constraint: seasonal exposure to PM2.5. Unlike the broader meteorological variables emphasized in previous literature, fine particulate air pollution in Northern Thailand appears to play a unique role by simultaneously obstructing flight safety and escalating demand for emergency medical services. For example, during haze season, elevated PM2.5 not only limits visibility and cancels missions, but also leads to spikes in emergency department visits for acute coronary syndromes and pneumonia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. This dual burden limited aerial access and increased medical need, which amplifies the vulnerability of populations in remote areas, underscoring the importance of geographically tailored mitigation strategies that account for the health and operational impacts of air pollution. In light of these findings, strengthening AMS resilience in Northern Thailand calls for a coordinated, real-time approach. Building on recent steps that include hourly PM2.5 reporting and route-specific forecasts developed with the Northern Meteorological Center, a national strategy should deploy dedicated Instrument Flight Rules (IFR)-capable fleets for low-visibility operations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], use GIS to target helipad expansion in underserved terrain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and integrate meteorology, air-quality, and aircraft-readiness data into a single dispatch dashboard to streamline mission triage. Haze-adapted flight protocols and IFR training for pilots and dispatchers should be standard, while broader environmental measures remain necessary because seasonal PM2.5 both degrades aviation safety and drives spikes in acute cardiovascular and respiratory illness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. When flight paths cannot avoid haze, crew-safety protocols should include in-flight air-quality monitoring, appropriate protective measures, and timely early warnings.</p><p id="Par30">Additionally, in this study, medical contraindication was the most frequent reason for AMT non-transport. These included patients with non-time-sensitive conditions, or contraindications such as active tuberculosis, COVID-19, untreated pneumothorax, pneumocephalus, or those considered too sick or expectant. Similar findings have been reported. In the Netherlands, over half of HEMS missions were cancelled due to patient reassessment, which was found to be undertriage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], while in Canada, 76% were cancelled due to not meeting trauma criteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Integrating clinical triage tools with real-time environmental data can enhance decision accuracy, ensuring both patient safety and operational efficiency. Future policy should support the development of dynamic protocols that account for both medical and environmental conditions, particularly in resource-limited or high-risk settings.</p><p id="Par31">This study has several limitations. First, as a retrospective study several variables had missing values (e.g., gender, age, time of request), which may reduce representativeness, although sensitivity analyses produced consistent results. Notably, time-of-request missingness clustered in the non-transported group (60.3%). This non-random missingness could distort the observed twilight association; although sensitivity analyses were consistent, readers should interpret this finding with appropriate caution. Second, air quality data were assigned from the nearest monitoring stations and PM2.5 was used as a proxy for visibility in the absence of METAR or VFR/IFR data, so overlap with other weather phenomena cannot be excluded. Third, although PM2.5 was independently associated with overall mission outcome, we were unable to model haze-related denials separately due to the small sample size. Moreover, the observed number of haze-related denials likely underestimates the true effect of air pollution, because during severe haze some requests may never have been initiated at all when flight infeasibility was presumed. This pre-request suppression would bias our estimates toward the null, suggesting that the actual impact of PM2.5 on mission feasibility may be even stronger than observed. Fourth, pandemic-related constraints were not analyzed separately and were coded under broader categories. Fifth, downstream clinical outcomes and survival data (&gt; 30% missing) were not fully assessed and should be interpreted as exploratory.</p><p id="Par32">Future research should adopt prospective designs with real-time data capture to minimize missingness and better characterize mission feasibility. System-level information such as daily call volumes, ground transfers, and organizational responses should be incorporated to clarify the denominator of need during haze seasons. Integrating aeronautical visibility metrics (e.g., METAR reports, VFR/IFR status) with spatio-temporal air pollution models may improve exposure assessment. Finally, linking mission outcomes with downstream clinical outcomes will provide a more comprehensive understanding of the impact of non-transport on patient care.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par33">AMT in Northern Thailand is significantly hindered by a combination of environmental hazards, limited infrastructure, and operational constraints. Seasonal haze and elevated PM2.5 levels emerged as key predictors of non-transport, along with twilight-hour mission requests and limited aircraft availability. Improving equitable access to AMT in this region requires a coordinated strategy that includes environmental surveillance, dedicated air fleets with IFR capability, infrastructure development, and policy reform. Addressing these barriers is essential not only for enhancing emergency care access, but also for building a resilient and environmentally adaptive emergency medical system.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="13049_2025_1498_MOESM1_ESM.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name 13049_2025_1498_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?suppdata-size 15020?><?suppdata-md5 d49d301c3d0a57019653baca4b385046?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:c6ba/12613902/d49d301c3d0a/13049_2025_1498_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors sincerely thank the Wiengping Dispatch Center and the EMS Unit of Maharaj Nakorn Chiang Mai Hospital for their valuable support in data collection. We also extend our appreciation to the Military and Police Aviation Units for their flight operations, and to the National Institute of Emergency Medicine for supporting transportation costs. Special thanks are due to the Health Region I Sky Doctor Team for their collaboration in developing this project. We gratefully acknowledge Miss Rudklao Sairai and her colleagues from the Research Unit, Department of Emergency Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University, for their kind assistance and facilitation throughout this study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>BW, KS: contributed to the conceptualization, methodology, formal analysis, investigation, data curation, writing – original draft, writing – review and editing, and visualization. PP, BK, NM: contributed to the conceptualization, methodology, software use, validation, formal analysis, investigation, and data curation. WK, WW: contributed to the formal analysis, writing – original draft, writing – review and editing, and supervision. This manuscript has been read and finally approved by all the authors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par34">None.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3"><title>Patient and public involvement</title><p id="Par35">Patient and public involvement was integral to the design, execution, and dissemination of this study. In recognition of the importance of the incorporation of patient perspectives and to ensure the relevance of our research, we engaged with patients and members of the public at multiple stages of the research process.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="Par36">This study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Medicine, Chiang Mai University (Protocol No. EME-2568-0410). Given the retrospective nature of the study and the use of de-identified records, the requirement for individual informed consent was waived by the committee. All procedures were conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and relevant institutional guidelines.</p></notes><notes id="FPar5"><title>Clinical trial number</title><p id="Par37">not applicable.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galvagno</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sikorski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirshon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Helicopter emergency medical services for adults with major trauma</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><year>2015</year><volume>2015</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>CD009228</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD009228.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26671262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8627175</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Galvagno SM, Sikorski R, Hirshon JM, et al. Helicopter emergency medical services for adults with major trauma. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;2015(12):CD009228. 10.1002/14651858.CD009228.pub3<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26671262</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD009228.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8627175</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brown JB, Stassen NA, Bankey PE, Sangosanya AT, Cheng JD, Gestring ML. Helicopters and the civilian trauma system: national utilization patterns demonstrate improved outcomes after traumatic injury. <italic toggle="yes">J Trauma</italic>. 2010;69(5):1030–1034; discussion 1034–1036. 10.1097/TA.0b013e3181f6f450<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/TA.0b013e3181f6f450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21068607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An Evidence-based guideline for the air medical transportation of prehospital trauma patients</article-title><source>Prehosp Emerg Care</source><year>2014</year><volume>18</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10903127.2013.844872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24279767</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Thomas SH, Brown KM, Oliver ZJ, et al. An Evidence-based guideline for the air medical transportation of prehospital trauma patients. Prehosp Emerg Care. 2014;18(Suppl 1):35–44. 10.3109/10903127.2013.844872<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24279767</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/10903127.2013.844872</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puckett</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dissanaike</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Helicopter versus ground ambulance: review of National database for outcomes in survival in transferred trauma patients in the USA</article-title><source>Trauma Surg Acute Care Open</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e000211</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/tsaco-2018-000211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31058235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6461140</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Michaels D, Pham H, Puckett Y, Dissanaike S. Helicopter versus ground ambulance: review of National database for outcomes in survival in transferred trauma patients in the USA. Trauma Surg Acute Care Open. 2019;4(1):e000211. 10.1136/tsaco-2018-000211<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31058235</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/tsaco-2018-000211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6461140</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rzońca</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gałązkowski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wójcik-Fatla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panasiuk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotlib</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Missions of the helicopter emergency medical service in rural and urban areas in Poland - A comparative retrospective analysis</article-title><source>Ann Agric Environ Med AAEM</source><year>2019</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26444/aaem/106223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31232071</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Rzońca P, Gałązkowski R, Wójcik-Fatla A, Panasiuk L, Gotlib J. Missions of the helicopter emergency medical service in rural and urban areas in Poland - A comparative retrospective analysis. Ann Agric Environ Med AAEM. 2019;26(2):355–60. 10.26444/aaem/106223<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31232071</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.26444/aaem/106223</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Federal Aviation Administration. Chapter 9: Aeromedical Factors. In: Balloon Flying Handbook: FAA-H-8083-11B. Department of Transportation, Federal Aviation Administration. 2017. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.faa.gov/regulations_policies/handbooks_manuals/aviation/Balloon_Flying_Handbook_FAA-H-8083-11B/bfh_chapter_9.pdf">https://www.faa.gov/regulations_policies/handbooks_manuals/aviation/Balloon_Flying_Handbook_FAA-H-8083-11B/bfh_chapter_9.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Araiza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aeromedical transport of critically ill patients: A literature review</article-title><source>Cureus</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e14889</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.14889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34109078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8180199</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Araiza A, Duran M, Surani S, Varon J. Aeromedical transport of critically ill patients: A literature review. Cureus. 2021;13(5):e14889. 10.7759/cureus.14889<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34109078</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7759/cureus.14889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8180199</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wachtel</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aeromedical transport of the mechanically ventilated patient</article-title><source>J Intensive Care Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/088506669701200604</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Wachtel AS, Allen HN, Lewis MI. Aeromedical transport of the mechanically ventilated patient. J Intensive Care Med. 1997;12(6):310–5. 10.1177/088506669701200604</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aeromedical evacuation of the trauma patient</article-title><source>Trauma</source><year>1999</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/146040869900100102</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Lockey D, Weller R. Aeromedical evacuation of the trauma patient. Trauma. 1999;1(1):12–22. 10.1177/146040869900100102</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Löfstedt</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Missonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new Approach—The World-Wide Air-Medical transport service network</article-title><source>Prehospital Disaster Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>13</volume><issue>S1</issue><fpage>S14</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1049023X00038292</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Löfstedt TJ, Missonen J. A new Approach—The World-Wide Air-Medical transport service network. Prehospital Disaster Med. 1998;13(S1):S14–5. 10.1017/S1049023X00038292</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Air medical casualty evacuation in high altitude: an experience of 100 cases in high altitude and hilly terrain of Northern India</article-title><source>J Med Sci Health</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46347/jmsh.v8i2.21.54</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Singh S, Singh D, Thakur H, Bhardwaj A, Chawla VC. Air medical casualty evacuation in high altitude: an experience of 100 cases in high altitude and hilly terrain of Northern India. J Med Sci Health. 2022;8(2):134–8. 10.46347/jmsh.v8i2.21.54</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luscombe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aeromedical transfer of the critically ill patient</article-title><source>J Intensive Care Soc</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/175114371101200412</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Johnson D, Luscombe M. Aeromedical transfer of the critically ill patient. J Intensive Care Soc. 2011;12(4):307–12. 10.1177/175114371101200412</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Problems of immediate medical care at Taipei community hospitals during typhoon Nari, 2001</article-title><source>Prehospital Disaster Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>17</volume><issue>S1</issue><fpage>S21</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1049023X00059045</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Chiang WC, Shih FY, Chang KJ, Chen WJ. Problems of immediate medical care at Taipei community hospitals during typhoon Nari, 2001. Prehospital Disaster Med. 2002;17(S1):S21–21. 10.1017/S1049023X00059045</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O’Meara</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tourle</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stirling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extending the paramedic role in rural australia: a story of flexibility and innovation</article-title><source>Rural Remote Health</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1978</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22497586</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">O’Meara PF, Tourle V, Stirling C, Walker J, Pedler D. Extending the paramedic role in rural australia: a story of flexibility and innovation. Rural Remote Health. 2012;12(2):1978.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22497586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Survey. and analysis of air transportation safety among air carrier operators and pilots in Alaska. Accessed April 26, 2025. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/11426">https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/11426</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Collision with terrain involving a Robinson R44, 13 km north of Thredbo, New South Wales on 13 October 2024 | ATSB. Accessed April 28. 2025. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.atsb.gov.au/publications/occurrence-briefs/2024/aviation/collision-terrain-involving-robinson-r44-13-km-north-thredbo-new-south-wales-13-october-2024">https://www.atsb.gov.au/publications/occurrence-briefs/2024/aviation/collision-terrain-involving-robinson-r44-13-km-north-thredbo-new-south-wales-13-october-2024</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhattacharya S, Publishing CI, for KD. Impact of Weather Conditions on Neonatal Transport in Ontario: A Retrospective Cohort Study. <italic toggle="yes">Can J Med CJM</italic>. Published online January 1, 2024. Accessed April 28, 2025. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.academia.edu/121073399/Impact_of_Weather_Conditions_on_Neonatal_Transport_in_Ontario_A_Retrospective_Cohort_Study">https://www.academia.edu/121073399/Impact_of_Weather_Conditions_on_Neonatal_Transport_in_Ontario_A_Retrospective_Cohort_Study</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>FAC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochieng</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Night-time offshore helicopter operations: a survey of risk levels per phase of flight, flying recency requirement and visual approach technique</article-title><source>Aeronaut J</source><year>2015</year><volume>119</volume><issue>1222</issue><fpage>1475</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0001924000011362</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Nascimento FAC, Majumdar A, Ochieng WY, Schuster W. Night-time offshore helicopter operations: a survey of risk levels per phase of flight, flying recency requirement and visual approach technique. Aeronaut J. 2015;119(1222):1475–98. 10.1017/S0001924000011362</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amnuaylojaroen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaewkanchanawong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panpeng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution and meteorological control of PM2.5 and its effect on visibility in Northern Thailand</article-title><source>Atmosphere</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>538</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/atmos14030538</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Amnuaylojaroen T, Kaewkanchanawong P, Panpeng P. Distribution and meteorological control of PM2.5 and its effect on visibility in Northern Thailand. Atmosphere. 2023;14(3):538. 10.3390/atmos14030538</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations based on near-surface visibility in the Northern hemisphere from 1959 to 2022</article-title><source>Earth Syst Sci Data</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>4051</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/essd-16-4051-2024</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Hao H, Wang K, Wu G, Liu J, Li J. PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations based on near-surface visibility in the Northern hemisphere from 1959 to 2022. Earth Syst Sci Data. 2024;16(9):4051–76. 10.5194/essd-16-4051-2024</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang J, Zhao P, Wang X, et al. Main factors influencing winter visibility at the Xinjin flight college of the civil aviation flight university of China. Adv Meteorol. 2020;2020. 10.1155/2020/8899750</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inlaung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chotamonsak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macatangay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surapipith</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of transboundary PM2.5 from biomass burning in Northern Thailand using the WRF-Chem model</article-title><source>Toxics</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>462</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxics12070462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39058114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11280843</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Inlaung K, Chotamonsak C, Macatangay R, Surapipith V. Assessment of transboundary PM2.5 from biomass burning in Northern Thailand using the WRF-Chem model. Toxics. 2024;12(7):462. 10.3390/toxics12070462<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39058114</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/toxics12070462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11280843</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying the relationship between PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration, visibility and planetary boundary layer height for long-lasting haze and fog–haze mixed events in Beijing</article-title><source>Atmospheric Chem Phys</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/acp-18-203-2018</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Luan T, Guo X, Guo L, Zhang T. Quantifying the relationship between PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration, visibility and planetary boundary layer height for long-lasting haze and fog–haze mixed events in Beijing. Atmospheric Chem Phys. 2018;18(1):203–25. 10.5194/acp-18-203-2018</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visibility: science and regulation</article-title><source>J Air Waste Manag Assoc 1995</source><year>2002</year><volume>52</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10473289.2002.10470813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12074426</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Watson JG. Visibility: science and regulation. J Air Waste Manag Assoc 1995. 2002;52(6):628–713. 10.1080/10473289.2002.10470813<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10473289.2002.10470813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12074426</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Seinfeld JH, Pandis SN. <italic toggle="yes">Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics: From Air Pollution to Climate Change</italic>. 3rd edition. Wiley; 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ICAO Safety Management Manual Doc 9859 | SKYbrary Aviation Safety. Accessed April 18. 2025. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://skybrary.aero/articles/icao-safety-management-manual-doc-9859">https://skybrary.aero/articles/icao-safety-management-manual-doc-9859</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Surit</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wongtanasarasin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boonnag</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wittayachamnankul</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between air quality index and effects on emergency department visits for acute respiratory and cardiovascular diseases</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e0294107</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0294107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37972204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10653395</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Surit P, Wongtanasarasin W, Boonnag C, Wittayachamnankul B. Association between air quality index and effects on emergency department visits for acute respiratory and cardiovascular diseases. PLoS ONE. 2023;18(11):e0294107. 10.1371/journal.pone.0294107<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37972204</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0294107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10653395</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Helicopter low level route operations in controlled and uncontrolled airspace | EUROCONTROL. June 28. 2023. Accessed May 3, 2025. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.eurocontrol.int/publication/helicopter-low-level-route-operations-controlled-and-uncontrolled-airspace">https://www.eurocontrol.int/publication/helicopter-low-level-route-operations-controlled-and-uncontrolled-airspace</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maraş</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dönmez</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emecen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GIS-Based determination of the optimal heliport and water source locations for forest fire suppression using Multi-Objective programming</article-title><source>Aerospace</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>305</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/aerospace10030305</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Maraş EE, Dönmez K, Emecen Y. GIS-Based determination of the optimal heliport and water source locations for forest fire suppression using Multi-Objective programming. Aerospace. 2023;10(3):305. 10.3390/aerospace10030305</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berkeveld</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sierkstra</surname><given-names>TCN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schober</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of helicopter emergency medical services (HEMS) dispatch cancellations during a six-year period in a Dutch HEMS region</article-title><source>BMC Emerg Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>50</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12873-021-00439-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33863280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8052688</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Berkeveld E, Sierkstra TCN, Schober P, et al. Characteristics of helicopter emergency medical services (HEMS) dispatch cancellations during a six-year period in a Dutch HEMS region. BMC Emerg Med. 2021;21(1):50. 10.1186/s12873-021-00439-x<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33863280</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12873-021-00439-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8052688</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Canceled air ambulance trauma scene calls: A prospective observational study of causes and outcomes of trauma Auto-launch cancellations</article-title><source>Air Med J</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amj.2022.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36153139</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Zhang T, Baumber B, Smith JA, et al. Canceled air ambulance trauma scene calls: A prospective observational study of causes and outcomes of trauma Auto-launch cancellations. Air Med J. 2022;41(5):435–41. 10.1016/j.amj.2022.07.004<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36153139</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.amj.2022.07.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>