
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><?da-xref-anchor-style superscripted?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12948998</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12948998.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12948998</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12948998</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41656328</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-026-39305-w</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">39305</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>GEMS satellite data fusion for hourly air quality prediction in Taiwan</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="WH">Wei-Han</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names initials="TC">Ta-Chien</given-names></name><address><email>tachien@sinica.edu.tw</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05bqach95</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.19188.39</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0546 0241</institution-id><institution>Institute of Health Data Analytics and Statistics, College of Public Health, </institution><institution>National Taiwan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Taipei, Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05bxb3784</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.28665.3f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2287 1366</institution-id><institution>Research Center for Humanities and Social Sciences, </institution><institution>Academia Sinica, </institution></institution-wrap>128 Academia Road, Section 2, Nankang, Taipei, 115 Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00se2k293</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.260539.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2059 7017</institution-id><institution>Institute of Public Health, School of Medicine, </institution><institution>National Yang Ming Chiao Tung University, </institution></institution-wrap>Taipei, Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/032d4f246</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412449.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9678 1884</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Health, College of Public Health, </institution><institution>China Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Taichung campus, Taichung, Taiwan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00mjawt10</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412036.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0531 9758</institution-id><institution>School of Medicine, College of Medicine, </institution><institution>National Sun Yat-sen University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kaohsiung, Taiwan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503847</issue-id><elocation-id>7766</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>08</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-03-01 00:25:13.187"><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41598_2026_Article_39305.pdf"><?pdf-name 41598_2026_Article_39305.pdf?><?pdf-size 3570478?><?pdf-md5 897ec1df81a13cc86f46b20e97e6c75d?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:17dc/12948998/897ec1df81a1/41598_2026_Article_39305.pdf?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="unstructured"><p id="Par1">Accurately assessing the health risks of air pollution remains challenging owing to the limited spatial coverage of ground-based monitoring stations. Geostationary satellites, such as the Geostationary Environment Monitoring Spectrometer (GEMS), provide unprecedented opportunities for real-time large-scale air quality surveillance. This study integrated multi-source data, including GEMS satellite observations, ground monitoring data, meteorological variables, and geographic information to predict daytime hourly concentrations of six key air pollutants (particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 2.5 μm [PM₂.₅], particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 10 μm [PM₁₀], O₃, NO₂, CO, and SO₂) across Taiwan. A multi-output categorical gradient boosting (CatBoost) model was developed to simultaneously estimate the concentrations of all six pollutants within a single framework. To enhance the robustness and operational relevance of the model, a rolling prediction approach was employed for training and validation. The model demonstrated strong predictive performance, with R² values of 0.86 (O₃), 0.84 (PM₁₀), 0.81 (PM₂.₅ and NO₂), 0.79 (CO), and 0.52 (SO₂), and mean absolute error (MAE) values ranging from 0.06 to 9.40. O₃ predictions were particularly stable, exhibiting relatively low root mean squared error (RMSE) and MAE values. A spatial comparison of predicted and observed concentrations from July‒December 2023 revealed strong concordance, although some localized discrepancies were observed. Overall, the model effectively captured complex spatiotemporal pollutant dynamics. These findings demonstrated that integrating GEMS observations with multisource data in a machine-learning framework enabled accurate, real-time, hourly predictions of multiple air pollutants and offers a scalable solution to support public health policy and exposure risk assessment.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Air quality forecasting</kwd><kwd>GEMS</kwd><kwd>Machine learning</kwd><kwd>Data fusion</kwd><kwd>Multi-output model</kwd><kwd>Multi-pollutants</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Climate sciences</kwd><kwd>Environmental sciences</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100020595</institution-id><institution>National Science and Technology Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NSTC 114-2628-M-001-012-MY3</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>Ta-Chien</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature Limited 2026</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Rapid urbanization and industrial expansion have intensified air pollution, posing serious threats to human health and environmental quality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. According to the Air Quality Annual Report of R.O.C. (Taiwan), 2024, the annual average PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration measured by Taiwan’s air quality automated monitoring stations was <inline-formula id="IEq1"><tex-math id="d33e255"><?equation-image-name d33e255.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 f36d4f36410e4ae09006b2122b3004ef?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/f36d4f36410e/d33e255.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:14.1\pm\:3.5$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> µg/m³<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, frequently exceeding the World Health Organization’s interim air quality target of 10 µg/m³<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. This intensification of air pollution poses a serious threat to human health, as research has concluded that long-term (30-year) exposure to PM<sub>2.5</sub> is associated with elevated risk of adenocarcinoma lung cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. The current air quality monitoring network consists of 80 ground stations (77 main islands and 3 outlying islands) that record hourly measurements of 6 pollutants: PM<sub>2.5</sub>, particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 10 μm (PM<sub>10</sub>), sulfur dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub>), nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>), carbon monoxide (CO), and ozone (O<sub>3</sub>). Most monitoring stations are concentrated in urban centers and industrial corridors, leaving some regions without direct measurements<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. This spatial imbalance makes it challenging to obtain a comprehensive, real-time understanding of air quality across the entire island.</p><p id="Par3">Owing to the limited coverage of ground stations, there is an increasing need for alternative methods to observe air quality. Satellite remote sensing has become a powerful tool to fill this gap by offering a wide-area view of atmospheric pollutants. Satellites can measure air quality in areas where ground monitors are lacking. Consequently, satellite data have become an essential complement to ground-based measurements for building a more complete picture of air pollution distribution. The satellite data used in this study were obtained from the Geostationary Environment Monitoring Spectrometer (GEMS), which was launched in February, 2020 aboard the Geostationary Korea Multi-Purpose Satellite 2 (GEO-KOMPSAT-2). Featuring ultra-violet–visible spectrometers with sub-nanometer spectral resolution and advanced retrieval algorithms, GEMS is capable of accurately estimating the column amounts of key atmospheric pollutants, including O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, formaldehyde (HCHO), glyoxal (CHOCHO), and aerosols. Most satellites in a low-Earth orbit can capture only one or two glimpses of the same spot each day. In contrast, the GEMS remains fixed over a specific region, enabling continuous observation of air pollution changes throughout the day with a much greater temporal resolution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. This type of continuous data is a game-changer for improving forecasts and understanding the behavior of pollutants in the atmosphere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">However, relying solely on satellite observations introduces notable constraints when forecasting ground-level air quality. These sensors derive pollutant burdens from optical signals rather than directly measuring surface concentrations, and thick cloud cover or darkness can interrupt the data stream. The GEMS has undeniably widened the temporal and spatial coverage; however, orbital retrievals cannot match the capabilities of in situ instruments for capturing neighborhood-scale fluctuations. Recognizing this tradeoff, researchers advocate embedding satellite, aircraft, and ground measurements within a stereoscopic three-dimensional monitoring framework to obtain a more reliable picture of atmospheric pollution ​<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Recent studies have demonstrated that combining satellite observations with meteorological data can significantly enhance pollutant forecasting<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Many researchers have applied machine learning to merge satellite, weather, and geographic information for air quality prediction. These models excel at capturing complex nonlinear relationships. However, most efforts still target a single pollutant (often PM<sub>2.5</sub>) and ignore how major pollutants interact under the same meteorological conditions. Building separate models for each pollutant not only duplicates work but also fails to capitalize on their physical connections.</p><p id="Par6">Specifically, studies utilizing Himawari-8 data have successfully modeled hourly concentrations of individual pollutants, such as PM<sub>2.5</sub> and O<sub>3</sub>, by employing algorithms ranging from ensemble tree-based models to deep forest architectures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Expanding beyond single-pollutant approaches, Yang et al. (2023) applied a multi-output random forest (MORF) model to GEMS spectral data to simultaneously retrieve six air pollutant criteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Recent research has explored specific applications of geostationary satellite data. For example, Chimla et al. (2025) demonstrated the effectiveness of integrating WRF-Chem model outputs with GEMS and ground-based observations to enhance PM<sub>2.5</sub> prediction accuracy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. O et al. (2025) utilized GEMS AOD products to validate the sensor’s capability for high-resolution PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> monitoring<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Zhang et al. (2025) developed specialized artificial intelligence techniques for air quality forecasting by utilizing Himawari-8 and meteorological data to demonstrate the potential of geostationary satellite observations in the predictive domain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. He et al. (2024) focused on hourly surface NO<sub>2</sub> estimation using GEMS, emphasizing the importance of evaluating model reliability in spatial estimation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Despite these advancements in model architecture and spatial assessment, a critical methodological gap remains regarding the validation of time-series models.When evaluating models for time-series data, conventional cross-validation methods that randomly split the dataset risk, leaking temporal information, can potentially lead to overly optimistic performance estimates. Standard k-fold cross-validation assumes that the data points are independent, a premise challenged by time-series data such as air quality, as highlighted by Bergmeir et al. (2014). These datasets typically exhibit autocorrelation, meaning that the value at a given time is related to its preceding and succeeding values. Consequently, randomly partitioning a dataset for cross validation without considering its temporal structure can inadvertently include future information within the training set relative to the test set, thereby causing data leakage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">Another research group conducted short-term air pollution forecasting using multi-pollutant data from Delhi and India. They collected and processed pollutant concentrations (PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, and O<sub>3</sub>) and meteorological information (e.g., wind speed, wind direction, humidity, and solar radiation) from various monitoring stations. Different temporal and spatial models were trained and evaluated, including Conv2D+ Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM), ConvLSTM1D, SGCN+LSTM, and several variants of a spatiotemporal graph convolutional network (STGCN) proposed in their study. All models were assessed on the same dataset to predict pollutant concentrations for the following 1, 24, and 48 h using the root mean squared error (RMSE), mean absolute error (MAE), and mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) as comparative metrics. The overall training process employed a sliding window approach (e.g., using the previous 24 h of data to predict future periods). Following effective integration of the graph structure and temporal features, a final evaluation was performed on the test set to validate the accuracy and stability of each model under multistep forecasting scenarios<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">The STGCN model variants introduced in this study, particularly STGCN-B and STGCN-C, demonstrated superior performance compared with other baseline models in most scenarios. Considering the univariate prediction of PM<sub>2.5</sub> in Delhi as an example, STGCN-C achieved the lowest MAE (9.18) and RMSE (12.54) for the 1-h ahead forecast. Although the errors for all models inevitably increased with longer prediction horizons (24 and 48 h), the STGCN models maintained relatively higher accuracy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">Nevertheless, this study had certain limitations. Common to many predictive models, forecasting accuracy diminishes as the prediction time increases, reducing the reliability of longer-term forecasts &gt; 48 h. Furthermore, the research relied solely on data from specific monitoring stations. This means that the model predictions are confined to these sites and their immediate surroundings, unlike satellite remote-sensing data such as GEMS, which can provide spatially continuous, gridded predictions covering the entire region. The model cannot directly estimate air quality conditions in areas lacking monitoring stations because the density and placement of the ground-based network inherently limit its spatial representativeness.</p><p id="Par10">Previous local research in Taiwan relied on ground-based monitoring stations operated by the Taiwan Air Quality Monitoring Network (TAQMN) to obtain reliable air quality measurements. The TAQMN, managed by Taiwan’s Environmental Protection Administration, provides high-quality PM<sub>2.5</sub> measurements at 77 monitoring stations across the island<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. However, conventional air quality monitoring has been conducted at a limited number of fixed locations using expensive measuring equipment, resulting in sparse spatial air quality data that do not adequately represent the actual air quality conditions of entire regions, particularly when pollution hotspots are overlooked<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">The limited number and uneven placement of monitoring stations make it challenging to capture detailed variations in urban air pollution. Although official stations are reliable, their high cost prevents the dense deployment required for high-resolution air quality assessment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. This spatial coverage limitation has been recognized as a fundamental constraint that necessitates development of complementary monitoring approaches to enhance the understanding of air quality patterns in the diverse urban landscapes in Taiwan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par12">To overcome this limitation, recent studies in Taiwan have focused on integrating multisource data to enhance the resolution and coverage of air quality estimations. A significant trend involves combining station data with deployment of low-cost microsensors such as Airbox. With their potential for low-cost, high-density deployment, these sensors offer a means by which to fill the spatial gaps left by existing monitoring networks. For example, Ho et al. (2020) employed a semiparametric additive model, integrating data from ground stations, meteorology, land use, and Airbox sensors (as nonlinear predictors) to successfully estimate daily PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations on a 3 × 3-km grid across Taiwan. Their study demonstrated that incorporating Airbox data significantly improved the model’s R<sup>2</sup> value from 0.40 to 0.87. They also estimated long-term PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure from 2006 to 2017 using a hindcasting approach, with cross-validation results indicating a monthly root mean squared prediction error of &lt; 5 µg/m³<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par13">However, the data quality of Airbox remains a significant challenge. Compared to standard instruments, Airbox measurements are unreliable and require calibrations, and can be affected by environmental interference or improper installation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Consequently, using raw Airbox data directly may introduce bias. To address this issue, Lin et al. (2020) proposed a spatiotemporal data fusion framework based on optimal linear data fusion to address this issue. This method integrates high-precision data from ground stations with high-density data from Airbox sensors using weighted averaging. The approach dynamically adjusts the weight based on data variance to achieve more reliable spatiotemporal PM<sub>2.5</sub> estimates than either source alone. Their validation yielded an R<sup>2</sup> value of 0.89, which effectively improved the spatial resolution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par14">In addition to data fusion, researchers have employed geospatial artificial intelligence (Geo-AI) methods to incorporate a broader range of geospatial information. Wong et al. (2024) developed a Geo-AI stacking ensemble model that integrated ground station data, kriging-interpolated PM<sub>2.5</sub> data, meteorological data, land-use information, road density, and distances to point sources such as incinerators. This model specifically estimated PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration changes during peak commuting hours in Taiwan (07:00‒09:00 and 16:00‒18:00) at a high spatial resolution of 50 × 50 m. The model achieved R<sup>2</sup> values ranging from 0.93 to 0.95, employed SHAP analysis to assess variable importance, and was validated using a 10-fold cross-validation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par15">These studies demonstrate notable advances in PM<sub>2.5</sub> estimation accuracy and in both spatial and temporal resolution, through integration of ground-based stations, microsensors, geospatial data, and geostatistical or machine-learning models. However, there remains scope for improvement in the methodologies employed in previous studies.</p><p id="Par16">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par17"><italic toggle="yes">Multi-source integration:</italic> Previous research focused on integrating ground-level measurements, such as those from monitoring stations and Airbox sensors, with geographical and meteorological data. Ho et al. (2020) mentioned that the limitations of satellite aerosol optical depth (AOD), including issues such as cloud obstruction and high temporal resolution (hourly) observations from geostationary satellites such as GEMS, are not yet available. Currently, GEMS provides a wide-area view of multiple gaseous pollutants (O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SO<sub>2</sub>) and aerosol optical characteristics. This capability presents an opportunity to capture regional features or integrated photochemical signals that may be overlooked by ground monitoring, thereby providing supplementary distinct dimensional information for modeling.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par18"><italic toggle="yes">Coverage of pollutant forecasting</italic>: Existing literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> has focused on modeling pollutants as independent target variables. For instance, early studies leveraged MODIS observations to establish long-term records of AOD-based PM<sub>2.5</sub>, dating back to 2001<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Subsequently, research utilizing the TROPOMI instrument on Sentinel-5P focused on refining the spatial precision of ground-level PM<sub>2.5</sub> estimates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, while studies employing Himawari-8/9 exploited high-frequency observations (10-minute intervals) to capture diurnal PM<sub>2.5</sub> variations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. However, multiple air pollutants, including PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub> O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, and CO, share common emission sources and are influenced by similar atmospheric conditions. These substances are interconnected via complex physical and chemical interactions. As a result, modeling them in isolation may overlook their critical interdependence.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19"><italic toggle="yes">Temporal validation</italic>: Although cross-validation is a commonly used technique, it is not well-suited for time-series forecasting. Rolling forecast validation more accurately simulates real-world prediction scenarios. This method effectively evaluates the generalization ability and stability of a model when facing future, unseen data and helps prevent potential data leakage.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par20">Building on the limitations identified in previous studies, our approach integrated hourly satellite remote-sensing data, ground-based monitoring stations, meteorological variables, and geographical information to predict hourly daytime concentrations of air pollutants. We employed the categorical gradient boosting (CatBoost) algorithm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, leveraged its native multi-output capability to simultaneously estimate the hourly levels of six major pollutants. This not only enhances computational efficiency but also enables the model to capture the interdependence among pollutants. Our approach aimed to overcome the spatial and temporal constraints of conventional monitoring networks and deliver more accurate high-resolution forecasts of local air quality.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Datasets</title><p id="Par21">The dataset integrated multiple sources to ensure that it accurately reflected the variation in air pollutant levels across Taiwan in both space and time. Our primary satellite input was the GEMS level 2 aerosol product, which has a nominal spatial resolution of 3.5 km × 8 km based on observations over the Seoul area. It provides detailed information on aerosol concentrations and radiative effects. For the meteorological context and background conditions, we also incorporated the European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) Reanalysis v5 dataset, specifically the ERA5-Land product (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets/reanalysis-era5-land">https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets/reanalysis-era5-land</ext-link>), with a spatial resolution of 0.1° × 0.1°<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">Additionally, we incorporated meteorological station data from the Taiwan Central Weather Administration along with the corresponding geographic information for these stations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. This step was crucial as it provided real-time ground-level meteorological parameters, significantly aiding the capture of local climatic features within the study area. Data on the concentrations of the six primary air pollutants were sourced from historical hourly monitoring records of<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the ultraviolet (UV) index data were obtained directly from the real-time UV monitoring system at the Lulin Atmospheric Background Station<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. A summary flowchart of this study is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par23">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Workflow of the study. GEMS - Geostationary Environment Monitoring Spectrometer; ERA5 - European Center for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) Reanalysis v5; CatBoost - categorical gradient boosting.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e574" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2026_39305_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 87170?><?image-md5 ef557d125161de7517dbcb8d41ddbf45?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2363?><?image-original-width 1866?><?image-scaled-height 945?><?image-scaled-width 746?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/ef557d125161/41598_2026_39305_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 3840?><?thumb-md5 f21e80dfa51925f1fe1da1e0d31e43df?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 127?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/f21e80dfa519/41598_2026_39305_Fig1_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Code availability</title><p id="Par24">The model training code and an example dataset are publicly available in an open-access repository at Zenodo (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/records/18291547">https://zenodo.org/records/18291547</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Data preprocessing</title><p id="Par25">The study area spans 21.5°N to 25.5°N latitude and 120°E to 122°E longitude. Variables gathered from various data sources were uniformly processed and resampled onto a 0.1° × 0.1° grid using nearest-neighbor interpolation based on their geographic coordinates. The GEMS L2 aerosol products supplied data with observational starting times ranging from 22:45 to 07:45 UTC. To facilitate integration with other datasets, meteorological and air pollutant records were temporally aligned with the GEMS data based on the nearest observation start time. For example, the meteorological data recorded at 08:00 UTC matched the GEMS observations that began at 07:45 UTC.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Feature engineering</title><p id="Par26">The spatiotemporal variables included the longitude, latitude, year, month, day, hour, and day of the week. They represent either fixed geographic attributes or readily calculable temporal information. For all time-based data, the timestamps were standardized to UTC + 8 to align with the local time zone in Taipei.</p><p id="Par27">Subsequently, feature engineering was applied specifically to the dynamic variables. A key step involved time-lagging these features by using values from the previous time step (t − 1) for each variable. This approach ensures that the model predicts air pollutant concentrations at a given time using only the information available prior to that time, thereby aligning with realistic forecasting conditions. These dynamic variables can be classified into three main categories: meteorological factors, pollutant concentration indicators, and radiation and optical characteristics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Meteorological factors</title><p id="Par28">Meteorological factors refer to surface and atmospheric weather conditions observed in the preceding hour. These include wind speed, the UV index, atmospheric pressure, relative humidity, mean water vapor pressure, global solar radiation, and altitude.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Gaseous pollutant concentration indicators</title><p id="Par29">Pollutant indicators were derived from GEMS satellite observations, which captured atmospheric column concentrations from the previous hour. The key variables included total O<sub>3</sub>, total NO<sub>2</sub>, and total SO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Radiation and optical characteristics</title><p id="Par30">These features describe atmospheric optical and radiative properties during the previous hour. These included AOD, aerosol layer height, cloud fraction, relative azimuth angle, solar zenith angle, viewing zenith angle, spectral radiation intensity at six wavelengths (354, 388, 412, 443, 477, and 490 nm), single-scattering albedo, and reflectance at 440 nm.</p><p id="Par31">A two-stage expansion of the time series features was implemented to enhance the predictive performance of the model. At each stage, the model was retrained and the feature importance was reassessed. In the first stage, all dynamic variables were augmented by incorporating their values from 2 h prior (t − 2), capturing short-term temporal dependencies. In the second stage, values from the same time on the previous day (t − 24) were added to account for diurnal patterns.</p><p id="Par32">The GEMS satellite, equipped with instruments operating in a geostationary orbit, utilizes UV-visible (UV-Vis) spectroscopy to retrieve atmospheric pollutant concentrations (including O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, and aerosols) by analyzing sunlight scattered and absorbed by atmospheric gases and particulates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par33">The GEMS instrument operates only during daylight hours because of its dependence on sunlight, resulting in nightly interruptions in data collection. Its daily observation frequency varies seasonally; fewer observations occur in winter because of lower solar altitude and weaker signals, whereas longer daylight and higher signal quality in summer allow for more frequent observations. Consequently, the total daily period for GEMS measurements was approximately 6 h in winter, extending to approximately 10 h in summer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. This inherent limitation results in daily discontinuities in the time series, posing challenges for air-quality models that rely on continuous temporal features.</p><p id="Par34">One major limitation is the lack of nighttime data, which makes it difficult to track pollutant behavior overnight. For example, if data are available at 15:00 but no further data is obtained until 06:00 the following day, we cannot directly model what happens in the interim period, such as the way in which pollutants move, disperse, or undergo chemical changes during the night.</p><p id="Par35">To address this constraint, we incorporated observational data from the same time on the previous day (t − 24) as surrogate input for the early hours of each day during model training and prediction. This augmentation partially restores temporal continuity and supports the learning of lag effects. However, expanding the time-series input in this way substantially increases feature dimensionality, raising the risk of the “curse of dimensionality.” To mitigate this, CatBoost was used to evaluate feature importance at both augmentation stages (t − 2 and t − 24), retaining only features with an importance score &gt; 0.5 for final model training.</p><p id="Par36">The feature of the importance metric employed in this study is the change in the prediction value, which quantifies the average change in the model prediction resulting from perturbations in the value of each feature. This metric is directly proportional to the magnitude of the predictive variation induced by a feature. Consequently, a higher prediction value change score indicates a greater influence on the output of the model.</p><p id="Par37">The calculation is based on how decision tree leaf nodes are split:<disp-formula id="Equa"><tex-math id="d33e640"><?equation-image-name d33e640.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 5957142211abf744b2208730b801cf9d?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/5957142211ab/d33e640.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:feature\_importance_{F} = \sum {\:_{{trees,leaf \in \:s_{F} }} } (v_{1} - avr)^{2} \bullet \:c_{1} + (v_{2} - avr)^{2} \bullet \:c_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equb"><tex-math id="d33e643"><?equation-image-name d33e643.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 8e9bf726d73b8fbdc5881d8c400c3b8e?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/8e9bf726d73b/d33e643.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$avr = \:\frac{{v_{1} \bullet \:c_{1} + v_{2} \bullet \:c_{2} }}{{c_{1} + c_{2} }},$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p><p id="Par38">where <italic toggle="yes">s</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic></sub> represents the set of all leaf nodes (across every tree in the ensemble) whose decision path includes at least one split on feature . <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">1</italic></sub> and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">2</italic></sub> represent the total weight of the objects that land in the left and right child leaves, respectively. If no explicit sample weights are given, these values equal the raw number of data points in each leaf. <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">1</italic></sub> and <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">2</italic></sub> denote the prediction (leaf value) assigned to the left and right child leaves, respectively.</p><p id="Par39">When the model bases its decisions on combinations of multiple features, the average importance of each feature combination should be calculated and then evenly distributed among all features within that combination. If a feature is also used individually, its importance is computed as follows:<disp-formula id="Equc"><tex-math id="d33e681"><?equation-image-name d33e681.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 b9ff03b93538bb4aa71da4446e94946c?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/b9ff03b93538/d33e681.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{feature\_total\_importance}_{F}={feature\_importance}_{j}+{\sum\:}_{i=1}^{N}{average\_feature\_importance}_{i}.$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p><p id="Par40">Through this feature-engineering process, we successfully addressed the temporal dynamics and seasonal cycles. Consequently, it provides a robust and sound data foundation for predicting air pollutant concentrations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Model development</title><p id="Par41">This study employed the CatBoost model to predict the ground-level concentrations of multiple pollutants. Hyperparameter tuning was conducted to optimize model performance within the rolling prediction framework. We performed a grid search over the parameter space, specifically targeting the iterations {700, 1000, 1200, 1400} and learning rates {0.3, 0.4, 0.5}. The optimal hyperparameter configuration was selected based on the lowest aggregate Root Mean Squared Error (RMSE) across all six pollutants derived from the comprehensive 6-month rolling validation period (July 1 to December 31, 2023). Balancing accuracy with computational efficiency, we set the number of iterations to 1400 and the learning rate to 0.4. The multiple root mean square error (MultiRMSE) was chosen as the loss function. As a common metric in multi-output regression, MultiRMSE effectively measures the model’s overall prediction error across various response variables. This makes it particularly suitable for tasks requiring the prediction of multiple dimensions.<disp-formula id="Equd"><tex-math id="d33e691"><?equation-image-name d33e691.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 8ce81f9715e8181820614563ae112f4e?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/8ce81f9715e8/d33e691.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$MultiRMSE = \sqrt {\frac{{\sum \: _{{i = 1}}^{N} \sum \: _{{d = 1}}^{{dim}} (a_{{i,d}} - t_{{i,d}} )^{2} w_{i} }}{{\sum \: _{{i = 1}}^{N} w_{i} }}} ,$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p><p id="Par42">Here, <inline-formula id="IEq2"><tex-math id="d33e696"><?equation-image-name d33e696.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 06261579b4229630bc8b6ab631d3f9f4?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/06261579b422/d33e696.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:dim\:$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>represents the number of output dimensions; <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> represents the number of samples; <inline-formula id="IEq3"><tex-math id="d33e703"><?equation-image-name d33e703.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 023fc4ffb517b330f88793ab94fb8b09?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/023fc4ffb517/d33e703.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{a}_{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>​ denote the model’s predicted values for the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th sample in the <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>-th dimension; <inline-formula id="IEq4"><tex-math id="d33e714"><?equation-image-name d33e714.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 4aa9949ec38c4975f049e4eae958fd4c?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/4aa9949ec38c/d33e714.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{t}_{i,d}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>​ represent the true values for the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th sample in the <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>-th dimension, and; <inline-formula id="IEq5"><tex-math id="d33e724"><?equation-image-name d33e724.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 866851d973fc2e052262ef0ff96b3910?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/866851d973fc/d33e724.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{w}_{i}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is the weight of the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th sample. Because the sample weights are not specified, they are assumed to be one by default.</p><p id="Par43">To evaluate the generalization capability of the model rigorously, we employed a rolling expanding-window validation strategy covering July 1 to December 31, 2023. The procedure began with an initial training set comprising data from January 1, 2022, to June 30, 2023 (18 months), with the following day (July 1, 2023) serving as the first validation target. In each subsequent iteration, the observed data from the validation day are appended to the training set to update the model and forecast the next day. This process was repeated daily until December 31, 2023, yielding a comprehensive six-month validation dataset. Importantly, the temporal structure of this approach ensured that all training data strictly preceded the prediction targets, thereby preventing data leakage.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Evaluation metrics</title><p id="Par44">The model performance was evaluated using a rolling prediction framework. In each iteration, data from the preceding 18 months were used to train the model and predict the pollutant concentrations for the following day. This process was repeated continuously until predictions were generated and validated over a six-month evaluation period. The rolling approach enables the model to learn from continuously updated data, thereby reflecting operational forecasting conditions. The performance was assessed using several standard metrics R<sup>2</sup>, MAE, RMSE, and MAPE.<disp-formula id="Eque"><tex-math id="d33e739"><?equation-image-name d33e739.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 64f7be8219f54184fd51787bb3d0dd8a?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/64f7be8219f5/d33e739.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R^{2} = 1 - \frac{{\sum \: _{{i = 1}}^{n} (y_{i} - \widehat{{y_{i} }})^{2} }}{{\sum \: _{{i = 1}}^{n} (y_{i} - \mathop y\limits^{ - } )^{2} }}\:,$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equf"><tex-math id="d33e742"><?equation-image-name d33e742.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 5b61e0aa9a53a5b1f89e5a900bf47d72?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/5b61e0aa9a53/d33e742.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$MAE = \frac{1}{n}\sum \: _{{i = 1}}^{n} \left| {y_{i} - \widehat{{y_{i} }}} \right|,$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equg"><tex-math id="d33e745"><?equation-image-name d33e745.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 350559bc0d153d2bf26c7fca8de1476e?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/350559bc0d15/d33e745.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$RMSE = \sqrt {\frac{1}{n}\sum \: _{{i = 1}}^{n} (y_{i} - \widehat{{y_{i} }})^{2} } ,$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equh"><tex-math id="d33e748"><?equation-image-name d33e748.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 c7f194833628191424a7574baea43e8c?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/c7f194833628/d33e748.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$MAPE = \frac{{100\% }}{n}\sum \: _{{i = 1}}^{n} \frac{{\left| {y_{i} - \widehat{{y_{i} }}} \right|}}{{y_{i} }},$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p><p id="Par45">Here, <inline-formula id="IEq6"><tex-math id="d33e753"><?equation-image-name d33e753.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 b3641c551ca913631c6e5e90c475dc4f?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/b3641c551ca9/d33e753.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{y}_{i}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> represents the real value, <inline-formula id="IEq7"><tex-math id="d33e757"><?equation-image-name d33e757.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 4ebd62ab95c6afe5de9ee71bd26c12b0?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/4ebd62ab95c6/d33e757.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\widehat{{y}_{i}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>​ represents the predicted value of the model, <inline-formula id="IEq8"><tex-math id="d33e761"><?equation-image-name d33e761.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 4e54fa5689c049c380c0b8c08a5f83ea?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/4e54fa5689c0/d33e761.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\stackrel{-}{y}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>​ is the average value of the real value sequence, and <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> represents the number of samples in the test set.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Model interpretation</title><p id="Par46">To improve interpretability and quantify the specific contributions of GEMS observations, meteorological variables, and geographic features, we employed the SHAP (SHapley Additive exPlanations) approach. We utilized training data (January 1, 2022, to June 30, 2023) to calculate the SHAP values, assessing both the magnitude and direction of each feature’s impact on the model’s predictions for the six criteria pollutants.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Model performance</title><p id="Par47">We applied multiple evaluation methods to assess the stability and generalization capability of the model. The results revealed notable variations in prediction performance across different pollutants (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Among them, the highest accuracy was achieved for O<sub>3</sub>, with an R<sup>2</sup> of 0.86. In contrast, the lowest value was for SO<sub>2</sub>, with an R² value of 0.52. A closer examination of the error metrics further confirmed this pattern. Relatively low RMSE and MAE values were found for O<sub>3</sub>, indicating a more stable performance. On the other hand, although PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> maintained reasonable accuracy in overall trends, their higher MAPE values suggested that the model struggled under certain extreme conditions or in areas with sparse station coverage. These limitations, including potential over- or underestimation, are discussed in greater detail in the following section.</p><p id="Par48">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Performance metrics of the multi-output catboost model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Method</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Evaluation<break/>metric</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq9"><tex-math id="d33e820"><?equation-image-name d33e820.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 3aad664852c52b372be9e8ccc454bc11?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/3aad664852c5/d33e820.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{P}\mathrm{M}}_{2.5}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq10"><tex-math id="d33e827"><?equation-image-name d33e827.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 81a900082a0e5bf49376d797eb50b3f0?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/81a900082a0e/d33e827.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{P}\mathrm{M}}_{10}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq11"><tex-math id="d33e834"><?equation-image-name d33e834.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 ee76f896a5b00ad89142105cc0ac7615?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/ee76f896a5b0/d33e834.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{O}}_{3}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq12"><tex-math id="d33e841"><?equation-image-name d33e841.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 a6177f0bc86f80b43e86d364ccddcea5?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/a6177f0bc86f/d33e841.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{N}\mathrm{O}}_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq13"><tex-math id="d33e848"><?equation-image-name d33e848.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 00d09b40bad437beb7299a78c1da5855?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/00d09b40bad4/d33e848.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mathrm{C}\mathrm{O}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq14"><tex-math id="d33e855"><?equation-image-name d33e855.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 1bb7e2361f632869d533a41b21d8f878?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/1bb7e2361f63/d33e855.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{S}\mathrm{O}}_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">CatBoost</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq15"><tex-math id="d33e866"><?equation-image-name d33e866.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 f00a8d372f8909542d18ca1c7e655993?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/f00a8d372f89/d33e866.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{R}}^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.13</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.05</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq16"><tex-math id="d33e901"><?equation-image-name d33e901.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 1a31060a2c02cd070bff4815d39bd778?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/1a31060a2c02/d33e901.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mathrm{R}\mathrm{M}\mathrm{S}\mathrm{E}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.89</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.39</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAPE(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">278</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">119</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Evaluation of metric anomalies and causes in Taiwan</title><p id="Par49">According to the various error metrics derived from the validation set, the MAPE stood out with unexpectedly high values for the following: PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub>. In contrast, other performance indicators were normal. We performed a statistical analysis of each residual for both particulate types to investigate this anomaly.</p><p id="Par50">As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, PM<sub>2.5</sub> values ranged from 0 to 168 and PM<sub>10</sub> values ranged from 0 to 295 in the validation set. Although most of the prediction residuals were concentrated between 0 and 20, a minority of data points exhibited residuals &gt; 100. In some cases, the residuals exceed the maximum observed pollutant concentrations. The calculation method for the MAPE inherently overemphasized the effect of such single-point errors. Consequently, the average MAPE may not have accurately represented the error distribution.</p><p id="Par51">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of prediction residuals for particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 2.5 μm (PM<sub>2.5</sub>) and ≤ 10 μm (PM<sub>10</sub>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e963" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2026_39305_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 22841?><?image-md5 ed26bcd42e46f579deb500ddeff0cfc2?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 524?><?image-original-width 1708?><?image-scaled-height 210?><?image-scaled-width 683?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/ed26bcd42e46/41598_2026_39305_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 2648?><?thumb-md5 ec8aa17ec053e131734dabf5dbe2a1c7?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 61?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/ec8aa17ec053/41598_2026_39305_Fig2_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par52">The MAPE calculation was further processed by substituting the median of the mean. The comparison results are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. A comparison with the original calculation method revealed that PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> exhibited the most dramatic changes; specifically, the MAPE values decreased from 278% to 40% and 119% to 31%, respectively.</p><p id="Par53">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of error variation under two mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) calculation methods: mean-based versus median-based approaches. PM<sub>2.5</sub> - particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 2.5 μm; PM<sub>10</sub> - particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 10 μm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e987" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2026_39305_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 24569?><?image-md5 4e72e45315ac3f9813ad42e5cb69598d?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1178?><?image-original-width 2008?><?image-scaled-height 392?><?image-scaled-width 669?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/4e72e45315ac/41598_2026_39305_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 2264?><?thumb-md5 1ee9d6dc55d97c5ba4594d57034a4288?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 136?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/1ee9d6dc55d9/41598_2026_39305_Fig3_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Feature importance analysis</title><p id="Par54">Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> presents SHAP summary plots for the six air pollutants and their ranked features based on their average impact on the model output. For O<sub>3</sub>, meteorological factors dominated with total sky irradiance and temperature showing strong positive contributions, whereas relative humidity exhibited a negative association. In contrast, wind speed was the most critical negative predictor for particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub>), wind speed is the most critical negative predictor, whereas satellite AOD showed a significant positive contribution. Primary pollutants (NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, and SO<sub>2</sub>) were primarily governed by temporal and geographic variables. Notably, UVI displayed a clear negative correlation with NO<sub>2</sub> levels.</p><p id="Par55">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>SHAP summary plots for the six air pollutants and their ranked features based on their average impact on the model output.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1017" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2026_39305_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 108462?><?image-md5 917c151106f8af4ed49a1096640df40e?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1331?><?image-original-width 1667?><?image-scaled-height 532?><?image-scaled-width 666?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/917c151106f8/41598_2026_39305_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 3949?><?thumb-md5 8f4d938a164ae4aa0bd3f4450783d555?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/8f4d938a164a/41598_2026_39305_Fig4_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Visualization of air pollution predictions in Taiwan</title><p id="Par56">This subsection presents visualizations of the CatBoost model’s predicted air pollutant concentrations in Taiwan. First, we focused on station locations where ground-truth data were available, allowing us to assess the model performance within specific station grids by comparing the predicted values with actual observations. Second, the predictions were extended to the full Taiwan grid to simulate the overall predictive performance of the model under practical application scenarios.</p><p id="Par57">Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the spatial distributions of the mean concentrations of the six air pollutants based on validation, where the first row displays the predicted values, the second row shows the observed values, and the third row shows the differences. In the third row, red areas indicate overestimation, whereas blue areas suggest underestimation. The evaluation period for this study spanned from July 1‒December 31, 2023. During this timeframe, the differences between the ground truth and predicted values were summarized using the average concentrations. Overall, the model’s predictions closely aligned with the observed data across most regions. However, noticeable deviations were observed in a few localized areas.</p><p id="Par58">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Spatial distributions of predicted and observed mean concentrations and the differences between predicted and observed concentrations from July 1 to December 31, 2023. There are six air pollutants (CO [ppm], NO<sub>2</sub> [ppb], 0<sub>3</sub> [ppm], particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 2.5 μm [PM<sub>2.5</sub>; µg/m³], particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 10 μm [PM<sub>10</sub>; µg/m³], and SO<sub>2</sub> [ppb]) based on the validation dataset over Taiwan. The model-predicted averages were compared with the corresponding ground-based observations. The first row shows the predicted values, the second row shows the observed values, and the third row shows the differences between them.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1047" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2026_39305_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 163461?><?image-md5 a83fe5f31482d6d7f4bcd41c0324e1ef?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1886?><?image-original-width 1716?><?image-scaled-height 754?><?image-scaled-width 686?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/a83fe5f31482/41598_2026_39305_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 5970?><?thumb-md5 e64cec2ea6a481e93c89acd496edccd9?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 110?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/e64cec2ea6a4/41598_2026_39305_Fig5_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p><p id="Par59">As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, the predictions were extended to cover the entire Taiwanese grid from 06:45 to 13:45 (UTC + 8) on July 12, 2023. This includes areas without the ground truth. The hourly concentrations of the six air pollutants were visualized using continuous color-scale maps to depict the spatial distribution of each pollutant. This type of full-coverage prediction simulates realistic application scenarios and provides valuable reference information for environmental monitoring and public health risk assessment.</p><p id="Par60">
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Predicted spatial distributions of six air pollutants (CO [ppm], NO<sub>2</sub> [ppb], O<sub>3</sub> [ppm], particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 2.5 μm [PM<sub>2.5</sub>; µg/m³], particulate matter with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 10 μm [PM<sub>10</sub>; µg/m³], and SO<sub>2</sub> [ppb]) across Taiwan for 08:45–13:45 (UTC + 8) on July 12, 2023.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1073" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41598_2026_39305_Fig6_HTML.jpg"><?image-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig6_HTML.jpg?><?image-size 307060?><?image-md5 2640f1dc32a505c140104b3ff32314a1?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2363?><?image-original-width 1254?><?image-scaled-height 1182?><?image-scaled-width 627?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/2640f1dc32a5/41598_2026_39305_Fig6_HTML.jpg?><?thumb-name 41598_2026_39305_Fig6_HTML.gif?><?thumb-size 16238?><?thumb-md5 2857e9a68884f78f19f63094bb7b8793?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 188?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/2857e9a68884/41598_2026_39305_Fig6_HTML.gif?></graphic></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>Interpretation of feature importance</title><p id="Par61">The driving mechanisms revealed by the SHAP analysis align with atmospheric physical and chemical principles.</p><p id="Par62">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par63">Ozone: Global solar radiation (<inline-formula id="IEq17"><tex-math id="d33e1089"><?equation-image-name d33e1089.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 a0fd7483ae04b15ef081e8931b874168?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/a0fd7483ae04/d33e1089.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\mathrm{MJ}}/{\mathrm{m}}^{{\mathrm{2}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>) showed a strong positive correlation with O<sub>3</sub> concentration. This aligns with the mechanism by which intense solar radiation accelerates the photolysis of NO<sub>2</sub>, thereby promoting ozone formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Conversely, relative humidity was negatively correlated. This likely reflects the fact that high humidity induces stomatal opening in vegetation, enhancing the dry deposition of ozone through stomatal uptake, thereby inhibiting accumulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par64">Particulate Matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>): Wind speed generally has a negative impact on PM concentrations, reflecting dispersion and dilution effects where strong winds prevent the local accumulation of pollutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par65">Primary Pollutants (NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, SO<sub>2</sub>): These pollutants are strongly influenced by temporal, geographic, and photochemical factors. Notably, a negative correlation was observed between the UVI (Ultraviolet Index) and NO<sub>2</sub> levels. This is physically consistent with the photolysis process (NO<sub>2</sub> + hv → NO + O), in which higher UV radiation accelerates the breakdown of NO<sub>2</sub> to generate ozone, leading to a decrease in the ambient NO<sub>2</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par66">Overall, SHAP analysis explains the physical dispersion and reaction conditions, while GEMS observations provide crucial real-time spatial information, collectively enhancing prediction accuracy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Research advantages</title><p id="Par67">This study utilized GEMS data combined with ground-based monitoring data to successfully predict the hourly surface concentrations of six air pollutants in Taiwan: PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, CO, and SO<sub>2</sub>. The GEMS operates as a geostationary orbit UV/visible spectrometer for air pollution monitoring, offering high temporal and spatial resolution (3.5 km × 8 km) that provides unprecedented opportunities for real-time regional air quality assessment and forecasting<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. The data from the GEMS enable a more effective capture of diurnal pollutant variations, which is a crucial aspect for understanding complex pollutant interactions and short-term air quality changes. This capability overcomes the limitations of traditional ground monitoring stations, which offer limited spatial coverage and low-Earth orbit satellites, which lack sufficient temporal resolution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par68">The strength of our approach is in its ability to predict multiple pollutants simultaneously. Instead of the conventional method of modeling each pollutant individually, we employed a CatBoost model that supports multiple outputs, enabling the concurrent handling of six pollutants within a single model. This approach not only significantly enhances modeling efficiency but also allows the model to learn and utilize potential interactions and shared influencing factors among different pollutants under the same atmospheric conditions. For example, similar meteorological conditions or emission sources can simultaneously affect the concentrations of various pollutants. This concept aligns with the work of Yang et al. (2023), who employed an MORF model in China to capture inter-pollutant dependencies through joint prediction, thereby enhancing the overall predictive performance.</p><p id="Par69">CatBoost was selected for this study primarily because it employs “Ordered Boosting,” a technique that fundamentally distinguishes it from standard GBDT algorithms like XGBoost or LightGBM. According to Prokhorenkova et al. (2018), standard GBDT models are susceptible to “prediction shift,” a phenomenon where the distribution of gradients estimated on training data diverges from that of the test data due to target leakage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. CatBoost mitigates this problem by using a permutation-driven approach, ensuring that the residual for each training example is computed using a model trained strictly on observations preceding it in the permutation, thereby enabling unbiased gradient estimation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Furthermore, independent reviews have highlighted the robustness of CatBoost in handling the heterogeneous data characteristics of big data tasks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Therefore, this model was adopted in this study.</p><p id="Par70">Another advantage of this approach is strategic integration of multiple datasets. This study combines GEMS satellite observations, which provide high temporal resolution and broad spatial coverage, with ground monitoring station data and the ECMWF ERA5-Land dataset. This ‘stereoscopic monitoring’ approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> combines satellite remote sensing with ground-based observations and overcomes the limitations of relying on single data sources. For example, the sparse placement of ground stations makes it challenging to reflect the overall pollution situation in a region accurately. Although satellite observations offer extensive coverage, the accuracy of AOD measurements is limited by the cloud cover and surface reflectivity. An evaluation of the GEMS AOD product in Korea by the Korean Society of Remote Sensing, for example, found that while GEMS AOD correlated positively with ground-level PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations and negatively (approximately − 0.6) with an atmospheric instability index, these relationships varied with season and land cover type<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par71">Similarly, another study in Southeast Asia by the Asian Disaster Preparedness Center compared GEMS AOD with AERONET ground station data, revealing a good overall correlation (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.75); however, GEMS tended to underestimate AOD, and the correlation weakened considerably in the rainy season (R<sup>2</sup> &lt; 0.13) compared with the dry season (R<sup>2</sup> ≤ 0.79). These findings underscore the limitations of AOD products under various meteorological conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Despite these constraints, fusing multisource data enables the model to fully utilize information from each source, fostering mutual supplementation for a more reliable and comprehensive air quality assessment.</p><p id="Par72">This study implements a rolling forecast framework for validation. This approach distinguishes this methodology from recent satellite-based air quality research. Prior studies using Himawari-8<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> or GEMS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> to advance multi-pollutant modeling have mostly used standard randomized cross-validation. In time-series analysis, random splitting risks “look-ahead bias,” where future data influences training. In contrast, the rolling framework preserves the temporal order using only historical data to predict future outcomes. This minimizes the data leakage. Combined with CatBoost’s permutation-driven Ordered Boosting algorithm, this validation offers a rigorous assessment fit for operational forecasting in Taiwan’s complex island environments. Although existing GEMS-based models have primarily focused on continental-scale applications, this study addresses the underexplored challenges posed by Taiwan’s complex island topography and highly dynamic atmospheric conditions. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to apply GEMS data for air quality forecasting in Taiwan.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Related research results</title><p id="Par73">In recent years, the field of air quality forecasting has made significant progress in terms of modeling techniques and data utilization. As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Yang et al. (2023) employed a MORF model in conjunction with GEMS data to successfully predict the concentrations of six major air pollutants across China. Their cross-validation results reported an average MAE &lt; 10 µg/m³, with robust performance in CO prediction. Jana et al. (2024) focused on the highly complex pollution conditions in Delhi, India, employing an STGCN. Their findings highlighted that the STGCN-C model achieved an MAE of 15.35 µg/m³ for 1-h univariate predictions of PM<sub>2.5</sub>, demonstrating the potential of spatiotemporal deep-learning models in highly variable pollution environments.</p><p id="Par74">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Performance of multi-pollutant prediction models in different regions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq18"><tex-math id="d33e1250"><?equation-image-name d33e1250.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 3aad664852c52b372be9e8ccc454bc11?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/3aad664852c5/d33e1250.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{P}\mathrm{M}}_{2.5}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq19"><tex-math id="d33e1257"><?equation-image-name d33e1257.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 81a900082a0e5bf49376d797eb50b3f0?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/81a900082a0e/d33e1257.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{P}\mathrm{M}}_{10}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq20"><tex-math id="d33e1264"><?equation-image-name d33e1264.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 ee76f896a5b00ad89142105cc0ac7615?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/ee76f896a5b0/d33e1264.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{O}}_{3}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq21"><tex-math id="d33e1271"><?equation-image-name d33e1271.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 a6177f0bc86f80b43e86d364ccddcea5?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/a6177f0bc86f/d33e1271.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{N}\mathrm{O}}_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq22"><tex-math id="d33e1278"><?equation-image-name d33e1278.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 00d09b40bad437beb7299a78c1da5855?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/00d09b40bad4/d33e1278.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mathrm{C}\mathrm{O}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq23"><tex-math id="d33e1285"><?equation-image-name d33e1285.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 1bb7e2361f632869d533a41b21d8f878?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/1bb7e2361f63/d33e1285.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{S}\mathrm{O}}_{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><p>MORF</p><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq24"><tex-math id="d33e1301"><?equation-image-name d33e1301.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 f00a8d372f8909542d18ca1c7e655993?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/f00a8d372f89/d33e1301.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:{\mathrm{R}}^{2}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.938</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.943</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.866</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.802</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.794</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.018</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.203</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.481</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.572</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.135</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.844</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq25"><tex-math id="d33e1336"><?equation-image-name d33e1336.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 1a31060a2c02cd070bff4815d39bd778?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/1a31060a2c02/d33e1336.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mathrm{R}\mathrm{M}\mathrm{S}\mathrm{E}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.939</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.767</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.194</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.677</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.221</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.884</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><p>ConvLSTM(24 step)</p><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.00</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq26"><tex-math id="d33e1377"><?equation-image-name d33e1377.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 1a31060a2c02cd070bff4815d39bd778?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/1a31060a2c02/d33e1377.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mathrm{R}\mathrm{M}\mathrm{S}\mathrm{E}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.88</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAPE(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60.73</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">111.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.98</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">141.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><p>Conv2D+LSTM(24 step)</p><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.86</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.36</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.81</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq27"><tex-math id="d33e1431"><?equation-image-name d33e1431.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 1a31060a2c02cd070bff4815d39bd778?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/1a31060a2c02/d33e1431.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mathrm{R}\mathrm{M}\mathrm{S}\mathrm{E}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.65</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAPE(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.84</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.33</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">116.41</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">78.34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">134.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><p>STGAN-C(24 step)</p><p>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAE</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.69</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq28"><tex-math id="d33e1485"><?equation-image-name d33e1485.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 1a31060a2c02cd070bff4815d39bd778?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/1a31060a2c02/d33e1485.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mathrm{R}\mathrm{M}\mathrm{S}\mathrm{E}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.59</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.68</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAPE(%)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">57.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.48</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">107.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.99</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>CatBoost</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>MAE</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>5.13</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>9.40</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>8.00</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>2.05</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.06</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.51</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula id="IEq29"><tex-math id="d33e1568"><?equation-image-name d33e1568.gif?><?equation-image-status ERROR?><?equation-image-md5 38db9c0ce2e880b1b98ee49d5507c545?><?equation-image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/17dc/12948998/38db9c0ce2e8/d33e1568.gif?>\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\mathbf{R}\mathbf{M}\mathbf{S}\mathbf{E}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>6.89</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>13.47</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>10.39</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>3.00</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.08</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.78</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>MAPE(%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>278</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>119</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>28</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>46</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>16</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>52</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par75">In Taiwan, Ho et al. (2020) applied a semi-parametric additive model that integrated data from Airbox micro-sensors, successfully improving the daily PM<sub>2.5</sub> estimation model’s R<sup>2</sup> value from 0.4 to 0.87 and reducing the RMSE to 4.1 µg/m³. In addition, Wong et al. (2024) developed a Geo-AI stacking ensemble model focused on estimating PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration changes during traffic rush hours in Taiwan. Their model achieved R<sup>2</sup> values of 0.95 during the morning period and 0.93 during the evening period. These studies, each adopting distinct methodological approaches, data integration strategies, and application contexts, have collectively contributed to improving air quality forecasting.</p><p id="Par76">Although air quality forecasting research has become increasingly diverse, fundamental differences in data characteristics make it challenging to interpret the model performance uniformly across studies. Even when the same modeling techniques are used, environmental conditions, such as climate, topography, pollution source composition, and baseline pollutant concentrations, vary significantly between studies. Additionally, differences in study periods and validation frameworks (e.g., rolling prediction versus cross-validation) result in performance metrics that reflect distinct aspects of model capability. As a result, the model quality cannot be judged solely by comparing metric values. However, because previous studies in Taiwan have not attempted multi-pollutant synchronous prediction using GEMS data, and have primarily focused on PM<sub>2.5</sub> with validation based on random cross-validation, it is difficult to make direct comparisons between this study and earlier local research.</p><p id="Par77">This study focuses on forecasting air pollutant concentrations in Taiwan. The results show that the MAE values are 5.13 µg/m³ for PM<sub>2.5</sub>, 9.4 µg/m³ for PM<sub>10</sub>, 8.00 ppm for O<sub>3</sub>, 2.05 ppb for NO<sub>2</sub>, 0.51 ppb for SO<sub>2</sub>, and 0.06 ppm for CO. Model outcomes of Yang et al. (2023) and Jana et al. (2024) are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> for comparison. These error values are influenced by the background concentrations of pollutants, dominant emission sources, and meteorological dispersion conditions specific to each study region.</p><p id="Par78">For example, the exceptionally high pollution levels in Delhi, India, largely explain why the MAE values reported by Jana et al. (2024) were considerably higher than those observed in our study. Compared with the results reported by Yang et al. (2023), the prediction errors for the six surface pollutants in our study differed only slightly in terms of RMSE and MAE. Although our performance metrics were marginally lower overall, this did not necessarily indicate that our approach was superior.</p><p id="Par79">However, by integrating multiple data sources and employing rigorous rolling-window validation, the traditional machine learning methods in this study demonstrated a solid level of credibility in predicting most pollutants. Although there remains scope for improvement in the predictions of O<sub>3</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub>, the prediction errors for pollutants such as CO, NO<sub>2</sub>, and SO<sub>2</sub> were significantly lower than those reported in other studies. This suggested that machine-learning models can capture complex meteorological information more effectively when supplemented with GEMS data. Furthermore, when dealing with variable and challenging environmental data, the impacts of data quality and feature engineering become even more critical.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Applicability of error metrics</title><p id="Par80">In addition, we examined the evaluation metrics for pollutant prediction. The MAPE has traditionally been a standard metric for assessing model performance in predicting pollutant concentrations. However, this study found that in the validation set, the MAPE values for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> were unusually high at 278% and 119%, respectively, whereas the other performance indicators appeared normal. To further investigate this anomaly, we analyzed each prediction residual for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub>. The results showed that PM<sub>2.5</sub> residual values ranged from 0 to 168, and those of PM<sub>10</sub> ranged from 0 to 295. Although most prediction residuals were concentrated within a narrow range of 0–20, a few data points exhibited residuals exceeding 100, sometimes surpassing the maximum observed concentrations for these pollutants. As the MAPE calculation inherently overemphasizes the effect of such single-point errors, these extreme outlier residuals have a disproportionately large impact on the final average. Consequently, the calculated MAPE values, such as 278% for PM<sub>2.5</sub> and 119% for PM<sub>10</sub>, may not accurately represent the overall prediction error of the model.</p><p id="Par81">To verify this inference, we processed the MAPE calculations by substituting the median with the mean. This adjustment revealed that PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> exhibited the most dramatic changes. Specifically, the MAPE values decreased from 278% to 40% and 119% to 31%, respectively. These results strongly supported our view that for pollutants susceptible to sudden events or sharp concentration fluctuations (such as PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> ​in this study), the traditional MAPE calculated using the mean may be distorted by the excessive influence of outliers and cannot provide a robust error assessment. Nevertheless, considering the prevalence of MAPE in the literature and the need for comparison with other studies, this study still used the traditional MAPE as an evaluation metric. However, we strongly recommend that when interpreting such data, the distribution of residuals and the potential impact of outliers should be considered simultaneously, and a comprehensive assessment should be supplemented with more robust indicators such as median-based MAPE.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Performance variation among pollutants</title><p id="Par82">Significant variation in predictive performance was observed among the targeted pollutants, with SO<sub>2</sub> exhibiting a notably lower R<sup>2</sup> (0.52) than others, such as O<sub>3</sub> (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.86). This performance disparity is consistent with the existing multi-pollutant literature; for instance, Yang et al. (2023) similarly reported that SO2 yielded the lowest R<sup>2</sup> (0.794) among six criteria pollutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par83">The primary driver of this limitation is the physical constraints of satellite retrieval compared to the ambient concentration. According to the TROPOMI SO<sub>2</sub> Algorithm Theoretical Basis Document (ATBD), most anthropogenic SO<sub>2</sub> is within the planetary boundary layer (PBL). Distinguishing pollution sources in the PBL requires a precision of 0.05 DU. However, the effective detection limit for single-satellite measurements is 1–3 DU<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. In Taiwan, the annual average O<sub>3</sub> concentration is expected to be relatively high at 30.4 ppb in 2024. In contrast, SO<sub>2</sub> averages only 1.18 ppb<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. The SO<sub>2</sub> levels in Taiwan consistently fell within this low background range. Consequently, satellite retrievals are prone to noise and systematic errors, which often exceed the true environmental variability. This low signal-to-noise ratio reduces the explanatory variance that the model can capture, leading to a lower R<sup>2</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Differences in air pollution prediction between countries</title><p id="Par84">In cross-regional comparisons (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), a key observation was that prediction errors in Taiwan did not decrease proportionally with generally lower background air pollutant concentrations when compared to areas such as mainland China or Delhi. This phenomenon underscores the complexity of air quality predictions. We believe that this discrepancy can be attributed to the unique island environment of Taiwan. A study indicates that PM<sub>2.5</sub> pollution in Taiwan is a “multi-scale phenomenon,” jointly controlled by synoptic weather systems and local topographic effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. This contrasts with the pollution characteristics in continental regions. For example, in Beijing, pollution dynamics are strongly influenced by large-scale regional transport, with neighboring provinces contributing ≤ 34% of total PM<sub>2.5</sub>. This resulted in highly synchronized daily concentration changes across all monitoring stations during pollution events (correlation coefficients ranging from 0.876 to 0.986), presenting relatively homogeneous pollution characteristics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par85">Pollution events in continental regions such as Beijing are typically triggered by slow-moving, large-scale, high-pressure systems that lead to prolonged atmospheric stagnation. According to the literature, these events in Beijing can persist from 2 to 9 d<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Such stagnant conditions provide sufficient time for pollutants to accumulate and often evolve into regular patterns over specific periods. In contrast, Taiwan has a more dynamic atmospheric environment. A study revealed that atmospheric stagnation events in Taiwan are typically brief, averaging 2–3 d in duration. This is attributed to the more frequent passage of frontal systems or monsoon transitions, which enhance low-level wind speeds, thereby interrupting the accumulation of pollutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par86">Pollution sources in Taiwan are complex and closely related. In addition to dense urban traffic and industrial activities, unique natural sources and local circulation features exist, including river dust, lee-side vortices, and downslope subsidence. Another study indicates that western Taiwan experiences an average of nine river dust events annually, with severe events capable of causing hourly PM<sub>10</sub> concentrations to exceed 600 µg/m³. This introduces a significant and discontinuous challenge for predictive models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Research limitations and future work</title><sec id="Sec30"><title>Research limitations</title><p id="Par87">In terms of satellite observations, the GEMS primarily operates in the UV-Vis spectrum. This limits its ability to directly observe pollutants with significant absorption features in other spectral bands, such as CO, which is primarily detected in the infrared range. Even when the total column data from the GEMS products are used, the lack of observations in these specific bands can still restrict improvements in the predictive accuracy for these pollutants. Another challenge is that the satellite signals are affected by atmospheric scattering and absorption. Coupled with this, the process of deriving ground-level concentrations from these observations is complex and uncertain, making precise prediction of surface pollutant levels challenging. Moreover, while the spatial resolution of GEMS (approximately 3.5 km × 8 km) is relatively high, it has limitations in capturing details of pollutant distribution at finer scales, such as the street level.</p><p id="Par88">Second, this study did not extensively investigate the physicochemical relationships between air pollutant concentrations and satellite-observed radiation data. Furthermore, while employing a multi-output model to predict the six pollutants can capture their intercorrelations simultaneously, this approach may also suffer from target conflicts or harmful interference among different prediction tasks. Such issues could impact the overall predictive performance for specific pollutants; for example, the model may tend to learn simpler patterns of pollutants, thereby marginalizing others. The distribution density of ground monitoring stations can also influence the model performance. Prediction errors may increase in areas with sparse station coverage owing to insufficient ground-truth data for training.</p><p id="Par89">Finally, the rigorous nature of the rolling prediction framework imposes significant computational constraints. Owing to the strict temporal dependency inherent in this framework, traditional k-fold cross-validation is inapplicable. Furthermore, to prevent selection bias arising from the tuning of partial temporal segments, each hyperparameter combination was validated using the complete six-month dataset. Although this approach ensures that the selected parameters remain robust across varying atmospheric conditions, it significantly increases the computational load. Consequently, a large-scale systematic grid search is computationally prohibitive, and the tuning process is strategically restricted to key parameters (number of iterations and learning rate) to balance efficiency with predictive accuracy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Future work</title><p id="Par90">Based on the research limitations previously discussed, future studies could explore several directions to further improve the model performance and practical value. First, in terms of model optimization and feature engineering, one direction is to explore additional variables that reflect emission source characteristics. These could include the locations of industrial zones, data from the automatic identification system of ships, or indicators of specific point-source emissions. In addition, although this study utilized time-lagged features, further evaluation of model architectures designed explicitly for sequential data, such as LSTM or transformer models, is warranted. This would help ascertain their ability to capture complex temporal dynamics and facilitate a comparison of their performance with the CatBoost model used in this research.</p><p id="Par91">Second, regarding the expansion of data sources and application of GEMS products, future work should consider integrating finer-resolution land-use and land-cover classifications, dynamic traffic flow data, and data on atmospheric characteristics. These additions can potentially enhance the ability of the model to capture local effects. Concurrently, there is a need to research and apply spatiotemporal data imputation techniques tailored to the specific environmental conditions in Taiwan. This would address the data gaps in GEMS observations caused by factors such as cloud cover, thereby improving data completeness. Moreover, future efforts could explore the combination of the multi-pollutant concentration prediction maps from this study with population distribution data, exposure assessments, and public health information to enhance our understanding of environmental health risks. Such an integration would facilitate studies on the health impacts of air pollution and offer scientific support for policymaking.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par92">This study demonstrated the feasibility and effectiveness of integrating GEMS satellite observations, ground-based monitoring, and meteorological data within a multi-output machine-learning framework for real-time, hourly prediction of multiple air pollutants across Taiwan. The CatBoost model enabled accurate and simultaneous forecasting of six key pollutants, and the rolling prediction validation approach ensured robust performance in practical scenarios. Notably, the model achieved superior predictive accuracy for several pollutants compared to that of existing GEMS-based models, highlighting its potential for operational deployment. These findings underscore the value of leveraging high-resolution multi-source data fusion and advanced learning algorithms to improve air quality surveillance. The proposed framework offers a scalable solution for timely public health interventions, environmental policy development, and long-term exposure risk assessments in Taiwan and other countries.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>WHL contributed to data analysis, interpretation and drafted the manuscript. TCC contributed to conception, design, and interpretation, acquired to research resources, and critically revised the manuscript. All the authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Science and Technology Council, Taiwan (Grant number: NSTC 114-2628-M-001-012-MY3).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data will be made available upon request to the corresponding author, Ta-Chien Chan.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar2" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par93">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impacts of urbanization on air quality and the related health risks in a City with complex terrain</article-title><source>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/acp-23-771-2023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Zhan, C. et al. Impacts of urbanization on air quality and the related health risks in a City with complex terrain. <italic toggle="yes">Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>23</bold> (1), 771–788 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministry of Environment, R.O.C.T. <italic toggle="yes">Air Quality Annual Report of R.O.C. (Taiwan), 2024</italic>, Taipei (2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO, WHO global air quality guidelines: particulate matter (PM2.5 and PM10), ozone, nitrogen dioxide, sulfur dioxide and carbon monoxide. Executive summary. Geneva (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34662007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A nationwide case-referent study on elevated risks of adenocarcinoma lung cancer by long-term PM(2.5) exposure in Taiwan since 1997</article-title><source>Environ. Res.</source><year>2024</year><volume>252</volume><issue>Pt 2</issue><fpage>118889</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2024.118889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38599452</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Lin, W. C. et al. A nationwide case-referent study on elevated risks of adenocarcinoma lung cancer by long-term PM(2.5) exposure in Taiwan since 1997. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Res.</italic><bold>252</bold> (Pt 2), 118889 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38599452</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envres.2024.118889</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ministry of Environment (MOENV), R.O.C.T., Historical Air Quality Monitoring Data, in Taiwan Air Quality Monitoring Network (TAQMN), R.O.C.T. Ministry of Environment (MOENV), Editor. 2025: Taipei, Taiwan (2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New era of air quality monitoring from space: geostationary environment monitoring spectrometer (GEMS)</article-title><source>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</source><year>2020</year><volume>101</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>E1</fpage><lpage>E22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/BAMS-D-18-0013.1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Kim, J. et al. New era of air quality monitoring from space: geostationary environment monitoring spectrometer (GEMS). <italic toggle="yes">Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>101</bold> (1), E1–E22 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stereoscopic monitoring: A promising strategy to advance diagnostic and prediction of air pollution</article-title><source>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</source><year>2021</year><volume>102</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>E730</fpage><lpage>E737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/BAMS-D-20-0217.1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Liu, C. et al. Stereoscopic monitoring: A promising strategy to advance diagnostic and prediction of air pollution. <italic toggle="yes">Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>102</bold> (4), E730–E737 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A synchronized Estimation of hourly surface concentrations of six criteria air pollutants with GEMS data</article-title><source>Npj Clim. Atmospheric Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41612-023-00407-1</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Yang, Q. et al. A synchronized Estimation of hourly surface concentrations of six criteria air pollutants with GEMS data. <italic toggle="yes">Npj Clim. Atmospheric Sci.</italic><bold>6</bold> (1), 94 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimation of near-surface Ozone concentration and analysis of main weather situation in China based on machine learning model and Himawari-8 TOAR data</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2023</year><volume>864</volume><fpage>160928</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.160928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36539084</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Chen, B. et al. Estimation of near-surface Ozone concentration and analysis of main weather situation in China based on machine learning model and Himawari-8 TOAR data. <italic toggle="yes">Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>864</bold>, 160928 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36539084</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.160928</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu, Z., Xiao, Q. &amp; Li, R. Full coverage hourly PM(2.5) concentrations’ estimation using Himawari-8 and MERRA-2 AODs in China. <italic toggle="yes">Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health</italic><bold>20</bold> (2), 1490 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph20021490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9864544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36674248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chimla, S., Chotamonsak, C. &amp; Chaipimonplin, T. Integration of WRF-Chem model-based, satellite-based, and ground-based observation data to predict PM2.5 concentration by machine learning approach. <italic toggle="yes">Atmosphere</italic><bold>16</bold> (11), 1304 (2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating hourly ground-level aerosols using geostationary environment monitoring spectrometer aerosol optical depth: a machine learning approach</article-title><source>Atmos. Meas. Tech.</source><year>2025</year><volume>18</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1471</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/amt-18-1471-2025</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">O, S., Yoon, J. W. &amp; Park, S. K. Estimating hourly ground-level aerosols using geostationary environment monitoring spectrometer aerosol optical depth: a machine learning approach. <italic toggle="yes">Atmos. Meas. Tech.</italic><bold>18</bold> (6), 1471–1484 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unleashing the potential of geostationary satellite observations in air quality forecasting through artificial intelligence techniques</article-title><source>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2025</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/acp-25-759-2025</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Zhang, C. et al. Unleashing the potential of geostationary satellite observations in air quality forecasting through artificial intelligence techniques. <italic toggle="yes">Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>25</bold> (2), 759–770 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantifying uncertainty in ML-Derived atmosphere remote sensing: hourly surface NO2 Estimation with GEMS</article-title><source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source><year>2024</year><volume>51</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>pe2024GL110468</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">He, Q. et al. Quantifying uncertainty in ML-Derived atmosphere remote sensing: hourly surface NO2 Estimation with GEMS. <italic toggle="yes">Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>51</bold> (18), pe2024GL110468 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergmeir</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benítez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the usefulness of cross-validation for directional forecast evaluation</article-title><source>Comput. Stat. Data Anal.</source><year>2014</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csda.2014.02.001</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Bergmeir, C., Costantini, M. &amp; Benítez, J. M. On the usefulness of cross-validation for directional forecast evaluation. <italic toggle="yes">Comput. Stat. Data Anal.</italic><bold>76</bold>, 132–143 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Middya</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short-term air pollution prediction using graph convolutional neural networks</article-title><source>Technol. Forecast. Soc. Chang.</source><year>2024</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>123684</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2024.123684</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Jana, S., Middya, A. I. &amp; Roy, S. Short-term air pollution prediction using graph convolutional neural networks. <italic toggle="yes">Technol. Forecast. Soc. Chang.</italic><bold>208</bold>, 123684 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tzeng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatially adaptive calibrations of airbox PM(2.5) data</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><year>2023</year><volume>79</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>3637</fpage><lpage>3649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/biom.13819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36594650</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Tzeng, S., Lai, C. W. &amp; Huang, H. C. Spatially adaptive calibrations of airbox PM(2.5) data. <italic toggle="yes">Biometrics</italic><bold>79</bold> (4), 3637–3649 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36594650</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/biom.13819</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Samad, A. et al. Developing a cloud-based air quality monitoring platform using low-cost sensors. <italic toggle="yes">Sens. (Basel)</italic>, <bold>24</bold>(3), 945 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/s24030945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10857248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38339662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vajs, I., Drajic, D. &amp; Cica, Z. Data-driven machine learning calibration propagation in A hybrid sensor network for air quality monitoring. <italic toggle="yes">Sens. (Basel)</italic>, <bold>23</bold> (5), 2815 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/s23052815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10007210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36905019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang, W. V., Lung, S. C. &amp; Liu, C. H. Application of machine learning for the in-field correction of a PM(2.5) low-cost sensor network. <italic toggle="yes">Sens. (Basel)</italic>, <bold>20</bold> (17), 5002. (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/s20175002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7506620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32899301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Velea, L. et al. A Community-based sensor network for monitoring the air quality in urban Romania. <italic toggle="yes">Atmosphere</italic><bold>14</bold> (5), 840 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating ground-level PM(2.5) levels in Taiwan using data from air quality monitoring stations and high coverage of microsensors</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut</source><year>2020</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>114810</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32559863</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Ho, C. C., Chen, L. J. &amp; Hwang, J. S. Estimating ground-level PM(2.5) levels in Taiwan using data from air quality monitoring stations and high coverage of microsensors. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Pollut</italic>. <bold>264</bold>, 114810 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32559863</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114810</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The improvement of spatial-temporal resolution of PM(2.5) Estimation based on micro-air quality sensors by using data fusion technique</article-title><source>Environ. Int.</source><year>2020</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>105305</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2019.105305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31739136</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Lin, Y. C., Chi, W. J. &amp; Lin, Y. Q. The improvement of spatial-temporal resolution of PM(2.5) Estimation based on micro-air quality sensors by using data fusion technique. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Int.</italic><bold>134</bold>, 105305 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31739136</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envint.2019.105305</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Explainable geospatial-artificial intelligence models for the Estimation of PM(2.5) concentration variation during commuting rush hours in Taiwan</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut</source><year>2024</year><volume>349</volume><fpage>123974</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.123974</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38615837</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Wong, P. Y. et al. Explainable geospatial-artificial intelligence models for the Estimation of PM(2.5) concentration variation during commuting rush hours in Taiwan. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Pollut</italic>. <bold>349</bold>, 123974 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38615837</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.123974</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Donkelaar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global estimates of ambient fine particulate matter concentrations from satellite-based aerosol optical depth: development and application</article-title><source>Environ. Health Perspect.</source><year>2010</year><volume>118</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.0901623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2898863</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">van Donkelaar, A. et al. Global estimates of ambient fine particulate matter concentrations from satellite-based aerosol optical depth: development and application. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Health Perspect.</italic><bold>118</bold> (6), 847–855 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20519161</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1289/ehp.0901623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2898863</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Handschuh, J., Erbertseder, T. &amp; Baier, F. Systematic evaluation of four satellite AOD datasets for estimating PM2.5 using a random forest approach. <italic toggle="yes">Remote Sens.</italic><bold>15</bold> (8), 2064 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An introduction to Himawari-8/9— japan’s New-Generation geostationary meteorological satellites</article-title><source>J. Meteorological Soc. Japan Ser. II</source><year>2016</year><volume>94</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2151/jmsj.2016-009</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Bessho, K. et al. An introduction to Himawari-8/9— japan’s New-Generation geostationary meteorological satellites. <italic toggle="yes">J. Meteorological Soc. Japan Ser. II</italic>. <bold>94</bold> (2), 151–183 (2016).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Prokhorenkova, L. et al. <italic toggle="yes">CatBoost: unbiased boosting with categorical features</italic>. arXiv:1706.09516. 10.48550/arXiv.1706.09516 (2017)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Muñoz Sabater, J. <italic toggle="yes">ERA5-Land hourly data from 1950 to present</italic> C.C.C.S. (C3S), Editor. Climate Data Store (CDS). (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Atmospheric Science Research and Application Databank (ASRAD), Atmospheric Science Research and Application Databank, C.C.U.N.S.a.T. Council, Editor (Atmospheric Science Research and Application Databank (ASRAD), Taipei, Taiwan, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Ministry of Environment (MOENV), R.O.C.T</collab></person-group><article-title>M.o.E. Department of environmental monitoring information</article-title><source>Ultraviolet Index Monitoring Station Data, Ministry of Environment</source><year>2025</year><publisher-loc>Taiwan</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Environmental Data Open Platform, Ministry of Environment</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="book">Ministry of Environment (MOENV), R.O.C.T. Ultraviolet Index Monitoring Station Data, Ministry of Environment, M.o.E. Department of environmental monitoring information, Editor. Environmental Data Open Platform, Ministry of Environment: Taipei, Taiwan (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Choi, W. J. et al. Reliability analysis based on air quality characteristics in East Asia using primary data from the test operation of geostationary environment monitoring spectrometer (GEMS). <italic toggle="yes">Atmosphere</italic><bold>14</bold> (9), 1458 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trebs</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between the NO &lt; sub&gt;2 photolysis frequency and the solar global irradiance</article-title><source>Atmos. Meas. Tech.</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/amt-2-725-2009</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Trebs, I. et al. Relationship between the NO &lt; sub&gt;2 photolysis frequency and the solar global irradiance. <italic toggle="yes">Atmos. Meas. Tech.</italic><bold>2</bold> (2), 725–739 (2009).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavassalis</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding ozone-meteorology correlations: A role for dry deposition</article-title><source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source><year>2017</year><volume>44</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2922</fpage><lpage>2931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/2016GL071791</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Kavassalis, S. C. &amp; Murphy, J. G. Understanding ozone-meteorology correlations: A role for dry deposition. <italic toggle="yes">Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>44</bold> (6), 2922–2931 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Meng, C. et al. <italic toggle="yes">The Impact of Meteorological Factors on Fine Particulate Pollution in Northeast China</italic> (Aerosol and Air Quality Research, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlation-Based evaluation of GEMS satellite products using environmental and meteorological measurements</article-title><source>Korean J. Remote Sens.</source><year>2024</year><volume>40</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>1252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7780/kjrs.2024.40.6.1.28</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Jeong, Y. et al. Correlation-Based evaluation of GEMS satellite products using environmental and meteorological measurements. <italic toggle="yes">Korean J. Remote Sens.</italic><bold>40</bold> (6), 1229–1252 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoshgoftaar</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CatBoost for big data: an interdisciplinary review</article-title><source>J. Big Data</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40537-020-00369-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33169094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7610170</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Hancock, J. T. &amp; Khoshgoftaar, T. M. CatBoost for big data: an interdisciplinary review. <italic toggle="yes">J. Big Data</italic>. <bold>7</bold> (1), 94 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33169094</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40537-020-00369-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7610170</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jang, B. et al. Validation and analysis of GEMS aerosol optical depth product against AERONET over mainland Southeast Asia. <italic toggle="yes">Aerosol Air Qual. Res.</italic><bold>25</bold>, 22 (2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimation of ground-level NO2 and its Spatiotemporal variations in China using GEMS measurements and a nested machine learning model</article-title><source>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>9645</fpage><lpage>9665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/acp-24-9645-2024</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Ahmad, N. et al. Estimation of ground-level NO2 and its Spatiotemporal variations in China using GEMS measurements and a nested machine learning model. <italic toggle="yes">Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>24</bold> (16), 9645–9665 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Theys, N. et al. Sentinel-5 precursor/TROPOMI level 2 algorithm theoretical basis document sulphur dioxide SO2. In <italic toggle="yes">S5P-BIRA-L2-400E-ATBD</italic> (Royal Belgian Institute for Space Aeronomy (BIRA-IASB), 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Su, S. H., Chang, C. W. &amp; Chen, W. T. The Temporal evolution of PM2.5 pollution events in Taiwan: clustering and the association with synoptic weather. <italic toggle="yes">Atmosphere</italic><bold>11</bold> (11), 1265 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batterman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of PM(2.5) concentrations across Beijing during 2013–2015</article-title><source>Atmos. Environ. (1994)</source><year>2016</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2016.08.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29062264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5650241</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Batterman, S. et al. Characteristics of PM(2.5) concentrations across Beijing during 2013–2015. <italic toggle="yes">Atmos. Environ. (1994)</italic>. <bold>145</bold>, 104–114 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29062264</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2016.08.060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5650241</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>River dust-induced air pollution in a changing climate: A study of taiwan’s Choshui and Kaoping rivers</article-title><source>Environ. Pollut</source><year>2024</year><volume>360</volume><fpage>124398</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.124398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38925217</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Tsai, C. W. &amp; Chen, C. K. River dust-induced air pollution in a changing climate: A study of taiwan’s Choshui and Kaoping rivers. <italic toggle="yes">Environ. Pollut</italic>. <bold>360</bold>, 124398 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38925217</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.envpol.2024.124398</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>