<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4448</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">trp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Thoracic Research and Practice</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Thorac Res Pract</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Turkish Thoracic Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12572900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12572900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12572900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41133810</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4274/ThoracResPract.2025.2025-1-3</article-id><title-group><article-title>Effect of Ambient Air Pollutants on Acute changes in Pulmonary Variables and Inflammatory Markers in Healthy Adults: A Pilot Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names initials="A">Amulya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names initials="KN">Kumar Nischay</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanmugasundaram</surname><given-names initials="K">Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandlecha</surname><given-names initials="L">Lokesh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagal</surname><given-names initials="S">Saksham</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Talwar</surname><given-names initials="A">Anjana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Bade</surname><given-names initials="G">Geetanjali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Cardiology, University of Kansas Medical Center, Kansas City, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Physiology, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Dr. Rajendra Prasad Centre for Ophthalmic Sciences, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Surgical Disciplines, All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India</aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>333</fpage><page-range>333–339</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright© 2025 The Author. Published by Galenos Publishing House on behalf of Turkish Thoracic Society.</copyright-statement><license><license-p>Content of this journal is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="TurkThoracJ-26-6-333.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path e486/12572900/355f99667f57/TurkThoracJ-26-6-333.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 193350?></self-uri><abstract id="abstract1" abstract-type="section"><title>Abstract</title><sec id="sec1" disp-level="2"><title>OBJECTIVE</title><p>Air pollution is associated with adverse health effects, particularly on respiratory and cardiovascular systems. Smog, prevalent in Northern India, contains particulate matter (PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>) and gaseous pollutants that can impair pulmonary function. Ambient air pollution can be quantified by the air quality index (AQI). Understanding the acute effects of air quality on respiratory physiology and inflammation is essential.</p></sec><sec id="sec2" disp-level="2"><title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title><p>A pilot prospective longitudinal observational study evaluated healthy volunteers during high (HAQI, AQI &gt;350) and low pollution (LAQI, AQI &lt;150) phases. Spirometry and impulse oscillometry (IOS) assessed lung function; and biomarkers (interleukin-6, tumor necrosis factor alpha) were measured from exhaled breath condensate (EBC) and serum. Paired t-tests or Wilcoxon signed-rank tests were used for analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec3" disp-level="2"><title>RESULTS</title><p>A total of 21 participants (mean age 25.4±7.4 years, female 33.3%, body mass index 23.9±3.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) completed measurement at both HAQI (395.7±43.8) and LAQI (85.4±9.7). Spirometry revealed significantly lower slow vital capacity (SVC%, 81.6±11.2 vs. 87.7±7.7%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.008) and forced vital capacity (FVC%, 86.2±9.8 vs. 90.9±9.4%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0005) under HAQI compared to LAQI. Forced expiratory volume at 1 second (FEV<sub>1</sub>) was also reduced (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001), while FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC remained unchanged. IOS showed higher airway resistance (R<sub>5</sub>, R<sub>20</sub>) during HAQI (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Inflammatory biomarkers in serum and EBC showed no statistical differences between HAQI and LAQI. Despite measurable differences, spirometry and IOS parameters remained within normal limits.</p></sec><sec id="sec4" disp-level="2"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Acute air pollution exposure impairs lung function and increases airway resistance in healthy adults. These findings underscore the need for larger longitudinal studies to clarify the mechanisms linking acute air pollution exposure to chronic health outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Air pollution, spirometry, impulse oscillometry, particulate matter, inflammatory markers</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 Jan 12; Accepted 2025 Sep 23; Collection date 2025 Oct.</p></sec></notes></front><body><boxed-text id="boxed-text1" position="float"><sec id="sec5" disp-level="1"><title>Main Points</title><p>• Acute exposure to air pollution can cause measurable worsening of respiratory function and airway parameters in healthy subjects.</p><p>• Higher air quality index (AQI) (worse air pollution) is associated with lower slow vital capacity and forced expiratory volume at 1 second.</p><p>• Higher AQI is associated with increased respiratory impedance (R<sub>5</sub> and R<sub>20</sub>) as measured on the impulse oscillometry.</p></sec></boxed-text><sec id="sec6" disp-level="1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Air pollution has been associated with detrimental health effects and reduced life expectancy.<sup><xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> The composition of air pollutants exhibits marked regional and temporal variation with differential health effects. Smog is a particularly detrimental type of air pollution, prevalent in Northern India due to a combination of emissions from vehicles, industries, and crop residue burning, which undergo photochemical reactions in sunlight. During winter, temperature inversion in this part of the country traps these pollutants near the surface, leading to dense, persistent smog.<sup><xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Smog contains high concentrations of small particulate matter, i.e., PM<sub>2.5</sub> (≤2.5 µm diameter) and PM<sub>10</sub> (≤10 µm diameter). PM<sub>2.5 </sub>and PM<sub>10</sub> are known to have significant negative effects on human health.<sup><xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> These particles, although small, have a relatively large surface area that facilitates the attachment of toxic substances. Due to their small size, they can evade nasal filtration, penetrate deep into the respiratory system, and reach the alveoli. Once deposited in the lungs, PM<sub>2.5 </sub>and PM<sub>10</sub> can induce local inflammation and may even enter the bloodstream, causing systemic adverse effects.<sup><xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Apart from particulate matter, ozone (O<sub>3</sub>), sulfur dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub>), nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>), carbon monoxide (CO), and lead are the main contaminants of outdoor air.</p><p>The Central Pollution Control Board’s website (Ministry of Environment, Forestry and Climate Change, India) provides real-time access to the air quality index (AQI).<sup><xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> The AQI ranges from 0-500 and is calculated from the concentration of 7 pollutants: PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, CO, SO<sub>2</sub>, ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub>). There are 6 categories of AQI: good, satisfactory, moderately polluted, poor, very poor, and severe. AQI is the generally accepted method for monitoring air pollution in India.</p><p>Acute exposure to air pollutants might result in respiratory symptoms, cardiovascular problems, hospital admissions, and even death.<sup><xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Further, lung cancer, atherosclerosis, chronic bronchitis, and increased mortality have all been connected to prolonged exposure to air pollution.<sup><xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Understanding the acute effects of air pollution on the respiratory system physiology is also important for comprehending the pathophysiological mechanisms of chronic detrimental effects.</p><p>In this study, we assessed the acute effects of changes in ambient air quality (measured by AQI) on lung volumes, capacities, airway mechanics and inflammatory biomarkers in North India.</p></sec><sec id="sec7" disp-level="1"><title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title><p>This was a prospective longitudinal observational study aimed at generating pilot data. Healthy volunteers aged 18-40 years who were never smokers, with no history of chronic lung diseases, thoracic surgery, cardiovascular  and systemic diseases, and with no acute upper respiratory diathesis (runny nose, cough, sore throat, etc.) or fever, were recruited through convenience sampling at a tertiary care center in New Delhi, India. Given the exploratory nature of the study, a formal sample size and power calculation was not performed. However, we aimed to maximize enrollment to achieve the highest possible power within real-world resource limitations.</p><p>The AQI is the air quality metric determined by the Central Pollution Control Board of India, calculated  the highest indexed value among seven ambient pollutants: PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, CO, SO<sub>2</sub>, and NH<sub>3</sub>.<sup><xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Their official AQI calculator and its recommended interpretation are available in the <xref rid="supplementlink-1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material 1</xref>. Briefly, AQI values of 0–50 are classified as “good” (minimal impact), 51–100 as “satisfactory” (minor breathing discomfort), 101–200 as “moderate” (discomfort for sensitive individuals), 201–300 as “poor” (discomfort with prolonged exposure), 301–400 as “very poor” (potential respiratory illness with prolonged exposure), and values above 400 as “severe” (respiratory effects even in healthy individuals).</p><p>For each volunteer, comprehensive evaluations of respiratory parameters were made in two phases: an initial high pollution phase (HAQI) and a later low pollution phase (LAQI). Phase definitions were determined based on typical local AQI trends in New Delhi in 2018, the year preceding the study, to ensure adequate contrast between high and low AQI exposures while maintaining sufficient sampling windows. In 2018, the mean AQI during winter months (November–January) was 341±59, during the rainy season (July–September) it was 109±42, and during the remaining months it was 231±70. Therefore, HAQI was defined as an average daily AQI of &gt;350 for at least 7 consecutive days, and LAQI as an average daily AQI of &lt;150 for at least 7 consecutive days. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants at the time of enrollment.</p><p>Spirometry was used to measure lung volumes and capacities, and impulse oscillometry (IOS) was used to estimate respiratory impedance at two time points, i.e., HAQI and LAQI. Exhaled breath condensate (EBC) and blood were collected to measure airway and systemic inflammation by estimating biomarkers, including tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α) and interleukin-6 (IL-6), at both time points.</p><p>The study was approved by the All-India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi’s Ethics Committee for human subjects (ref. no.: IEC-622/6.09.2019, RP-15/2019).</p><sec id="sec8" disp-level="2"><title>Assessment of Lung Volumes and Capacities by Spirometry (Spiro’air Pulmonary Function Test System-Medisoft)</title><p>Spirometry was performed as per the guidelines of the American Thoracic Society and the European Respiratory Society (ERS).<sup><xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Of the three acceptable and repeatable slow vital capacity (SVC) and forced vital capacity (FVC) maneuvers, the highest values were considered. The parameters recorded were SVC, FVC, forced expiratory volume in the first second (FEV<sub>1</sub>), FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC ratio, and peak expiratory flow (PEF).</p></sec><sec id="sec9" disp-level="2"><title>Assessment of Respiratory Impedance by Impulse Oscillometry (MS-IOS Digital JAEGER System)</title><p>IOS, is a simple, non-invasive technique that mainly uses forced oscillations, to evaluate the mechanics of the lungs or airways. The participant’s effort is minimal when this method is compared to spirometry, to evaluate lung function. Sound waves of different frequencies ranging between 5Hz and 35Hz are superimposed over normal tidal breathing, and impedance is measured by the ratio of pressure signal to flow signal. Sound waves of smaller frequencies (&lt;15Hz) can reach the alveoli, but higher frequencies lose their strength in the central airways. The procedure was explained to the participants, and while the participants were in a sitting position, the sound waves were superimposed onto normal tidal breathing for 90 seconds. A tight seal between lips and mouthpiece was ensured. The cheeks were held firmly by the participant with their hands. The parameters recorded were airway impedance (Z), airway resistance at 5Hz and 20Hz (R<sub>5</sub>, R<sub>20</sub>), and airway reactance at 5Hz and 20Hz (X<sub>5</sub>, X<sub>20</sub>). The other oscillometry indices taken into consideration were peripheral airway resistance (R<sub>5</sub>- R<sub>20</sub>), resonant frequency, and an area under reactance.<sup><xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p><p>Assessment of inflammatory biomarkers using EBC and enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). EBC was performed according to ERS guidelines.<sup><xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> EBC was collected using an R-tube (Respiratory Research, Inc., USA). R-tube is a disposable collection system that consists of a large Tee section made of polypropylene, which separates saliva from the exhaled breath, a one-way valve (made of silicone rubber), and a polypropylene collection tube, which is cooled by a cooling aluminium sleeve placed around it. Subjects were instructed to breathe tidally by inhaling through the nose and exhaling through the mouthpiece connected to the R-tube for 10 minutes. Approximately 1.5 mL of the condensate was collected and  immediately stored at -20 °C. Separated serum from peripheral blood samples was also stored at -20 °C. Human ELISA kits of Boster Biotech, USA (Cat No: EK0525, EK0410) were used to quantify serum levels of TNF-α and IL-6, respectively. According to the manufacturer’s instructions, ELISA was performed, and a microplate reader (BioTek, EpochTM 2 microplate reader) was used to read the colour that developed in the 96-well plates. The detection range was 15.6-1000 pg/mL for TNF-α (sensitivity 1 pg/mL) and 4.69-300 pg/mL for IL-6 (sensitivity 0.3 pg/mL).</p></sec><sec id="sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>GraphPad Prism 9.0.1 for Windows (GraphPad Software, Inc., USA) was used for analysis. Each parameter was tested for distribution of the data based on standard normality tests (the D’Agostino-Pearson normality test, the Anderson-Darling test, the Shapiro-Wilk test). Based on the normality of the data, group comparisons were carried out using the paired t-test or the Wilcoxon signed-rank test along with the appropriate post-hoc comparison tests. The level of statistical significance was set at <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05. Bonferroni corrections were applied within each test domain (spirometry, IOS, and biomarkers) to adjust the significance thresholds for multiple comparisons.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec11" disp-level="1"><title>RESULTS</title><p>A total of 21 participants (mean age 25.4±7.4 years, female 33.3%, body mass index 23.9±3.5 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) who completed recordings at both time points was considered for analysis. The mean AQI was 395.7±43.8 during HAQI and 85.4±9.7 during LAQI phases (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0001). Detailed distribution of pollutants during the two phases is available in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table-1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 1. Air pollution parameters at two different time-points</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Parameters</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>High Pollution (AQI &gt;350 for 7 consecutive days)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Low pollution (AQI &lt;150 for 7 consecutive days)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold><italic>P</italic> value</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>AQI</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>395.7±43.8</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>85.4±9.7</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>PM<sub>2.5</sub></bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>394.6±43.9</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>54.0±17.0</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>PM<sub>10</sub></bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>369.6±55.7</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>64.7 ±19.4</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>NO<sub>2</sub></bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>51 (49-58)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>39 (26-41)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>0.02</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>NH<sub>3</sub></bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>6.6±1.3</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>23.1±0.7</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>SO<sub>2</sub></bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>14.0±1.2</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>16.4±2.7</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.07</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>CO</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>55.4±10.0</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>64.6±34.8</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.5</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>O<sub>3</sub></bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>19.6±1.7</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>35.1±9.9</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>0.01</bold>
</p>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p79"><p>Values presented are mean ± standard deviation or median (minimum-maximum), analyzed by Paired t-test (two-tailed) or Wilcoxon signed-rank test (two-tailed), respectively</p><p>AQI: air quality index, PM<sub>2.5</sub>: particulate matter 2.5, PM<sub>10</sub>: particulate matter 10, NO<sub>2</sub>: nitrogen dioxide, NH<sub>3</sub>: ammonia, SO<sub>2</sub>: sulfur dioxide, CO: carbon monoxide, O<sub>3</sub>: ozone</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="sec12" disp-level="2"><title>Spirometry Parameters</title><p>SVC<sub>(%pred)</sub> was lower in HAQI (81.6±11.2) compared to LAQI (87.7±7.7, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0008). Similarly, FVC<sub>(%pred)</sub> was lower in HAQI (86.2±9.8 vs. 90.9±9.4, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0005). While FEV<sub>1(%pred) </sub> was lower during HAQI [83 (75-89) vs. 89 (86-94), <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001], FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC was similar between both groups (95.0±11.2 vs. 96.4±10.0, <italic>P</italic> = 0.6). Results of spirometry are summarized in <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table-2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2. Spirometry parameters at two different time-points</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Spirometry parameters</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>High pollution (AQI &gt;350 for 7 consecutive days)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Low pollution (AQI &lt;150 for 7 consecutive days)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold><italic>P</italic> value*</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>SVC (%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>81.6±11.2</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>87.7±7.7</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>0.0008</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>FVC (%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>86.2±9.8</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>90.9±9.4</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>0.0005</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>FEV<sub>1</sub> (%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>83 (75-89)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>89 (86-94)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>95.0±11.2</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>96.4±10.0</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.6</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>MMEF (%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>75.5±23.1</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>88.0±18.5</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>0.003</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>PEF (%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>83.2±24.1</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>95.5±17.8</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>0.003</bold>
</p>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p109"><p>*The Bonferroni-corrected significance threshold was set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0083 (6 comparisons)</p><p>Values presented are mean ± standard deviation or median (minimum-maximum), analyzed by Paired t-test (two-tailed) or Wilcoxon signed-rank test (two-tailed) respectively</p><p>AQI: air quality index, SVC: slow vital capacity, FVC: forced vital capacity, FEV<sub>1</sub>: forced expiratory volume at 1<sup>st</sup> second, MMEF: maximum mid expiratory flow, PEF: peak expiratory flow</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec13" disp-level="2"><title>IOS Parameters</title><p>The airway resistance was higher in HAQI compared to LAQI, as measured by R<sub>5</sub> (%pred) [104.0 (94.2-123.2) vs. 75.0 (68.4-92.8), <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001] and R<sub>20</sub> (%pred) [108.7 (100.0-122.6) vs. 77.3 (69.5-89.6), <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001]. The reactance [X<sub>5</sub> (%pred) and X<sub>20</sub> (%pred)] was similar in both groups (<italic>P</italic> = 0.3 and <italic>P</italic> = 0.4), although absolute values of X<sub>5 </sub>were more negative in HAQI [-0.11 (-0.16-(-0.09)) vs. -0.07 (-0.09-(-0.05)), <italic>P</italic> =0.001]. The results of the IOS parameters are summarized in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table-3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3. Impulse oscillometry parameters at two different time-points</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Impulse oscillometry parameters</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>High pollution (AQI &gt;350 for 7 consecutive days)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Low pollution (AQI &lt;150 for 7 consecutive days)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold><italic>P</italic> value*</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>R<sub>5 </sub>[kPa/(L/s)]</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.27 [0.25-0.39]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.22 [0.18-0.29]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>R<sub>5</sub> (%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>104.0 [94.2-123.2]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>75.0 [68.4-92.8]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>R<sub>20 </sub>[kPa/(L/s)]</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.25 [0.23-0.34]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.18 [0.15-0.23]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>R<sub>20 </sub>(%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>108.7 [100.0-122.6]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>77.3 [69.5-89.6]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>&lt;0.0001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>R<sub>5</sub>-R<sub>20 </sub>[kPa/(L/s)]</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.04 [0.02-0.05]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.03 [0.02-0.05]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.09</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>X<sub>5 </sub>[kPa/(L/s)]</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>-0.11 [-0.16-(-0.09)]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>-0.07 [-0.09-(-0.05)]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>0.001</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>X<sub>5</sub> (%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>-333.3 [-491.7- 412.5]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>-200.0 [-308.3-395.8]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.2</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>X<sub>20 </sub>[kPa/(L/s)]</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>.06 [-0.01- 0.09]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.04 [0.01-0.07]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.2</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>X<sub>20</sub> (%predicted)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>66.7 [-11.7-100.0]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>57.1 [18.3-88.9]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.4</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Ax [kPa/L]</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.30 [0.21-0.90]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.28 [0.17-0.56]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.03</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Fres [1/sec]</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>13.8 [10.7-18.7]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>15.1 [11.3-18.4]</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.8</p>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p160"><p>*The Bonferroni-corrected significance threshold was set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0045 (11 comparisons)</p><p>Values presented are mean ± standard deviation or median (minimum-maximum), analyzed by Paired t-test (two-tailed) or Wilcoxon signed-rank test (two-tailed) respectively</p><p>AQI: air quality index, R<sub>5</sub>: resistance at 5Hz, R<sub>20</sub>: resistance at 20 Hz, R<sub>5</sub>-R<sub>20</sub>: peripheral airway resistance, X<sub>5</sub>: reactance at 5Hz, X<sub>20</sub>: reactance at 20Hz, Ax: area under reactance, Fres: resonant frequency</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec14" disp-level="2"><title>Inflammatory Biomarkers</title><p>There was no difference in the serum and EBC levels of TNF-α (<italic>P</italic> = 0.1 and <italic>P</italic> = 0.4) and IL-6 (<italic>P</italic> = 0.3 and <italic>P</italic> = 0.5) between the two groups. These results are summarized in <xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table-4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 4. Inflammatory biomarker parameters at two different time-points</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Inflammatory biomarkers</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>High pollution (AQI &gt;350 for 7 consecutive days)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>Low pollution (AQI &lt;150 for 7 consecutive days)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold><italic>P</italic> value*</bold>
</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>TNF-α in EBC (pg/mL)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>6.4±1.7</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>7.2±0.6</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.1</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>TNF-α in serum (pg/mL)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>4.6 (0.8-7.5)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>4.71 (0.0-6.5)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.4</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>IL-6 in EBC (pg/mL)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.3 (0.1-0.7)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.3 (0.2-0.5)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.3</p>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>
<bold>IL-6 in serum (pg/mL)</bold>
</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.5 (0.2-1.1)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.4 (0.0-1.6)</p>
</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<p>0.5</p>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p183"><p>*The Bonferroni-corrected significance threshold was set at <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0125 (4 comparisons)</p><p>Values presented are mean ± standard deviation or median (minimum-maximum), analyzed by Paired t-test (two-tailed) or Wilcoxon signed-rank test (two-tailed), respectively</p><p>AQI: air quality index, TNF-α: tumor necrosis factor-alpha, IL-6: interleukin 6, EBC: exhaled breath condensate</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="sec15" disp-level="1"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to prospectively evaluate comprehensive respiratory parameters using spirometry, IOS, and inflammatory markers in healthy volunteers regarding short-term changes in air pollution. Despite a small sample size for a pilot study, we found statistically significant differences associated with higher air pollution, including lower lung capacities, lower expiratory volume, and higher airway resistance. It is important to note, however, that these values remained within the normal prescribed limits. There was no statistically significant difference in the inflammatory markers noted in our study. Overall, higher ambient air pollution was associated with deleterious effects on clinically measurable pulmonary and airway parameters even over relatively short exposure periods in healthy individuals.</p><p>Our spirometry results are supported by conclusions from previous studies. In a 2019 systematic review, Edington et al. reported that short-term exposure to higher PM<sub>2.5  </sub>level was associated with a statistically significant decrease in FEV<sub>1</sub>.<sup><xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> In a retrospective cohort study in Belgium, Int Panis et al.<sup><xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> reported that FVC, FEV<sub>1</sub>, and PEF were negatively correlated with PM<sub>10</sub> concentrations on the day of examination. In a study on asthmatic patients in Thailand, Chujit et al.<sup><xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> found that PEF was most affected by NO<sub>2</sub> levels 2 days before and PM<sub>10</sub> levels 6 days before spirometry, proposing that this lag is required for these pollutants to affect the airway.</p><p>While SVC and FVC are generally expected to be similar in healthy individuals, a reduction in FVC and FEV<sub>1</sub> with a preserved SVC may serve as a sensitive marker of small airway limitation. Therefore, both parameters were measured and reported. In our study, however, the mean SVC% was lower than the mean FVC%, likely reflecting a measurement artifact. Given the more relaxed nature of the SVC manoeuvre, suboptimal respiratory effort may occur despite extensive participant coaching, particularly when compared to the more forceful and dynamic effort required during the FVC manoeuvre.</p><p>Although there is less literature exploring the acute impact of air pollution on IOS parameters, previous studies provide a theoretical framework for understanding the increased resistance observed during HAQI. In a cross-sectional study, De<sup><xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>, observed that long-term exposure to high levels of ambient air pollution during early life is associated with increased respiratory impedance in children, compared to those with lower pollution levels. This finding shows that ambient air pollution affects small airway resistance and elastic characteristics but not proximal airway resistance. Additionally, children who live in more polluted areas had a greater absolute magnitude of X<sub>5</sub> (more negative), suggesting that exposure to ambient air pollution may alter the respiratory system’s elastic properties or increase ventilation heterogeneity.<sup><xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> In a retrospective study of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients, Zhu et al.<sup><xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> found that short-term exposure to higher PM<sub>2.5</sub> was associated with worsening of IOS parameters, including respiratory impedance and reactance.</p><p>Friedman et al.<sup><xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> measured spirometry and IOS parameters among area workers and residents, who had breathed dust and fumes from the World Trade Centre tragedy in 2001. Among these participants, cases, i.e., those who developed lower respiratory symptoms, were more likely to have abnormal spirometry and increased respiratory impedance compared to controls, which persisted 7-8 years after exposure. They concluded that these abnormalities were primarily associated with dysfunction in the peripheral airways. </p><p>We observed that HAQI and LAQI had comparable levels of serum IL-6 and TNF-α in both EBC and serum. This is likely an artifact arising from our small sample size. Robust longitudinal measurements by Sabeti et al.<sup><xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> in Iran show that ambient PM<sub>2.5 </sub>and metal concentrations in places with high pollution levels is positively associated with increased TNF-α but negatively correlated with IL-6. A study on healthy Swiss adults found that serum levels of IL-6 and TNF-α were positively associated with short-term exposure to PM<sub>10</sub>. These findings provide strong support for the notion that short-term exposure to PM<sub>10</sub> is probably sufficient to induce systemic inflammation. Nevertheless, it is plausible that the very short duration of exposure to high pollution in our study (7 days), within a setting characterized by year-round elevated pollution levels, may have limited our ability to detect appreciable changes in inflammatory markers. Furthermore, unmeasured factors such as occult infections and other environmental exposures could have influenced baseline inflammatory status, potentially obscuring subtle differences.</p><p>Acute exposure to air pollutants can significantly impair respiratory function through several pathophysiological mechanisms. Inhaled pollutants, including particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5 </sub>and PM<sub>10</sub>), O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, and heavy metals, can irritate the respiratory mucosa, triggering oxidative stress and inflammation.<sup><xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> This leads to increased production of inflammatory cytokines, recruitment of immune cells, and disruption of epithelial barriers in the airways and gaseous exchange surfaces.<sup><xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Further, this can cause bronchoconstriction, airway edema, and reduced mucociliary clearance, as evidenced by exacerbations of conditions like asthma and COPD.<sup><xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Our study demonstrates, even in apparently healthy individuals, these processes can cause small yet measurable adverse effects on airway mechanics and pulmonary function. Further research is needed to elucidate the exact mechanisms by which this acute inflammatory reaction to air pollutants translates to long-term respiratory complications and other detrimental health effects.</p><p>While our results demonstrate a correlation between higher pollution levels and worse respiratory parameters, it is important to note that we did not adjust for other environmental confounders, including ambient temperature and humidity. Since the HAQI phase was predominantly recorded during winter months, cold temperatures may have influenced the spirometry and IOS measurements. Although cold dry air is generally known to induce bronchoconstriction, the effect of the winter season on spirometry parameters is complex. Recent studies suggest a paradoxical linear increase in FEV<sub>1</sub> and FVC with colder temperatures,<sup><xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> likely driven by factors such as reduced outdoor allergen exposure during winter months. The impact of seasonal variation in temperature and humidity on IOS parameters remains unclear. Future analyses should adjust for these covariates to better isolate the independent effect of ambient air pollution.</p><p>Interestingly, ambient levels of NH<sub>3</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, CO, and O<sub>3</sub> during the HAQI phase were similar to or paradoxically lower than those during the LAQI phase compared to the LAQI phase, despite substantially higher PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, and AQI. This trend may reflect chemical conversion of these gases into particulate matter or other compounds, leading to artificially low readings during the HAQI period.<sup><xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Temperature, humidity, and local wind patterns may also contribute. Nevertheless, it is important to note that despite lower gas levels, the elevated particulate matter and smog, during HAQI periods, result in worse overall air quality.</p><sec id="sec16" disp-level="2"><title>Study Limitations</title><p>This study should be interpreted in the context of several limitations. The use of a small convenience sample introduces potential selection bias and increases the risk of type II errors. Airway measurements may have been influenced by environmental confounders, beyond pollution, including ambient temperature, humidity, air conditioning, and circulating seasonal viruses. Participant-level factors such as time since last meal, recent exercise, stress, sleep, and caffeine intake were also not accounted for. Additionally, we did not record information regarding time spent indoors versus outdoors and recent travel history, which could impact cumulative exposure to air pollution. We have also not used any instrument to measure the volunteers’ personal exposure to air pollution. Given the relatively young age of our study population, these findings may not be generalizable to older individuals. Finally, we were unable to evaluate a dose-response relationship as only two measurements were made for each participant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec17" disp-level="1"><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Acute increase in air pollution adversely affects spirometry parameters and respiratory impedance in healthy adults. Larger longitudinal studies are needed to elucidate the effect of air pollution on local and systemic inflammation, as well as their link to chronic health outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="sec18" disp-level="1"><title>Ethics</title><p><bold>Ethics Committee Approval:</bold> The study was approved by the All-India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi’s Ethics Committee for human subjects (ref. no.: IEC-622/6.09.2019, RP-15/2019).</p><p><bold>Informed Consent:</bold> Written informed consent was obtained from all participants at the time of enrollment.</p></sec><sec id="sec19" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="supplementlink-1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Supplementary Material 1</label><caption><p>Parameters used to calculate Air Quality Index. AQI ranges indicate different levels of air quality- higher numbers indicate worse air quality</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://d2v96fxpocvxx.cloudfront.net/68ab204c-182b-49da-b227-bc7efe058632/content-images/928cd5de-ae8d-4b9a-9dc4-eebd127a1131.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://d2v96fxpocvxx.cloudfront.net/68ab204c-182b-49da-b227-bc7efe058632/content-images/928cd5de-ae8d-4b9a-9dc4-eebd127a1131.pdf</ext-link>
</p></caption></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn-1"><p><bold>Authorship Contributions:</bold> Surgical and Medical Practices: Surgical and Medical Practices: G.B., A.T., Concept: G.B., A.T., Design: G.B., A.G., A.T., Data Collection or Processing: A.G., L.M., S.G., K.S., Analysis or Interpretation: K.S., K.N.J., G.B., A.T., Literature Search: K.S., A.G., K.N.J., L.M., S.G., G.B., A.T., Writing: A.G., K.S., G.B.</p></fn><fn id="fn-2"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> No conflict of interest was declared by the authors.</p></fn><fn id="fn-3"><p><bold>Financial Disclosure:</bold> Financial support was provided by All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi, India.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="ref-list1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="ref-list1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="ref-1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Azimi MN, Rahman MM. Unveiling the health consequences of air pollution in the world’s most polluted nations. Sci Rep. 20. 2414;(1):9856. doi: 10.1038/s41598-024-60786-0.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-024-60786-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11058277"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38684837"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=20&amp;title=Unveiling the health consequences of air pollution in the world’s most polluted nations. Sci Rep.&amp;author=MN Azimi&amp;author=MM Rahman&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2414&amp;pages=9856&amp;pmid=38684837&amp;doi=10.1038/s41598-024-60786-0&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Garg A, Gupta NC. The great smog month and spatial and monthly variation in air quality in Ambient Air in Delhi, India. J Health Pollut. 2020;10(27):200910. doi: 10.5696/2156-9614-10.27.200910.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5696/2156-9614-10.27.200910"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7453814"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32874766"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Health Pollut&amp;title=The great smog month and spatial and monthly variation in air quality in Ambient Air in Delhi, India.&amp;author=A Garg&amp;author=NC Gupta&amp;volume=10&amp;issue=27&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=200910&amp;pmid=32874766&amp;doi=10.5696/2156-9614-10.27.200910&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lu F, Xu D, Cheng Y, Dong S, Guo C, Jiang X, Zheng X. Systematic review and meta-analysis of the adverse health effects of ambient PM2.5 and PM10 pollution in the Chinese population. Environ Res. 2015;136:196–204. doi: 10.1016/j.envres.2014.06.029.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envres.2014.06.029"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25460637"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ Res&amp;title=Systematic review and meta-analysis of the adverse health effects of ambient PM2.5 and PM10 pollution in the Chinese population.&amp;author=F Lu&amp;author=D Xu&amp;author=Y Cheng&amp;author=S Dong&amp;author=C Guo&amp;volume=136&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=196-204&amp;pmid=25460637&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envres.2014.06.029&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Marín-Palma D, Tabares-Guevara JH, Taborda N, Rugeles MT, Hernandez JC. Coarse particulate matter (PM10) induce an inflammatory response through the NLRP3 activation. J Inflamm (Lond) 2024;21(1):15. doi: 10.1186/s12950-024-00388-9.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12950-024-00388-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11064351"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38698414"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Inflamm (Lond)&amp;title=Coarse particulate matter (PM10) induce an inflammatory response through the NLRP3 activation.&amp;author=D Marín-Palma&amp;author=JH Tabares-Guevara&amp;author=N Taborda&amp;author=MT Rugeles&amp;author=JC Hernandez&amp;volume=21&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=15&amp;pmid=38698414&amp;doi=10.1186/s12950-024-00388-9&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">National Air Quality Index. Accessed Jan 24, 2024.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shang Y, Sun Z, Cao J, et al.  Systematic review of Chinese studies of short-term exposure to air pollution and daily mortality. Environ Int. 2013;54:100–111. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2013.01.010.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envint.2013.01.010"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23434817"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ Int&amp;title=Systematic review of Chinese studies of short-term exposure to air pollution and daily mortality.&amp;author=Y Shang&amp;author=Z Sun&amp;author=J Cao&amp;volume=54&amp;publication_year=2013&amp;pages=100-111&amp;pmid=23434817&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envint.2013.01.010&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lee BJ, Kim B, Lee K. Air pollution exposure and cardiovascular disease. Toxicol Res. 2014;30(2):71–75. doi: 10.5487/TR.2014.30.2.071.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5487/TR.2014.30.2.071"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4112067"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25071915"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Toxicol Res&amp;title=Air pollution exposure and cardiovascular disease.&amp;author=BJ Lee&amp;author=B Kim&amp;author=K Lee&amp;volume=30&amp;issue=2&amp;publication_year=2014&amp;pages=71-75&amp;pmid=25071915&amp;doi=10.5487/TR.2014.30.2.071&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Graham BL, Steenbruggen I, Miller MR, et al.  Standardization of Spirometry 2019 Update. An Official American Thoracic Society and European Respiratory Society Technical Statement. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2019;200(8):e70–e88. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201908-1590st.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1164/rccm.201908-1590st"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6794117"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31613151"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Am J Respir Crit Care Med&amp;title=Standardization of Spirometry 2019 Update. An Official American Thoracic Society and European Respiratory Society Technical Statement.&amp;author=BL Graham&amp;author=I Steenbruggen&amp;author=MR Miller&amp;volume=200&amp;issue=8&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=e70-e88&amp;pmid=31613151&amp;doi=10.1164/rccm.201908-1590st&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bickel S, Popler J, Lesnick B, Eid N. Impulse oscillometry: interpretation and practical applications. Chest. 2014;146(3):841–847. doi: 10.1378/chest.13-1875.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1378/chest.13-1875"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25180727"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Chest&amp;title=Impulse oscillometry: interpretation and practical applications.&amp;author=S Bickel&amp;author=J Popler&amp;author=B Lesnick&amp;author=N Eid&amp;volume=146&amp;issue=3&amp;publication_year=2014&amp;pages=841-847&amp;pmid=25180727&amp;doi=10.1378/chest.13-1875&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Horváth I, Hunt J, Barnes PJ, et al.  Exhaled breath condensate: methodological recommendations and unresolved questions. Eur Respir J. 2005;26(3):523–548. doi: 10.1183/09031936.05.00029705.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1183/09031936.05.00029705"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16135737"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Eur Respir J&amp;title=Exhaled breath condensate: methodological recommendations and unresolved questions.&amp;author=I Horváth&amp;author=J Hunt&amp;author=PJ Barnes&amp;volume=26&amp;issue=3&amp;publication_year=2005&amp;pages=523-548&amp;pmid=16135737&amp;doi=10.1183/09031936.05.00029705&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Edginton S, O'Sullivan DE, King W, Lougheed MD. Effect of outdoor particulate air pollution on FEV 1 in healthy adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Occup Environ Med. 2019;76(8):583–591. doi: 10.1136/oemed-2018-105420.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1136/oemed-2018-105420"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31189694"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Occup Environ Med&amp;title=Effect of outdoor particulate air pollution on FEV 1 in healthy adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis.&amp;author=S Edginton&amp;author=DE O'Sullivan&amp;author=W King&amp;author=MD Lougheed&amp;volume=76&amp;issue=8&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=583-591&amp;pmid=31189694&amp;doi=10.1136/oemed-2018-105420&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Int Panis L, Provost EB, Cox B, et al.  Short-term air pollution exposure decreases lung function: a repeated measures study in healthy adults. Environ Health. 2017;16(1):60. doi: 10.1186/s12940-017-0271-z.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12940-017-0271-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5471732"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28615020"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ Health&amp;title=Short-term air pollution exposure decreases lung function: a repeated measures study in healthy adults.&amp;author=Panis L Int&amp;author=EB Provost&amp;author=B Cox&amp;volume=16&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2017&amp;pages=60&amp;pmid=28615020&amp;doi=10.1186/s12940-017-0271-z&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chujit W, Wiwatanadate P, Deesomchok A, Sopajaree K, Eldeirawi K, Tsai YI. Air pollution levels related to peak expiratory flow rates among adult asthmatics in Lampang, Thailand. Aerosol and Air Quality Research. 2020;20(6):1398–1410. doi: 10.4209/aaqr.2020.03.0092.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4209/aaqr.2020.03.0092"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Aerosol and Air Quality Research&amp;title=Air pollution levels related to peak expiratory flow rates among adult asthmatics in Lampang, Thailand.&amp;author=W Chujit&amp;author=P Wiwatanadate&amp;author=A Deesomchok&amp;author=K Sopajaree&amp;author=K Eldeirawi&amp;volume=20&amp;issue=6&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=1398-1410&amp;doi=10.4209/aaqr.2020.03.0092&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">De S. Long-term ambient air pollution exposure and respiratory impedance in children: a cross-sectional study. Respir Med. 2020;170:105795. doi: 10.1016/j.rmed.2019.09.015.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.rmed.2019.09.015"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32843155"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Respir Med&amp;title=Long-term ambient air pollution exposure and respiratory impedance in children: a cross-sectional study.&amp;author=S De&amp;volume=170&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=105795&amp;pmid=32843155&amp;doi=10.1016/j.rmed.2019.09.015&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhu RX, Nie XH, Liu XF, Zhang YX, Chen J, Liu XJ, Hui XJ. Short-term effect of particulate matter on lung function and impulse oscillometry system (IOS) parameters of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) in Beijing, China. BMC Public Health. 2023;23(1):1417. doi: 10.1186/s12889-023-16308-0.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12889-023-16308-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10367330"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37488590"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMC Public Health&amp;title=Short-term effect of particulate matter on lung function and impulse oscillometry system (IOS) parameters of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) in Beijing, China.&amp;author=RX Zhu&amp;author=XH Nie&amp;author=XF Liu&amp;author=YX Zhang&amp;author=J Chen&amp;volume=23&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=1417&amp;pmid=37488590&amp;doi=10.1186/s12889-023-16308-0&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Friedman SM, Maslow CB, Reibman J, et al.  Case-control study of lung function in World Trade Center Health Registry area residents and workers. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2011;184(5):582–589. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201011-1909oc.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1164/rccm.201011-1909oc"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21642248"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Am J Respir Crit Care Med&amp;title=Case-control study of lung function in World Trade Center Health Registry area residents and workers.&amp;author=SM Friedman&amp;author=CB Maslow&amp;author=J Reibman&amp;volume=184&amp;issue=5&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=582-589&amp;pmid=21642248&amp;doi=10.1164/rccm.201011-1909oc&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sabeti Z, Ansarin K, Seyedrezazadeh E, et al.  Acute responses of airway oxidative stress, inflammation, and hemodynamic markers to ambient PM 2.5 and their trace metal contents among healthy adolescences: a panel study in highly polluted versus low polluted regions. Environ Pollut. 2021;288:117797. doi: 10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117797.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117797"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34329054"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ Pollut&amp;title=Acute responses of airway oxidative stress, inflammation, and hemodynamic markers to ambient PM 2.5 and their trace metal contents among healthy adolescences: a panel study in highly polluted versus low polluted regions.&amp;author=Z Sabeti&amp;author=K Ansarin&amp;author=E Seyedrezazadeh&amp;volume=288&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=117797&amp;pmid=34329054&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envpol.2021.117797&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tsai DH, Amyai N, Marques-Vidal P, et al.  Effects of particulate matter on inflammatory markers in the general adult population. Part Fibre Toxicol. 2012;9(1):24. doi: 10.1186/1743-8977-9-24.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1743-8977-9-24"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3464812"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22769230"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Part Fibre Toxicol&amp;title=Effects of particulate matter on inflammatory markers in the general adult population.&amp;author=DH Tsai&amp;author=N Amyai&amp;author=P Marques-Vidal&amp;volume=9&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=24&amp;pmid=22769230&amp;doi=10.1186/1743-8977-9-24&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Barbier E, Carpentier J, Simonin O, et al.  Oxidative stress and inflammation induced by air pollution-derived PM 2.5 persist in the lungs of mice after cessation of their sub-chronic exposure. Environ Int. 2023;181:108248. doi: 10.1016/j.envint.2023.108248.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envint.2023.108248"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37857188"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ Int&amp;title=Oxidative stress and inflammation induced by air pollution-derived PM 2.5 persist in the lungs of mice after cessation of their sub-chronic exposure.&amp;author=E Barbier&amp;author=J Carpentier&amp;author=O Simonin&amp;volume=181&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=108248&amp;pmid=37857188&amp;doi=10.1016/j.envint.2023.108248&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lodovici M, Bigagli E. Oxidative stress and air pollution exposure. J Toxicol. 2011;2011:487074. doi: 10.1155/2011/487074.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1155/2011/487074"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3155788"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21860622"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Toxicol&amp;title=Oxidative stress and air pollution exposure.&amp;author=M Lodovici&amp;author=E Bigagli&amp;volume=2011&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=487074&amp;pmid=21860622&amp;doi=10.1155/2011/487074&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dadvand P, Nieuwenhuijsen MJ, Agustí À, et al.  Air pollution and biomarkers of systemic inflammation and tissue repair in COPD patients. Eur Respir J. 2014;44(3):603–613. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00168813.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1183/09031936.00168813"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24558180"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Eur Respir J&amp;title=Air pollution and biomarkers of systemic inflammation and tissue repair in COPD patients.&amp;author=P Dadvand&amp;author=MJ Nieuwenhuijsen&amp;author=À Agustí&amp;volume=44&amp;issue=3&amp;publication_year=2014&amp;pages=603-613&amp;pmid=24558180&amp;doi=10.1183/09031936.00168813&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pope CA 3rd, Bhatnagar A, McCracken JP, Abplanalp W, Conklin DJ, O'Toole T. Exposure to fine particulate air pollution is associated with endothelial injury and systemic inflammation. Circ Res. 2016;119(11):1204–1214. doi: 10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.309279.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.309279"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5215745"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27780829"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Circ Res&amp;title=Exposure to fine particulate air pollution is associated with endothelial injury and systemic inflammation.&amp;author=CA 3rd Pope&amp;author=A Bhatnagar&amp;author=JP McCracken&amp;author=W Abplanalp&amp;author=DJ Conklin&amp;volume=119&amp;issue=11&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=1204-1214&amp;pmid=27780829&amp;doi=10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.116.309279&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Raby KL, Michaeloudes C, Tonkin J, Chung KF, Bhavsar PK. Mechanisms of airway epithelial injury and abnormal repair in asthma and COPD. Front Immunol. 2023;14:1201658. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2023.1201658.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fimmu.2023.1201658"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10374037"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37520564"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Front Immunol&amp;title=Mechanisms of airway epithelial injury and abnormal repair in asthma and COPD.&amp;author=KL Raby&amp;author=C Michaeloudes&amp;author=J Tonkin&amp;author=KF Chung&amp;author=PK Bhavsar&amp;volume=14&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=1201658&amp;pmid=37520564&amp;doi=10.3389/fimmu.2023.1201658&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rice MB, Li W, Wilker EH, Gold DR, et al.  Association of outdoor temperature with lung function in a temperate climate. Eur Respir J. 2019;53(1):1800612. doi: 10.1183/13993003.00612-2018.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1183/13993003.00612-2018"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6903481"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30578386"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Eur Respir J&amp;title=Association of outdoor temperature with lung function in a temperate climate.&amp;author=MB Rice&amp;author=W Li&amp;author=EH Wilker&amp;author=DR Gold&amp;volume=53&amp;issue=1&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=1800612&amp;pmid=30578386&amp;doi=10.1183/13993003.00612-2018&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ismaeel A, Tai APK, Wu J. Understanding the spatial patterns of atmospheric ammonia trends in South Asia. Sci Total Environ. 2024;954:176188. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.176188.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.176188"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39265679"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Sci Total Environ&amp;title=Understanding the spatial patterns of atmospheric ammonia trends in South Asia.&amp;author=A Ismaeel&amp;author=APK Tai&amp;author=J Wu&amp;volume=954&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=176188&amp;pmid=39265679&amp;doi=10.1016/j.scitotenv.2024.176188&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Supplementary Material 1</label><caption><p>Parameters used to calculate Air Quality Index. AQI ranges indicate different levels of air quality- higher numbers indicate worse air quality</p><p>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://d2v96fxpocvxx.cloudfront.net/68ab204c-182b-49da-b227-bc7efe058632/content-images/928cd5de-ae8d-4b9a-9dc4-eebd127a1131.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://d2v96fxpocvxx.cloudfront.net/68ab204c-182b-49da-b227-bc7efe058632/content-images/928cd5de-ae8d-4b9a-9dc4-eebd127a1131.pdf</ext-link>
</p></caption></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body></article>