<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3532</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">isci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>iScience</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>iScience</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11883379</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11883379</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11883379</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40051831</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2025.111894</article-id><title-group><article-title>Ensemble stacking of machine learning models for air quality prediction for Hyderabad city in India</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravindiran</surname><given-names initials="G">Gokulan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Karthick</surname><given-names initials="K">K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajamanickam</surname><given-names initials="S">Sivarethinamohan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names initials="D">Deepshikha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names initials="B">Bimal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Shyamala</surname><given-names initials="G">G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayder</surname><given-names initials="G">Gasim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Maria</surname><given-names initials="A">Azees</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="author-notes">10</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="author-notes">∗</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Civil Engineering, Dayananda Sagar College of Engineering, Bengaluru, Karnataka 560078, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Institute of Energy Infrastructure, Universiti Tenaga Nasional (UNITEN), 43000 Kajang, Selangor Darul Ehsan, Malaysia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Electrical and Electronics Engineering, GMR Institute of Technology, Rajam 532 127, Andhra Pradesh, India</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Symbiosis Centre for Management Studies, Bengaluru Campus, Symbiosis International (Deemed University), Bengaluru, Karnataka, India</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Chemistry, Brainware University, Barasat, Kolkata, West Bengal, India</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Chemical Engineering, National Institute of Technology, Durgapur, Durgapur, West Bengal, India</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Civil Engineering, SR University, Warangal 506371, Telangana, India</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Civil Engineering, College of Engineering, Universiti Tenaga Nasional (UNITEN), 43000 Kajang, Selangor Darul Ehsan, Malaysia</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>School of Computer Science and Engineering, VIT-AP University, Amaravati, Andhra Pradesh 522 237, India</aff><author-notes><fn id="cor1"><label>∗</label><p>Corresponding author <email>azeesmm@gmail.com</email></p></fn><fn id="fn1"><label>10</label><p id="ntpara0010">Lead contact</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>111894</fpage><page-range>111894</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="main.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b537/11883379/de1ab6199ae8/main.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 5227795?></self-uri><abstract id="abs0010"><title>Summary</title><p>Hyderabad, one of the rapidly developing cities in India, is facing with severe air pollution due to rapid urbanization, industrial operations, and climatic factors. To alleviate the negative impact on human health and the environment, accurate monitoring and forecasting of air quality are essential. This research utilized various machine learning models, such as XGBoost, LarsCV, Bayesian Ridge, AdaBoost, and ensemble stacking methods, to forecast the air quality index (AQI) using data from August 2016 to October 2023, which included 18 different air pollutants, including meteorological parameters. The ensemble stacking method showed excellent performance, attaining high training (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.994) and validation (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.999) accuracy with low error metrics (mean absolute error [MAE] = 0.496, mean square error [MSE] = 0.429, root-mean-square error [RMSE] = 0.655). These results highlight the efficacy of ensemble stacking for AQI prediction, providing crucial information for policymakers to formulate strategies to reduce air pollution’s effects on public health and environmental sustainability.</p><sec id="kwrds0010" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject areas:</bold> Environmental health, Environmental monitoring, Artificial intelligence</p></sec></abstract><abstract id="abs0015" abstract-type="graphical"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="fx1.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/82da43c679cd/fx1.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 996?><?original-width 996?><?scaled-height 664?><?scaled-width 664?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="fx1.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/beb76306cde0/fx1.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></abstract><abstract id="abs0020" abstract-type="author-highlights"><title>Highlights</title><list list-type="label" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>•</label><p id="p0010">Air quality index (AQI) is predicted for Hyderabad city, India</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>•</label><p id="p0015">Machine learning models used air pollutants and meteorological parameters to predict AQI</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>•</label><p id="p0020">Hyperparameter tuning was done using GridSearchCV with 5-fold cross-validation</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><label>•</label><p id="p0025">Ensemble stacking achieves top accuracy with R<sup>2</sup> of 0.999 and low error rates</p></list-item></list></abstract><abstract id="abs0025" abstract-type="teaser"><p>Environmental health; Environmental monitoring; Artificial intelligence</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2024 Oct 15; Revised 2024 Nov 27; Accepted 2025 Jan 22; Collection date 2025 Feb 21.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">Air pollution is considered one of the most serious threats to humans and the environment compared to all other pollution.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Air pollutants associated with human health disorders include particulate matter 2.5 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>) and 10 (PM<sub>10</sub>), carbon monoxide, ozone, nitrogen dioxide, and sulfur dioxide. The World Health Organization (WHO) reported that approximately 11% of deaths are due to air pollution, and 92% of the population lives in polluted cities. Air pollution is the most common and severe impact in low- and middle-income countries where air pollutant concentration in the atmosphere increases vigorously due to urbanization and industrial activities.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> PM<sub>2.5</sub> exposure is the maximum in Asia, Africa, and the Middle East. Some air pollutants, like black carbon and ozone precursors, play a role in global warming, whereas greenhouse gases (GHGs) are the main factors driving climate change. Many governments and non-governmental organizations (NGOs) are combating the impact of climate change by adopting strict regulations. To successfully implement air pollution control strategies, it is essential to monitor air pollutant emissions, analyze air quality, and predict or forecast air quality.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Almost all countries have started monitoring and recording air pollutants in major cities and using them to adapt and implement strategies to reduce them.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p id="p0035">Air pollution is a complex problem, and analyzing the reason for high levels of air pollutants that exist in a region is difficult because several parameters affect the air quality. Metrological factors, namely, rainfall, wind speed, and wind direction, play a major role in the dispersion of air pollutants from one place to another. The city’s geography also plays a major role in the elevated atmospheric concentrations.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> India is also a developing country where air pollution is a significant problem.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> In India, it is predicted that, by 2050, the urban population will account for approximately 53%.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> This urban development will change land use and land cover patterns and will be a root cause of climate change.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Furthermore, urbanization increases anthropogenic emissions, such as carbon dioxide, methane, and nitrous oxide. It also results in natural disasters, such as extreme heat, heat waves, floods, droughts, and changes in rainfall patterns.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Urbanization also increases the emission of aerosols and other GHGs into the atmosphere due to vehicular and industrial emissions.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref></p><p id="p0040">The 2022 World Air Quality Report focused on PM<sub>2.5</sub> and examined 7,323 cities in 131 countries, unions, and regions (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://shorturl.at/UjpO1" ext-link-type="uri">https://shorturl.at/UjpO1</ext-link>). IQAir is a Swiss air quality monitoring company that releases AQI annually to understand the global trends in many developed and developing countries. IQAir aims to deliver data about the current status of air pollution to the government, NGOs, researchers, educators, and several other organizations. As per the report released by IQAir, only 13 out of 131 countries meet the guideline values of PM<sub>2.5</sub> less than the 5 μg/m<sup>3</sup> prescribed by the WHO. In India, the PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration was observed as 53.3 μg/m<sup>3</sup> and ranked eighth; in 2021, the average PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration was 58.5 μg/m<sup>3</sup> and ranked fifth globally. It was observed that, of the 20 top-polluted cities, 14 were from India. Bhiwadi, India, stood at third position in the world and first in India with an average PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration of 92.7 μg/m<sup>3</sup> and 106.2 μg/m<sup>3</sup> in 2021. It is also observed that all 14 cities are from north India, five are from Bihar (Darbhanga, Asopur, Patna, Chapra, and Muzaffarpur), three towns are from Haryana (Dharuhera, Bahadurgarh, and Faridabad), three cities are from Uttar Pradesh (Ghaziabad, Muzaffarnagar, and Greater Noida), two are from Delhi (Delhi [National Capital Territory] and New Delhi), and one city is from Rajasthan (Bhiwadi). All five states are located very close to each other. Industrial activities, agricultural practices, and alluvial soil along the Gangetic plains are some of the primary causes of pollution. Alluvium, as a fertile soil, is made up of loose, unconsolidated particles, and as a result, dry alluvial soil contributes significantly to wind-blown dust.</p><p id="p0045">The air quality index (AQI) determines the air quality and categorizes it as good, satisfactory, moderate, poor, or very poor. <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref> summarizes the different AQI categories and sub-indexes of pollutants with possible human health impacts. In India, the AQI is determined according to the standards set by the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB) as part of the National Air Quality Index framework. For every pollutant, a sub-index is generated using the measured concentration of the pollutant and its relevant breakpoint values outlined in the CPCB AQI table. The overall AQI is calculated based on the highest sub-index value from the pollutants measured. This approach ensures that the pollutant with the most significant health risk influences the AQI. The AQI is divided into six categories (from good to severe), each linked with specific color codes and health recommendations to assist the public in interpreting and reacting to air quality conditions. Forecasting the AQI has numerous significant applications and advantages, especially regarding public health, urban development, and environmental stewardship. The primary benefits include safeguarding health, aiding policy and planning, optimizing resources, promoting climate and ecological gains, providing economic advantages, and enhancing disaster readiness. By utilizing machine learning (ML) and sophisticated predictive models, AQI prediction enables communities, governments, and industries to take proactive measures, leading to improved health outcomes, sustainable growth, and strengthened environmental resilience.</p><p id="p0050">Forecasting AQI is very important, and ML models are promising techniques compared to conventional methods. ML is crucial for enhancing air quality through its sophisticated abilities to monitor, forecast, and regulate air pollution. By utilizing its potential to analyze intricate datasets, reveal underlying trends, and offer practical recommendations, ML dramatically improves the ability to oversee, anticipate, and control air quality, leading to healthier environments and enhanced quality of life.</p><p id="p0055">The present study uses an ensemble stacking algorithm model to forecast the AQI of Hyderabad city and Telangana state of India. In recent years, Hyderabad has experienced several climate change impacts and urban heat island effects.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> The current PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration in Hyderabad exceeds the WHO annual air quality guideline value by 5.9 times. According to the report released by IQAir 2023, based on PM<sub>2.5</sub>, Hyderabad ranked 308<sup>th</sup> globally, 301<sup>st</sup> in the Asia continent, 151<sup>st</sup> in India, and 2<sup>nd</sup> in Telangana State.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> In the southern part of India, Hyderabad is a rapidly growing metropolitan city that provides a strong basis for forecasting the AQI owing to its elevated pollution levels. Hyderabad faces significant air quality issues caused by industrial operations, vehicle emissions, and construction dust. The city’s air pollution has recently deteriorated, consistently surpassing both the WHO and national standards for PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentrations, posing serious health risks to its residents. Furthermore, its distinct climate and seasonal variations make predicting AQI crucial to managing public health and policy measures. The city’s high population density and urban expansion further worsen these conditions, emphasizing the necessity for accurate AQI prediction to improve adverse environmental and human health impacts.</p></sec><sec id="sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec2.1" disp-level="2"><title>AQI</title><p id="p0060"><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the seasonal and annual variations in the AQI. The maximum mean AQI was observed at 111.2, followed by the minimum AQI in 2016. It is observed that the AQI ranges between 81.6 and 111.2, indicating that the air is moderately polluted and that long-term exposure will result in health issues for human health and affect the environment. The results also clearly demonstrated that AQI was higher in winter than in the summer and monsoon seasons. The winter season in India spans between November and February, and the AQI was 133.4, 14.1.5, 144.2, and 136.6 for November, December, January, and February, respectively. The higher AQI in winter may be due to temperature inversion, slower wind speed, Diwali festival, vehicular emissions, and construction activities.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> The AQI also decreased drastically from June to September, and the AQI rate was between 41 and 58.7. The probable reason for the reduced AQI was the monsoon season. During the monsoon period, atmospheric pollutants are collected and dispersed to the surroundings by heavy rainfall and high wind speed.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>
<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows that AQI values decreased from 104.5 in 2019 to 100.4 in 2020 and decreased to 98.1 in 2021. This was due to the COVID-19 pandemic lockdown, where vehicular emissions were reduced drastically and infrastructure development was almost stopped, which might have reduced air pollutants.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Based on seasonal trends, some strategies that could mitigate air pollution include strengthening vehicle emission standards during winter and encouraging using natural gas or electric heating systems.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Mean AQI variation of Hyderabad city</p><p>(A) Monthly variation.</p><p>(B) Yearly variation.</p><p>This graph illustrates the monthly and yearly variations of air quality index of Hyderabad city from 2016 to 2023.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/401786aa7a2b/gr1.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1770?><?original-width 2244?><?scaled-height 590?><?scaled-width 748?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="gr1.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/ea6b492fb941/gr1.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.2" disp-level="2"><title>PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub></title><p id="p0065"><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> illustrate the seasonal and monthly variations in PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10.</sub> The results show that, for PM<sub>2.5</sub>, the concentration increased from 43.9 to 52 from 2016 to 2022 but suddenly decreased in 2021 and 2023. The decrease in concentration may be due to several reasons, namely the COVID-19 impact in 2021; seasonal and weather conditions; and adapting green initiatives, policies, and regulations. In 2023, the average mean value may be slightly less than that in 2022; this may also be due to the availability of datasets. The datasets were used until October 2023, and, generally, the values were high in November and December, which may also reduce the average mean values. PM<sub>2.5</sub>, in 2021, is lower than that in 2020, despite the COVID-19 lockdown in 2020. This may be due to the pre-existing PM<sub>2.5</sub> levels being high in 2020, and the lockdown in 2020 might have reduced the available PM<sub>2.5</sub>, so reduced PM<sub>2.5</sub> was observed in 2021 compared to 2020. It is also observed that the seasonal variation trend of particulate matter is similar to AQI, confirming that PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> play a significant role in the final AQI values. Therefore, it is recommended that green initiatives and technological advancements be initiated to reduce PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, and other pollutants to reduce AQI values.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Mean PM<sub>2.5</sub> variation of Hyderabad city</p><p>(A) Monthly variation.</p><p>(B) Yearly variation.</p><p>This graph illustrates the monthly and yearly variations of particulate matter 2.5 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>) in Hyderabad city, India, from 20016 to 2023.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/c190f9c8609c/gr2.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1797?><?original-width 2244?><?scaled-height 599?><?scaled-width 748?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="gr2.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/0cf06badae82/gr2.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Mean PM<sub>10</sub> variation of Hyderabad city</p><p>(A) Monthly variation.</p><p>(B) Yearly variation.</p><p>This graph illustrates the monthly and yearly variations of particulate matter 10 (PM<sub>10</sub>) in Hyderabad city, India, from 20016 to 2023.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/dc8ecaa4f05f/gr3.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1794?><?original-width 2244?><?scaled-height 598?><?scaled-width 748?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="gr3.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/57216dabd92d/gr3.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.3" disp-level="2"><title>Gaseous pollutants and meteorological factors</title><p id="p0070">Gaseous pollutants are equally significant in determining the AQI and maintaining a healthy environment. Like PM<sub>2.5</sub>, higher concentrations of gaseous pollutants in the atmosphere harm human health and the environment. The key gaseous pollutants with severe effects were O<sub>3</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, CO, and NH<sub>3</sub>. The study datasets revealed that NOx, NO<sub>2</sub>, and CO significantly impacted the AQI values, with correlation coefficients of 0.59, 0.58, and 0.57, respectively. Other gaseous pollutants, namely ozone, benzene, xylene, and toluene, correlate negatively. <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2</xref> illustrates the variation in gaseous pollutants, with NO concentration reaching approximately 40 μg/m³ from 2016 to 2019. During 2020, the concentration of NO was maintained in the range between 2 and 2.6 μg/m³, a reduction attributed to the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. The lockdown led to a drastic reduction in vehicular emissions and limited industrial operations, resulting in lower levels. Post-COVID, the NO concentration started to increase in the atmosphere by 2021. However, the atmospheric concentration was less than that in the pre-COVID situation, possibly due to increased emission standards and other meteorological parameters.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> The same trend was observed for NO<sub>2</sub>, NOx, NH<sub>3</sub>, SO<sub>2</sub>, and O<sub>3</sub>. NO<sub>2</sub> concentrations were high during the period 2016 to 2020, and, after 2020, the NO<sub>2</sub> concentration also decreased. Initially, the NO<sub>2</sub> concentration varied between 10 and 100 μg/m³ during 2016–2020, and, after 2020, the NO<sub>2</sub> concentration was found to be less than 60 μg/m³ and varied between 20 and 40 μg/m³. NO<sub>2</sub> was found to have strong correlations of 0.60, 0.59, and 0.95 with PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, and NOx, respectively.</p><p id="p0075">O<sub>3</sub> levels increased from 2016 to 2018, reaching a maximum concentration of 120 μg/m³. After 2020, the ozone concentrations were stable with minor fluctuations, and this concentration was much lower than those from 2016 to 2018. A similar trend was observed for the NOx emissions from 2016 to 2018. The NOx concentration was high and gradually decreased until 2020. The NO<sub>x</sub> concentration was found to stay decreased between 2020 and 2024, and the average concentration was between 40 and 60 μg/m³. NOx emissions mainly come from vehicular emissions, which started reducing in 2020, possibly due to the implementation of Bharat stage VI norms in 2020 and the utilization of electric vehicles.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> NO<sub>x</sub> is considered as one of the main precursors for the formation of ground-level ozone. Because of solar irradiation, nitrogen oxides and volatile organic compounds react and form ground-level ozone. Therefore, increased NO<sub>x</sub> emissions will result in increased ground-level ozone and vice versa.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></p><p id="p0080">Similar to NOx and O<sub>3</sub>, NH<sub>3</sub> exhibited the same trend. From 2016 to early 2020, the NH<sub>3</sub> concentration was found to have a maximum concentration of 60–80 μg/m³, and, on most days, it was between 10 and 40 μg/m³ after 2020. The NH<sub>3</sub> concentration was reduced to be less than 20 μg/m³. No direct link exists between NO<sub>x</sub> and O<sub>3</sub>, but, due to the COVID-19 lockdown, reduced industrial emissions might have reduced these levels. The main source of NH<sub>3</sub> emissions is agricultural activities, where the utilization of fertilizers results in the emission of ammonia, and waste management is another primary sector that results in NH<sub>3</sub> emissions.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> The reduced NH<sub>3</sub> concentration may reduce the utilization of fewer fertilizers in and around Hyderabad city and improve waste management strategies adopted by the government.</p><p id="p0085">NH<sub>3</sub> is strongly correlated with temperature (0.57) and vertical wind speed (0.60), and an increase in temperature results in ammonia volatilization from the soil, organic manure, and fertilizers. During hot or warm climates, NH<sub>3</sub> concentrations will be high in the atmosphere because the volatilization rate of ammonia from the sources will be maximum.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Generally, ammonia is highly soluble in water, and an increase in temperature warms water bodies, resulting in a lower solubility. This results in the release of more gaseous ammonia into the atmosphere. Ammonia reacts with other gaseous pollutants, SO<sub>2</sub> and NO<sub>x</sub>, to form secondary particulate matter.</p><p id="p0090">These gaseous pollutants at elevated levels cause several health issues. Prolonged exposure to NOx elevates the chances of experiencing strokes and heart diseases. Short exposure to ozone leads to respiratory irritation, reduced lung capacity, and worsening asthma symptoms. Long-term exposure to ozone increases the likelihood of developing chronic respiratory problems like chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Short-term exposure to SOx irritates the respiratory tract and results in coughing and difficulty in breathing, while extended exposure results in lung diseases, such as bronchitis. NH₃ acts as an irritant, leading to coughing and throat irritation. CO interacts with hemoglobin to produce carboxyhemoglobin, which reduces oxygen transport in the bloodstream, resulting in headaches, dizziness, and potentially death at elevated levels. Extended exposure to CO impacts both the cardiovascular and neurological systems. Benzene is considered carcinogenic and is associated with leukemia and various other cancers. Xylene can lead to headaches, dizziness, and neurological impacts with long-term exposure.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></p><p id="p0095">Metrological factors also play a significant role in atmospheric pollutant concentrations. Wind speed and direction play significant roles in the dispersion of pollutants, and relative humidity also plays a crucial role in air pollution.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref>
<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S3</xref> illustrates the different meteorological parameters and their seasonal variation. Temperature, relative humidity, and solar radiation exhibit uniform seasonal variations. Small spikes and fluctuations may be due to extreme weather events like cyclones and storms. Some parameters are strongly correlated, namely, wind speed, which corresponds to a decrease in barometric pressure, and relative humidity, which varies with temperature fluctuations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4" disp-level="2"><title>Wind direction and its impact on AQI</title><p id="p0100">The wind rose diagram was used to understand the wind speed and direction of the city, which affects the migration of air pollutants from one place to another.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref>
<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> illustrates Hyderabad’s daily wind rose diagram from 2016 to 2023. <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> shows that the average wind speed in the city was always in the range of 0–1.9 m/s, and, on some days, the average daily wind speed was approximately 1.9–3.8 m/s. The maximum wind speed during the study period was 9.35 m/s. According to the wind rose diagram results, Hyderabad receives 12% wind from the west and 12% from the south. Furthermore, approximately 27% of the wind blows from the south-west and 31% from southeast directions.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Wind rose diagram of Hyderabad city for the study period of 2016–2023</p><p>This graph illustrates the wind rose diagram of Hyderabad city, considering data from 2016 to 2023. Wind speed and wind directions are illustrated to understand the impact of these meteorological parameters on the movement of air pollutants.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/b9c183a3993a/gr4.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1715?><?original-width 2244?><?scaled-height 572?><?scaled-width 748?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="gr4.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/ea48448f7654/gr4.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="p0105"><xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4</xref> illustrates the annual variation of the wind rose diagram from 2016 to 2023, depicting wind speed and direction. <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4</xref> shows that, in 2016, the predominant wind direction was from the east and south, with wind speeds varying between 0.3 and 3.9 m/s. In 2017, the wind direction changed slightly from the southeast to the south-west. In most observations, the wind speed exceeded 2.3 m/s. In 2018, the wind direction was primarily from the east, with a maximum speed of 5.8 m/s. There is a border distribution of wind throughout the year. Scattered wind direction was observed in 2019, mainly from the northeast and southeast, with a maximum wind speed of 6.9 m/s. In 2020, the wind speed and direction were similar to those in 2016; the wind speed was much lower than that in 2019. In 2021, wind directions were identical to those in 2017, and the maximum wind speed in a few observations exceeded 3.7 m/s. In 2022, the wind direction is from the east, and the wind speed exceeds 2.2 m/s. In 2023, varying wind directions and speeds were observed, possibly due to atmospheric instability and climate change. The wind direction was uniform in almost all years except 2019 and 2023, when more variation was observed. Similarly, the monthly variation of the wind direction is illustrated in <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S5</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5" disp-level="2"><title>Ensemble stacking algorithm performance for AQI prediction</title><p id="p0110"><xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents the optimal hyperparameters for four ML models, namely XGBoost, AdaBoost, Bayesian Ridge, and LarsCV, determined using 5-fold cross-validation via GridSearchCV. These models were fine-tuned to enhance their predictive performance in the AQI prediction task for Hyderabad city. <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> provides the performance evaluation of these models for AQI prediction on the training and validation datasets. The ensemble stacking algorithm achieves the best overall performance, with an R<sup>2</sup> of 0.994 on the training and significantly lower error metrics (mean absolute error [MAE] = 0.496, mean square error [MSE] = 0.429, root-mean-square error [RMSE] = 0.655), demonstrating its superior AQI predictive ability. Compared to training datasets, the ensemble stacking algorithm achieved R<sup>2</sup> of 0.999 and significantly very few error metrics. The enhanced performance of the ensemble stacking algorithm on the test dataset can be linked to its capability to integrate the advantages of several models, which helps to lessen overfitting to the training data. Moreover, the regularization methods present in the base models or the meta-model might assist in alleviating the impact of model complexity and adjusting more effectively to changes in the dataset distribution. XGBoost demonstrates the best performance among the base models, with a training R<sup>2</sup> of 0.999 and a validation R<sup>2</sup> of 0.989, though the errors (MAE = 1.521, MSE = 22.158, RMSE = 4.707) during validation are higher than for other models. AdaBoost performs moderately well with a validation R<sup>2</sup> of 0.967, but it shows higher error metrics (MAE = 6.058, RMSE = 8.397). Bayesian Ridge and LarsCV perform similarly, with validation R<sup>2</sup> scores of 0.957 and 0.958, respectively, but they have relatively higher errors than the XGBoost and ensemble stacking algorithm. <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> visually depicts the performance of the ensemble stacking model. The scatterplot in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>A shows the alignment of predicted vs. actual values, indicating excellent model fit as most points lie near the diagonal line. The residual plot in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>B demonstrates that the residuals are centered around zero, indicating no significant bias. The histogram of residuals in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>C shows that the residuals are normally distributed, with most errors concentrated around zero, further validating the model’s reliability. <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> compares the performance of different ML models based on R<sup>2</sup> value. <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> summarizes the comparison of various ML models’ performance in AQI prediction of different cities.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><caption><p>Location map of Hyderabad city, Telangana, and study area</p><p>The data used in the present study were collected from the location of the Zoological Park station, Hyderabad, having a latitude and longitude of 17.350221 and 78.45155.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="fx2.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/40a33a637216/fx2.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2105?><?original-width 2972?><?scaled-height 526?><?scaled-width 743?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="fx2.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/9fa737f3cd49/fx2.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Optimal hyperparameters for regression models selected via 5-fold cross-validation using GridSearchCV</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">ML algorithm</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Best hyperparameters</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">‘learning_rate': 0.1, ‘max_depth': 5, ‘n_estimators': 200</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AdaBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">{‘learning_rate': 0.1, ‘loss': ‘exponential', ‘n_estimators': 200}</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bayesian Ridge</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">{‘alpha_1': 1e-06, ‘alpha_2': 0.0001, ‘lambda_1': 0.0001, ‘lambda_2': 1e-06}</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LarsCV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">{‘eps': 2.220446049250313e-16, ‘max_n_alphas': 100}</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of various machine learning models in predicting the AQI for Hyderabad</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">S. no.</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Machine learning model</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Training<hr/></th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Validation/testing<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MSE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">RMSE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MSE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">RMSE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1"><bold>Base models performance</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.321</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.204</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.452</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.521</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.158</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.707</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.989</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AdaBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">55.398</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.443</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.974</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.058</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">70.518</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.397</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.967</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bayesian Ridge</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.870</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">98.061</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.902</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.954</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.564</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">90.574</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.517</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.957</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LarsCV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.232</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">105.80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.285</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9507</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.642</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.713</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.471</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.958</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1"><bold>Ensemble model performance</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ensemble stacking algorithm</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.304</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.112</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.180</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.994</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.496</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.429</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.655</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.999</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Performance of stacked regression model</p><p>(A) Scatterplot showing the true values vs. predicted values.</p><p>(B) Residual plot.</p><p>(C) Histogram of residuals.</p><p>The graph is used to evaluate the model performance of the ensemble stacked regression using scatterplots, residual plots, and histogram plots.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/c9f2d3619e64/gr5.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1870?><?original-width 2244?><?scaled-height 623?><?scaled-width 748?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="gr5.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/9e1d3bbded66/gr5.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Comparison of performance of different ML models based on R<sup>2</sup> value</p><p>This graph illustrates the comparison of different machine learning models with respect to both training and testing datasets. The blue color graph represents the training datasets, and the orange color represents the testing data.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/8c79f6674bb0/gr6.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1223?><?original-width 2244?><?scaled-height 408?><?scaled-width 748?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="gr6.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/26b5d0c9838f/gr6.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparing the performance of various machine learning models in predicting AQI for different cities</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">City</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Machine learning model</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MSE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">RMSE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">MAPE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Bagdad</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">random forest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.977</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.41 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.35 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.67 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Khadom et al.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">decision tree</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.957</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.08 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.24 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.45 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">KNN</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.525</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55 × 10<sup>−2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.42 × 10<sup>−2</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.89 × 10<sup>−2</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MLP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.971</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.89 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.08 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSTM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.983</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.15 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.21 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Chennai</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9252</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0857</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.022</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1501</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Ravindiran et al.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">random forest (RF)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9149</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0915</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0256</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1601</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">bagging regressor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9167</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09032</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0251</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1584</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LightGBM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9054</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0971</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0285</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1688</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Visakhapatnam</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LightGBM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9915</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Ravindiran et al.<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">random forest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.999</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.75</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CatBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9998</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AdaBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9753</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.38</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.82</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGboost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9981</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.93</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">Shunyi</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SVM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9215</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3164</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0609</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1265</td><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">Su et al.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ELM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9207</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.412</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1086</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1270</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSTM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9213</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4423</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.0705</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1288</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TCN</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9251</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4007</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.8526</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1313</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9238</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.4372</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9280</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1326</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">MLP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.9265</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3167</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7641</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1316</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Wuhan</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RF</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Li and Li<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SVM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BP</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Delhi</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LR</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.22</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Sarkar et al.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">KNN</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">51.63</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SVM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSTM</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.97</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GRU</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">42.66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Hyderabad</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.989</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.521</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.158</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.707</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">current research</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">random forest</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.990</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.291</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.718</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.551</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">bagging regressor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.989</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.367</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.176</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.709</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LightGBM regressor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.983</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.269</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.862</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.988</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CatBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.987</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.143</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.488</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.846</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2.6" disp-level="2"><title>Impact of climate change on Hyderabad city</title><p id="p0115">The impact of air pollutants on climate change is significant, and, as one of the fastest-growing cities, Hyderabad has experienced several environmental issues in recent decades due to particulate matter emissions resulting from urbanization. Air pollutants in Hyderabad have resulted in changes in rainfall patterns, extreme heat waves during summer, urban heat island effects, and air quality degradation.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> In 2020, Hyderabad recorded extreme rainfall of 22.4 cm, the highest in the last 130 years. This single-day extreme rainfall event was observed in 2017, 2019, and 2021. Due to heavy rain in 2019, Moti Darwaza of Golconda Fort collapsed, and, in 2020, Majnu Burj of the Golconda Fort and the wall portion of Quila Shahpur subsided. Air pollutants also affect many structures in Hyderabad. Some instances are cracking of wooden surfaces in Naqqar Khana of Badshahi Ashoorkhana, possibly due to high levels of incident solar radiation; tilting of vertical wall surfaces in Sarai Khana of Badshahi Ashoorkhana, possibly due to ground subsidence on one side due to groundwater fluctuations; and cracks on the minaret dome and flaking of plaster on the minaret dome of Toli Masjid, possibly due to high levels of incident solar radiation.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Hyderabad has also experienced the urban heat island effect due to rapid urbanization in the last few years. Hyderabad’s built-up area grew from 234 km<sup>2</sup> in 2001 to 379 km<sup>2</sup> (an increase of 161.97%) by 2011 and further expanded to 590 km<sup>2</sup> (a total increase of 252.14%) by 2021. During the first decade (2001–2011), urbanization led to an average land surface temperature (LST) rise of 0.81°C in the converted areas of Hyderabad, while, in the second decade (2011–2021), the average LST rise was 0.72°C.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Overall, from 2001 to 2021, the average LST of the urbanized areas in Hyderabad increased by 1.3°C. The average urban heat island intensity for Hyderabad over the past two decades was 2.44°C, with an annual increase of 0.033°C/year, 0.030°C/year for the summer season, and 0.044°C/year for the winter season.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref>
<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref> illustrates the urban heat island effects of the major developed cities in India. Similar to Bengaluru and Hyderabad, other major cities, namely Delhi, Kolkata, Mumbai, and Chennai, also faced the urban heat island effect.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The urban heat island effect of major developed cities in India shows a temperature rise compared to nearby rural areas</p><p>This information is obtained from the previous studies where the temperature of these cities is higher than that of the surrounding areas.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="gr7.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/6c782c0ebc36/gr7.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 945?><?original-width 2244?><?scaled-height 315?><?scaled-width 748?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="gr7.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/93efefd57ee4/gr7.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.7" disp-level="2"><title>Implication and perspectives</title><p id="p0120">Various models, such as XGBoost, AdaBoost, Bayesian Ridge, and LarsCV techniques, provide adaptability in managing different data distributions, noise, and complexity. This variety ensures resilience and applicability in diverse situations. This analysis offers insights into the balance between model precision and computational efficiency. XGBoost, a non-linear and complex model, outperforms linear models such as Bayesian Ridge and LarsCV when dealing with datasets containing intricate relationships. However, XGBoost may encounter overfitting issues if regularization is not properly implemented. Although AdaBoost performs well in many scenarios, it may exhibit a different level of robustness than XGBoost, particularly when handling noisy or extensive datasets. Linear models like Bayesian Ridge and LarsCV have limitations in capturing complex, non-linear relationships, resulting in relatively inferior performance. Stacking, an ensemble technique, delivers the most favorable outcomes, underscoring the effectiveness of combining models to enhance prediction accuracy and generalization capabilities. Furthermore, applying these models to various regions or variables may help to affirm their applicability.</p><p id="p0125">The findings of these models can assist policymakers and public health officials in developing strategies to mitigate air pollution and its health effects, thereby enhancing urban living conditions. Analyzing AQI trends offers valuable insights for shaping policies, but forecasting AQI delivers practical advantages that extend beyond historical data examination. It facilitates proactive measures by predicting days with poor air quality, which allows for timely actions such as implementing traffic restrictions and issuing health warnings. Predictions based on ML can adjust to changing factors like weather conditions and industrial emissions, providing immediate responses and insights during significant events such as smog or dust storms. Furthermore, these forecasts address gaps in monitoring systems, improve public understanding, and aid in scenario planning to assess policy effectiveness. Such forward-thinking capabilities are essential for emergency responses, resource distribution, and long-term strategies that align with sustainable development objectives. Continual model assessment and updating with new data are essential for maintaining accuracy and relevance, particularly in dynamic environments such as air quality monitoring. By effectively leveraging these models, this study contributes to the broader objective of utilizing ML to address intricate environmental issues such as air pollution. However, applicability to other locations requires careful consideration of several factors: variability in pollution sources, climatic and geographic differences, data availability, and quality. Some of the model generalization requirements are data customization, feature adaptation, and transfer learning.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8" disp-level="2"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0130">The present study predicted the AQI based on the data available from 2016 to 2023. The results showed that the pollution levels increased from 2016 to 2019, and, in 2020, pollution levels decreased, possibly due to the nationwide lockdown due to COVID-19. However, the pollutant levels were found to increase the gain from 2021 due to industrial activities, vehicular emissions, and agricultural activities. Further, PM<sub>10</sub> was found to influence the AQI values significantly, and its correlation coefficient was observed to be 0.96. Other gaseous pollutants were found to have less impact on the AQI, and metrological factors had minimal impact on the AQI predictions. The ML models used in the present study accurately predicted the AQI. The ensemble stacking algorithm demonstrated the highest accuracy, with a correlation coefficient (R<sup>2</sup>) of 0.999 for both the training and validation datasets. XGBoost also performed well, with a correlation coefficient of 0.999 for the training dataset and 0.989 for the validation dataset. This study demonstrates that ML models, particularly ensemble methods, can successfully apply to AQI predictions. However, the scalability of these models to other regions and cities will depend on the quality and availability of localized datasets. The diverse air pollutants and metrological parameters vary, and it will be challenging for the model to apply and assess the transferability of these models to those regions for the prediction of AQI, which needs to be studied.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9" disp-level="2"><title>Limitations of the study</title><p id="p0135">ML models offer strong and informative forecasts for air quality. However, various constraints must be addressed to enhance accuracy, dependability, and applicability. These limitations include issues with data quality, the risk of overfitting, variations in different regions, and the omission of socioeconomic and policy-related elements. By confronting these obstacles in future studies, the models could evolve into even more effective instruments for comprehending and addressing air pollution, particularly in dynamic settings such as India.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3" disp-level="1"><title>Resource availability</title><sec id="sec3.1" disp-level="2"><title>Lead contact</title><p id="p0140">Further information and requests for resources should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the lead contact, Azees Maria (<email>azeesmm@gmail.com</email>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2" disp-level="2"><title>Materials availability</title><p id="p0145">This study did not generate new unique reagents.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3" disp-level="2"><title>Data and code availability</title>
<list list-type="label" id="ulist0015"><list-item id="u0030"><label>•</label><p id="p0155">All data reported in this paper are shared in the relevant literature, with DOIs provided in the <xref rid="sec8.1" ref-type="sec">key resources table</xref> under deposited data.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0035"><label>•</label><p id="p0160">The source code employed in the current research can be accessed on the GitHub page, and the link is given in the <xref rid="sec8.1" ref-type="sec">key resources table</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0040"><label>•</label><p id="p0165">Additional information for reanalyzing the data reported in this paper is available from the <xref rid="sec3.1" ref-type="sec">lead contact</xref> upon request.</p></list-item></list>
</sec></sec><sec id="sec5" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0175">The authors would like to express their gratitude to the Higher Institution Centre of Excellence (HICoE), Ministry of Higher Education, Malaysia, under the project code 2024001HICOE as referenced in JPT(BPKI)1000/016/018/34(5). This work was supported by Tenaga Nasional Berhad and Universiti Tenaga Nasional through the BOLD Refresh Postdoctoral Fellowships under the project code of J510050002-IC-6 BOLDREFRESH2025-Centre of Excellence.</p></sec><sec id="sec6" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0180">Conceptualization and methodology, G.R. and K.K.; resources, S.R. and D.D.; data curation, B.D. and G.S.; writing – original draft, G.R. and K.K.; writing – review and editing, G.S., B.D., and A.M.; visualization, D.D. and A.M.; supervision, G.H.</p></sec><sec id="sec7" disp-level="1"><title>Declaration of interests</title><p id="p0185">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="sec8" disp-level="1"><title>STAR★Methods</title><sec id="sec8.1" disp-level="2"><title>Key resources table</title>
<table-wrap id="undtbl1" position="float"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">REAGENT or RESOURCE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">SOURCE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">IDENTIFIER</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Deposited data</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dataset</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Central Pollution Board</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://app.cpcbccr.com/ccr/#/caaqm-dashboard-all/caaqm-landing/data" ext-link-type="uri">https://app.cpcbccr.com/ccr/#/caaqm-dashboard-all/caaqm-landing/data</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Software and algorithms</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Python</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Python Software Foundation</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.python.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.python.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Numpy</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Harris et al.<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://numpy.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://numpy.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pandas</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">McKinney et al.<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pandas.pydata.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pandas.pydata.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Matplotlib</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hunter et al.<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://matplotlib.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://matplotlib.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Seaborn</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Waskom et al.<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://seaborn.pydata.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://seaborn.pydata.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scikit-learn</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pedregosa et al.<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/" ext-link-type="uri">https://scikit-learn.org/stable/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGBoost</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chen et al.<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://xgboost.readthedocs.io/" ext-link-type="uri">https://xgboost.readthedocs.io/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AdaBoostRegressor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Freund et al.<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.ensemble.AdaBoostRegressor.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.ensemble.AdaBoostRegressor.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">StackingRegressor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wolpert et al.<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.ensemble.StackingRegressor.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.ensemble.StackingRegressor.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">LarsCV</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hastie et al.<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.linear_model.LarsCV.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.linear_model.LarsCV.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bayesian Ridge Regression</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tipping et al.<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.linear_model.BayesianRidge.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.linear_model.BayesianRidge.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DecisionTreeRegressor</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Breiman et al.<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.tree.DecisionTreeRegressor.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://scikit-learn.org/stable/modules/generated/sklearn.tree.DecisionTreeRegressor.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Matplotlib.pyplot</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hunter et al.<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://matplotlib.org/stable/api/_as_gen/matplotlib.pyplot.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://matplotlib.org/stable/api/_as_gen/matplotlib.pyplot.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">DateTime</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Python datetime module</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/datetime.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://docs.python.org/3/library/datetime.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Codes used in the Present Study</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Present Study</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/kkarthiks1/Hyderabad-Air-Quality-Data" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/kkarthiks1/Hyderabad-Air-Quality-Data</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</sec><sec id="sec8.2" disp-level="2"><title>Method details</title><sec id="sec8.2.1" disp-level="3"><title>Study area</title><p id="p0195">Hyderabad is the capital of Telangana, India. The city is located on the Deccan Plateau and covers an area of 625 km<sup>2</sup> at an average elevation of 542 m from the mean sea level. Hyderabad is well known for its cultural heritage, and some of the most important monuments are Golconda Fort, Charminar, and Qutb Shahi Tombs. According to the recent census of India in 2020, Hyderabad has a population of more than 10 million. Hyderabad is also called the “city of pearls” for its early diamond business history of over 400 years. The city is diverse, with different industrial sectors, namely, the IT sector, pharmaceutical industries, and biotechnological research. The city experiences a hot, dry, and tropical wet climate, with hot summers, wet monsoons, and mild winters. March to June is considered summer, and the maximum temperature is approximately 45°C; June to September is considered monsoon season, and temperatures range from 25 to 35°C. October to February is a winter period with a temperature range of 15 to 25°C. April to May is considered the pre-monsoon season, and October to November is the post-monsoon season. The average rainfall is approximately 750 mm, and the city receives maximum rainfall from the south-west monsoon between June and September. Figure 8 illustrates a map of the study area.</p></sec><sec id="sec8.2.2" disp-level="3"><title>Feature selection for the prediction of AQI</title><p id="p0200">The datasets used in this research were downloaded from the Central Pollution Board – Central Control Room for Air (CPCBCRR- <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://app.cpcbccr.com/ccr/#/caaqm-dashboard-all/caaqm-landing/data" ext-link-type="uri">https://app.cpcbccr.com/ccr/#/caaqm-dashboard-all/caaqm-landing/data</ext-link>). The data used for the study were collected from the Zoological Park Station, Hyderabad, located at a latitude and longitude of 17.350221 and 78.451558, respectively (Data &amp; Code Link: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/kkarthiks1/Hyderabad-Air-Quality-Data" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/kkarthiks1/Hyderabad-Air-Quality-Data</ext-link><bold>).</bold> For the prediction of AQI, both air quality and meteorological parameter data were used. The air quality data used are Particulate matter 2.5 and 10, (PM<sub>2.5</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>), PM<sub>10</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)), Nitric oxide (NO (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)), Nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)), Nitrogen oxides (NOx (ppb)), Ammonia (NH<sub>3</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)), Sulphur dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)), Carbon monoxide (CO (mg/m<sup>3</sup>)), Ozone (O<sub>3</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)), Xylene (μg/m<sup>3</sup>), and Benzene (μg/m<sup>3</sup>). Meteorological parameters included Wind Direction (WD (degree)), Solar Radiation (SR (W/mt<sup>2</sup>)), Barometric Pressure (BP (mmHg)), vertical wind speed (VWS (m/s)), Ambient Temperature (AT (degree C)), rainfall (RF (mm)), and TOT-RF (mm). AQI was considered the target variable in the present study. The data used in the present study were collected from 09<sup>th</sup> August 9, 2016, to 27<sup>th</sup> October 27, 2023, with a total observation of 2636 (daily average data). The overall process involved in the prediction of AQI begins with data preprocessing steps, including missing value handling, data analysis, and Box-Cox transformation. The dataset is then split into training and test sets. After hyperparameter tuning using GridSearchCV with 5-fold cross-validation, the best hyperparameters for XGBoost, LarsCV, Bayesian Ridge, and AdaBoost models are determined. These models are then combined in an ensemble stacking approach, with Bayesian Ridge serving as the meta-model to produce the final AQI prediction.</p></sec><sec id="sec8.2.3" disp-level="3"><title>Ensemble Stacking Algorithm</title><p id="p0205">In this research, an ensemble stacking algorithm combining multiple regression models (XGBoost, Lasso Least Angle Regression (LarsCV), Bayesian Ridge, and AdaBoost) was used, with their best hyperparameters found via GridSearchCV. Stacking is an ensemble learning technique that combines multiple base models to improve predictive performance. Instead of using a simple average or majority vote, as in bagging or boosting, stacking uses a meta-model (a secondary model) that learns from the outputs of the base models to produce a final prediction. The idea is to leverage the strengths of different algorithms to create a model that performs better than any individual model.</p><p id="p0210">XGBoost, LarsCV, Bayesian Ridge, and AdaBoost are used as base learners. XGBoost trains multiple weak learners (decision trees) sequentially, where each new learner corrects the errors of the previous ones. LarsCV iteratively builds a regression model by including features that are most correlated with the residuals. Bayesian Ridge optimises the weights by considering the uncertainty in the model's parameters and regularizing the model by adding penalty terms to the likelihood function to avoid overfitting. AdaBoost sequentially trains weak learners (usually decision trees), with each subsequent model focusing more on instances where the previous model made errors.</p><p id="p0215">Bayesian Ridge is used as the meta-model (final estimator), which learns from the predictions made by the base models to make a final prediction. The predictions from the base models (XGBoost, LarsCV, Bayesian Ridge, and AdaBoost) are treated as input features for the Bayesian Ridge model. Bayesian Ridge adds a probabilistic framework to linear regression, which is useful for handling uncertainty and variance in the predictions from the base models. A 5-fold cross-validation strategy is employed to make the ensemble more robust and avoid overfitting. The stacking process involves training each base model on the training data, collecting the predictions of each base model on the validation sets during cross-validation, and using these predictions as inputs to the meta-model, which then learns to combine the base models' outputs to generate the best possible predictions.</p></sec><sec id="sec8.2.4" disp-level="3"><title>Pre-processing of datasets</title><p id="p0220">2636 observations were obtained from the CPCBCRR for the above duration for 23 parameters, including AQI. In all the datasets, missing values may arise due to malfunction in the sensors, errors during data transmission, and issues with data collection. These will result in data errors and reduce the accuracy of the model. Missing values in the dataset must be removed before processing. The missing values in all 23 parameters were removed, and the final imputed dataset consisted of 2113 observations. The AQI category distribution was made using the 2113 observations, which showed that 1153 observations were moderate, 537 observations were satisfactory, 408 observations were good, 13 observations were poor, and two observations were very poor. <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref> shows the AQI categories based on these datasets. The AQI underwent a conversion from object type to float type. Statistical analysis of the air pollutant and meteorological parameter datasets is summarised in Table 4. The available data was split into training (80% of datasets) and testing (20% of the datasets) to develop the Ensemble Stacking Algorithm for AQI Prediction. The performance and accuracy of the different ML models in the prediction of the AQI were analysed using various types of errors, namely the root mean square error (RMSE), Mean Absolute Error (MAE), Mean Square Error (MSE) and R<sup>2</sup> (Correlation coefficient).</p><table-wrap id="tbl4" position="float"><caption><p>Statistical analysis of the datasets used in AQI prediction</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Features</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Count</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Std</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Min</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">25%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">50%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">75%</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">126.18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">101.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">49.91</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">104.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">145.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">241</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.81</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.65</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">50.35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">130.59</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NOx (ppb)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.65</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.94</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">102.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NH<sub>3</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.89</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.71</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.97</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.72</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.69</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.13</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">77.84</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CO (mg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.78</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.43</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ozone (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.53</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.85</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.11</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">127.92</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Benzene (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.07</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.94</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.32</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">WD (degree)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">189.76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">66.50</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">138.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">186.72</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">246.91</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">360</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SR (W/mt<sup>2</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">121.55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.01</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.54</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">80.94</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">111.56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">145.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,065.51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BP (mmHg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">714.37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">700.88</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">708.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">711.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">715.77</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,054.96</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">VWS (m/s)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−14.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AT (degree C)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.73</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RF (mm)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Xylene (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.99</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.78</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TOT-RF (mm)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">143.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,070</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2,113</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">101.58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">61.94</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">106.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">139.95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">304.75</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec8.2.5" disp-level="3"><title>Exploratory data analysis</title><p id="p0225">Exploratory data analysis (EDA) is a preliminary step in understanding the key characteristics and relationships between different variables/features used in the datasets. It is generally used to understand the dataset distributions and their ranges, central tendencies, and distributions. EDA can detect outliers, handle missing values, and calculate key statistics.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> A correlogram is a heatmap variant used to find the correlation between each variable, and other variables spread over two axes. Figure 9 Illustrates a heatmap of the variables used in the datasets, demonstrating the variables that significantly impact the AQI prediction. A correlation greater than 0.5 is considered as threshold, and a correlation is classified as positive or negative. The correlation coefficient varies from -1 to +1, and a correlation close to 1 indicates a perfect fit of the model to the actual data. The Pearson correlation coefficient was developed to understand the relationship between the two features.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> Figure 9 shows that PM<sub>2.5</sub> and PM<sub>10</sub> have a more significant correlation of 0.95 and 0.96, respectively, with AQI. Metrological parameters have minimal impact on AQI compared with air pollutants.</p><fig id="fig9" position="float"><caption><p>Heatmap-correlation analysis of different features used in AQI predictions</p><p>This image illustrates the correlation of each variable used in the data with other variables to understand the impact.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="fx3.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/2fcf83bcbda1/fx3.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 3509?><?original-width 3387?><?scaled-height 779?><?scaled-width 752?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="fx3.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b537/11883379/cadc17b7c914/fx3.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="sec8.2.6" disp-level="3"><title>Data transformation</title><p id="p0230">The skewness and kurtosis of the datasets with various features are outlined in Table 5, both before and after Box-Cox transformation (BCT). Skewness and kurtosis were used to analyse other features and how much they deviated from the normal distribution. Skewness was used to measure the symmetry of the distribution of the various features.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref> Generally, skewness ranges between -1 and +1, which is excellent; -2 to 2 is acceptable, and values greater than -2 to +2 suggest that the distribution is abnormal. Kurtosis analyses datasets that are too peak or flat compared with the normal distribution. The peak distribution is called positive kurtosis, and the flat distribution is called negative kurtosis.<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> A kurtosis greater than +2 is called positive kurtosis, and less than -2 is called negative kurtosis. The dataset was found to be normally distributed when skewness and kurtosis were close to zero. From Table 5, it was observed that features, namely NO, SO<sub>2</sub>, CO, Ozone, Benzene, Toluene, WS, SR, BP, RF, Xylene and TOT-RF, had skewness and kurtosis of more than +1, indicating that the features were not normally distributed. Some parameters, namely PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, NO<sub>2</sub>, NOx, NH<sub>3</sub> and RH, have less skewness and kurtosis, indicating that the data are typically distributed. BCT was applied to make the feature a normal distribution, and the results showed that skewness and kurtosis were reduced and better suited for further data analysis. BCT is a statistical technique used to reduce the raw datasets' variance, skewness, and kurtosis and convert them into normal distribution. The significance of the BCT is to achieve high accuracy using the ML algorithm. If BCT is not used, accuracy and bias in AQI predictions will be reduced. Applying BCT in the present study enhanced the data scaling, and data was distributed normally.</p><table-wrap id="tbl5" position="float"><caption><p>Data transformation (before and after) of skewness and kurtosis for the datasets</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Before data transformation<hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">After data transformation<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Skew</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kurtosis</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Skew</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kurtosis</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.095</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.218</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.095</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.218</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.086</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.173</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.086</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.173</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.724</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.423</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.608</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.764</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.329</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.764</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.329</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NOx (ppb)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.714</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.391</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.714</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.391</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">NH<sub>3</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.776</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.657</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.776</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.657</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SO<sub>2</sub> (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.252</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.172</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.326</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CO (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.224</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.401</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.009</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ozone (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.879</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.036</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.069</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.456</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Benzene (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.407</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.925</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.090</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.011</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Toluene (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.457</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.783</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.012</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.511</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Temp (degree C)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.414</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.607</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.414</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.607</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RH (%)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.086</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.142</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.086</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.142</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">WS (m/s)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.395</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.145</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.315</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.023</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">WD (degree)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.098</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.726</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.098</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.726</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SR (W/mt<sup>2</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.693</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.668</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.225</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.112</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">BP (mmHg)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.504</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">106.892</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">VWS (m/s)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.416</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.648</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.416</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.648</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AT (degree C)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.087</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.826</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.087</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.826</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">RF (mm)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.442</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">65.939</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.338</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.175</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Xylene (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.305</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.482</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.213</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.876</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">TOT-RF (mm)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.980</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">79.797</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.791</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−1.271</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.002</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.719</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.002</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">−0.719</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec8.2.7" disp-level="3"><title>Data splitting and composition</title><p id="p0235">The dataset was organised into features (X) and target variables (y), excluding the 'Date' and 'AQI' columns. It was divided into training and test sets at an 80:20 ratio. The present research used a training set of 1690 samples to train the machine learning models and a test set of 423 samples to evaluate their performance. Both sets contain 22 features, excluding the 'Date' and 'AQI' features.</p></sec><sec id="sec8.2.8" disp-level="3"><title>GridSearchCV-based hyperparameter tuning</title><p id="p0240">Hyperparameter tuning for the base models—XGBoost, Lasso Least Angle Regression (LarsCV), Bayesian Ridge, and AdaBoost—was performed using GridSearchCV with 5-fold cross-validation. Initially, the hyperparameters to be tuned for the machine learning algorithms were defined. GridSearchCV systematically searches through combinations of hyperparameter values specified in the parameter grid to find the optimal configuration that maximises model performance. The model's performance is evaluated using the R<sup>2</sup> score, which measures how well the model explains the variance in the target variable. A 5-fold cross-validation strategy was employed to identify the best hyperparameters. The data was split into five subsets, each serving as a validation set while the remaining folds were used for training. Cross-validation ensures that the model's performance is evaluated across multiple data splits, making it more robust to overfitting and less dependent on a specific data partition.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec8.3" disp-level="2"><title>Quantification and statistical analysis</title><p id="p0245">Table 4 summarises the statistical analysis of the features used in AQI prediction. The standard deviation was very high for PM<sub>2.5</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, WD, SR, BP, and TOT-RF, indicating more fluctuation and variation in the datasets compared to the other features with fewer standard deviations. A lower standard deviation indicates that the dataset values are close to the mean values, and a high standard deviation indicates the variability of the data.<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> The 1<sup>st</sup> quartile, median and 3<sup>rd</sup> quartiles are the key statistics used to understand the distribution of the datasets. It also identifies the central tendency, variability, and skewness of data. The 1<sup>st</sup> quartile or 25<sup>th</sup> percentile, or Q1, denotes the lower end of the distribution.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref> For example, PM<sub>2.5</sub> had for 25% of the data less than 25.15 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. Similarly, 25% of the data was less than 56.17 μg/m<sup>3</sup> for PM<sub>10</sub>. The median or 50<sup>th</sup> percentile or Q2 indicates the data's midpoint; for instance, 50% of the PM<sub>2.5</sub> is less than 50.3 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. The 3<sup>rd</sup> quartile, or 75<sup>th</sup> percentile, represents the upper bound of the data, and indicates the higher end of the data. For instance, 75% of the PM<sub>2.5</sub> are less than 69.74 μg/m<sup>3</sup>. In addition to these quartiles, interquartile ranges were used to find the spread of datasets close to the middle 50% to identify the variability that was not included by outliers. For instance, the PM<sub>2.5</sub> interquartile was calculated as the difference between Q3 and Q1 and was observed as 44.59 μg/m<sup>3</sup> which is close to the median of PM<sub>2.5.</sub></p></sec><sec id="sec8.4" disp-level="2"><title>Additional resources</title><p id="p0250">No additional resources were generated or used.</p></sec></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><p id="misc9010">Published: January 25, 2025</p></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="appsec1"><p id="p0255">Supplemental information can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2025.111894" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2025.111894</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="appsec2" disp-level="1"><title>Supplemental information</title>
<supplementary-material id="mmc1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><caption><title>Document S1. Figures S1–S5 and Table S1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b537/11883379/fc2e9a4bdf15/mmc1.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1005129?></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="cebib0010" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="cebib0010_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="sref1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Manisalidis I., Stavropoulou E., Stavropoulos A., Bezirtzoglou E. Environmental and Health Impacts of Air Pollution: A Review. Front. Public Health. 2020;8 doi: 10.3389/FPUBH.2020.00014.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/FPUBH.2020.00014"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7044178"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32154200"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Front. Public Health&amp;title=Environmental and Health Impacts of Air Pollution: A Review&amp;author=I. Manisalidis&amp;author=E. Stavropoulou&amp;author=A. Stavropoulos&amp;author=E. Bezirtzoglou&amp;volume=8&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pmid=32154200&amp;doi=10.3389/FPUBH.2020.00014&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="sref2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhao C., Wang B. How does new-type urbanization affect air pollution? Empirical evidence based on spatial spillover effect and spatial Durbin model. Environ. Int. 2022;165 doi: 10.1016/J.ENVINT.2022.107304.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.ENVINT.2022.107304"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35640449"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Int.&amp;title=How does new-type urbanization affect air pollution? Empirical evidence based on spatial spillover effect and spatial Durbin model&amp;author=C. Zhao&amp;author=B. Wang&amp;volume=165&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pmid=35640449&amp;doi=10.1016/J.ENVINT.2022.107304&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="sref3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Imam M., Adam S., Dev S., Nesa N. Air quality monitoring using statistical learning models for sustainable environment. Intell. Syst. Appl. 2024;22 doi: 10.1016/J.ISWA.2024.200333.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.ISWA.2024.200333"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Intell. Syst. Appl.&amp;title=Air quality monitoring using statistical learning models for sustainable environment&amp;author=M. Imam&amp;author=S. Adam&amp;author=S. Dev&amp;author=N. Nesa&amp;volume=22&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;doi=10.1016/J.ISWA.2024.200333&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="sref4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Saadeh R., Khader Y., Malkawi M., Allouh M.Z. Communicating the Risks of Air Pollution to the Public: A Perspective from Jordan and Lebanon. Environ. Health Insights. 2022;16 doi: 10.1177/11786302221127851.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/11786302221127851"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9583232"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36277840"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Health Insights&amp;title=Communicating the Risks of Air Pollution to the Public: A Perspective from Jordan and Lebanon&amp;author=R. Saadeh&amp;author=Y. Khader&amp;author=M. Malkawi&amp;author=M.Z. Allouh&amp;volume=16&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pmid=36277840&amp;doi=10.1177/11786302221127851&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="sref5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sokhi R.S., Singh V., Querol X., Finardi S., Targino A.C., Andrade M.d.F., Pavlovic R., Garland R.M., Massagué J., Kong S., et al.  A global observational analysis to understand changes in air quality during exceptionally low anthropogenic emission conditions. Environ. Int. 2021;157 doi: 10.1016/J.ENVINT.2021.106818.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.ENVINT.2021.106818"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34425482"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Int.&amp;title=A global observational analysis to understand changes in air quality during exceptionally low anthropogenic emission conditions&amp;author=R.S. Sokhi&amp;author=V. Singh&amp;author=X. Querol&amp;author=S. Finardi&amp;author=A.C. Targino&amp;volume=157&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pmid=34425482&amp;doi=10.1016/J.ENVINT.2021.106818&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="sref6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh R., Sharma C., Agrawal M. Emission inventory of trace gases from road transport in India. Transport. Res. Transport Environ. 2017;52:64–72. doi: 10.1016/J.TRD.2017.02.011.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.TRD.2017.02.011"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Transport. Res. Transport Environ.&amp;title=Emission inventory of trace gases from road transport in India&amp;author=R. Singh&amp;author=C. Sharma&amp;author=M. Agrawal&amp;volume=52&amp;publication_year=2017&amp;pages=64-72&amp;doi=10.1016/J.TRD.2017.02.011&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="sref7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kaur R., Pandey P. Air Pollution, Climate Change, and Human Health in Indian Cities: A Brief Review. Front. Sustain. Cities. 2021;3 doi: 10.3389/FRSC.2021.705131.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/FRSC.2021.705131"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Front. Sustain. Cities&amp;title=Air Pollution, Climate Change, and Human Health in Indian Cities: A Brief Review&amp;author=R. Kaur&amp;author=P. Pandey&amp;volume=3&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;doi=10.3389/FRSC.2021.705131&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="sref8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shepherd J.M. A Review of Current Investigations of Urban-Induced Rainfall and Recommendations for the Future. Earth Interact. 2005;9:1–27. doi: 10.1175/EI156.1.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1175/EI156.1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Earth Interact.&amp;title=A Review of Current Investigations of Urban-Induced Rainfall and Recommendations for the Future&amp;author=J.M. Shepherd&amp;volume=9&amp;publication_year=2005&amp;pages=1-27&amp;doi=10.1175/EI156.1&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="sref9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yang B., Zhang Y., Qian Y. Simulation of Urban climate with high-resolution WRF model: A case study in Nanjing, China. Asia. Pac. J. Atmos. Sci. 2012;48:227–241. doi: 10.1007/S13143-012-0023-5.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/S13143-012-0023-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Asia. Pac. J. Atmos. Sci.&amp;title=Simulation of Urban climate with high-resolution WRF model: A case study in Nanjing, China&amp;author=B. Yang&amp;author=Y. Zhang&amp;author=Y. Qian&amp;volume=48&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=227-241&amp;doi=10.1007/S13143-012-0023-5&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="sref10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ren G., Zhou Y., Chu Z., Zhou J., Zhang A., Guo J., Liu X. Urbanization Effects on Observed Surface Air Temperature Trends in North China. J. Clim. 2008;21:1333–1348. doi: 10.1175/2007JCLI1348.1.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1175/2007JCLI1348.1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J. Clim.&amp;title=Urbanization Effects on Observed Surface Air Temperature Trends in North China&amp;author=G. Ren&amp;author=Y. Zhou&amp;author=Z. Chu&amp;author=J. Zhou&amp;author=A. Zhang&amp;volume=21&amp;publication_year=2008&amp;pages=1333-1348&amp;doi=10.1175/2007JCLI1348.1&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="sref11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chestnut L.G., Breffle W.S., Smith J.B., Kalkstein L.S. Analysis of differences in hot-weather-related mortality across 44 U.S. metropolitan areas. Environ. Sci. Pol. 1998;1:59–70. doi: 10.1016/S1462-9011(98)00015-X.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S1462-9011(98)00015-X"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Sci. Pol.&amp;title=Analysis of differences in hot-weather-related mortality across 44 U.S. metropolitan areas&amp;author=L.G. Chestnut&amp;author=W.S. Breffle&amp;author=J.B. Smith&amp;author=L.S. Kalkstein&amp;volume=1&amp;publication_year=1998&amp;pages=59-70&amp;doi=10.1016/S1462-9011(98)00015-X&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="sref12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ramanathan V., Crutzen P.J., Kiehl J.T., Rosenfeld D. Atmosphere: Aerosols, climate, and the hydrological cycle. Science. 2001;294:2119–2124. doi: 10.1126/SCIENCE.1064034.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/SCIENCE.1064034"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11739947"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Science&amp;title=Atmosphere: Aerosols, climate, and the hydrological cycle&amp;author=V. Ramanathan&amp;author=P.J. Crutzen&amp;author=J.T. Kiehl&amp;author=D. Rosenfeld&amp;volume=294&amp;publication_year=2001&amp;pages=2119-2124&amp;pmid=11739947&amp;doi=10.1126/SCIENCE.1064034&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="sref13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Srikanth K., Swain D. Urbanization and Land surface temperature changes over Hyderabad, a semi-arid mega city in India. Remote Sens. Appl. 2022;28 doi: 10.1016/J.RSASE.2022.100858.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.RSASE.2022.100858"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Remote Sens. Appl.&amp;title=Urbanization and Land surface temperature changes over Hyderabad, a semi-arid mega city in India&amp;author=K. Srikanth&amp;author=D. Swain&amp;volume=28&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;doi=10.1016/J.RSASE.2022.100858&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="sref14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">World’s Most Polluted Cities in 2023 - PM2.5 Ranking | IQAir. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.iqair.com/in-en/world-most-polluted-cities?continent=59af92b13e70001c1bd78e53&amp;country=SPLi4goKT3JDgP4Mm&amp;state=&amp;sort=-rank&amp;page=4&amp;perPage=50&amp;cities=" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.iqair.com/in-en/world-most-polluted-cities?continent=59af92b13e70001c1bd78e53&amp;country=SPLi4goKT3JDgP4Mm&amp;state=&amp;sort=-rank&amp;page=4&amp;perPage=50&amp;cities=</ext-link></named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="sref15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chanchpara A., Muduli M., Prabhakar V., Madhava A.K., Thorat R.B., Haldar S., Ray S. Pre-to-post Diwali air quality assessment and particulate matter characterization of a western coastal place in India. Environ. Monit. Assess. 2023;195:413. doi: 10.1007/S10661-023-11018-X.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/S10661-023-11018-X"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9937863"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36807008"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Monit. Assess.&amp;title=Pre-to-post Diwali air quality assessment and particulate matter characterization of a western coastal place in India&amp;author=A. Chanchpara&amp;author=M. Muduli&amp;author=V. Prabhakar&amp;author=A.K. Madhava&amp;author=R.B. Thorat&amp;volume=195&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=413&amp;pmid=36807008&amp;doi=10.1007/S10661-023-11018-X&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="sref16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cugerone K., De Michele C., Ghezzi A., Gianelle V. Aerosol removal due to precipitation and wind forcings in Milan urban area. J. Hydrol. (Amst.) 2018;556:1256–1262. doi: 10.1016/J.JHYDROL.2017.06.033.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.JHYDROL.2017.06.033"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J. Hydrol. (Amst.)&amp;title=Aerosol removal due to precipitation and wind forcings in Milan urban area&amp;author=K. Cugerone&amp;author=C. De Michele&amp;author=A. Ghezzi&amp;author=V. Gianelle&amp;volume=556&amp;publication_year=2018&amp;pages=1256-1262&amp;doi=10.1016/J.JHYDROL.2017.06.033&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="sref17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dasgupta P., Srikanth K. Reduced air pollution during COVID-19: Learnings for sustainability from Indian Cities. Glob. Transit. 2020;2:271–282. doi: 10.1016/J.GLT.2020.10.002.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.GLT.2020.10.002"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Glob. Transit.&amp;title=Reduced air pollution during COVID-19: Learnings for sustainability from Indian Cities&amp;author=P. Dasgupta&amp;author=K. Srikanth&amp;volume=2&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=271-282&amp;doi=10.1016/J.GLT.2020.10.002&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="sref18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kumar P., Hama S., Omidvarborna H., Sharma A., Sahani J., Abhijith K.V., Debele S.E., Zavala-Reyes J.C., Barwise Y., Tiwari A. Temporary reduction in fine particulate matter due to ‘anthropogenic emissions switch-off’ during COVID-19 lockdown in Indian cities. Sustain. Cities Soc. 2020;62 doi: 10.1016/J.SCS.2020.102382.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.SCS.2020.102382"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7357527"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32834936"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Sustain. Cities Soc.&amp;title=Temporary reduction in fine particulate matter due to ‘anthropogenic emissions switch-off’ during COVID-19 lockdown in Indian cities&amp;author=P. Kumar&amp;author=S. Hama&amp;author=H. Omidvarborna&amp;author=A. Sharma&amp;author=J. Sahani&amp;volume=62&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pmid=32834936&amp;doi=10.1016/J.SCS.2020.102382&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="sref19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gajbhiye M.D., Lakshmanan S., Aggarwal R., Kumar N., Bhattacharya S. Evolution and mitigation of vehicular emissions due to India’s Bharat Stage Emission Standards – A case study from Delhi. Environ. Dev. 2023;45 doi: 10.1016/J.ENVDEV.2023.100803.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.ENVDEV.2023.100803"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Dev.&amp;title=Evolution and mitigation of vehicular emissions due to India’s Bharat Stage Emission Standards – A case study from Delhi&amp;author=M.D. Gajbhiye&amp;author=S. Lakshmanan&amp;author=R. Aggarwal&amp;author=N. Kumar&amp;author=S. Bhattacharya&amp;volume=45&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;doi=10.1016/J.ENVDEV.2023.100803&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="sref20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hui K., Yuan Y., Xi B., Tan W. A review of the factors affecting the emission of the ozone chemical precursors VOCs and NOx from the soil. Environ. Int. 2023;172 doi: 10.1016/J.ENVINT.2023.107799.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.ENVINT.2023.107799"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36758299"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Int.&amp;title=A review of the factors affecting the emission of the ozone chemical precursors VOCs and NOx from the soil&amp;author=K. Hui&amp;author=Y. Yuan&amp;author=B. Xi&amp;author=W. Tan&amp;volume=172&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pmid=36758299&amp;doi=10.1016/J.ENVINT.2023.107799&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="sref21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wyer K.E., Kelleghan D.B., Blanes-Vidal V., Schauberger G., Curran T.P. Ammonia emissions from agriculture and their contribution to fine particulate matter: A review of implications for human health. J. Environ. Manag. 2022;323 doi: 10.1016/J.JENVMAN.2022.116285.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.JENVMAN.2022.116285"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36261990"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J. Environ. Manag.&amp;title=Ammonia emissions from agriculture and their contribution to fine particulate matter: A review of implications for human health&amp;author=K.E. Wyer&amp;author=D.B. Kelleghan&amp;author=V. Blanes-Vidal&amp;author=G. Schauberger&amp;author=T.P. Curran&amp;volume=323&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pmid=36261990&amp;doi=10.1016/J.JENVMAN.2022.116285&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="sref22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fan X.H., Li Y.C., Alva A.K. Effects of Temperature and Soil Type on Ammonia Volatilization from Slow-Release Nitrogen Fertilizers. Commun. Soil Sci. Plant Anal. 2011;42:1111–1122. doi: 10.1080/00103624.2011.566957.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/00103624.2011.566957"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Commun. Soil Sci. Plant Anal.&amp;title=Effects of Temperature and Soil Type on Ammonia Volatilization from Slow-Release Nitrogen Fertilizers&amp;author=X.H. Fan&amp;author=Y.C. Li&amp;author=A.K. Alva&amp;volume=42&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=1111-1122&amp;doi=10.1080/00103624.2011.566957&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="sref23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Vaishali, Verma G., Das R.M. Influence of Temperature and Relative Humidity on PM2.5 Concentration over Delhi. MAPAN-J. Metrol. Soc. India. 2023;38:759–769. doi: 10.1007/S12647-023-00656-8.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/S12647-023-00656-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=MAPAN-J. Metrol. Soc. India&amp;title=Influence of Temperature and Relative Humidity on PM2.5 Concentration over Delhi&amp;author= Vaishali&amp;author=G. Verma&amp;author=R.M. Das&amp;volume=38&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=759-769&amp;doi=10.1007/S12647-023-00656-8&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="sref24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ibe F.C., Opara A.I., Duru C.E., Obinna I.B., Enedoh M.C. Statistical analysis of atmospheric pollutant concentrations in parts of Imo State, Southeastern Nigeria. Sci. Afr. 2020;7 doi: 10.1016/J.SCIAF.2019.E00237.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.SCIAF.2019.E00237"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Sci. Afr.&amp;title=Statistical analysis of atmospheric pollutant concentrations in parts of Imo State, Southeastern Nigeria&amp;author=F.C. Ibe&amp;author=A.I. Opara&amp;author=C.E. Duru&amp;author=I.B. Obinna&amp;author=M.C. Enedoh&amp;volume=7&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;doi=10.1016/J.SCIAF.2019.E00237&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="sref25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Jayachandran V., Rao T.N. Long-term regional air pollution characteristics in and around Hyderabad, India: Effects of natural and anthropogenic sources. Atmos. Environ. X. 2024;22 doi: 10.1016/J.AEAOA.2024.100254.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.AEAOA.2024.100254"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmos. Environ. X&amp;title=Long-term regional air pollution characteristics in and around Hyderabad, India: Effects of natural and anthropogenic sources&amp;author=V. Jayachandran&amp;author=T.N. Rao&amp;volume=22&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;doi=10.1016/J.AEAOA.2024.100254&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="sref26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sridharan K., Ji S. Climate Change Impacts on the Built Heritage of Hyderabad. Smart Innovation. Syst. Technol. 2023;342:1087–1101. doi: 10.1007/978-981-99-0264-4_89.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/978-981-99-0264-4_89"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Syst. Technol.&amp;title=Climate Change Impacts on the Built Heritage of Hyderabad. Smart Innovation&amp;author=K. Sridharan&amp;author=S. Ji&amp;volume=342&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=1087-1101&amp;doi=10.1007/978-981-99-0264-4_89&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="sref28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Khadom A.A., Albawi S., Abboud A.J., Mahood H.B., Hassan Q. Predicting air quality index and fine particulate matter levels in Bagdad city using advanced machine learning and deep learning techniques. J. Atmos. Sol. Terr. Phys. 2024;262 doi: 10.1016/J.JASTP.2024.106312.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.JASTP.2024.106312"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J. Atmos. Sol. Terr. Phys.&amp;title=Predicting air quality index and fine particulate matter levels in Bagdad city using advanced machine learning and deep learning techniques&amp;author=A.A. Khadom&amp;author=S. Albawi&amp;author=A.J. Abboud&amp;author=H.B. Mahood&amp;author=Q. Hassan&amp;volume=262&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;doi=10.1016/J.JASTP.2024.106312&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="sref27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Arunab K.S., Mathew A. Geospatial and statistical analysis of urban heat islands and thermally vulnerable zones in Bangalore and Hyderabad cities in India. Remote Sens. Appl. 2023;32 doi: 10.1016/J.RSASE.2023.101049.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.RSASE.2023.101049"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Remote Sens. Appl.&amp;title=Geospatial and statistical analysis of urban heat islands and thermally vulnerable zones in Bangalore and Hyderabad cities in India&amp;author=K.S. Arunab&amp;author=A. Mathew&amp;volume=32&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;doi=10.1016/J.RSASE.2023.101049&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="sref29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ravindiran G., Rajamanickam S., Kanagarathinam K., Hayder G., Janardhan G., Arunkumar P., Arunachalam S., AlObaid A.A., Warad I., Muniasamy S.K. Impact of air pollutants on climate change and prediction of air quality index using machine learning models. Environ. Res. 2023;239 doi: 10.1016/J.ENVRES.2023.117354.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.ENVRES.2023.117354"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37821071"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Res.&amp;title=Impact of air pollutants on climate change and prediction of air quality index using machine learning models&amp;author=G. Ravindiran&amp;author=S. Rajamanickam&amp;author=K. Kanagarathinam&amp;author=G. Hayder&amp;author=G. Janardhan&amp;volume=239&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pmid=37821071&amp;doi=10.1016/J.ENVRES.2023.117354&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="sref30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ravindiran G., Hayder G., Kanagarathinam K., Alagumalai A., Sonne C. Air quality prediction by machine learning models: A predictive study on the indian coastal city of Visakhapatnam. Chemosphere. 2023;338 doi: 10.1016/J.CHEMOSPHERE.2023.139518.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.CHEMOSPHERE.2023.139518"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37454985"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Chemosphere&amp;title=Air quality prediction by machine learning models: A predictive study on the indian coastal city of Visakhapatnam&amp;author=G. Ravindiran&amp;author=G. Hayder&amp;author=K. Kanagarathinam&amp;author=A. Alagumalai&amp;author=C. Sonne&amp;volume=338&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pmid=37454985&amp;doi=10.1016/J.CHEMOSPHERE.2023.139518&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="sref31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Su M., Liu H., Yu C., Duan Z. A novel AQI forecasting method based on fusing temporal correlation forecasting with spatial correlation forecasting. Atmos. Pollut. Res. 2023;14 doi: 10.1016/J.APR.2023.101717.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.APR.2023.101717"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Atmos. Pollut. Res.&amp;title=A novel AQI forecasting method based on fusing temporal correlation forecasting with spatial correlation forecasting&amp;author=M. Su&amp;author=H. Liu&amp;author=C. Yu&amp;author=Z. Duan&amp;volume=14&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;doi=10.1016/J.APR.2023.101717&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="sref32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li Y., Li R. A hybrid model for daily air quality index prediction and its performance in the face of impact effect of COVID-19 lockdown. Process Saf. Environ. Protect. 2023;176:673–684. doi: 10.1016/J.PSEP.2023.06.021.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.PSEP.2023.06.021"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10264166"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37350802"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Process Saf. Environ. Protect.&amp;title=A hybrid model for daily air quality index prediction and its performance in the face of impact effect of COVID-19 lockdown&amp;author=Y. Li&amp;author=R. Li&amp;volume=176&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=673-684&amp;pmid=37350802&amp;doi=10.1016/J.PSEP.2023.06.021&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="sref33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sarkar N., Gupta R., Keserwani P.K., Govil M.C. Air Quality Index prediction using an effective hybrid deep learning model. Environ. Pollut. 2022;315 doi: 10.1016/J.ENVPOL.2022.120404.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/J.ENVPOL.2022.120404"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36240962"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ. Pollut.&amp;title=Air Quality Index prediction using an effective hybrid deep learning model&amp;author=N. Sarkar&amp;author=R. Gupta&amp;author=P.K. Keserwani&amp;author=M.C. Govil&amp;volume=315&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pmid=36240962&amp;doi=10.1016/J.ENVPOL.2022.120404&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="sref40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Harris C.R., Millman K.J., van der Walt S.J., Gommers R., Virtanen P., Cournapeau D., Wieser E., Taylor J., Berg S., Smith N.J., et al.  Array programming with NumPy. Nature. 2020;585:357–362. doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7759461"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32939066"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nature&amp;title=Array programming with NumPy&amp;author=C.R. Harris&amp;author=K.J. Millman&amp;author=S.J. van der Walt&amp;author=R. Gommers&amp;author=P. Virtanen&amp;volume=585&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=357-362&amp;pmid=32939066&amp;doi=10.1038/s41586-020-2649-2&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation id="sref41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">McKinney W. pandas: a Foundational Python Library for Data Analysis and Statistics. Python for High Performance and Scientific Computing. 2011;14:1–9.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Python for High Performance and Scientific Computing&amp;title=pandas: a Foundational Python Library for Data Analysis and Statistics&amp;author=W. McKinney&amp;volume=14&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=1-9&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation id="sref42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hunter J.D. Matplotlib: A 2D graphics environment. Comput. Sci. Eng. 2007;9:90–95. doi: 10.1109/MCSE.2007.55.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1109/MCSE.2007.55"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Comput. Sci. Eng.&amp;title=Matplotlib: A 2D graphics environment&amp;author=J.D. Hunter&amp;volume=9&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=90-95&amp;doi=10.1109/MCSE.2007.55&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="sref43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Waskom M. seaborn: statistical data visualization. J. Open Source Softw. 2021;6:3021. doi: 10.21105/JOSS.03021.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.21105/JOSS.03021"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J. Open Source Softw.&amp;title=seaborn: statistical data visualization&amp;author=M. Waskom&amp;volume=6&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=3021&amp;doi=10.21105/JOSS.03021&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation id="sref44"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pedregosa F., Varoquaux G., Gramfort A., Michel V., Thirion B., Grisel O., Blondel M., Müller A., Nothman J., Louppe G., et al.  Scikit-learn: Machine Learning in Python. J. Mach. Learn. Res. 2011;12:2825–2830.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J. Mach. Learn. Res.&amp;title=Scikit-learn: Machine Learning in Python&amp;author=F. Pedregosa&amp;author=G. Varoquaux&amp;author=A. Gramfort&amp;author=V. Michel&amp;author=B. Thirion&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=2825-2830&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="sref45"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chen T., Guestrin C. XGBoost: A scalable tree boosting system. Proceedings of the ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining 13-17-August-2016. ACM DIgital Library. 2016:785–794. doi: 10.1145/2939672.2939785.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1145/2939672.2939785"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=ACM DIgital Library&amp;title=XGBoost: A scalable tree boosting system. Proceedings of the ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining 13-17-August-2016&amp;author=T. Chen&amp;author=C. Guestrin&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=785-794&amp;doi=10.1145/2939672.2939785&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="sref46"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Freund Y., Schapire R.E. A Decision-Theoretic Generalization of On-Line Learning and an Application to Boosting. J. Comput. Syst. Sci. 1997;55:119–139. doi: 10.1006/JCSS.1997.1504.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1006/JCSS.1997.1504"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J. Comput. Syst. Sci.&amp;title=A Decision-Theoretic Generalization of On-Line Learning and an Application to Boosting&amp;author=Y. Freund&amp;author=R.E. Schapire&amp;volume=55&amp;publication_year=1997&amp;pages=119-139&amp;doi=10.1006/JCSS.1997.1504&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="sref47"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wolpert D.H. Stacked generalization. Neural Network. 1992;5:241–259. doi: 10.1016/S0893-6080(05)80023-1.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S0893-6080(05)80023-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Neural Network.&amp;title=Stacked generalization&amp;author=D.H. Wolpert&amp;volume=5&amp;publication_year=1992&amp;pages=241-259&amp;doi=10.1016/S0893-6080(05)80023-1&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="sref48"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Efron B., Hastie T., Johnstone I., Tibshirani R., Ishwaran H., Knight K., Loubes J.M., Massart P., Madigan D., Ridgeway G., et al.  Least angle regression. Ann. Stat. 2004;32:407–499. doi: 10.1214/009053604000000067.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1214/009053604000000067"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Ann. Stat.&amp;title=Least angle regression&amp;author=B. Efron&amp;author=T. Hastie&amp;author=I. Johnstone&amp;author=R. Tibshirani&amp;author=H. Ishwaran&amp;volume=32&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=407-499&amp;doi=10.1214/009053604000000067&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="sref49"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Efron B., Hastie T., Johnstone I., Tibshirani R. Least angle regression. Ann. Stat. 2004;32:407–499.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Ann. Stat.&amp;title=Least angle regression&amp;author=B. Efron&amp;author=T. Hastie&amp;author=I. Johnstone&amp;author=R. Tibshirani&amp;volume=32&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=407-499&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation id="sref50"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Breiman L., Friedman J.H., Olshen R.A., Stone C.J.  2017. Classification and regression trees; pp. 1–358.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1201/9781315139470"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Breiman L., Friedman J.H., Olshen R.A., Stone C.J. 2017. Classification and regression trees; pp. 1–358."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="sref34"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Komorowski M., Marshall D.C., Salciccioli J.D., Crutain Y. Exploratory data analysis. In: MIT Critical Data. Secondary Analysis of Electronic Health Records. Springer. 2016:185–203. doi: 10.1007/978-3-319-43742-2_15.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/978-3-319-43742-2_15"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31314267"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Springer&amp;title=Exploratory data analysis. In: MIT Critical Data. Secondary Analysis of Electronic Health Records&amp;author=M. Komorowski&amp;author=D.C. Marshall&amp;author=J.D. Salciccioli&amp;author=Y. Crutain&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=185-203&amp;pmid=31314267&amp;doi=10.1007/978-3-319-43742-2_15&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation id="sref35"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Berman J.J. Understanding your data. In: Data Simplification: Taming Information with Open Source Tools. Morgan Kaufmann. 2016:135–187. doi: 10.1016/B978-0-12-803781-2.00004-7.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/B978-0-12-803781-2.00004-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Morgan Kaufmann&amp;title=Understanding your data. In: Data Simplification: Taming Information with Open Source Tools&amp;author=J.J. Berman&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=135-187&amp;doi=10.1016/B978-0-12-803781-2.00004-7&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation id="sref36"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gandhi S.M., Sarkar B.C. Conventional and statistical resource/reserve estimation. Essentials of Mineral Exploration and Evaluation. Elsevier. 2016:271–288. doi: 10.1016/B978-0-12-805329-4.00018-1.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/B978-0-12-805329-4.00018-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Elsevier&amp;title=Conventional and statistical resource/reserve estimation. Essentials of Mineral Exploration and Evaluation&amp;author=S.M. Gandhi&amp;author=B.C. Sarkar&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=271-288&amp;doi=10.1016/B978-0-12-805329-4.00018-1&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation id="sref37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Green J.L., Manski S.E., Hansen T.A., Broatch J.E.  International Encyclopedia of Education: Fourth Edition. Elsevier; 2022. Descriptive statistics; pp. 723–733.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/B978-0-12-818630-5.10083-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="title=International Encyclopedia of Education: Fourth Edition&amp;author=J.L. Green&amp;author=S.E. Manski&amp;author=T.A. Hansen&amp;author=J.E. Broatch&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation id="sref38"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Barde M.P., Barde P.J. What to use to express the variability of data: Standard deviation or standard error of mean? Perspect. Clin. Res. 2012;3:113–116. doi: 10.4103/2229-3485.100662.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4103/2229-3485.100662"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3487226"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23125963"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Perspect. Clin. Res.&amp;title=What to use to express the variability of data: Standard deviation or standard error of mean?&amp;author=M.P. Barde&amp;author=P.J. Barde&amp;volume=3&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=113-116&amp;pmid=23125963&amp;doi=10.4103/2229-3485.100662&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation id="sref39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Han J., Kamber M., Pei J. Getting to Know Your Data. Data Min. 2012:39–82. doi: 10.1016/B978-0-12-381479-1.00002-2.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/B978-0-12-381479-1.00002-2"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Data Min.&amp;title=Getting to Know Your Data&amp;author=J. Han&amp;author=M. Kamber&amp;author=J. Pei&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=39-82&amp;doi=10.1016/B978-0-12-381479-1.00002-2&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><caption><title>Document S1. Figures S1–S5 and Table S1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b537/11883379/fc2e9a4bdf15/mmc1.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1005129?></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title>
<list list-type="label"><list-item><label>•</label><p>All data reported in this paper are shared in the relevant literature, with DOIs provided in the <xref rid="sec8.1" ref-type="sec">key resources table</xref> under deposited data.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>The source code employed in the current research can be accessed on the GitHub page, and the link is given in the <xref rid="sec8.1" ref-type="sec">key resources table</xref>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>Additional information for reanalyzing the data reported in this paper is available from the <xref rid="sec3.1" ref-type="sec">lead contact</xref> upon request.</p></list-item></list>
</sec></sec></body></article>