<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Sci Rep</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12586577</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12586577</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12586577</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41188403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-22474-5</article-id><title-group><article-title>Accurate AQI forecasting in a high-altitude city using a simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM hybrid model: a case study of Lhasa, Tibet</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names initials="F">Fangjing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaomei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="G">Guibin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Bu</surname><given-names initials="D">Duo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qiangying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Key Laboratory of Biodiversity and Environment on the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, Ministry of Education, School of Ecology and Environment, Xizang University, Lhasa, 850000 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>State Key Laboratory of Environmental Chemistry and Ecotoxicology, Research Center for Eco-Environmental Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100085 China </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>38625</fpage><page-range>38625</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>6</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_Article_22474.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path e1a8/12586577/16a572f2cd78/41598_2025_Article_22474.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 3523281?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Forecasting of the Air Quality Index (AQI) in high-altitude cities is significantly challenged by nonlinear temporal dynamics, particularly due to complex interactions between atmospheric physics and pollutant transport. A hybrid forecasting model integrating a simulated Complex-Valued Optical Convolution Accelerator (CVOCA) with a Bidirectional Long Short-Term Memory (BiLSTM) network is presented to improve prediction accuracy and computational efficiency. The simulated CVOCA module enables high-speed, complex-valued convolution to extract amplitude and phase features from high-dimensional AQI sequences, while the BiLSTM component captures bidirectional temporal dependencies. Performance was evaluated using daily AQI data from Lhasa (2014–2024, 4018 samples). The hybrid model achieved RMSE = 1.60, MAE = 0.93, MAPE = 1.60%, R = 0.997, and R<sup>2</sup> = 0.996, outperforming standalone LSTM and BiLSTM models. The proposed model captures complex AQI dynamics in plateau environments and provides a scalable solution for real-time forecasting and environmental decision support.</p><sec id="sec1" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-22474-5.</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group1" xml:lang="en" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> AQI forecasting, CVOCA-BiLSTM hybrid model, Exceptional predictive performance, Tibet</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group2" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Atmospheric science, Environmental sciences</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 Jun 20; Accepted 2025 Sep 29; Collection date 2025.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par46">In recent years, the escalating frequency and intensity of large-scale wildfires worldwide have become a critical driver of atmospheric pollution, severely undermining urban environmental sustainability and endangering public health<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Exceedance of hazardous Air Quality Index (AQI) thresholds constitutes a significant threat to ecosystem stability<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par47">The Tibetan Plateau, often called the “Third Pole” performs an indispensable function in both regional and global sustainability. Nonetheless, polar and high-altitude regions constitute sensitive interfaces within the Earth’s climate system. Residents of these regions face heightened risks from amplified climate variability and increased pollutant transport<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. The Tibetan Plateau’s highly variable topography causes dramatic swings in Planetary Boundary-Layer Height (PBLH), directly affecting near-surface pollutant dispersion and deposition. Studies have indicated that warming over the Tibetan Plateau can enhance vertical mixing and may influence secondary aerosol formation processes, thereby contributing to increased complexity and variability in AQI time series<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Compared with urban plains, AQI monitoring stations across the Tibetan Plateau are sparse and unevenly distributed, yielding input data with poor spatial continuity and representativeness<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. Moreover, the region’s dry climate and limited pollution sources produce relatively small AQI fluctuations and overly smooth time series, reducing model sensitivity and robustness to subtle changes<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. For instance, over the past decade, Lhasa’s AQI exhibited a relative standard deviation (RSD) of 30.86% and a standard deviation (SD) of 17.81, which are substantially lower than those of Beijing (RSD: 65.09%, SD: 60.34) and Shanghai (RSD: 45.32%, SD: 33.22), highlighting the markedly weaker variability in Lhasa’s air quality data. Finally, the proportions of secondary aerosols versus primary emissions vary sharply with humidity and temperature, creating complex spatiotemporal interactions that conventional models struggle to capture<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Collectively, these factors—including the plateau’s unique high-altitude boundary-layer dynamics, sparse and smooth monitoring data, and complex transboundary transport—substantially elevate the challenge of AQI forecasting on the Tibetan Plateau.</p><p id="Par48">AQI forecasting methods are generally classified into two primary categories: process-driven models and data-driven models<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. Process-driven models are based on the principles of atmospheric physics and chemical mechanisms. These models simulate the generation, dispersion, transport, and deposition of pollutants to predict air quality. Representative examples include chemical transport models such as the Community Multiscale Air Quality (CMAQ) model and the Weather Research and Forecasting model coupled with chemistry (WRF-Chem)<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. These models require numerous input parameters, including meteorological fields, emission inventories, and topographic data. While process-driven models provide strong interpretability and are grounded in physical principles, they are computationally demanding and highly sensitive to the quality of initial input data, making their predictive accuracy susceptible to various uncertainties. In contrast, data-driven models focus on learning statistical patterns and latent relationships from historical datasets, without explicitly modeling the physical transport mechanisms of pollutants. This category encompasses traditional statistical methods (e.g., ARMA, SVR), machine learning algorithms (e.g., Random Forest, XGBoost), and deep learning architectures (e.g., LSTM, CNN, Transformer). Data-driven models are typically more flexible and capable of achieving higher predictive accuracy, particularly when modeling nonlinear and highly dynamic AQI patterns<sup><xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. However, pure temporal deep learning models without feature enhancement tend to overfit “flat” patterns when data is sparse and low in noise, while also incurring high computational costs that hinder real-time forecasting<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. Ensemble machine learning algorithms offer limited threshold segmentation for smoothed AQI sequences and lack adequate modeling of temporal dependencies<sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. Therefore, recent studies on AQI and air pollutant forecasting have demonstrated a growing interest in hybrid models, which integrate feature engineering or decomposition techniques with advanced neural networks. These hybrid models have shown superior forecasting performance and robustness across diverse environmental contexts.</p><p id="Par49">However, traditional hybrid models typically combine signal decomposition techniques—such as wavelet transform, Variational Mode Decomposition (VMD), or Empirical Mode Decomposition (EMD)—with unidirectional models like LSTM or SVR to process original real-valued AQI time series<sup><xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. While these methods have demonstrated effectiveness in capturing general trends, they often fall short in responding to nonlinear fluctuations and abrupt shifts. Moreover, their performance is highly contingent upon the selection of decomposition parameters, thereby constraining their generalizability across diverse datasets and geographic regions. To effectively extract deep dynamic patterns from time series data, this study introduces a novel simulated Complex-Valued Optical Convolution Accelerator (CVOCA), built upon a complex-valued neural network architecture that preserves data integrity while enhancing phase and amplitude information capture, thereby effectively enhance the information of minor fluctuations and achieve richer hidden representations<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. Subsequently, the extracted features are fed into a Bidirectional Long Short-Term Memory (BiLSTM) network for deep temporal modeling of both forward and backward dependencies. Moreover, regularization strategies combined with a robust loss function mitigated overfitting to flat patterns. The use of Huber loss, dropout, and early stopping ensured that training and validation curves converged smoothly, demonstrating strong generalization rather than mechanical memorization of smoothed segments. Collectively, the simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM framework significantly enhances the model’s capability to fit complex temporal structures. With respect to predictive accuracy, robustness, and computational efficiency, the proposed model outperforms conventional hybrid approaches and exhibits significant potential for practical deployment.</p><p id="Par50">This study proposes a hybrid deep learning model that integrates a simulated CVOCA with a Bidirectional LSTM to improve AQI forecasting in high-altitude cities. By leveraging simulated CVOCA’s nonlinear feature extraction and BiLSTM’s temporal dependency modeling, the framework offers improved accuracy and reliable performance under complex climatic conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Study area and data collection</title><p id="Par51">The proposed simulated CVOCA–BiLSTM hybrid model was validated using AQI time series data from Lhasa, a representative high-altitude city on the Qinghai–Tibet Plateau. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, AQI values were calculated as the mean of six monitoring sites—Xizang University, Railway Station, Monitoring Station, Barkhor Street, Environmental Protection Agency, and Radiation Station—using historical data from the China National Environmental Monitoring centre (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cnemc.cn/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cnemc.cn/</ext-link>) and the AQI Study database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.aqistudy.cn/historydata/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.aqistudy.cn/historydata/</ext-link>). The dataset comprised daily AQI values for Lhasa, Shanghai, and Beijing from January 1, 2014, through December 31, 2024, yielding a total of 12,054 observations. To ensure data integrity, the series was first examined for missing entries, and any gaps were filled using linear interpolation based on adjacent values. To improve training stability, all AQI inputs were normalized to the [0, 1] interval via MinMaxScaler, and model outputs were subsequently denormalized. Following preprocessing, the dataset was partitioned into training (70%), validation (15%), and testing (15%) subsets. The convolutional layer in the simulated CVOCA model was configured with 64 filters, a kernel size of 3, and the ReLU activation function to extract localized temporal features from the AQI time series. The BiLSTM component comprised three stacked layers with 256 hidden units each and a dropout rate of 0.1, using a time step of 10 and the tanh activation function to model temporal dependencies in both forward and backward directions. The model was trained for 100 epochs with a learning rate of 0.0005, utilizing CPU-based parallel computation to enhance efficiency. The optimized network architectures and hyperparameters of all models are summarized in Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> (Supporting Information). Model performance was assessed using five standard metrics: root mean square error (RMSE), mean absolute error (MAE), mean absolute percentage error (MAPE), Pearson correlation coefficient (R), and coefficient of determination (R<sup>2</sup>). The selection of Lhasa as a case study enables a robust evaluation of the proposed model’s effectiveness and stability under high-altitude environmental conditions.</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study area and air monitoring station location. Photos taken from Google Maps. Map data <sup>©</sup>2025 Google.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO1" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/0bc693388a0f/41598_2025_22474_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1205?><?original-width 1592?><?scaled-height 603?><?scaled-width 796?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/d51c1ef0ae89/41598_2025_22474_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par52">The methodology employed in this study involves the integration of a simulated CVOCA and a BiLSTM neural network. A brief overview of these methods is provided below:</p><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="3"><title>Complex-Valued Optical Convolutional Accelerator (CVOCA)</title><p id="Par53">The Complex-Valued Optical Convolution Accelerator (CVOCA) was first introduced by Bai et al.<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> CVOCA is a novel optical convolutional framework designed for the extraction of high-dimensional, ultrafast, and hierarchical features from waveform or complex-valued data streams. In this study, simulated CVOCA—not only denoting a software-based algorithmic implementation of the complex-valued convolution operation but also encompassing specific simulations of amplitude and phase information in optical physical processes—is employed as a front-end feature extractor for AQI data, enabling the efficient decomposition of complex temporal patterns. The feature extraction process is mathematically represented in Eqs. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>) and (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par54">For a complex-valued input <inline-formula id="IEq1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e596" xlink:href="d33e596.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/baedbf277f27/d33e596.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>​, and a complex-valued convolutional kernel <inline-formula id="IEq2"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e602" xlink:href="d33e602.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/135adc688a12/d33e602.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, the resulting complex-valued convolution can be expressed as:</p><disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e608" xlink:href="d33e608.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/4615463a499b/d33e608.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par55">Expanding this expression, the complex convolution result becomes:</p><disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e616" xlink:href="d33e616.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/ffa405708f82/d33e616.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par56">Here, <inline-formula id="IEq3"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e624" xlink:href="d33e624.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/17ce202ffcef/d33e624.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> ; <inline-formula id="IEq4"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e630" xlink:href="d33e630.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/6a4dfe495d0a/d33e630.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> ; <inline-formula id="IEq5"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e636" xlink:href="d33e636.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/e689f5db7732/d33e636.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> ; <inline-formula id="IEq6"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e642" xlink:href="d33e642.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/3cf33e0135b5/d33e642.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>
<inline-formula id="IEq7"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e648" xlink:href="d33e648.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/12a87a8d84d0/d33e648.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e655" xlink:href="d33e655.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/43a760dcd512/d33e655.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> represent the real and imaginary parts of the input data, respectively. <inline-formula id="IEq9"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e661" xlink:href="d33e661.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/b2c71b50e507/d33e661.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq10"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e667" xlink:href="d33e667.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/5cc2777aa13a/d33e667.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> represent the real and imaginary parts of the convolution kernel. ∗ denotes the convolution operation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="3"><title>Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM)</title><p id="Par57">The Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) network, introduced by Hochreiter et al.<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> incorporates an improved strategy to optimize the training of traditional Recurrent Neural Networks (RNNs). By using Backpropagation Through Time (BPTT), LSTM effectively mitigates the vanishing gradient problem<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. This model is particularly well-suited for handling and predicting significant events that occur with long time intervals or delays in time series data. Unlike conventional neurons, LSTM networks are composed of memory blocks connected across layers. Each LSTM layer consists of a set of recurrently connected memory blocks, which can be seen as differentiable versions of memory chips in digital computers.</p><p id="Par65">The LSTM unit is controlled by three gating mechanisms: the forget gate, the input gate, and the output gate, along with a cell state. The mathematical expressions for these operations are given by Eqs. (<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>)–(<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">8</xref>) as follows:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par59"> The forget gate <inline-formula id="IEq11"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e699" xlink:href="d33e699.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/ea4208735f29/d33e699.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e705" xlink:href="d33e705.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/7b6faeca4f90/d33e705.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></p><p id="Par60">Here, <inline-formula id="IEq12"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e713" xlink:href="d33e713.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/2aabd379ce4a/d33e713.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> represents the sigmoid activation function, <inline-formula id="IEq13"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e719" xlink:href="d33e719.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/3ccd661778e6/d33e719.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the hidden state at the previous time step, <inline-formula id="IEq14"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e725" xlink:href="d33e725.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/1ce4c82e497b/d33e725.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the current input, <inline-formula id="IEq15"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e731" xlink:href="d33e731.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/fdfc10496d34/d33e731.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq16"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e737" xlink:href="d33e737.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/7257957f3f17/d33e737.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> are the weight and bias terms, respectively.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par61">The input gate <inline-formula id="IEq17"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e748" xlink:href="d33e748.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/92f00733930a/d33e748.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and Candidate Cell State <inline-formula id="IEq18"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e754" xlink:href="d33e754.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/8dfd33a93398/d33e754.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e760" xlink:href="d33e760.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/c70452a9bf0f/d33e760.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e766" xlink:href="d33e766.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/cfe8ffc0fe67/d33e766.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par62">Cell State Update <inline-formula id="IEq19"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e777" xlink:href="d33e777.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/beb6a8ba6e40/d33e777.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e783" xlink:href="d33e783.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/430739e343b7/d33e783.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></p><p id="Par63">Here, <inline-formula id="IEq20"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e791" xlink:href="d33e791.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/6445f76fcc3c/d33e791.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> represents the cell state from the previous time step.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par64">Output Gate <inline-formula id="IEq21"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e802" xlink:href="d33e802.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/02dd61a34426/d33e802.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and Final Hidden State <inline-formula id="IEq22"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e808" xlink:href="d33e808.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/4e3a58abc03e/d33e808.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e814" xlink:href="d33e814.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/bb1f74007bb2/d33e814.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e820" xlink:href="d33e820.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/4135458cfe5b/d33e820.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></p><p>During the training process, the various gating mechanisms collaboratively contribute to the updating of weights. This process is visually depicted in the LSTM structure diagram shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. It is important to note that the LSTM structure incorporates the Sigmoid activation function (<inline-formula id="IEq23"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e831" xlink:href="d33e831.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/2aabd379ce4a/d33e831.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>) and the Tanh activation function, as well as element-wise addition ( ⊕) and multiplication ( ⊗) operations.</p></list-item></list><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>LSTM architecture.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO2" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/397ca0305df9/41598_2025_22474_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 728?><?original-width 968?><?scaled-height 485?><?scaled-width 645?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/aa5631a05ecc/41598_2025_22474_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="3"><title>Bidirectional Long Short-Term Memory (BiLSTM)</title><p id="Par66">Bidirectional Long Short-Term Memory (BiLSTM) was first introduced by Graves et al.<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> as an enhanced version of the LSTM network, designed to handle and predict sequential patterns in time-series data. Unlike traditional LSTMs, BiLSTM consists of two independent LSTM units: one processes the input sequence in the forward direction (forward LSTM), and the other processes the sequence in the reverse direction (backward LSTM). This bidirectional structure allows BiLSTM to capture both forward and backward temporal features, adapt to delayed contamination effects, be more sensitive to anomalous fluctuations, and exhibit strong compatibility with other feature extraction modules. Therefore, the construction of the BiLSTM network is represented by Eqs. (<xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref>)–(<xref rid="Equ10" ref-type="disp-formula">11</xref>).</p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p> Forward LSTM Output <inline-formula id="IEq24"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e866" xlink:href="d33e866.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/6c48eec3ee19/d33e866.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e872" xlink:href="d33e872.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/536571bd86a3/d33e872.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par68"> Backward LSTM Output <inline-formula id="IEq25"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e883" xlink:href="d33e883.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/ab9bbbcbb2b6/d33e883.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e889" xlink:href="d33e889.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/33a7e9097ec5/d33e889.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par69"> Bidirectional LSTM Output <inline-formula id="IEq26"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e900" xlink:href="d33e900.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/4e3a58abc03e/d33e900.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e906" xlink:href="d33e906.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/36a82e877a8e/d33e906.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula></p></list-item></list>
</sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="3"><title>Model construction</title><p id="Par70">Simulated CVOCA can rapidly extract features from the entire AQI data process and connect with the BiLSTM model to build a simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM model for predicting AQI values. The process follows these steps:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par71">Step 1: Construct Complex Input Data.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par72">Convert the AQI time series into complex form, where:</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par73">Real part = original AQI values;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par74">Imaginary part = the second-order differences + Fast Fourier Transform (FFT);</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par75">The second-order differences = the acceleration of AQI value;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par76">FFT = amplitude + phase information.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par77">Step 2: Feature Extraction Using Simulated CVOCA.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par78">Perform sliding convolutions with multiple complex kernels on the input complex sequence to extract local trends and phase features.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par79">Step 3: Connect to BiLSTM/LSTM Model.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par80">Sliding one-dimensional convolutions employing multiple complex‐valued kernels of length three were applied to the time series to extract local trend and phase features.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par81">Step 4: Predict AQI Values.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par82">Output the future AQI predictions through a fully connected layer.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par83">The combination of BiLSTM and the complex features extracted by simulated CVOCA allows for deeper spatiotemporal feature fusion, enhancing the model’s ability to learn both local trends and long-term dependencies.</p></list-item></list><p id="Par84">In previous studies, hybrid models based on LSTM networks have been widely applied to AQI forecasting tasks<sup><xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. The innovation of this study lies in the introduction of the fast simulated CVOCA feature extraction combined with a three-layer BiLSTM model. The main distinction of this model from previous approaches is its ability to rapidly extract high-dimensional data features while capturing both forward and backward dependencies in time series data. Unlike LSTM, which is a unidirectional structure that processes data sequentially over time and is suitable for tasks where past information influences future predictions, BiLSTM, with its bidirectional structure, can simultaneously capture both past and future contextual information. This makes BiLSTM more effective in tasks that require a deeper understanding of time dependencies<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. BiLSTM is particularly well-suited for exploring the relationship of each data point in both forward and backward directions across the time dimension, which is especially crucial when making long-term predictions.</p><p id="Par85">Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> illustrates the structure of the simulated CVOCA-LSTM model, simplified to a sequence length of 1. As shown in the diagram, the 10-time-step input is sequentially fed into the first layer of the LSTM for training. The model’s predicted output is then compared with the actual value at the future time point (t11), and the loss is calculated. This process is repeated in the second and third layers of LSTM, with the cumulative loss from the three layers being used as the overall loss of the model. During training, the model is optimized until convergence. Finally, when the loss is minimized, the data is passed into the fully connected layer (Dense) to output the prediction.</p><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Illustration of a three-layer simulated CVOCA-LSTM architecture for sequential data processing.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO3" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/43abb5c76b36/41598_2025_22474_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1767?><?original-width 2007?><?scaled-height 589?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/7c7c6d68f733/41598_2025_22474_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par86">Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> illustrates the structure of the simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM model. Each layer contains two LSTM units: one for forward training and the other for backward training. For clarity, a sequence length of 1 is still used in this diagram. It is important to note that the data is simultaneously fed into both the forward and backward directions, and the loss is calculated separately for each direction. The results from both directions are then summed to compute the total loss for that layer. The output from the first layer of BiLSTM is concatenated and integrated before being passed into the second layer of BiLSTM, where the same process is repeated. This continues through the third layer, with the final output being processed by the fully connected layer to generate the prediction.</p><fig id="Fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Illustration of a three-layer simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM model architecture for sequential data processing.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO4" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/6d527980a710/41598_2025_22474_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2362?><?original-width 1584?><?scaled-height 1181?><?scaled-width 792?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig4_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/9bd656136739/41598_2025_22474_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="2"><title>Model evaluation metrics</title><p id="Par87">In this study, the performance of the proposed hybrid model is quantitatively assessed using five metrics: RMSE, MAE, MAPE, R, R<sup>2</sup>. Generally, lower values of RMSE, MAE, and MAPE, along with higher values of R and R<sup>2</sup>, indicate better model performance. The formulas for these evaluation metrics are presented in Eqs. (<xref rid="Equ12" ref-type="disp-formula">12</xref>)–(<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="disp-formula">16</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1009" xlink:href="d33e1009.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/7ddc8280839e/d33e1009.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1015" xlink:href="d33e1015.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/6b23c16f0753/d33e1015.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1022" xlink:href="d33e1022.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/a4a1206998a3/d33e1022.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>15</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1028" xlink:href="d33e1028.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/7296686f6270/d33e1028.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ16"><label>16</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1034" xlink:href="d33e1034.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/7a5fe958ecd2/d33e1034.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par88">Here, <inline-formula id="IEq27"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1042" xlink:href="d33e1042.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/26bd34447712/d33e1042.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> represents the actual value at time step <italic>i</italic>, <inline-formula id="IEq28"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1051" xlink:href="d33e1051.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/eb81a748c5f4/d33e1051.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>​ denotes the predicted value at the corresponding time step, and <inline-formula id="IEq29"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1057" xlink:href="d33e1057.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/72ed46328696/d33e1057.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the mean of all actual values <inline-formula id="IEq30"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1063" xlink:href="d33e1063.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/26bd34447712/d33e1063.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, where<italic> i</italic> = 1, 2, …, <italic>n</italic>, and <italic>n</italic> is the total number of samples. All data points from the test set are individually used to calculate the evaluation metrics, thereby assessing the predictive capability of the machine learning model for AQI forecasting.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="1"><title>Results and discussion</title><p id="Par89">Following rapid feature extraction via simulated CVOCA, a CVOCA-BiLSTM model was constructed to predict AQI values. The performance of the proposed simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM model was validated using daily average AQI data from Lhasa. To demonstrate the advantages of the proposed approach, LSTM, BiLSTM, and simulated CVOCA-LSTM—were selected for comparative analysis. The prediction results and comparative evaluation of these models are discussed in detail in the following subsections.</p><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="2"><title>Model optimization</title><p id="Par90">Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a illustrates the learning curves of the LSTM, BiLSTM, simulated CVOCA-LSTM, and simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM models, depicting changes in training and validation loss. It is evident that all four models adopt the Huber loss function, which integrates the advantages of both mean squared error (MSE) and mean absolute error (MAE). The Huber loss not only ensures continuity and differentiability of the loss function but also leverages the gradient behavior of MSE for small errors, allowing for more precise minimization. Furthermore, its robustness to outliers makes it particularly effective in handling anomalous data. Ultimately, the training and validation loss curves converge closely, indicating good generalization. Several regularization techniques were also employed to mitigate overfitting. For example, the early stopping mechanism was applied, halting training at around the 50th epoch out of 100 iterations to prevent overtraining. Dropout was used during training to randomly deactivate a portion of the neurons, forcing the model to learn under varied structures and enhancing generalization ability. Additionally, normalization and denormalization were employed—scaling features to a uniform range improved training speed, model stability, and activation function performance, while reducing gradient-related issues. Denormalizing the predictions allowed results to be restored to their original scale, making them easier to interpret, compare, and evaluate, and more suitable for practical applications.</p><fig id="Fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>The training loss and validation loss of the Huber function of the four models (<bold>a</bold>), Comparison of models based on first-order (<bold>b</bold>) and second-order differences (<bold>c</bold>).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO5" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/343525540693/41598_2025_22474_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2194?><?original-width 2007?><?scaled-height 731?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig5_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/677849501665/41598_2025_22474_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par91">As an adaptive study, initially, two-layer LSTM and BiLSTM models were used to train the system in order to minimize computational requirements. However, this configuration did not yield satisfactory accuracy results. Accordingly, feature extraction was performed using the CVOCA module, and the network depth was increased to three layers to optimize the model structure and performance. The real part was represented by the original values, while the second-order differences (acceleration) and FFT were used as the imaginary part to represent frequency domain features. The second-order difference was chosen for its ability to enrich the feature space with higher-order temporal dynamics, improving sensitivity to local variations that may be missed with first-order changes. Experimentally, models using the second-order difference achieved lower prediction errors (e.g., reduced RMSE and MAPE) and better captured inflection points in the AQI trajectory (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b, c). This complementary information enhanced the model’s discriminative power and robustness. This approach elevated the original time series data into a more complex feature space, enhancing the predictive capability, which resulted in outcomes closer to the expected results.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="2"><title>Prediction performance</title><p id="Par92">The comparison of observed and predicted AQI series for Lhasa, Shanghai, and Beijing (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) showed that the simulated CVOCA–BiLSTM hybrid model achieved the highest predictive accuracy across environments, reproducing baseline trends while preserving short-term fluctuations. In high-altitude, low-variability Lhasa, the hybrid model produced the narrowest residuals centered near zero, indicating that amplitude–phase feature enhancement and bidirectional temporal fusion preserved subtle signals and reduced systematic bias. In coastal Shanghai, it more faithfully tracked transient oscillations but exhibited greater residual variance owing to stronger local and regional variability. In highly variable Beijing, overall trend agreement remained strong, though residual tails were heavier, reflecting sensitivity to sporadic, externally driven extremes. Model comparisons indicated that simulated CVOCA mitigated non-stationarity and improved peak reconstruction, while BiLSTM reduced information loss via forward–backward fusion; together they yielded robust cross-scenario performance. In summary, the simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM model demonstrates remarkable strengths in predictive accuracy, environmental adaptability, and methodological innovation.</p><fig id="Fig6" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Comparison of actual AQI values in Lhasa (<bold>a</bold>), Shanghai (<bold>b</bold>), and Beijing (<bold>c</bold>) with predictions from four models, including error histograms.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO6" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig6_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/46a1f9e2ed84/41598_2025_22474_Fig6_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1636?><?original-width 2007?><?scaled-height 545?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig6_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/77cf91f8052b/41598_2025_22474_Fig6_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="2"><title>Model evaluation</title><p id="Par93">Figure <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> presents scatter plots comparing the predicted and actual AQI values for each model, showing a progressive improvement in model performance. The proposed simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM model achieves the highest coefficient of determination, with R and R<sup>2</sup> values of 0.997 and 0.996, respectively—significantly outperforming both LSTM and BiLSTM. This superior performance is attributed to the feature enhancement mechanism of simulated CVOCA, which markedly boosts the model’s predictive capabilities. Additionally, it is evident that the models incorporating bidirectional temporal structures, such as simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM and BiLSTM, demonstrate slightly better performance than their unidirectional counterparts. This indicates that bidirectional structures further enhance the extraction of temporal dependencies. In terms of MAPE, the standard LSTM exceeds 10%, indicating relatively large prediction errors at certain points—suggesting it may be less reliable in practical applications. In contrast, both simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM and simulated CVOCA-LSTM models achieve MAPE values below 5%, demonstrating excellent control over relative errors. The simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM model also records the lowest RMSE and MAE values, at 1.60 and 0.93, respectively—highlighting its superior overall accuracy.</p><fig id="Fig7" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Scatter plots comparing predicted and actual AQI values from the four models for Lhasa (<bold>a</bold>–<bold>d</bold>), Shanghai (<bold>e</bold>–<bold>h</bold>), and Beijing (<bold>i</bold>–<bold>l</bold>).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO7" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig7_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/96fb8a2bc063/41598_2025_22474_Fig7_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1486?><?original-width 2007?><?scaled-height 495?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig7_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/89ffeb1c74d5/41598_2025_22474_Fig7_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="2"><title>Comparative analysis</title><sec id="Sec15" disp-level="3"><title>Robustness and generalizability</title><p id="Par94">Across evaluations in Lhasa, Shanghai, and Beijing, the simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM consistently achieved the highest AQI prediction accuracy, with R<sup>2</sup> values of 0.996, 0.992, and 0.991, respectively, and corresponding RMSE of 1.60, 2.83, and 4.77 (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). These results demonstrate clear advantages over LSTM, BiLSTM, and simulated CVOCA-LSTM, particularly in capturing high-frequency fluctuations and reducing local deviations. Compared with recent approaches such as BWO-CAformer (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.931; RMSE = 9.82) and pollutant-level process frameworks (e.g., GML), the hybrid model showed superior accuracy without relying on decomposition or preprocessing strategies. By integrating simulated CVOCA’s amplitude–phase feature enhancement with bidirectional sequence modeling, the proposed method robustly preserved both baseline levels and transient oscillations, achieving stable and generalizable forecasting across plateau and plain-city environments.</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparative summary of recent AQI/pollutant forecasting models and their best-reported performance across regions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Subject</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Method</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Region</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Time</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Best result</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lhasa, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.996</p><p>R = 0.997</p><p>MAE = 0.93</p><p>MAPE = 1.60%</p><p>RMSE = 1.60</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shanghai, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.992</p><p>R = 0.995</p><p>MAE = 2.15</p><p>MAPE = 4.25%</p><p>RMSE = 2.83</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beijing, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.991</p><p>R = 0.997</p><p>MAE = 3.71</p><p>MAPE = 7.08%</p><p>RMSE = 4.77</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BWO-CAformer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Beijing/</p><p>Wuhan, China</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.931</p><p>MAE = 6.909</p><p>MAPE = 15.265%</p><p>RMSE = 9.822</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LR/DTR/RF/KNN/KNR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Beijing/</p><p>Shanghai/Hubei/</p><p>Shaanxi, China</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9995 (RF)</p><p>RMSE = 0.8660 (RF)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GRU/CNN/FNN/LSTM/MLP</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Azamgarh, India</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9971 (FNN)</p><p>MAE = 2.89 (FNN)</p><p>RMSE = 4.99 (FNN)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TimeGAN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Beijing/</p><p>Tangshan, China</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>MAE = 3.651</p><p>MAPE = 5.072%</p><p>RMSE = 6.407</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">STL-Metis-MHBA-TC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Beijing/</p><p>Wuxi/</p><p>Guangzhou, China</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9971 MAE = 2.1744 MAPE = 4.96%</p><p>RMSE = 3.3636</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RF/XGBoost/LightGBM/CatBoost/GB/KNR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chhattisgarh, India</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.93</p><p>MAE = 0.20</p><p>MSE = 0.08 RMSE = 0.29</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LR/RF/DTR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delhi, India</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.99 (RF)</p><p>RMSE = 0.27 (RF)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGBoost/LarsCV/Bayesian Ridge/AdaBoost</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hyderabad, India</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.999</p><p>MAE = 0.496</p><p>MSE = 0.429</p><p>RMSE = 0.655</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MLP/SVR/RF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beijing, China /Istanbul, Turkey</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.91</p><p>MAE = 6.67</p><p>RMSE = 8.80</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">OA-LSTM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Tehran, Iran</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.88</p><p>RMSE = 3.01</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CNN/ANN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hefei, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.88 (CNN)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.74 (ANN)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CNN-Transformer</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cangzhou, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.930</p><p>MAE = 9.504 MAPE = 18.097%</p><p>RMSE = 13.026</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RF/KNN/WKNN/SVR/LASSO</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zabol, Iran</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.75 (RF)</p><p>MAE = 244.87</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>ANFIS-FCM/</p><p>ANN/ARMA/CNN/GRU/LSTM/CNN-GRU/CNN-LSTM</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Istanbul/Ankara, Turkey</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9547</p><p>MSE = 0.474 MAE = 0.252</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SLNet</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">England, UK</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.914</p><p>MAE = 3.405</p><p>RMSE = 4.898</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSTM/ANN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Liaocheng, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.689</p><p>MAE = 21.384</p><p>RMSE = 27.466</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PM<sub>2.5</sub>/O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GBDT/XGBoost/RF</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Wuhan, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.987 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>)</p><p>MAE = 3.909 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 6.784 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.947 (O<sub>3</sub>)</p><p>MAE = 3.942 (O<sub>3</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 6.323 (O<sub>3</sub>)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PM<sub>2.5</sub>/</p><p>PM<sub>10</sub>/</p><p>O<sub>3</sub></p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PSO-LSTM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Harbin, China</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9486 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>)</p><p>MAE = 0.0014 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 0.0033 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9419 (PM<sub>10</sub>)</p><p>MAE = 0.0037 (PM<sub>10</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 0.0077 (PM<sub>10</sub>)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9698 (O<sub>3</sub>)</p><p>MAE = 0.0113 (O<sub>3</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 0.0184 (O<sub>3</sub>)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>PM<sub>2.5</sub>/</p><p>PM<sub>10</sub>/</p><p>O<sub>3</sub>/</p><p>NO<sub>2</sub>/</p><p>SO<sub>2</sub>/</p><p>CO</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GML</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Global</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2025</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.97 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 9.43 (PM<sub>2.5</sub>)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.93 (PM<sub>10</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 8.99 (PM<sub>10</sub>)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.95 (O<sub>3</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 17.37 (O<sub>3</sub>)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.97 (NO<sub>2</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 2.88 (NO<sub>2</sub>)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.80 (SO<sub>2</sub>)</p><p>RMSE = 2.55 (SO<sub>2</sub>)</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.96 (CO)</p><p>RMSE = 3.50 (CO)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><sup><xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" disp-level="2"><title>Computational efficiency and scalability</title><p id="Par95">As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, the integration of the CVOCA module markedly enhances both the computational efficiency and scalability of LSTM and BiLSTM models. Specifically, CVOCA-enhanced models achieve approximately 2.5 × faster inference and substantially reduced training times per epoch compared to their vanilla counterparts, while maintaining moderate memory usage (&lt; 1 GB). The inference time per sample of the CVOCA-LSTM is roughly one-third that of the baseline LSTM, and the simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM reaches an average prediction time of 0.00049 s per sample, representing a 59.3% speedup over the standard BiLSTM. Importantly, despite modest increases in total trainable parameters, both CVOCA-LSTM and CVOCA-BiLSTM exhibit significantly improved predictive performance (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.967 and 0.996, respectively), demonstrating that the architecture effectively leverages the additional capacity without compromising efficiency. These quantitative results provide solid evidence for the high computational efficiency and scalability of the proposed framework, underscoring its potential for large-scale, high-dimensional AQI forecasting tasks.</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Compare and analyze the quantitative data on the computational efficiency and cost of the four models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total trainable parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Training time/epoch (s)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total training time (s)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inference time/sample (ms)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Peak RAM<break/>(GB)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Predictive Performance Metrics</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSTM (baseline)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,350,913</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.90</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">689.99</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2587</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.598</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RMSE = 9.87</p><p>MSE = 6.84</p><p>MAPE = 11.95%</p><p>R = 0.8509</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.7240</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BiLSTM (baseline)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,750,145</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.74</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">974.10</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.2076</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.777</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RMSE = 9.52</p><p>MSE = 6.73</p><p>MAPE = 11.99%</p><p>R = 0.8665</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.7494</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Simulated CVOCA-LSTM</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1,361,153</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.21</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">421.03</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4687</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.635</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RMSE = 3.35</p><p>MSE = 2.48</p><p>MAPE = 4.49%</p><p>R = 0.9837</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9672</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3,881,601</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.06</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">506.49</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4913</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.820</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>RMSE = 1.60</p><p>MSE = 0.93</p><p>MAPE = 1.60%</p><p>R = 0.9965</p><p>R<sup>2</sup> = 0.9956</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec17" disp-level="2"><title>Prediction of AQI values</title><p id="Par96">Using the LSTM, BiLSTM, simulated CVOCA-LSTM, and simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM models developed in this study, we forecasted AQI levels for January 2025 in three representative cities—Lhasa, Shanghai, and Beijing. The results are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, where distinct prediction patterns emerged across these cities, reflecting their contrasting environmental contexts as well as the evolution and driving mechanisms of eco-environmental quality across different urbanization stages<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>.</p><fig id="Fig8" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Predictions of the AQI for January 2025 in Lhasa (<bold>a</bold>), Shanghai (<bold>b</bold>), and Beijing (<bold>c</bold>) by four models.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="MO8" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig8_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/41f8d083dd31/41598_2025_22474_Fig8_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2362?><?original-width 1302?><?scaled-height 1181?><?scaled-width 651?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_Fig8_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1a8/12586577/1481266524ad/41598_2025_22474_Fig8_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par97">In Lhasa, where AQI time series are relatively smooth due to limited local emission sources and high-altitude boundary-layer dynamics, the simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM produced a stable prediction curve that closely aligned with historical variability. Specifically, for January 2025, the average AQI predicted by simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM was stable at 52.63, compared to the actual average AQI value of 53 for January 2014–2024. This makes simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM’s prediction more accurate than the other three models for January 2025, leading to the conclusion that the AQI level for the first month of 2025 falls within the “Good” category (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In contrast, the LSTM model predicted an average AQI of 45.56, indicating an “Excellent” quality level<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>, which significantly differed from the other models. While the prediction trends for pollution levels from simulated CVOCA-LSTM and simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM were similar in terms of pattern changes, the AQI levels showed some variations. This could be attributed to the bidirectional time series structure, which allows for a more accurate overall prediction of AQI values over time. The differences in AQI levels predicted by the LSTM, BiLSTM, simulated CVOCA-LSTM, and simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM models explain the variations in model accuracy and precision. In contrast, the prediction curves for Shanghai and Beijing exhibited more pronounced short-term fluctuations, consistent with their denser emission sources and stronger meteorological variability. Across both plain cities, the simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM captured these fluctuations more effectively than the other models, providing forecasts that preserved both baseline levels and transient variations. Notably, the conventional LSTM tended to underestimate AQI in all three cities, with particularly smoothed predictions in Lhasa, failing to capture the subtle dynamics of plateau environments. BiLSTM improved upon this by partially incorporating temporal dependencies, while simulated CVOCA-LSTM benefited from enhanced feature extraction but still exhibited limitations in reproducing bidirectional temporal dynamics. By contrast, the simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM consistently yielded the most balanced forecasts, simultaneously maintaining stability in plateau conditions and adaptability to the higher variability observed in plain cities.</p><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The standard Air Quality Index and related information, for China.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Grade</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AQI classes</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Notes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0–50</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">I</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Excellent</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">The air quality is very good, with little impact on health</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">51–100</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">II</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">May have a slight impact on a small number of sensitive individuals</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101–150</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">III</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light pollution</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">It has some effect on sensitive people</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">151–200</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IV</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate pollution</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">It affects most people</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">201–300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">V</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Serious pollution</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">It affects everyone</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"> &gt; 300</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">VI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heavy pollution</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Will have a significant impact on the health of all populations</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par98">These results highlight that the hybrid model not only excels under the relatively low-fluctuation conditions of high-altitude cities but also generalizes effectively to plain urban environments characterized by more dynamic AQI patterns. The differences in AQI levels predicted by the LSTM, BiLSTM, simulated CVOCA-LSTM, and simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM models explain the variations in model accuracy and precision.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par99">This study proposes a novel simulated CVOCA-BiLSTM hybrid model for high-accuracy AQI prediction in the high-altitude environment of Lhasa, Tibet. The model integrates the ultra-fast feature extraction capability of the simulated CVOCA for high-dimensional AQI data and the bidirectional time series dependency modeling ability of the BiLSTM network. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed model achieves outstanding predictive performance, with RMSE, MAE, MAPE, R, and R<sup>2</sup> values of 1.60, 0.93, 1.60%, 0.997, and 0.996, respectively, outperforming standalone LSTM, BiLSTM, and conventional hybrid models. The synergy between the simulated CVOCA’s capacity to process complex amplitude–phase features and BiLSTM’s bidirectional learning capability effectively addresses the nonlinear dynamics, sudden anomalies, and pollution lag effects in AQI time series. Validation using actual data from Lhasa (2014–2024) confirms the model’s robustness under the unique high-altitude setting, while additional assessments in Shanghai (coastal plain with moderate variability) and Beijing (inland plain with high variability) demonstrate its transferability across contrasting geographical and variability regimes. This research framework not only enhances the accuracy of air quality predictions but also contributes to data-driven urban environmental management, offering feasible decision support for public health protection in ecologically fragile areas. Future research will extend to multi-pollutant coupling mechanisms and regional-scale spatiotemporal dynamics to further improve the model’s general applicability.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM1" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path e1a8/12586577/1fe76dc7b5a9/41598_2025_22474_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 29849?><caption><p>Supplementary Information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to express our sincere gratitude to the Laboratory of Environmental Chemistry and Atmospheric Sciences on the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau and the Key Laboratory of Biodiversity and Environment on the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau of the Ministry of Education for their support and resources, which have played an important role in the successful completion of this research.</p></sec><sec id="glossary1" sec-type="glossary" disp-level="1"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AdaBoost</term><def><p id="Par2">Adaptive Boosting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANN</term><def><p id="Par3">Artificial Neural Network</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AQI</term><def><p id="Par4">Air Quality Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANFIS</term><def><p id="Par5">Adaptive Neuro-Fuzzy Inference System</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ARMA</term><def><p id="Par6">Autoregressive Moving Average</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BPTT</term><def><p id="Par7">Backpropagation Through Time</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BR</term><def><p id="Par8">Bayesian Ridge</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BWO</term><def><p id="Par9">Beluga Whale Optimization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAformer</term><def><p id="Par10">Convolutional Block Attention Module augmented Informer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CatBoost</term><def><p id="Par11">Categorical Boosting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNN</term><def><p id="Par12">Convolutional Neural Network</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CVOCA</term><def><p id="Par13">Complex-Valued Optical Convolutional Accelerator</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DTR</term><def><p id="Par14">Decision Tree Regression</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FCM</term><def><p id="Par15">Fuzzy C-Means</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FFT</term><def><p id="Par16">Fast Fourier Transform</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FNN</term><def><p id="Par17">Feedforward Neural Network</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GB</term><def><p id="Par18">Gradient Boosting</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GBDT</term><def><p id="Par19">Gradient Boosted Decision Trees</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GML</term><def><p id="Par20">Geographics Machine Learning</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GRU</term><def><p id="Par21">Gated Recurrent Units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KNN</term><def><p id="Par22">K-Nearest Neighbors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KNR</term><def><p id="Par23">K-Neighbors Regressor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LARS</term><def><p id="Par24">Least Angle Regression</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LarsCV</term><def><p id="Par25">Least Angle Regression with Cross-Validation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LASSO</term><def><p id="Par26">Least Absolute Shrinkage and Selection Operator</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LightGBM</term><def><p id="Par27">Light Gradient Boosting Machine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LSTM</term><def><p id="Par28">Long Short-Term Memory</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LR</term><def><p id="Par29">Logistic Regression</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAE</term><def><p id="Par30">Mean Absolute Error</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAPE</term><def><p id="Par31">Mean Absolute Percentage Error</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MHBA</term><def><p id="Par32">Modified Honey Badger Algorithm</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MLP</term><def><p id="Par33">Multi-Layer Perceptron</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OA</term><def><p id="Par34">Orchard Algorithm</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBLH</term><def><p id="Par35">Planetary Boundary-Layer Height</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PSO</term><def><p id="Par36">Particle Swarm Optimization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RF</term><def><p id="Par37">Random Forest</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RMSE</term><def><p id="Par38">Root Mean Square Error</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNN</term><def><p id="Par39">Recurrent Neural Networks</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SLNet</term><def><p id="Par40">Spatial-and-Local-Aware Deep Learning Network</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STL</term><def><p id="Par41">Seasonal-Trend Decomposition based on Loess</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SVR</term><def><p id="Par42">Support Vector Regression</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TimeGAN</term><def><p id="Par43">Time Generative Adversarial Networks</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WKNN</term><def><p id="Par44">Weighted K-Nearest Neighbor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>XGBoost</term><def><p id="Par45">Extreme Gradient Boosting</p></def></def-item></def-list></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Data curation, F.X.; methodology, F.X.;writing—original draf preparation, F.X.; formal analysis, X.C.; supervision, G.J. and D.B.; writing—review and editing, F.X. and Q.Z. All the authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 22266032, 22466032), Talent Incentive Project of Tibet University (No. ZDRC202410), Science and Technology Plan Projects of Shigatse City (No. RKZ2024ZY-06), the Lhasa Municipal Major Science and Technology Project (No. LSKJ202543), Science and Technology projects of Xizang Autonomous Region (XZ202501ZY0072, XZ202501ZY0008), Central Financial Support Special Funds for Local Colleges and Universities (No. [2024]01, [2025]01).</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data used in this study were obtained from the China National Environmental Monitoring centre (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cnemc.cn/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cnemc.cn/</ext-link>) and historical data from the AQI Study database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.aqistudy.cn/historydata/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.aqistudy.cn/historydata/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="1"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par100">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="_ci93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="contrib-info" disp-level="1"><title>Contributor Information</title><p>Duo Bu, Email: phudor@vip.163.com.</p><p>Qiangying Zhang, Email: zhangqiangying@utibet.edu.cn.</p></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gewin, V. How a dangerous stew of air pollution is choking the United States. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>612</bold>, 204–207. 10.1038/d41586-022-04333-9 (2022).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/d41586-022-04333-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36473970"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gewin, V. How a dangerous stew of air pollution is choking the United States. Nature612, 204–207. 10.1038/d41586-022-04333-9 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Canadell, J. G. et al. Multi-decadal increase of forest burned area in Australia is linked to climate change. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>12</bold>(1), 6921. 10.1038/s41467-021-27225-4 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-021-27225-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8626427"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34836974"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Canadell, J. G. et al. Multi-decadal increase of forest burned area in Australia is linked to climate change. Nat. Commun.12(1), 6921. 10.1038/s41467-021-27225-4 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Balsari, S. &amp; Mohanan, M. Local government actions can curb air pollution in India and Pakistan. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>634</bold>, 1055–1056. 10.1038/d41586-024-03314-4 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/d41586-024-03314-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39443759"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Balsari, S. &amp; Mohanan, M. Local government actions can curb air pollution in India and Pakistan. Nature634, 1055–1056. 10.1038/d41586-024-03314-4 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, X. et al. Polar regions are critical in achieving global sustainable development goals. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>16</bold>(1), 3879. 10.1038/s41467-025-59178-3 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-025-59178-3"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12022344"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40274805"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, X. et al. Polar regions are critical in achieving global sustainable development goals. Nat. Commun.16(1), 3879. 10.1038/s41467-025-59178-3 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhao, S., Feng, T., Tie, X. &amp; Wang, Z. The warming Tibetan Plateau improves winter air quality in the Sichuan Basin. <italic>China. Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>20</bold>(23), 14873–14887. 10.5194/acp-20-14873-2020 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhao, S., Feng, T., Tie, X. &amp; Wang, Z. The warming Tibetan Plateau improves winter air quality in the Sichuan Basin. China. Atmos. Chem. Phys.20(23), 14873–14887. 10.5194/acp-20-14873-2020 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yin, X. et al. Gaseous and particulate pollutants in Lhasa, Tibet during 2013–2017: Spatial variability, temporal variations and implications. <italic>Environ. Pollut.</italic><bold>253</bold>, 68–77. 10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.113 (2019).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.113"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31302404"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yin, X. et al. Gaseous and particulate pollutants in Lhasa, Tibet during 2013–2017: Spatial variability, temporal variations and implications. Environ. Pollut.253, 68–77. 10.1016/j.envpol.2019.06.113 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liang, Q. et al. Spatial–temporal characteristics and influencing mechanisms of air quality index by considering COVID-19 in Yunnan. <italic>Southeastern Tibetan Plateau. Atmosphere</italic><bold>14</bold>(2), 378. 10.3390/atmos14020378 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liang, Q. et al. Spatial–temporal characteristics and influencing mechanisms of air quality index by considering COVID-19 in Yunnan. Southeastern Tibetan Plateau. Atmosphere14(2), 378. 10.3390/atmos14020378 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sokhi, R. S. et al. Advances in air quality research–current and emerging challenges. <italic>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>22</bold>(7), 4615–4703. 10.5194/acp-22-4615-2022 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sokhi, R. S. et al. Advances in air quality research–current and emerging challenges. Atmos. Chem. Phys.22(7), 4615–4703. 10.5194/acp-22-4615-2022 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dong, X., Li, D., Wang, W. &amp; Shen, Y. BWO-CAformer: An improved Informer model for AQI prediction in Beijing and Wuhan. <italic>Process Saf. Environ. Prot.</italic><bold>195</bold>, 106800. 10.1016/j.psep.2025.106800 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Dong, X., Li, D., Wang, W. &amp; Shen, Y. BWO-CAformer: An improved Informer model for AQI prediction in Beijing and Wuhan. Process Saf. Environ. Prot.195, 106800. 10.1016/j.psep.2025.106800 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sarwar, G. et al. Representing particulate nitrate photolysis over seawater improves CMAQ ozone predictions over the contiguous United States. <italic>Sci. Total Environ.</italic><bold>970</bold>, 178968. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2025.178968 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2025.178968"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12067099"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40043651"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sarwar, G. et al. Representing particulate nitrate photolysis over seawater improves CMAQ ozone predictions over the contiguous United States. Sci. Total Environ.970, 178968. 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2025.178968 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang, H. et al. Contribution of dust emissions from farmland to particulate matter concentrations in North China Plain: Integration of WRF-Chem and WEPS model. <italic>Environ. Int.</italic><bold>195</bold>, 109191. 10.1016/j.envint.2024.109191 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envint.2024.109191"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39673873"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhang, H. et al. Contribution of dust emissions from farmland to particulate matter concentrations in North China Plain: Integration of WRF-Chem and WEPS model. Environ. Int.195, 109191. 10.1016/j.envint.2024.109191 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Uluocak, I., Pinar, E. &amp; Bilgili, M. Atmospheric NO<sub>2</sub> concentration prediction with statistical and hybrid deep learning methods. <italic>Environ. Ecol. Stat.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 89–118. 10.1007/s10651-024-00637-3 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Uluocak, I., Pinar, E. &amp; Bilgili, M. Atmospheric NO2 concentration prediction with statistical and hybrid deep learning methods. Environ. Ecol. Stat.32, 89–118. 10.1007/s10651-024-00637-3 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, S., Ren, Y. &amp; Xia, B. Estimation of urban AQI based on interpretable machine learning. <italic>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.</italic><bold>30</bold>(42), 96562–96574. 10.1007/s11356-023-29336-5 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s11356-023-29336-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37580474"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, S., Ren, Y. &amp; Xia, B. Estimation of urban AQI based on interpretable machine learning. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res.30(42), 96562–96574. 10.1007/s11356-023-29336-5 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mu, X., Wang, S., Jiang, P. &amp; Wu, Y. Estimation of surface ozone concentration over Jiangsu province using a high-performance deep learning model. <italic>J. Environ. Sci.</italic><bold>132</bold>, 122–133. 10.1016/j.jes.2022.09.032 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jes.2022.09.032"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37336603"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mu, X., Wang, S., Jiang, P. &amp; Wu, Y. Estimation of surface ozone concentration over Jiangsu province using a high-performance deep learning model. J. Environ. Sci.132, 122–133. 10.1016/j.jes.2022.09.032 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ahmed, D. M., Hassan, M. M. &amp; Mstafa, R. J. A review on deep sequential models for forecasting time series data. <italic>Appl. Comput. Intell. Soft Comput.</italic>10.1155/2022/6596397 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ahmed, D. M., Hassan, M. M. &amp; Mstafa, R. J. A review on deep sequential models for forecasting time series data. Appl. Comput. Intell. Soft Comput.10.1155/2022/6596397 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ravindiran, G. et al. Ensemble stacking of machine learning models for air quality prediction for Hyderabad City in India. <italic>iScience</italic><bold>28</bold>(2), 111894. 10.1016/j.isci.2025.111894 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.isci.2025.111894"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11883379"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40051831"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ravindiran, G. et al. Ensemble stacking of machine learning models for air quality prediction for Hyderabad City in India. iScience28(2), 111894. 10.1016/j.isci.2025.111894 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wu, Q. &amp; Lin, H. Daily urban air quality index forecasting based on variational mode decomposition, sample entropy and LSTM neural network. <italic>Sustain. Cities Soc.</italic><bold>50</bold>, 101657. 10.1016/j.scs.2019.101657 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wu, Q. &amp; Lin, H. Daily urban air quality index forecasting based on variational mode decomposition, sample entropy and LSTM neural network. Sustain. Cities Soc.50, 101657. 10.1016/j.scs.2019.101657 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dong, J., Zhang, Y. &amp; Hu, J. Short-term air quality prediction based on EMD-transformer-BiLSTM. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>14</bold>(1), 20513. 10.1038/s41598-024-67626-1 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-024-67626-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11372107"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39227685"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Dong, J., Zhang, Y. &amp; Hu, J. Short-term air quality prediction based on EMD-transformer-BiLSTM. Sci. Rep.14(1), 20513. 10.1038/s41598-024-67626-1 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bai, Y. et al. TOPS-speed complex-valued convolutional accelerator for feature extraction and inference. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>16</bold>(1), 292. 10.1038/s41467-024-55321-8 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-024-55321-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11697240"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39747029"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bai, Y. et al. TOPS-speed complex-valued convolutional accelerator for feature extraction and inference. Nat. Commun.16(1), 292. 10.1038/s41467-024-55321-8 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hochreiter, S. &amp; Schmidhuber, J. Long short-term memory. <italic>Neural Comput.</italic><bold>9</bold>(8), 1735–1780. 10.1162/neco.1997.9.8.1735 (1997).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1162/neco.1997.9.8.1735"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="9377276"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hochreiter, S. &amp; Schmidhuber, J. Long short-term memory. Neural Comput.9(8), 1735–1780. 10.1162/neco.1997.9.8.1735 (1997)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Graves, A. &amp; Schmidhuber, J. Framewise phoneme classification with bidirectional LSTM and other neural network architectures. <italic>Neural Netw.</italic><bold>18</bold>(5–6), 602–610. 10.1016/j.neunet.2005.06.042 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.neunet.2005.06.042"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16112549"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Graves, A. &amp; Schmidhuber, J. Framewise phoneme classification with bidirectional LSTM and other neural network architectures. Neural Netw.18(5–6), 602–610. 10.1016/j.neunet.2005.06.042 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang, J. &amp; Li, S. Air quality index forecast in Beijing based on CNN-LSTM multi-model. <italic>Chemosphere</italic><bold>308</bold>, 136180. 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.136180G (2022).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.136180"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36058367"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhang, J. &amp; Li, S. Air quality index forecast in Beijing based on CNN-LSTM multi-model. Chemosphere308, 136180. 10.1016/j.chemosphere.2022.136180G (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rabie, R., Asghari, M., Nosrati, H., Niri, M. E. &amp; Karimi, S. Spatially resolved air quality index prediction in megacities with a CNN-Bi-LSTM hybrid framework. <italic>Sustain. Cities Soc.</italic><bold>109</bold>, 105537. 10.1016/j.scs.2024.105537 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rabie, R., Asghari, M., Nosrati, H., Niri, M. E. &amp; Karimi, S. Spatially resolved air quality index prediction in megacities with a CNN-Bi-LSTM hybrid framework. Sustain. Cities Soc.109, 105537. 10.1016/j.scs.2024.105537 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, J. et al. An air quality index prediction model based on CNN-ILSTM. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>12</bold>(1), 8373. 10.1038/s41598-022-12355-6 (2022).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-022-12355-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9120089"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35589914"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, J. et al. An air quality index prediction model based on CNN-ILSTM. Sci. Rep.12(1), 8373. 10.1038/s41598-022-12355-6 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fan, Y., Tang, Q. &amp; Guo, Y. BiLSTM-MLAM: a multi-scale time series prediction model based on Bi-LSTM and local attention mechanism. 10.21203/rs.3.rs-4229520/v1 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/s24123962"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11207626"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38931746"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mubeen, M. et al. Smart prediction and optimization of air quality index with artificial intelligence. <italic>J. Environ. Sci.</italic>10.1016/j.jes.2025.02.041 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jes.2025.02.041"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40841051"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mubeen, M. et al. Smart prediction and optimization of air quality index with artificial intelligence. J. Environ. Sci.10.1016/j.jes.2025.02.041 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ansari, A. &amp; Quaff, A. R. Data-driven analysis and predictive modelling of hourly air quality index (AQI) using deep learning techniques: A case study of Azamgarh, India. <italic>Theor. Appl. Climatol.</italic><bold>156</bold>(1), 74. 10.1007/s00704-024-05304-y (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ansari, A. &amp; Quaff, A. R. Data-driven analysis and predictive modelling of hourly air quality index (AQI) using deep learning techniques: A case study of Azamgarh, India. Theor. Appl. Climatol.156(1), 74. 10.1007/s00704-024-05304-y (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, K., Yang, T., Kong, S. &amp; Li, M. Air quality index prediction through TimeGAN data recovery and PSO-optimized VMD-deep learning framework. <italic>Appl. Soft Comput.</italic><bold>170</bold>, 112626. 10.1016/j.asoc.2024.112626 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, K., Yang, T., Kong, S. &amp; Li, M. Air quality index prediction through TimeGAN data recovery and PSO-optimized VMD-deep learning framework. Appl. Soft Comput.170, 112626. 10.1016/j.asoc.2024.112626 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Qian, S. et al. A novel ensemble framework based on intelligent weight optimization and multi-model fusion for air quality index prediction. <italic>Urban Clim.</italic><bold>59</bold>, 102233. 10.1016/j.uclim.2024.102233 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Qian, S. et al. A novel ensemble framework based on intelligent weight optimization and multi-model fusion for air quality index prediction. Urban Clim.59, 102233. 10.1016/j.uclim.2024.102233 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gond, A. K., Jamal, A. &amp; Verma, T. Developing a machine learning model using satellite data to predict the air quality index (AQI) over Korba Coalfield, Chhattisgarh (India). <italic>Atmos. Pollut. Res.</italic><bold>16</bold>(2), 102398. 10.1016/j.apr.2024.102398 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gond, A. K., Jamal, A. &amp; Verma, T. Developing a machine learning model using satellite data to predict the air quality index (AQI) over Korba Coalfield, Chhattisgarh (India). Atmos. Pollut. Res.16(2), 102398. 10.1016/j.apr.2024.102398 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pande, C. B. et al. Forecasting of monthly air quality index and understanding the air pollution in the urban city, India based on machine learning models and cross-validation. <italic>J. Atmos. Chem.</italic><bold>82</bold>(1), 1. 10.1007/s10874-024-09466-x (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pande, C. B. et al. Forecasting of monthly air quality index and understanding the air pollution in the urban city, India based on machine learning models and cross-validation. J. Atmos. Chem.82(1), 1. 10.1007/s10874-024-09466-x (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Emeç, M. U. R. A. T. &amp; Yurtsever, M. A novel ensemble machine learning method for accurate air quality prediction. <italic>Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>22</bold>(1), 459–476. 10.1007/s13762-024-05671-z (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Emeç, M. U. R. A. T. &amp; Yurtsever, M. A novel ensemble machine learning method for accurate air quality prediction. Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol.22(1), 459–476. 10.1007/s13762-024-05671-z (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kaveh, M., Mesgari, M. S. &amp; Kaveh, M. A novel evolutionary deep learning approach for PM<sub>2.5</sub> prediction using remote sensing and spatial–temporal data: A case study of Tehran. <italic>ISPRS Int. J. Geo Inf.</italic><bold>14</bold>(2), 42. 10.3390/ijgi14020042 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kaveh, M., Mesgari, M. S. &amp; Kaveh, M. A novel evolutionary deep learning approach for PM2.5 prediction using remote sensing and spatial–temporal data: A case study of Tehran. ISPRS Int. J. Geo Inf.14(2), 42. 10.3390/ijgi14020042 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Xia, S., Zhang, R., Zhang, L., Wang, T. &amp; Wang, W. Multi-dimensional distribution prediction of PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration in urban residential areas based on CNN. <italic>Build. Environ.</italic><bold>267</bold>, 112167. 10.1016/j.buildenv.2024.112167 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Xia, S., Zhang, R., Zhang, L., Wang, T. &amp; Wang, W. Multi-dimensional distribution prediction of PM2.5 concentration in urban residential areas based on CNN. Build. Environ.267, 112167. 10.1016/j.buildenv.2024.112167 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, Y. Z., He, H. D., Huang, H. C., Yang, J. M. &amp; Peng, Z. R. High-resolution spatiotemporal prediction of PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration based on mobile monitoring and deep learning. <italic>Environ. Pollut.</italic><bold>364</bold>, 125342. 10.1016/j.envpol.2024.125342 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2024.125342"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39566710"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, Y. Z., He, H. D., Huang, H. C., Yang, J. M. &amp; Peng, Z. R. High-resolution spatiotemporal prediction of PM2.5 concentration based on mobile monitoring and deep learning. Environ. Pollut.364, 125342. 10.1016/j.envpol.2024.125342 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kalantari, E., Gholami, H., Malakooti, H., Kaskaoutis, D. G. &amp; Saneei, P. An integrated feature selection and machine learning framework for PM<sub>10</sub> concentration prediction. <italic>Atmos. Pollut. Res.</italic><bold>16</bold>(5), 102456. 10.1016/j.apr.2025.102456 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kalantari, E., Gholami, H., Malakooti, H., Kaskaoutis, D. G. &amp; Saneei, P. An integrated feature selection and machine learning framework for PM10 concentration prediction. Atmos. Pollut. Res.16(5), 102456. 10.1016/j.apr.2025.102456 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, S., Zhang, S., Wang, D. &amp; Li, W. Spatial-and-local-aware deep learning approach for Ground-Level NO<sub>2</sub> estimation in England with multisource data from satellite-based observations and chemical transport models. <italic>Int. J. Appl. Earth Obs. Geoinf.</italic><bold>139</bold>, 104506. 10.1016/j.jag.2025.104506 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, S., Zhang, S., Wang, D. &amp; Li, W. Spatial-and-local-aware deep learning approach for Ground-Level NO2 estimation in England with multisource data from satellite-based observations and chemical transport models. Int. J. Appl. Earth Obs. Geoinf.139, 104506. 10.1016/j.jag.2025.104506 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Guo, Q., He, Z. &amp; Wang, Z. Assessing the effectiveness of long short-term memory and artificial neural network in predicting daily ozone concentrations in Liaocheng City. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold>(1), 6798. 10.1038/s41598-025-91329-w (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-025-91329-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11861296"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40000767"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Guo, Q., He, Z. &amp; Wang, Z. Assessing the effectiveness of long short-term memory and artificial neural network in predicting daily ozone concentrations in Liaocheng City. Sci. Rep.15(1), 6798. 10.1038/s41598-025-91329-w (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Xu, J., Liu, M., Chao, Y. &amp; Chen, H. A novel prediction framework for estimating high spatial resolution near-ground PM<sub>2.5</sub> and O3 concentrations at street-level in urban areas. <italic>Build. Environ.</italic><bold>267</bold>, 112141. 10.1016/j.buildenv.2024.112141 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Xu, J., Liu, M., Chao, Y. &amp; Chen, H. A novel prediction framework for estimating high spatial resolution near-ground PM2.5 and O3 concentrations at street-level in urban areas. Build. Environ.267, 112141. 10.1016/j.buildenv.2024.112141 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chen, M. et al. Air pollution prediction based on optimized deep learning neural networks: PSO-LSTM. <italic>Atmos. Pollut. Res.</italic><bold>16</bold>(3), 102413. 10.1016/j.apr.2025.102413 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chen, M. et al. Air pollution prediction based on optimized deep learning neural networks: PSO-LSTM. Atmos. Pollut. Res.16(3), 102413. 10.1016/j.apr.2025.102413 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Anggraini, T. S., Irie, H., Sakti, A. D. &amp; Wikantika, K. Global Air Quality Index Prediction using integrated spatial observation data and geographics machine learning. <italic>Sci. Remote Sens.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 100197. 10.1016/j.srs.2025.100197 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Anggraini, T. S., Irie, H., Sakti, A. D. &amp; Wikantika, K. Global Air Quality Index Prediction using integrated spatial observation data and geographics machine learning. Sci. Remote Sens.11, 100197. 10.1016/j.srs.2025.100197 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">He, Z., Guo, Q., Yin, Z., Luo, X. &amp; Sun, M. Evolution and driving mechanisms of eco-environmental quality across different urbanization stages. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 22101. 10.1038/s41598-025-06084-9 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-025-06084-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12216039"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40593086"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="He, Z., Guo, Q., Yin, Z., Luo, X. &amp; Sun, M. Evolution and driving mechanisms of eco-environmental quality across different urbanization stages. Sci. Rep.15, 22101. 10.1038/s41598-025-06084-9 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, Z. et al. Prospect of China’s ambient air quality standards. <italic>J. Environ. Sci.</italic><bold>123</bold>, 255–269. 10.1016/j.jes.2022.03.036 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jes.2022.03.036"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36521988"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, Z. et al. Prospect of China’s ambient air quality standards. J. Environ. Sci.123, 255–269. 10.1016/j.jes.2022.03.036 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Guo, Q., He, Z. &amp; Wang, Z. Monthly climate prediction using deep convolutional neural network and long short-term memory. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 17748. 10.1038/s41598-024-68906-6 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-024-68906-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11291741"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39085577"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Guo, Q., He, Z. &amp; Wang, Z. Monthly climate prediction using deep convolutional neural network and long short-term memory. Sci. Rep.14, 17748. 10.1038/s41598-024-68906-6 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2025_22474_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path e1a8/12586577/1fe76dc7b5a9/41598_2025_22474_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 29849?><caption><p>Supplementary Information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The data used in this study were obtained from the China National Environmental Monitoring centre (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cnemc.cn/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cnemc.cn/</ext-link>) and historical data from the AQI Study database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.aqistudy.cn/historydata/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.aqistudy.cn/historydata/</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec></body></article>