
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Inquiry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Inquiry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3386</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">inquiry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">INQ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Inquiry: A Journal of Medical Care Organization, Provision and Financing</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0046-9580</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1945-7243</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12789392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12789392.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12789392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12789392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41510629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00469580251411470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_00469580251411470</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Beyond the Visibility: Addressing Intangible and Non-economic Losses for Health and Well-Being in Global Context of Climate Change and Disaster</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4326-0059</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Assaf</surname><given-names initials="RR">Raymen R.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH, MA</degrees><xref rid="aff1-00469580251411470" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2-00469580251411470" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="corresp1-00469580251411470" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shelton</surname><given-names initials="SK">Shelby K.</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff1-00469580251411470" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff3-00469580251411470" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morphew</surname><given-names initials="T">Tricia</given-names></name><degrees>MSc, MPH</degrees><xref rid="aff3-00469580251411470" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff4-00469580251411470" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names initials="S">Susan</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff5-00469580251411470" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff2-00469580251411470" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-00469580251411470"><label>1</label>Children’s Hospital, Orange County, CA, USA</aff><aff id="aff2-00469580251411470"><label>2</label>University of California, Irvine, USA</aff><aff id="aff3-00469580251411470"><label>3</label>CHOC Research Institute, Orange, CA, USA</aff><aff id="aff4-00469580251411470"><label>4</label>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA</aff><aff id="aff5-00469580251411470"><label>5</label>The College of Wooster, OH, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-00469580251411470">Raymen R. Assaf, Rady Children’s Health-Orange County, 1201 W. La Veta Avenue, Orange, CA 92868-3874, USA. Email: <email>rassaf@emsoc.net</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Dec</season><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>63</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">503875</issue-id><elocation-id>00469580251411470</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-01-11 00:25:14.650"><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="10.1177_00469580251411470.pdf"><?pdf-name 10.1177_00469580251411470.pdf?><?pdf-size 660587?><?pdf-md5 7a270eb91217960f0df104e6d1023863?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:c22f/12789392/7a270eb91217/10.1177_00469580251411470.pdf?></self-uri><abstract><p>Climate change and mental health research has predominantly focused on adults in non-clinical settings; investigations among youth and in clinical settings are lacking. Our objectives were to understand the relationship between adult caregiver and adolescent patient climate-anxiety and to examine caregivers’ community-level concerns and their association with adolescent climate anxiety. This cross-sectional study occurred in a single-center pediatric emergency department (ED) and data collection spanned January to December 2024. Exposures included adolescent demographic factors (age group, sex, race and ethnicity, insurance payor) and adolescent and caregiver general anxiety disorder-7 (GAD-7) scores, as well as caregiver perspectives captured on (1) the climate change anxiety scale (CCAS), (2) a domestic and global issues poll, and (3) an environmental community survey. The outcome was adolescent climate anxiety, operationalized using the CCAS. In total, 557 patient-caregiver dyads completed CCAS surveys, with low within-dyad agreement in scores, ICC = 0.224 (95% CI 0.142, 0.274). Both caregivers and adolescents had higher levels of climate anxiety if the caregiver reported concerns about housing, public services, and pollution in their community (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05). Moderate-severe generalized anxiety (GAD-7) was the strongest predictor of climate anxiety in both adolescents and caregivers (OR<sub>adj</sub> 6.59, 95% CI 3.52-12.30, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). Caregivers viewing climate change as very important had higher odds of moderate-severe CCAS (OR<sub>adj</sub> = 4.50 (95% CI 2.03, 9.98), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001), with no significant effect of their perception on adolescent CCAS (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .172). Generalized anxiety and adult caregiver community-level concerns appear to be associated with adolescent climate anxiety in this large pediatric study, but there is no direct relationship between caregiver climate anxiety and the climate anxiety of the adolescent.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>climate anxiety</kwd><kwd>pediatric</kwd><kwd>emergency department</kwd><kwd>caregiver</kwd><kwd>social drivers of health</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2026</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>typesetter</meta-name><meta-value>ts1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-00469580251411470"><title>Introduction</title><p>The adolescent period is defined by physical, social, and cognitive changes in development which drive emotional responses and sensitivity to world issues.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr1-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</sup> Today’s youth in the United States are exposed to highly publicized and reported severe global weather and climate events, with 85% feeling at least moderately worried about climate change, 42.8% reporting climate change impact on their mental health, and 38.3% acknowledging that their feelings about climate change negatively affect their daily life and functioning.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bibr2-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Despite these alarming statistics, the mechanisms underlying youth anxiety about climate change remain poorly understood.</p><p>Climate anxiety is defined as heightened emotional, mental, or somatic distress in response to detrimental changes in the climate.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> It represents a specific form of eco-anxiety, the broader construct encompassing distress about negative environmental changes in general, including pollution and biodiversity.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> While climate- and eco-anxiety are often used interchangeably in the literature, we focus specifically on climate change-related anxiety. In addition to being a psychological descriptor, the term climate anxiety has been operationalized as a psychometric construct in the climate change anxiety scale (CCAS), increasingly implemented in samples of young people.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<xref rid="bibr6-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr7-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr8-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr9-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Climate anxiety represents a growing mental health crisis among young people: climate-related events are associated with posttraumatic stress, sleep disruption, depression, and anxiety.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup> These disastrous events also can disrupt caregiving and family functioning as stressors such as loss of financial, food, and housing resources can wear on familial relationships and connectivity.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup></p><p>Despite growing recognition of climate anxiety as a public health concern, 4 critical gaps persist in the literature. First, research has focused predominantly on adult populations in non-clinical settings (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/00469580251411470" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Table 1</ext-link>).<sup>
<xref rid="bibr11-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
</sup> Second, there is no widely validated youth-focused instrument for measuring climate anxiety, though the adult CCAS has been recently applied to adolescent samples.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr5-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
</sup> Third, the familial transmission of climate anxiety remains unexplored, with few studies investigating the interaction between parental climate perspectives and those of the adolescent child.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bibr13-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Fourth, the role of socioeconomic and community resources – such as housing quality, food security, access to public services – in shaping youth climate anxiety has not been systematically investigated, although youth in underserved, low-resource communities are particularly susceptible to climate anxiety.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr14-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</sup></p><p>The primary objective of this clinical study was to identify factors affecting climate anxiety in adolescent patients and adult caregivers. The secondary objective was to characterize caregivers’ community-level concerns and their association with climate anxiety (as measured on the CCAS) in both adolescents and caregivers. A familial dyad-based approach is expected to provide insight on intra- and interpersonal, as well as community level factors contributing to climate anxiety.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section2-00469580251411470"><title>Methods</title><sec id="section3-00469580251411470"><title>Study Design</title><p>This study utilized a cross-sectional design in a single emergency department (ED) of a free-standing pediatric hospital in Southern California. Adolescents ages 12 to 17 years of age who presented to the ED with medical and mental health chief complaints from January 8, 2024 to December 11, 2024 and were accompanied by an adult caregiver were included. Patients with an Emergency Severity Index (ESI) of 1 (most severe, acute medical or trauma presenting complaint) or on a 72-h involuntary psychiatric hold (eg, 5585 hold) were excluded. A team of 32 trained study personnel completed an IRB-approved verbal consent procedure after sharing a study information sheet with adolescent patient participants and their adult caregiver, collecting data on REDCap (Research Electronic Data Capture) via digital tablet.</p><p>We utilized a convenience sampling approach between the hours of 8am and 10pm, 6 days a week, during 12 contiguous months and no monetary compensation was offered. The surveys are described in the following sub-section. Surveys were available in English and Spanish for caregivers, with the Spanish surveys prepared through a certified Spanish translator. Data collectors were immediately alerted via a REDCap response if participants indicated an acute mental health concern such as suicidal ideation. A protocol was in place for the study investigator to alert a clinician to determine if a social worker intervention was needed. The Institutional Review Board approved all study activity (#230104).</p></sec><sec id="section4-00469580251411470"><title>Measures</title><sec id="section5-00469580251411470"><title>Climate Anxiety</title><p>Both adolescent and caregiver participants completed the CCAS, a 13-item, five-point Likert-scale-based measurement of emotional and behavioral response to climate change, validated in adults (<xref rid="app1-00469580251411470" ref-type="app">Appendix 1</xref>).<sup><xref rid="bibr15-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bibr16-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> The CCAS score is a measure of cognitive-emotional and functional impairment. The instrument was recently introduced in 2020; although it was not developed specifically for children, the CCAS has been implemented in youth under 18 years of age<sup><xref rid="bibr6-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<xref rid="bibr7-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr8-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr9-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> and a shorthand youth version internally validated<sup>
<xref rid="bibr5-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
</sup> – therefore, we utilized the CCAS among both our adult and pediatric samples in this study. In collaboration with the original scale developer (SC), wording of select items on the CCAS underwent minor adaptation – for example, simplifying the words “analyze” (item 7), “sustainability” (item 10), and “undermine” (item 12) in the original scale – to be implemented in readers as young as 12 years.</p><p>Internal consistency of all scale items was high in our sample (α = .92). We utilized established clinical thresholds and optimal Youden’s index with severe generalized anxiety (GAD-7 score ≥ 15) to categorize total CCAS scores (13-65) into 4 levels: minimal (≤18), mild (19-22), moderate (23-32), and severe (≥33).<sup>
<xref rid="bibr17-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
</sup> Only complete CCAS survey data from adolescent-caregiver dyads were included; of 788 adolescents who completed the CCAS, 557 had a corresponding caregiver survey. A Spanish adaptation of the CCAS was recently validated in a Spanish population sample with high psychometric adequacy, Cronbach’s alpha coefficient, α = .87.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr18-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
</sup></p></sec><sec id="section6-00469580251411470"><title>Generalized Anxiety</title><p>Both adolescent and caregiver participants completed the general anxiety disorder-7 (GAD-7), a widely implemented 7-item measure validated in general<sup><xref rid="bibr19-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="bibr20-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and pediatric populations<sup>
<xref rid="bibr21-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
</sup> (<xref rid="app2-00469580251411470" ref-type="app">Appendix 2</xref>). It is scored on a four-point Likert scale (maximum summative score = 21) with 4 levels of severity: not detected (&lt;5), mild (5-9), moderate (10-14), and severe (≥15). Our sample yielded high internal consistency (α = .918).</p></sec><sec id="section7-00469580251411470"><title>Domestic and Global Issues</title><p>Only the caregiver participants completed the Washington Post-Kaiser Family Foundation Poll, an assessment of the perception of 8 common public policy domains<sup>
<xref rid="bibr22-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
</sup> (<xref rid="app3-00469580251411470" ref-type="app">Appendix 3</xref>). This measure was integrated to gage the perceived importance of climate change relative to other domestic and global issues. In the public poll, each item is tallied on a four-point Likert scale with an additional “No opinion” option. Among responses, we used a dichotomous variable to capture perceived importance (“very important” or “extremely important) or ambivalence (“somewhat important,” “not important,” or “no opinion”) of a given domain.</p></sec><sec id="section8-00469580251411470"><title>Community-Level Concerns</title><p>Only the caregiver participants completed an adapted version of the Alameda County Environmental Justice Community Survey, an assessment of 5 community-level domains: housing, public facilities, health and physical activity, access to healthy food, and pollution<sup>
<xref rid="bibr23-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
</sup> (<xref rid="app4-00469580251411470" ref-type="app">Appendix 4</xref>). We integrated this measure not just in recognition of climate change as a social driver of health (SDOH),<sup>
<xref rid="bibr24-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
</sup> but also to gather contextual data of social and political forces that determine differential exposure to environmental harm and adversity among populations. Each item contains a variable amount of responses, and participants may select as many as apply to them.</p></sec><sec id="section9-00469580251411470"><title>Demographic Information</title><p>Demographic data was self-reported by the adult caregiver of the adolescent patient seen in the ED. Data – including patient gender, race and ethnicity, and insurance payor type (public or private) – was retrospectively extracted from the electronic medical record. Health insurance coverage type was used as a proxy for household income status.<sup><xref rid="bibr25-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="bibr26-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Categorization of the social construct of race and ethnicity (Hispanic, non-Hispanic) was based on the Office of Management and Budget Standards.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr27-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
</sup> Multi-racial participants selected “Other” racial category, and missing racial data was categorized as “unknown.” Presenting chief complaints of the adolescent patient in our ED were categorized as medical, mental health, or psychosomatic. We defined the latter category as physical symptoms without an underlying medical condition or pathology identified on physical, laboratory, and/or imaging examinations and each patient case was reviewed by a pediatric emergency medicine physician (RRA) to determine appropriate category.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section10-00469580251411470"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Patient and caregiver characteristics were described in terms of counts and percentages with defined trait or mean (SD) for continuous variables. Climate change anxiety severity, categorized as: not detected, mild, and moderate–severe was described for adolescents and caregivers overall and across characteristics. The Stuart-Maxwell test compared CCAS distributions between roles (adolescents and caregivers) within each factor level, and Chi-square tests compared CCAS distributions across factors within each role.</p><p>We conducted mixed effects logistic regression to identify predictors of moderate-severe CCAS and to assess whether associations differed by role. The modeling procedure considered main effects for demographic and SDOH variables, as well as 2-way interaction terms with role. A random intercept was included to account for clustering within dyad. Terms included in the final model were selected based on a stepwise approach, in which variables were entered in order of significance from univariate analyses, and both main and interaction terms were retained if statistically significant at the .05 level. Forest plots were constructed using the <italic toggle="yes">ggplot2</italic> package in <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> (version 4.4.2), based on model estimates generated with the <italic toggle="yes">lme4</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">broom.mixed</italic> packages, to display adjusted odds ratios (ORs) and their 95% confidence intervals for fixed effects retained in the final model. ICC assessing agreement in CCAS score between adolescent and caregiver within each dyad was estimated using the <italic toggle="yes">performance</italic> package with weighted kappa reported on categorical scale. Descriptive statistics and univariate comparisons were performed using SPSS Statistics, version 29.0 (IBM Corp).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section11-00469580251411470"><title>Results</title><p>Characteristics of the 557 adolescent patient-adult caregiver dyads are summarized in <xref rid="table1-00469580251411470" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The adolescent sample was racially and ethnically diverse, the majority of which presented with medical chief complaints (80.3%) and with public health insurance (59.8%). Detected levels of generalized anxiety among both adolescent and caregiver groups were widely distributed, ranging from not detected, mild, and moderate-severe. A total of 36 caregivers (6.5%) completed surveys in Spanish.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-00469580251411470" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Description of the Family Dyads (Adolescent Patient and Adult Caregiver), n = 557.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_00469580251411470-table1.jpg"><?image-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table1.jpg?><?image-size 222931?><?image-md5 1024057829a5fb58b5ed94585c70c4f1?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2747?><?image-original-width 1058?><?image-scaled-height 1830?><?image-scaled-width 705?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/1024057829a5/10.1177_00469580251411470-table1.jpg?><?thumb-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table1.gif?><?thumb-size 12938?><?thumb-md5 be1970fcbf46be4f8aa844e4e2c598b0?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 260?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/be1970fcbf46/10.1177_00469580251411470-table1.gif?></graphic><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescent characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N = 557</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age, years</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 12-13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176 (31.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 14-15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187 (33.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 16-17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">194 (34.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">307 (55.1%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Ethnicity, race</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic, non-white</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152 (27.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic, white</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (35.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic, non-white</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (15.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic, white</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119 (21.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.7%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Insurance</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Public</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (59.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Private</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217 (39.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1.3%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Chief complaint during ED visit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Medical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">447 (80.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mental health</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (2.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Psychosomatic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98 (17.6%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Season of ED visit</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cool (Nov-Apr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">281 (50.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Warm (May-Oct)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">276 (49.6%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">GAD-7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;5 (not detected)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">257 (46.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5-9 (mild)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (24.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥10 (mod-severe)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (25.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (4.7%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">CCAS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;18 (not detected)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">405 (72.7%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 19-22 (mild)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (10.1%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;23 (mod-severe)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (17.2%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Caregiver characteristics</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">#Household integrants<sup>
<xref rid="table-fn2-00469580251411470" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>
</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 (SD = 1.5)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Education</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Some high school (HS)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (10.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HS diploma or equivalent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (17.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Vocational/some college/AA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">168 (30.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bachelor’s degree or higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (28.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (13.6%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">GAD-7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;5 (not detected)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (59.8%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5-9 (mild)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (21.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥10 (mod-severe)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (13.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (5.9%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">CCAS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;18 (not detected)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">417 (74.9%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 19-22 (mild)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (8.6%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &gt;23 (mod-severe)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (16.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-00469580251411470"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> In 307 parents who responded to sex question: 80.5% identified as female.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn2-00469580251411470"><label>a</label><p>Missing (n = 60).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A comparison of adolescent and caregiver CCAS score (not detected, mild, moderate-severe) by respondent characteristics via univariate analysis is presented in <xref rid="table2-00469580251411470" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Overall, the distribution of climate anxiety (not detected, mild, moderate-severe) was not significantly different between the adolescents and caregivers. Interestingly, we observed low within-dyad agreement in climate anxiety score on both a continuous scale (ICC = 0.224: 95% CI 0.142, 0.274), and on 3-point scale (weighted kappa (quadratic weights) = .249: 95% CI 0.158, 0.339). Notable demographic differences in CCAS among adolescents included higher rates of moderate-severe climate anxiety in females (21.2%) compared to males (12.4%), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .014, and in those with public health insurance (21.0%) compared to private (11.1%), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .009. Generalized anxiety in adolescents was strongly associated with their level of climate anxiety (proportion of moderate-severe climate anxiety in those with moderate-severe generalized anxiety vs no generalized anxiety (32.4% vs 7.4%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001); this was also observed among caregivers (32.4% vs 9.3%, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table2-00469580251411470" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Comparison of Adolescent and Caregiver CCAS Overall and by Respondent Characteristics (Univariate Analyses).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_00469580251411470-table2.jpg"><?image-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table2.jpg?><?image-size 101504?><?image-md5 7ac32d61f4501be162b482bd9abb9bad?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 2089?><?image-original-width 2809?><?image-scaled-height 522?><?image-scaled-width 702?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/7ac32d61f450/10.1177_00469580251411470-table2.jpg?><?thumb-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table2.gif?><?thumb-size 10948?><?thumb-md5 2462cbc494f7a54ea19c697fbca05772?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 107?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/2462cbc494f7/10.1177_00469580251411470-table2.gif?></graphic><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Row %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Adolescents (A) – CCAS</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Caregivers (C) – CCAS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not detected (≤18)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (19-22)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mod-severe (≥23)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not detected (≤18)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (19-22)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mod-severe (≥23)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-val<xref rid="table-fn4-00469580251411470" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">557</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.622</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adolescent characteristics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .701, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .863)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 12-13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.936</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 14-15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.156</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 16-17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.923</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex, female <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .014, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .892)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">307</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.080</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.361</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethnicity, race <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .093, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> =.483)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic, non-white</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.752</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hispanic, white</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.469</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic, non-white</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.700</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Non-Hispanic, white</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.846</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insurance <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .009, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .163)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Public</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.469</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Private</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.779</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chief complaint <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .435, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .132)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Medical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">447</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.916</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Mental health</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.135</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Psychosomatic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.135</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Season <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .135, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .215)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Cool (Nov-Apr)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">281</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.661</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Warm (May-Oct)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">276</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.588</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAD-7 adolesc. <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .066)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;5 (not detected)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>.041</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5-9 (mild)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.953</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥10 (mod-severe)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>.012</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caregiver characteristics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"># Household <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .268, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .558)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≤3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.232</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 4-5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.243</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.779</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .356, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .918)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Some high school (HS)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HS diploma or equivalent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.156</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Vocational/some college</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.445</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Bachelor’s degree or higher</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.988</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Prefer not to answer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.321</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAD-7 caregiver <sup>(A P = .022, C P &lt; .001)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;5 (not detected)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.104</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 5-9 (mild)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.253</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥10 (mod-severe)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.247</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn3-00469580251411470"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> Superscript <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value next to variable name in first column was based on Chi-square test and assessed difference in CCAS level across factor levels within each role: <sup>A</sup> (adolescents), <sup>C</sup> (caregivers).</p></fn><fn id="table-fn4-00469580251411470"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value in far right column was based on Stuart-Maxwell test and assessed distributional difference in response within stratum comparing adolescents to their caregiver’s response. The bold values indicates <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The domestic and global issues poll (Washington Post-Kaiser Family Foundation Poll) results are presented in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/00469580251411470" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Table 2</ext-link>. Caregivers who rated climate change as important (n = 220 of 505 respondents) tended to have higher levels of moderate-severe CCA (compare 25.9% vs 7.7% among those who were ambivalent to climate change, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). Though not statistically significant, children of caregivers who believe climate change is important also demonstrated relatively higher reported climate anxiety compared to children whose caregivers were ambivalent to climate change (19.1% vs 15.4% moderate-severe climate anxiety). Additionally, caregivers who rated affordable education, renewable energy, and immigration as important also reported significantly higher levels of moderate-severe climate anxiety compared to caregivers who felt ambivalent about these subjects (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05).</p><p>Caregivers’ community-level concerns (Alameda County Environmental Justice Community Survey) are presented in <xref rid="table3-00469580251411470" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. In caregivers with concerns (access to housing, public services, recreational exercise, and healthy food, as well as exposure to pollution), there was a statistically significant portion reporting moderate-severe climate anxiety (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). The adolescent children of these particular caregivers mirrored that trend, particularly among housing (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .027), public services (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .013), and pollution (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .019).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table3-00469580251411470" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Comparison of Adolescent and Caregiver CCAS Responses Overall and by Neighborhood Level Caregiver-Perceptions (Univariate Analyses) In Subset Who Answered Alameda County Environmental Justice Community Survey (n = 506).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_00469580251411470-table3.jpg"><?image-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table3.jpg?><?image-size 76249?><?image-md5 3ecafb64505f27ed7fa70276f048f022?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1447?><?image-original-width 2809?><?image-scaled-height 362?><?image-scaled-width 702?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/3ecafb64505f/10.1177_00469580251411470-table3.jpg?><?thumb-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table3.gif?><?thumb-size 11104?><?thumb-md5 4df8f8f1743d0000ae56b6d9cd66d945?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 155?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/4df8f8f1743d/10.1177_00469580251411470-table3.gif?></graphic><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Row %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Adolescents (A) – CCAS</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Caregivers (C) – CCAS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not detected (≤18)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (19-22)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mod-severe (≥23)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not detected (≤18)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild (19-22)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mod-severe (≥23)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-val<sup>
<xref rid="table-fn6-00469580251411470" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.412</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alameda County EJ Survey in caregivers:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. I do not have housing problems <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .027, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.231</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">335</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.379</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. I have access to the facilities and services I need <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> =.013, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.515</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.101</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. I bike, walk and exercise as much as I like <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .165, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.271</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">290</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>.039</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. I can access and afford healthy food <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .213, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.338</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>.023</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. I am not concerned with pollution problems in my community <sup>(A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .019, C <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001)</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">334</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.515</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.101</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn5-00469580251411470"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> Superscript <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value next to variable name in first column was based on Chi-square test and assessed difference in CCAS level across factor levels within each role: <sup>A</sup> (adolescents), <sup>C</sup> (caregivers). No – Did not check box “Does not apply” and checked boxes indicating reason(s) why they have problems/issues/concerns. Yes – Respondent checked box that indicated “Does not apply” with description listed in table.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn6-00469580251411470"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value in far right column was based on Stuart-Maxwell test and assessed distributional difference in response within stratum comparing adolescents to their caregiver’s response. The bold values indicates <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In adjusted analyses (<xref rid="fig1-00469580251411470" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/00469580251411470" ext-link-type="uri">Supplemental Table 3</ext-link>), moderate-severe generalized anxiety was the strongest predictor of moderate-severe climate anxiety in both adolescents and caregivers (OR<sub>adj</sub> 6.59, 95% CI 3.52-12.3, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). Limited access to public services continued to be associated with moderate-severe CCAS (ORadj = 2.63 (95% CI 1.59, 4.35), <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001). Caregivers viewing climate change as very important had higher odds of moderate-severe CCAS (OR<sub>adj</sub> = 4.50 [95% CI 2.03, 9.98], <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001); however, their perception on this issue had no significant effect on adolescent CCAS (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .172).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1-00469580251411470" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Predictors of moderate-to-severe climate change anxiety (CCAS ≥23) and role-specific associations (adolescents vs. caregivers), adjusted for significant predictors and role interactions in the final model as shown in forest plot.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_00469580251411470-fig1.jpg"><?image-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-fig1.jpg?><?image-size 107189?><?image-md5 68752ebb6b478aeb3b8d204a89a3725f?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1645?><?image-original-width 1812?><?image-scaled-height 657?><?image-scaled-width 724?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/68752ebb6b47/10.1177_00469580251411470-fig1.jpg?><?thumb-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-fig1.gif?><?thumb-size 15458?><?thumb-md5 825f210eee623d2826737807fe0ed826?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 91?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/825f210eee62/10.1177_00469580251411470-fig1.gif?></graphic></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section12-00469580251411470"><title>Discussion</title><p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to examine climate anxiety in adolescent-caregiver dyads within a clinical setting and to integrate perspectives on environmental and community-level issues. Our findings extend the predominantly adult-focused, non-clinical climate anxiety literature in important ways.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr28-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
<xref rid="bibr29-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr30-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr31-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr32-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> We found that generalized anxiety was a strong predictor of climate anxiety among both adult caregivers and adolescent patients as measured on the CCAS. However, neither caregiver CCAS score nor their perspectives on domestic and global issues – including climate change – were associated with adolescent CCAS score. Rather, public health insurance (as a proxy of household income) and caregiver concerns about neighborhood factors – particularly access to public services – were associated with adolescent CCAS. Our findings expand understanding of adolescents’ unique psychological, emotional, and social vulnerabilities to climate-related stressors, suggesting that climate-related distress is impacted by socioeconomic disparity and existing generalized anxiety, and less so by familial perspective on climate change.</p><p>The strong association between generalized anxiety and climate anxiety observed in this clinical sample of adolescent patients and adult caregivers points toward the various interactions and manifestations of anxiety in the 2 age groups. Climate anxiety can be a manifestation or specific subtype of generalized anxiety, while generalized anxiety may also increase vulnerability to climate-specific distress.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr17-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bibr29-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="bibr33-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> Further, climate anxiety is a psychological stressor that may lead to cognitive-emotional and functional impairment while negatively impacting existing mood disorders and overall well-being, as seen in both adult<sup><xref rid="bibr2-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr15-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bibr29-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="bibr33-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
<xref rid="bibr34-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr35-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> and youth literature.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
<xref rid="bibr6-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr7-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr8-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr9-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> Longitudinal research is needed to disentangle these pathways. There may be an <italic toggle="yes">indirect</italic> relationship between caregiver generalized anxiety and adolescent climate anxiety, since familial interactions influence youth development of anxiety disorders. In fact, a meta-analysis of anxiety disorders found that offspring of adults with generalized anxiety are at a 2.54-fold risk for any anxiety disorder.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr36-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
</sup> Additionally, climate anxiety may indirectly influence child development by disrupting family relationships and functioning, with increases in family conflict and anxious parenting reported in the literature.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup></p><p>Between 38.3% and 45% of youth describe climate anxiety as a daily challenge impacting their functioning, which has implications on adolescent resilience and long-term mental health trajectories.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Climate anxiety is known to trigger poor sleep, appetite, and concentration,<sup><xref rid="bibr37-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="bibr38-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> as well as developmental regression, such as showing less independence in daily routine and episodes of acting out behaviorally.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr37-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
</sup> Generalized anxiety appears to be just one underlying vulnerability in children – who are inherently dependent on their caregivers – and is likely exacerbated by climate-related stressors.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr39-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
</sup></p><p>A lack of correlation between adult caregiver perspective on domestic/global issues and CCAS score with the adolescent patient CCAS score challenges the existing theoretical framework of social learning, which presumes that youth observe and imitate their caregiver’s belief system.<sup><xref rid="bibr28-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="bibr40-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bibr41-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> The results observed in our study can be explained by several developmental and contextual factors. First, adolescents have a unique combination of developmental growth, socialization, and education.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bibr14-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> According to family systems theory, adolescents may demonstrate emotional differentiation by unconsciously avoiding matching parental anxiety patterns<sup>
<xref rid="bibr42-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
</sup> – this is likely reinforced by a lack of role modeling among adult caregivers and authority figures on the urgency of climate change.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr37-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
</sup> Second, adolescent psychosocial well-being may be more influenced by the opinions of their peers and social media news sources<sup>
<xref rid="bibr9-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</sup> than their caregivers – a form of social reference group effect – although we did not investigate peer influence in this clinical study.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr43-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>
</sup> Third, the absence of visible parental action on climate change, despite expressed concern, may lead adolescents to discount parental anxiety as performative rather than genuine. A unique psycho-developmental pathway driving generational incongruency around climate perspectives is becoming evident in literature documenting a predominant sense of “betrayal” that climate anxious youth feel regarding their parents’ generation,<sup><xref rid="bibr2-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> while aligning themselves with peer-driven eco-advocacy.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> While caregiver climate anxiety itself did not directly predict adolescent climate anxiety in our study, caregiver concerns about community resource and SDOH did emerge as significant predictors, suggesting an indirect transmission pathway.</p><p>Specifically, adult caregiver concerns about access to public services, along with economic disadvantage (public health insurance) were associated with adolescent CCAS in adjusted analyses, while concerns of housing and pollution were significant in univariate analyses. Climate change is a ubiquitous SDOH given its negative health impact on vulnerable communities and exacerbation of other existing SDOH that disproportionately impact under-resourced communities facing challenges in food/housing insecurity, transportation, and social support.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="bibr44-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> Examples of how climate may compound existing SDOH include poor housing quality (lack of insulation and increased penetrance of outdoor pollutants), difficulty paying energy bills,<sup>
<xref rid="bibr45-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
</sup> and decreased ability to evacuate during extreme weather-related events,<sup>
<xref rid="bibr46-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>
</sup> all of which may be sources of distress and negatively impact resiliency of children and their families. Following climate-related events, lower-income adult caregivers may suffer psychological distress through a strain on financial resources with downstream deterioration of family functioning.<sup>
<xref rid="bibr10-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
</sup> A combination of less socioeconomic advantage and the emotional-cognitive functional burden of climate anxiety<sup><xref rid="bibr2-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr14-00469580251411470" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> may serve as a double hit to adolescent resiliency and limit opportunity for growth and academic success.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section13-00469580251411470"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our findings address a research gap in further characterizing climate change-derived stressors through a caregiver-child dyad lens. We propose a distinct theoretical pathway: emotional responses to climate change (measured by the CCAS) do not transmit directly from caregiver to child, but environmental values and concerns do. Adult caregiver practical concerns may have influenced adolescent climate anxiety scores through an indirect transmission pathway in which caregivers guide adolescent attention – consciously or subconsciously – toward particular environmental and community-level issues, without necessarily modeling specific anxiety responses. Adolescents may internalize parental values and concerns about community and environmental issues and go on to develop their own anxiety response based on their own cognitive appraisal and emotional regulation patterns.</p><p>In the developing field of youth climate anxiety, we advocate that mental health practitioners integrate demographic and community-level data to identify adolescent patients most vulnerable to climate change-derived stressors. Our data points toward socioeconomic disadvantage and existing generalized anxiety as 2 underlying predictors of climate anxiety. As screening for climate anxiety in adolescents is still in its infancy, we encourage greater collaboration between pediatric psychological and medical societies to develop policy and practice guidelines in rollout of adolescent climate anxiety screening alongside routine mental health assessments. Wider, external validation of a youth-specific climate or eco-anxiety tool is instrumental in this effort, including in the general pediatric clinical setting. Researchers and educators should recognize that, similar to other social drivers of health, climate change burdens low-resource communities disproportionately and should continue to identify community level features that play a role in youth climate anxiety, such as housing quality and access to fresh food. Targeting subgroups with inequitable drivers of climate anxiety should guide resource allocation and interventions.</p><p>This study is limited by a cross-sectional design in which reported findings are limited to associations rather than casual relationships. Generalizability is limited by convenience sampling data collection in a single clinical site rather than community setting, with climate and weather patterns typical to Southern California compared to other regional settings which may experience different climatic and weather events. Due to the exploratory nature of this child-caregiver dyad study in the pediatric ED, we did not calculate a precise sample size, but rather, collected data for 12 consecutive months to control for possible seasonal variability effect on climate anxiety outlook. Those with the most severe medical conditions (ESI 1) and on involuntary psychiatric holds were excluded per the IRB protocol. Demographically, the study sample was diverse and included both Spanish- and English-speaking caregivers. The adapted CCAS that we implemented among adolescents and adults for ease of readability has not been validated, and more generally, the CCAS itself has not been widely validated in children. There was limited assessment of potential confounders, such as amount and type of news consumption, as well as family communication. Collected SDOH variables were also limited and not comprehensive (eg, immigration and employment status, income) and we collected data on concerns related to community and environmental exposures, rather than the objective exposure.</p><p>Further analyses should explore additional socioeconomic factors that shape youth climate anxiety. It would be beneficial to conduct studies in the general pediatric office setting, where routine mental health assessments are performed. Also needed in the literature are studies on the impact of peer relationships on youth climate anxiety.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="section14-00469580251411470" specific-use="figshare"><title>Supplemental Material</title><supplementary-material id="suppl1-00469580251411470" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-1-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470 – Supplemental material for An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-1-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name sj-docx-1-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx?><?suppdata-size 16874?><?suppdata-md5 3546e716f0a44d10a6a774b4ff92e32a?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:c22f/12789392/3546e716f0a4/sj-docx-1-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx?></media><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-1-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470 for An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department by Raymen R. Assaf, Shelby K. Shelton, Tricia Morphew, Susan Clayton and Jun Wu in INQUIRY: The Journal of Health Care Organization, Provision, and Financing</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="suppl2-00469580251411470" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-2-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470 – Supplemental material for An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-2-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name sj-docx-2-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx?><?suppdata-size 20428?><?suppdata-md5 0fd1231a749f9e9b36c449314af4f03f?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:c22f/12789392/0fd1231a749f/sj-docx-2-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx?></media><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-2-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470 for An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department by Raymen R. Assaf, Shelby K. Shelton, Tricia Morphew, Susan Clayton and Jun Wu in INQUIRY: The Journal of Health Care Organization, Provision, and Financing</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="suppl3-00469580251411470" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-3-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470 – Supplemental material for An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-3-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name sj-docx-3-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx?><?suppdata-size 16670?><?suppdata-md5 446b7adcaa717d95028ff951386d4508?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:c22f/12789392/446b7adcaa71/sj-docx-3-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx?></media><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-3-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470 for An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department by Raymen R. Assaf, Shelby K. Shelton, Tricia Morphew, Susan Clayton and Jun Wu in INQUIRY: The Journal of Health Care Organization, Provision, and Financing</p></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="suppl4-00469580251411470" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>sj-docx-4-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470 – Supplemental material for An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sj-docx-4-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><?suppdata-name sj-docx-4-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx?><?suppdata-size 33312?><?suppdata-md5 0bc74cb6a3ed841926e38e2094f8430b?><?suppdata-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?suppdata-mime-type application?><?suppdata-mime-sub-type vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document?><?suppdata-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:c22f/12789392/0bc74cb6a3ed/sj-docx-4-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470.docx?></media><p>Supplemental material, sj-docx-4-inq-10.1177_00469580251411470 for An Adolescent-Caregiver Dyad Approach to Climate Anxiety in the Pediatric Emergency Department by Raymen R. Assaf, Shelby K. Shelton, Tricia Morphew, Susan Clayton and Jun Wu in INQUIRY: The Journal of Health Care Organization, Provision, and Financing</p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>Carolina Amaya, Kellie Bacon, Selena Nguyen, Phat Nguyen, Parisha Babuta, Vanessa Ngo, Myra Thai, Raymond Nguyen, Shelly Yu, David Vu, Kyle Tran, Shadawn Henderson, Khang Bui, Leone Manaloto, Ngoc-Han Nguyen, Axs Avenido, Shannon Phan, Mikel Concepcion, Brian Alba, Gabrielle Norris, Mason Do, Zoe Ta-Perez, Dishita Arora, Christine Huynh, John Francisco, Mai-Vy Tran, Saba Firouzabadi, Shazabe Siddique, Aisha Ahmad, Haneen Allahaleh, Grace Yip, Karen Sarabia.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Raymen R. Assaf <inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="10.1177_00469580251411470-img1.jpg"><?image-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-img1.jpg?><?image-size 9522?><?image-md5 4223d99d1c781bb9990bc09e09f6400b?><?image-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/4223d99d1c78/10.1177_00469580251411470-img1.jpg?></inline-graphic>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4326-0059" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4326-0059</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethical Considerations:</bold> All research activity was approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB, #230104).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Consent to Participate:</bold> Informed consent was verbal only; formal consent was waived by the IRB based on risk/benefit ratio and project design wherein risks have been minimized.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr. Raymen Assaf conceptualized and designed the study, contributed substantially to interpretation of data, drafted the initial manuscript, and critically reviewed and revised the manuscript for important intellectual content.</p><p>Shelby Shelton contributed to study design, directed and supervised data collection, contributed substantially to data interpretation, and critically revised the manuscript.</p><p>Tricia Morphew led modeling for acquisition of data, data analysis, and interpretation, drafted portions of the manuscript, and critically reviewed and revised the manuscript.</p><p>Drs. Susan Clayton and Jun contributed substantially to study conceptualization, analysis and interpretation of the data and critically reviewed and revised the manuscript for important intellectual content.</p><p>All authors approved the final manuscript as submitted and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Data Availability Statement:</bold> The authors abide by the journal’s data sharing policy. Data is available and shared upon approved request.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p><bold>Supplemental Material:</bold> Supplemental material for this article is available online.</p></fn></fn-group><app-group><app id="app1-00469580251411470"><title>Appendix 1</title><sec id="section18-00469580251411470"><title>Adapted Climate Change Anxiety Scale</title><p>Please rate how often the following statements are true of you.</p><p>  1    2     3     4    5</p><p> Never  Rarely  Sometimes  Often  Almost always</p><list list-type="order" id="list1-00469580251411470"><list-item><p>Thinking about climate change makes it difficult for me to concentrate.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Thinking about climate change makes it difficult for me to sleep.</p></list-item><list-item><p>I have nightmares about climate change.</p></list-item><list-item><p>I find myself crying because of climate change.</p></list-item><list-item><p>I think, “why can’t I handle climate change better?”</p></list-item><list-item><p>I go away by myself and think about why I feel this way about climate change.</p></list-item><list-item><p>I write down my thoughts about climate change and think about them deeply.</p></list-item><list-item><p>I think, “why do I react to climate change this way?”</p></list-item><list-item><p>My concerns about climate change make it hard for me to have fun with my family or friends.</p></list-item><list-item><p>I have problems balancing my concerns about the planet with the needs of my family.</p></list-item><list-item><p>My concerns about climate change get in the way of my ability to get work or school assignments done.</p></list-item><list-item><p>My concerns about climate change keep me from working at my best level.</p></list-item><list-item><p>My friends say I think about climate change too much.</p></list-item></list><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note. Items 1 to 8 form the cognitive impairment subscale; items 9 to 13 are the functional impairment subscale.</italic>
</p></sec></app><app id="app2-00469580251411470"><title>Appendix 2</title><table-wrap position="anchor" id="table4-00469580251411470" orientation="portrait"><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_00469580251411470-table4.jpg"><?image-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table4.jpg?><?image-size 41338?><?image-md5 a208ad93c5e628a64fd321d093bb13d7?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 836?><?image-original-width 2138?><?image-scaled-height 278?><?image-scaled-width 712?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/a208ad93c5e6/10.1177_00469580251411470-table4.jpg?><?thumb-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table4.gif?><?thumb-size 8751?><?thumb-md5 f12131c8814aa3f11e36eb5b8e8de01b?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 78?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/f12131c8814a/10.1177_00469580251411470-table4.gif?></graphic><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Over the <underline>last 2 weeks</underline>, how often have you been bothered by the following problems?</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not at all</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Several days</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">More than half the days</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nearly every day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeling nervous, anxious, or on edge</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not being able to stop or control worrying</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worrying too much about different things</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trouble relaxing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Being so restless that it is hard to sit still</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Becoming easily annoyed or irritable</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeling afraid, as if something awful might happen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Column totals:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn7-00469580251411470"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note.</italic> Total score: _________</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></app><app id="app3-00469580251411470"><title>Appendix 3</title><sec id="section19-00469580251411470"><title>Washington Post-Kaiser Family Foundation Poll</title><table-wrap position="anchor" id="table5-00469580251411470" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>How Important Are the Following Issues to You Personally?</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="10.1177_00469580251411470-table5.jpg"><?image-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table5.jpg?><?image-size 28819?><?image-md5 648b9d36fe6fe444f1817c32c66f319f?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 730?><?image-original-width 2139?><?image-scaled-height 243?><?image-scaled-width 713?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/648b9d36fe6f/10.1177_00469580251411470-table5.jpg?><?thumb-name 10.1177_00469580251411470-table5.gif?><?thumb-size 7481?><?thumb-md5 ea7e12f32951763585a79c76f1ad3731?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 68?><?thumb-scaled-width 200?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/c22f/12789392/ea7e12f32951/10.1177_00469580251411470-table5.gif?></graphic><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extremely important</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very important</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Somewhat important</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not so important</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No opinion</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health care</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The economy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gun policy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Climate change</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immigration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renewable energy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Affordable education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">War and armed conflict</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec></app><app id="app4-00469580251411470"><title>Appendix 4</title><sec id="section20-00469580251411470"><title>Adapted Alameda County Environmental Justice Community Survey, 2022</title><list list-type="order" id="list2-00469580251411470"><list-item><p><underline>Housing</underline>: Do you have any problems with your housing? Please check all that apply:<list list-type="simple" id="list3-00469580251411470"><list-item><p>[] Does not apply. I do not have housing problems</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] My rent or mortgage is too expensive</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] My home or apartment is in bad condition</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] My home or apartment is too small or too crowded</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] It’s hard to communicate with my landlord</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] I am worried about losing my housing</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Other (please specify): <italic toggle="yes">free text</italic></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p><underline>Public Facilities</underline>: What do you need better access to or what needs improvement? Please check all that apply<list list-type="simple" id="list4-00469580251411470"><list-item><p>[] Does not apply. I have access to the facilities and services I need</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Parks, playgrounds, and green space</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Community gardens</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Sports and organized activities</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Exercise classes</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Libraries</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] After-school programs</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Community and recreation center</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Job training</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Bicycle Lanes</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Public transportation</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Lighting/Security cameras</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Other (please specify): <italic toggle="yes">free text</italic></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p><underline>Health and Physical Activity</underline>: Are you able to walk, bike and exercise as much as you would like? If not, what are some of the reasons? Please check all that apply<list list-type="simple" id="list5-00469580251411470"><list-item><p>[] Does not apply. I bike, walk and exercise as much as I like</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Not enough bike lanes</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Too scary to walk/bike because of traffic and speed of cars and trucks</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Bike paths are not connected</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Not enough sidewalks</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Too hot and not enough shade</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] I do not have a bike, or there are no places to get my bike fixed</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] I do not have a place nearby I can go to exercise (park, open space, etc.)</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] I don’t feel safe from crime when I exercise outside</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] I do not have time to exercise</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] I have physical disabilities that prevent me from exercising</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Other (please specify): <italic toggle="yes">free text</italic></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p><underline>Healthy Foods</underline>: Is it hard for you to get fresh fruits and vegetables and other healthy food? What are some of the reasons? The following statements were marked as a reason as to why it is hard to obtain fresh fruits/vegetables/other healthy food:<list list-type="simple" id="list6-00469580251411470"><list-item><p>[] Does not apply. I can access and afford healthy food</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Too expensive</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Healthy stores are too far</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] No garden space to grow my own</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] High-quality fruits/vegetables not available where I shop</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Hard to shop using public transportation</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Travel time</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Other (please specify): <italic toggle="yes">free text</italic></p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p><underline>Pollution</underline>. Which pollution problems are you most concerned about in your community? Please check all that apply.<list list-type="simple" id="list7-00469580251411470"><list-item><p>[] Does not apply. I am not concerned with pollution</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Air pollution from cars and trucks</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Air pollution from industrial land uses or other type of use</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Trash in public spaces or vacant lots</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Dumping of dangerous chemicals</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Water quality</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Lead paint where I live or work</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Noisy cars, trucks, or airplanes</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Graffiti</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Soil pollution from land uses (eg, gas stations, hazard sites, etc.)</p></list-item><list-item><p>[] Other (please specify): <italic toggle="yes">free text</italic></p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list></sec></app></app-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-00469580251411470"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>UCLA Center for the Developing Adolescent</collab>. <source>The opportunities and effects of climate action on adolescents</source>. <publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc>. Published April 28, 2025. <comment>Accessed October 18, 2025</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://developingadolescent.semel.ucla.edu/blog/item/the-opportunities-and-effects-of-climate-action-on-adolescents" ext-link-type="uri">https://developingadolescent.semel.ucla.edu/blog/item/the-opportunities-and-effects-of-climate-action-on-adolescents</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-00469580251411470"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Olbrich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Climate emotions, thoughts, and plans among US adolescents and young adults: a cross-sectional descriptive survey and analysis by political party identification and self-reported exposure to severe weather events</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):E879-E893.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(24)00229-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39427673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-00469580251411470"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ndugga</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Artiga</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Climate change and health equity: key questions and answers</article-title>. <publisher-name>KFF</publisher-name>. Published May 24, 2022. <comment>Accessed April 16, 2025</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.kff.org/racial-equity-and-health-policy/issue-brief/climate-change-and-health-equity-key-questions-and-answers/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.kff.org/racial-equity-and-health-policy/issue-brief/climate-change-and-health-equity-key-questions-and-answers/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-00469580251411470"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Climate Psychology Alliance</collab>. <source>The handbook of climate psychology</source>. <publisher-name>Climate Psychology Alliance</publisher-name>. Published August 29, 2022. <comment>Accessed August 15, 2025</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.climatepsychologyalliance.org/index.php/component/content/article/climate-psychology-handbook?catid=15&amp;Itemid=101" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.climatepsychologyalliance.org/index.php/component/content/article/climate-psychology-handbook?catid=15&amp;Itemid=101</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-00469580251411470"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hafez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Samji</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Development and validation of a youth climate anxiety scale for the youth development instrument survey</article-title>. <source>Int J Ment Health Nurs</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1473</fpage>-<lpage>1483</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37605318</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/inm.13201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-00469580251411470"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>MES</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carmen</surname><given-names>BPB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luminarias</surname><given-names>MEP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mangulabnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunbode</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An investigation into the relationship between climate change anxiety and mental health among gen Z Filipinos</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>7448</fpage>-<lpage>7456</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34305362</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12144-021-02099-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8280276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-00469580251411470"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Becht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Grapsas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Feeling anxious and being engaged in a warming world: climate anxiety and adolescents’ pro-environmental behavior</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1270</fpage>-<lpage>1282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38940197</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jcpp.14035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-00469580251411470"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The relationship between climate change anxiety and pro-environmental behavior in adolescents: the mediating role of future self-continuity and the moderating role of green self-efficacy</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>241</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38678287</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40359-024-01746-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11056057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-00469580251411470"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Benoit</surname><given-names>L, R.</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Amsalem</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Climate change hopefulness, anxiety, and behavioral intentions among adolescents: randomized controlled trial of a brief “selfie” video intervention</article-title>. <source>Child Adolesc Psychiatry Ment Health</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39987228</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13034-025-00872-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11847372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-00469580251411470"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Proulx</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Daelmans</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baltag</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Banati</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Climate change impacts on child and adolescent health and well-being: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>J Global Health</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>04061</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7189/jogh.14.04061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11115477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38781568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-00469580251411470"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pihkala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Climate anxiety in children and young people and their beliefs about government responses to climate change: a global survey</article-title>. <source>Lancet Planet Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):e863-e873.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(21)00278-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34895496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-00469580251411470"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meherali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nisa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Aynalem</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Impact of climate change on adolescents’ health outcomes: an evidence gap map review</article-title>. <source>J Adolesc</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>-<lpage>619</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39726081</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jad.12455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11973863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-00469580251411470"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Power</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malhi</surname><given-names>NK.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Growing up amid climate change: impact on children’s mental health</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Online</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>59</volume>. Published <month>June</month>
<day>18</day>, <year>2024</year>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.pn.2024.07.7.37</pub-id>. <comment>Accessed October 18, 2025</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-00469580251411470"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Léger-Goodes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Malboeuf-Hurtubise</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mastine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Généreux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Camden</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Eco-anxiety in children: a scoping review of the mental health impacts of the awareness of climate change</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>872544</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35959069</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyg.2022.872544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9359205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-00469580251411470"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karazsia</surname><given-names>BT.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Development and validation of a measure of climate change anxiety</article-title>. <source>J Environ Psychol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>101434</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-00469580251411470"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wullenkord</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tröger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamann</surname><given-names>KRS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Loy</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Anxiety and climate change: a validation of the climate anxiety scale in a German-speaking quota sample and an investigation of psychological correlates</article-title>. <source>Clim Change</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>3-4</issue>):<fpage>20</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-00469580251411470"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cosh</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lykins</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bartik</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>PJ.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Detecting and classifying eco-anxiety: development of clinical cut-off scores for the climate change anxiety scale</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>738</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39696553</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40359-024-02240-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11657576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-00469580251411470"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro-Carrillo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Marin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moya-Garofano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Psychometric evaluation of the Spanish adaptation of the Climate change anxiety scale</article-title>. <source>PsyEcology</source>. <year>2025</year>. <comment>Accessed August 14, 2025</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/385972255_Psychometric_Evaluation_of_the_Spanish_Adaptation_of_the_Climate_Change_Anxiety_Scale" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/385972255_Psychometric_Evaluation_of_the_Spanish_Adaptation_of_the_Climate_Change_Anxiety_Scale</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-00469580251411470"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kroenke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Löwe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A brief measure for assessing generalized anxiety disorder: the GAD-7</article-title>. <source>Arch Intern Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1092</fpage>-<lpage>1097</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16717171</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/archinte.166.10.1092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-00469580251411470"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Löwe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Validation and standardization of the Generalized Anxiety Disorder Screener (GAD-7) in the general population</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>266</fpage>-<lpage>274</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18388841</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MLR.0b013e318160d093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-00469580251411470"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Casares</surname><given-names>MÁ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Díez-Gómez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez-Albéniz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas-Molina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fonseca-Pedrero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Screening for anxiety in adolescents: validation of the generalized anxiety disorder assessment-7 in a representative sample of adolescents</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>354</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>331</fpage>-<lpage>338</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38490592</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jad.2024.03.047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-00469580251411470"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>The Washington Post</collab>. <article-title>Washington post-Kaiser family foundation climate change survey, July 9-August 5, 2019</article-title>. Climate and Environment. Updated <month>December</month>
<day>9</day>, <year>2019</year>. <comment>Accessed September 9, 2023</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/context/washington-post-kaiser-family-foundation-climate-change-survey-july-9-aug-5-2019/601ed8ff-a7c6-4839-b57e-3f5eaa8ed09f/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.washingtonpost.com/context/washington-post-kaiser-family-foundation-climate-change-survey-july-9-aug-5-2019/601ed8ff-a7c6-4839-b57e-3f5eaa8ed09f/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-00469580251411470"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>Alameda County Community Development Agency</collab>. <article-title>Alameda County: environmental justice element</article-title>. Published August 2024. <comment>Accessed September 2024</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.acgov.org/cda/planning/generalplans/documents/EJElement_adoptedAug2024.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.acgov.org/cda/planning/generalplans/documents/EJElement_adoptedAug2024.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-00469580251411470"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ragavan</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marcil</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Climate change as a social determinant of health</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>145</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):e20193169.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1542/peds.2019-3169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7193972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32265296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-00469580251411470"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The convergence of racial and income disparities in health insurance coverage in the United States</article-title>. <source>Int J Equity Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>96</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33827600</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12939-021-01436-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8025443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-00469580251411470"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KC.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Investigating the causal effect of socioeconomic status on quality of care under a universal health insurance system - a marginal structural model approach</article-title>. <source>BMC Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>987</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31870361</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12913-019-4793-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6929314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-00469580251411470"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Orvis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>OMB publishes revisions to statistical policy directive no.15: standards for maintaining, collecting, and presenting federal data on race and ethnicity</article-title>. <publisher-name>The White House</publisher-name>. Published <month>March</month>
<day>28</day>, <year>2024</year>. <comment>Accessed December 3, 2024</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/briefing-room/2024/03/28/omb-publishes-revisions-to-statistical-policy-directive-no-15-standards-for-maintaining-collecting-and-presenting-federal-data-on-race-and-ethnicity/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/briefing-room/2024/03/28/omb-publishes-revisions-to-statistical-policy-directive-no-15-standards-for-maintaining-collecting-and-presenting-federal-data-on-race-and-ethnicity/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-00469580251411470"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The psychology of climate anxiety</article-title>. <source>BJPsych Bull</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>222</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34006345</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1192/bjb.2021.18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8499625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-00469580251411470"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ojala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cunsolo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunbode</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Anxiety, worry, and grief in a time of environmental and climate crisis: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Environ Resour</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-00469580251411470"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Everitt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>JA.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Review: the impact of climate change awareness on children’s mental well-being and negative emotions - a scoping review</article-title>. <source>Child Adolesc Ment Health</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34873823</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/camh.12525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-00469580251411470"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The psychological impacts of global climate change</article-title>. <source>Am Psychol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>265</fpage>-<lpage>276</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21553952</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037/a0023141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-00469580251411470"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hajek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>König</surname><given-names>HH.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Do individuals with high climate anxiety believe that they will die earlier? first evidence from Germany</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>5064</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36981973</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph20065064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10048977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-00469580251411470"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cosh</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fallander</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The relationship between climate change and mental health: a systematic review of the association between eco-anxiety, psychological distress, and symptoms of major affective disorders</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>833</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39567913</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12888-024-06274-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11577747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-00469580251411470"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunbode</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pallesen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bohm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Negative emotions about climate change are related to insomnia symptoms and mental health: cross-sectional evidence in 25 countries</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>845</fpage>-<lpage>854</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-00469580251411470"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Climate change and mental health</article-title>. <source>Curr Environ Health Rep</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33389625</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40572-020-00303-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-00469580251411470"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Creswell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis: anxiety and depressive disorders in offspring of parents with anxiety disorders</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>46</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30577938</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaac.2018.07.898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-00469580251411470"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Allured</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Easterlin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<part-title>Chapter 10: Therapists’ perspectives: psychotherapeutic techniques with applicability to climate distress</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Climate Change &amp; Youth Mental Health</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2024</year>;<fpage>189</fpage>-<lpage>209</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-00469580251411470"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<collab>American Psychological Association</collab>. <article-title>Stress in America: Generation Z</article-title>. Published <year>2018</year>. <comment>Accessed August 18, 2025</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.apa.org/news/press/releases/stress/2018/stress-gen-z.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.apa.org/news/press/releases/stress/2018/stress-gen-z.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-00469580251411470"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ojala</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>How do children, adolescents, and young adults relate to climate change? implications for developmental psychology</article-title>. <source>Eur J Dev Psychol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>929</fpage>-<lpage>943</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-00469580251411470"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>, ed. <source>Theories of Adolescence</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>. <publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-00469580251411470"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sheffield</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Landrigan</surname><given-names>PJ.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Global climate change and children’s health: threats and strategies for prevention</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>298</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20947468</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1289/ehp.1002233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3059989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-00469580251411470"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Strauss Cohen I</collab>. <article-title>Understanding Bowen family systems theory</article-title>. <publisher-name>Psychology Today</publisher-name>. Published <month>November</month>
<day>13</day>, <year>2023</year>. <comment>Accessed August 20, 2025</comment>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/your-emotional-meter/202311/understanding-bowen-family-systems-theory#:~:text=%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B,with%20greater%20clarity%20and%20resilience" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/your-emotional-meter/202311/understanding-bowen-family-systems-theory#:~:text=%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B,with%20greater%20clarity%20and%20resilience</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-00469580251411470"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lajnef</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The effect of social media influencers on teenagers’ behavior: an empirical study using cognitive map technique</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychol</source>. Published online January 31, 2023. doi: 10.1007/s12144-023-04273-1<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12144-023-04273-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9887568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36742063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-00469580251411470"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ahdoot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cataletto</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>American academy of pediatrics, council on environmental health and climate change; council on children and disasters; section on pediatric pulmonology and sleep medicine; section on minority health, equity, and inclusion. Climate change and children’s health: building a healthy future for every child</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):e2023065505.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1542/peds.2023-065505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38374808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-00469580251411470"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Memmott</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Carley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Graff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Konisky</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Sociodemographic disparities in energy insecurity among low-income households before and during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>Nat Energy</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>186</fpage>-<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46-00469580251411470"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morello-Frosch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Obasogie</surname><given-names>OK.</given-names></name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The climate gap and the color line — racial health inequities and climate change</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>388</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>943</fpage>-<lpage>949</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36884328</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMsb2213250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>