
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">FEMS Microbiol Ecol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">FEMS Microbiol Ecol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2712</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">femsme</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">femsec</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>FEMS Microbiology Ecology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0168-6496</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1574-6941</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13170800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC13170800.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13170800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13170800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">42018483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsec/fiag044</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">fiag044</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Minireview</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI01150</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A systematic review on soil microbial shifts under drought stress: a climate-smart agriculture perspective</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7779-3764</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramatsitsi</surname><given-names initials="N">Ndivhuwo</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="Conceptualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization">Conceptualization</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="Investigation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation">Investigation</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="Writing - original draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft">Writing - original draft</role><aff>Department of Agronomy, <institution>University of Fort Hare, Private Bag X1314, Alice, 5700</institution>, <country country="ZA">South Africa</country></aff><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4756-0895</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Manyevere</surname><given-names initials="A">Alen</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="Investigation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation">Investigation</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="Writing - review &amp; editing" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing">Writing - review &amp; editing</role><aff>Department of Agronomy, <institution>University of Fort Hare, Private Bag X1314, Alice, 5700</institution>, <country country="ZA">South Africa</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horn</surname><given-names initials="M">Marcus</given-names></name><role>Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Corresponding author. Department of Agronomy, University of Fort Hare, Private Bag X1314, Alice, 5700, South Africa. E-mail: <email>nramatsitsi@ufh.ac.za</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2026-04-22"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>102</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">511890</issue-id><elocation-id>fiag044</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2026</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2026</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>05</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-05-14 16:25:17.203"><day>14</day><month>05</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of FEMS.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fiag044.pdf"><?pdf-name fiag044.pdf?><?pdf-size 829889?><?pdf-md5 d81b865a64b0917fb1f6164db0bae543?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:0c00/13170800/d81b865a64b0/fiag044.pdf?></self-uri><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="fiag044.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Major shifts in temperature and rainfall patterns resulting from climate change are projected to continue increasing intensely over the course of the century. Ecosystems’ functionality and well-being of above-ground plant community are all significantly impacted by soil microbes’ response to these shifting abiotic stresses. With an emphasis on improving their usefulness in climate-smart agriculture (CSA), we reviewed how soil bacteria and fungi tolerate drought stress and improve plant development under water shortage conditions. This systematic analysis used Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) to elaborate how microbe-based solutions could be incorporated in CSA. A total of 31 articles satisfied the inclusion criteria. The review demonstrated that soil microbial diversity and abundance are considerably altered by drought stress, improve resilience of plants, and soil functionality. There was a further observation of high microbial community in the endosphere, and rhizosphere as compared to bulk soil; a clear indication of plants’ potential to facilitate soil microbial assemblages. Evidently, plants under drought conditions exude metabolites that stimulate drought-tolerant microbes; that in-turn promote the plants’ tolerance to drought. Accordingly, this remarkable synergy between microbes and plants could help forecast how agroecosystems would function in the face of climate change.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>The paper evaluated how drought resistant bacteria and fungi promote plant growth and development under water shortage, in accordance with several sustainable development goals and emphasis on climate-smart agriculture.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>climate change</kwd><kwd>drought-resistant</kwd><kwd>microbial diversity</kwd><kwd>resilience</kwd><kwd>water scarcity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="17"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Global warming is causing drastic changes in temperature and rainfall regimes, and these changes are predicted to get exacerbated over the next century (Tang et al. <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>). Increased drought-related stress from global warming and climate change has detrimental impacts on plant functionality and survival because it induces metabolic dysfunction and inhibits photosynthetic carbon dioxide fixation, which lead to substantial growth declines and often premature plant death (Chaudhry and Sidhu <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). Prospective projections indicate that due to water scarcity, this abiotic stress will reduce the yield of both agricultural (Junaid and Gokce <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>) and bioenergy crops in low-latitude regions (Heikonen et al. <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>). Although it is inconceivable to pinpoint the precise proportion of worldwide farms that utilize covered structures including plastic mulch or greenhouses, it is understood to constitute a negligible portion of all agricultural areas. It has been estimated that between 4–5 million hectares of land are under protected structures, representing a rather minute percentage of all arable land (Tong et al. <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Approximately 1.6 billion hectares were utilized for agricultural production in 2024 (Ritchie and Roser <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Of this, ∼40% is made up of drylands, which are home to more than two billion people. Most arid and semi-arid regions are anticipated to undergo modified rainfall patterns, encompassing variations in overall precipitation totals and fewer but more intense rainfall occurrences punctuated by extended dry spells (UN <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). As such, there is a global dire need for climate-smart agriculture (CSA) strategies for improved productivity in water-scarce regions.</p><p>To raise awareness and restructure policy in response to climate change, CSA explores trade-offs and synergies between food security, adaptation, and mitigation. The goal of CSA is to enhance food security in the face of the current climatic challenges by readjusting and reshaping agricultural systems (Azadi et al. <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). According to Engel and Muller (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), CSA can increase agricultural output and revenue while fostering climate change resilience and reducing greenhouse gas emissions by implementing adaptation techniques. The main objective of CSA is to create resilient systems and high yields by utilizing modern agricultural technology and advancements. These include biologically derived inputs such as microbial inoculants and plant-based bio-stimulants, as well as sustainable land management practices such as conservation tillage, cover cropping, and the application of organic amendments. This is essential to meeting the food needs of a growing population and promoting the economic expansion needed to reduce poverty (Hussain et al. <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>). The close interaction between plants and micro-organisms can be exploited to achieve sustainable development goals (SDG) such as SDG No. 13 of “Climate action” and reduce negative environmental effects. Through root exudates, plants provide micro-organisms in the rhizosphere with carbon sources including sugars and amino acids, which promote microbial development (Hartmann et al. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>, Vives-Peris et al. <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). In exchange, by facilitating nutrient uptake, strengthening root development, providing ecological resilience, micro-organisms enhance plant health. Because micro-organisms foster growth, development and provide resilience to a variety of abiotic stressors, they can be employed to aid in climate change adaption (Ajala et al. <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).</p><p>Abiotic stressors such as drought can simultaneously affect the physiology, growth, and productivity of plants while altering host-associated microbiomes. Prolonged water stress may remodel microbial networks, and favor recognized drought-tolerant micro-organisms in rhizospheres or roots, such as Actinobacteria, Chloroflexi, and Firmicutes (Bogati and Walczak <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>, Mazumder et al. <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>). Soil microbial communities are pivotal for ecosystem resilience, especially in the face of climate change. Plant–microbiome interactions play a significant role in enhancing ecosystem resilience by supporting plant health, restoring soil functionality, and acting as natural mediators of plant stress responses, enabling plants to recover from environmental stressors (Philippot et al. <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). The purpose of this study was to systematically review how plants physiologically respond to water stress and concurrently modify belowground microbiomes. This review aims not only to summarize existing studies but to synthesize current knowledge by identifying key mechanisms underlying plant–microbe interactions under drought stress and evaluating their consistency across diverse agroecosystems. The following questions were the focus of this review: (i) What are plant-microbe abundance and diversity under drought stress? (ii) How do plant species facilitate soil microbial assemblages under water stress? and (iii) How do drought-resistant microbes influence plant adaptability to drought stress? This review adopts a broad, global perspective by integrating studies across diverse agroecosystems, plant species, and experimental conditions to identify general patterns in bacteria and fungi responses to drought stress within the context of CSA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>Methodology</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Search strategy</title><p>Relevant articles were searched for, chosen, and collected by applying a methodical process that adhered to the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) flow-diagram (Page et al. <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Research papers, reviews, and book chapters on plant-microbe interactions under drought stress were compiled from the following search databases: Science Direct, Google Scholar, and SCOPUS . “Drought-resistant microbes” and “climate-smart agriculture”, “distribution of drought-resistant microbes”, “effects of drought-resistant microbes on plant growth and productivity,” and “incorporation of drought-resilient microbes in climate-smart agriculture” were search terms used to collect research material on this topic from peer-reviewed scientific publications. A search protocol was created once the search queries were crafted to get pertinent data where the search terms were used to find the original material (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). A formal meta-analysis was not conducted due to heterogeneity in experimental designs, microbial metrics, and reporting approaches across studies, which limited direct quantitative comparisons.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Research protocol.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Research question</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">What are the plant-microbe interactions under drought stress?</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search database</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Science Direct, Google Scholar, and SCOPUS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search query 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TITLE-ABS-KEY [(“drought-resistant” OR “drought-resilient” OR “drought-tolerant”) AND (“microbial communities” OR “microbial diversity” OR “microbial abundance” OR “microbial shift” OR “microbial functional groups”) AND (“drought” OR “water stress” OR “water scarcity”) AND (“respond” OR “react” OR “influence” OR “impact” OR “effect”)] AND PUBYEAR &gt; 2010 AND PUBYEAR &lt; 2025 AND [LIMIT-TO (DOCTYPE, “ar”)] AND [LIMIT-TO (LANGUAGE, “English”)]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search query 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TITLE-ABS-KEY (“plant species” OR “plant community” OR “plant diversity”) AND TITLE-ABS-KEY (“functional trait” OR “plant trait” OR “agronomic trait”) AND TITLE-ABS-KEY (“microbial stimulation” OR “chemoreception” OR “symbiotic”) AND PUBYEAR &gt; 2010 AND PUBYEAR &lt; 2025</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search query 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TITLE-ABS-KEY [(“endosphere” OR “rhizosphere” OR “bulk soil”)]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search time frame</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Articles published between 2010 and 2025</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boolean operators</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">“AND”, “OR”</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Screening process</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PRISMA checklists were followed for the screening process.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data extraction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-designed data extraction form.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Assessment and selection of articles</title><p>The inclusion criteria were intentionally stringent to ensure the selection of studies with clearly defined microbial responses to drought stress and comparable experimental conditions. While this approach enhances the reliability of comparisons, it may have excluded studies that provide broader contextual insights. The primary literature search terms focused on the publication’s title, yielding an initial collection of 511 publications. These papers underwent further review in pursuit of research that included quantitative and qualitative evaluation of the following: (i) drought-resistant bacteria and fungi; (ii) microbial diversity and abundance under drought stress; and (iii) microbial shift under drought stressed plants. Reviews and book chapters were also included for the study since the experimental research papers that were cited were cross-referenced and assessed for inclusion eligibility. The collected articles were vetted according to a subsequent selection criterion: (i) studies that identified bacteria and fungi to family level; (ii) studies that identified bacteria or fungi when studied in conjunction with plants; (iii) studies that included a positive control (i.e. regular irrigation intervals), and (iv) studies that encompassed forest, field, or greenhouse conditions. Both quantitative and qualitative information regarding the experiment’s location, bacteria, or fungi families/genus/species, plant types/species, experimental conditions and experiment duration were gathered from the carefully curated publications. The literature was reduced to 97 peer-reviewed publications published between 2010 and 2025 after additional screening eliminated duplicate research and those that focused on biotic stressors. Although attempts were made to get translated copies of non-English papers, only the abstracts of papers of relevance were translated. Due to the abstracts’ failure to include bacteria and/or fungi species/genus or identification methods, these studies were subsequently disqualified. With a mechanism-based synthesis across systems shown in Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, our thorough review adhered to these steps and standards.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The criteria for selection of articles for comparative assessment of drought-resilient microbes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Criteria</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exclusion</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inclusion</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grey literature including magazines, bulletins and newsletters</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peer-reviewed literature such as experimental original papers, review papers, book chapters, government gazettes and policies</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Article</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Articles that only had access to abstracts</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full text articles</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abiotic stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that did not focus on drought-exposed plants/microbes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plants that focused on drought-exposed plants/microbes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatments</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that did not include comparative irrigated control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that included comparative irrigated control</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microbes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that did not focus on soilborne drought-resilient microbes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that focused on at least soilborne drought-resilient microbes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study conditions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that were exclusively conducted under laboratory without inclusion of plants</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that were conducted under greenhouse, glasshouse, field and forest with the inclusion of at least one plant species.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-English</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">English</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publication date</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before 2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 2010</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Risk of bias assessment</title><p>In assessing the changes in bacteria or fungi composition or biomass, bias analysis facilitates insightful comparisons, because it enables us to systematically assess the methodological quality of observational studies. For carrying out risk of bias assessment, the Crowe Critical tool was used to assess different criteria such as design, sampling, and data collection, ultimately categorizing studies into different quality tiers. This ensured that studies were compared using reliable methodologies, thus facilitating accurate interpretations and conclusions regarding the shift in bacteria and fungi and subsequent influence on ecosystem functionality.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Data extraction and data analysis</title><p>The initial exclusion process involved removing duplicates, resulting in the exclusion of 356 articles. Subsequently, 155 unique articles remained and among these, 47 articles were found ineligible based on their titles and abstracts, as they did not focus on assessing the microbial response to drought. After the screening process, 108 papers qualified for a full-text review. However, 77 articles were excluded during this phase as they did not meet the eligibility criteria established for the review. Ultimately, 31 articles met the selection criteria and were included for data extraction in the study, as illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) flow diagram for showing the steps taken for selection of eligible articles for inclusion in the systematic review.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fiag044fig1.jpg"><?image-name fiag044fig1.jpg?><?image-size 94300?><?image-md5 3d8d2f3672847723c25849c824ac35ff?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1787?><?image-original-width 1575?><?image-scaled-height 893?><?image-scaled-width 787?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0c00/13170800/3d8d2f367284/fiag044fig1.jpg?><?thumb-name fiag044fig1.gif?><?thumb-size 3672?><?thumb-md5 5cf8db835d0fbf35940811bedfd8ab08?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 113?><?thumb-scaled-width 100?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/0c00/13170800/5cf8db835d0f/fiag044fig1.gif?><alt-text>PRISMA flow diagram showing the study selection process. A total of 511 records were identified through database searching. After removal of 356 duplicates, 155 records were screened, of which 47 were excluded based on title and abstract. 48 full-text articles were assessed for eligibility, with 17 excluded for reasons including lack of relevant outcomes, insufficient methodological detail, or absence of empirical data. A final total of 31 studies were included in the review.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Geographical distribution of bacteria response to drought</title><p>The reviewed studies cover a wide range of regions with different climates and experimental conditions (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). They included areas in Asia, Europe, Australia, America and Africa, showcasing how drought-resistant microbes are essential in CSA on a scale. Several research studies focused on subtropical areas with a notable emphasis in Asia, where seven studies were conducted (Dai et al. <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, Ullah et al. <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, Liu et al. <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, Xie et al. <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, Peng et al. <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>, Wu et al. <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>, Halo et al. <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>) on various plants, highlighting Asia’s significance in CSA research within tropical ecosystems. These studies delved into identifying bacteria from plants’ endosphere, rhizosphere and bulk soil The prevalence of China’s influence in the study highlights the importance of advancing towards CSA from microbial perspective in regions where continuous growth leads to ongoing challenges with water scarcity. Studies from temperate regions including United States (Zapata et al. <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, Yang et al. <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>), Europe (de Souza et al. <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>), and Australia (Maisnam et al. <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>) were also explored in the current review. In these studies, they aimed to assess temporal and spatial microbial shifts under different plant species subjected to drought. In the arid and semi-arid continental climates of Africa, studies including those by (Marasco et al. <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, Huber et al. <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>, Legeay et al. <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>, Ehinmitan et al. <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>) also identified microbes with potential for mitigating drought stress.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Spatial and temporal shifts of soilborne bacteria subjected to drought stress on different plant species.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Objective</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conditions</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identified bacteria</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Vigna unguiculata</italic> [L.] Walp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To identify the epiphytic rhizobacterial community in cowpea and investigate how their biodiversity responds to drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth room</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compared to the control, epiphytic bacterial communities showed increased diversity on drought-treated cowpea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Methylophaga, Nocardioides, Paenibacillus, Kangiella koreensis, Halobacteriovorax, Ornithinicoccus halotolerans, Haliea atlantica, Pseudonocardia saturnea, Halocatena pleomorpha, Maricaulis maris, Pelagibacterium halotolerans, Tistlia consotensis, Marinobacter bryozoorum, Thermochromatium tepidum, Streptomyces sediminis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oman</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Halo et al. <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Populus tomentosa</italic> Carrière</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To characterise changes in microbes during drought stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Even though overall diversity declined, plant-beneficial fungi were relatively widespread</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces rochei, Bacillus arbutinivorans, B. endophyticus, B. megaterium, Aspergillus terreus, Penicillium raperi, Trichoderma ghanense, Gongronella butleri, Rhizopus stolonifer</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Xie et al. <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">japonica</italic> cv. Jia 67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore how drought stress impacts bacterial co-occurring networks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drought changed the bacterial community assemblages and raised the Shannon bacteriomes diversity on rice rhizosphere and endosphere</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Sphingomonas, Paracoccus, Mesorhizobium, Streptomyces, Pseudomonas, Exiguobacterium, Anaeromyxobacter</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Wu et al. <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Gossypium hirsutum</italic> cv. Jin668</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine microbes that are most suited for cotton’s drought resistance.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greenhouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacterial community significantly increased in the soil with cotton plants compared to fallow</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Sphingomonas, Streptomyces, Gemmatimonas, Sphingopyxis, Acidothermus, Jatrophihabitans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Ullah et al. <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Panicum miliaceum</italic> L., <italic toggle="yes">Arachis hypogaea</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To study the rhizospheric and bulk soil microbial communities in a cereal/ legume monoculture and intercropping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drought was the main factor influencing bacterial composition with no significant differences in monoculture and intercropping</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actinobacteriota, Proteobacteria, Chloroflexi, Acidobacteriota, Firmicutes, Basidiomycota, Ascomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Peng et al. <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Arachis hypogaea</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate how peanut developmental stages affect structure the root microbial community after drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greenhouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drastic increase in abundance of Actinobacteria and Acidobacteria in seedling and podding stages, and an increase of Cyanobacteria and Gemmatimonadetes during the flowering stage in drought-treated rhizospheres</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Saccharibacteria, Gaiellales, Sphingomonas, Micrococcaceae, Acidimicrobiales, Microcoleus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Dai et al. <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Saccharum officinarum</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate the rhizosphere microbial species response to drought stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greenhouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The change in the bacterial community structure under drought stress had a 25.2% correlation with the drought adaptability of sugarcane</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alphaproteobacteria, Gammaproteobacteria, Sphingobacteriia, Betaproteobacteria, Actinobacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Liu et al. <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Avena barbata</italic> Pott ex Link., <italic toggle="yes">Bromus diandrus</italic> Roth., <italic toggle="yes">Medicago polymorpha</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To test how soil microbial diversity, composition and co-occurrence relationships are affected by drought and vegetation restoration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compared to soils receiving ambient precipitation, drought dramatically decreased bacterial diversity and composition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verrucomicrobia, Proteobacteria, Chloroflexi, Cyanobacteria, Planctomycetes, Acidobacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States of America</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Yang et al. <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Manihot esculenta</italic> Crantz</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To isolate bacterial strains from the rhizosphere of cassava subjected to water shortage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glasshouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">An increase in the diversity, abundance, and species richness of rhizobacterial community was found in cassava plants subjected to water-deficit stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Achromobacter, Acinetobacter, Aeromonas, Buttiauxella, Cronobacter, Klebsiella, Ochrobactrum, Pluralibacter, Pseudomonas, Rhizobium, Serratia, Sphingomonas, Pseudomonas luteola, Ochrobactrum anthropi</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colombia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Zapata et al. <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grasses, herbs, legumes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the changes in bacterial diversity and composition across plant species richness gradient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Found the taxa that are strongly influenced by drought at each plant richness level and the substantial impact of plant species richness on the makeup of the soil microbial community</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gemmatimonadota, Chloroflexi, Myxococcota, Bacteroidota, Patescibacteria, Actinobacteriota, Planctomycetota, Verrucomicrobiota,</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(de Souza et al. <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Woodland, shrubs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate shifts in the structure of microbial community pre- and post-drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wet periods had high abundances in taxa of Gemmatimonadetes, Acidobacteria, Chytridiomycota. While Actinobacteria, Alphaproteobacteria, Ascomycota, Planctomycetes, Basidiomycota increased during drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actinobacteria, Planctomycetes, Ascomycota, Basidiomycota, Alphaproteobacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Maisnam et al. <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Malva sylvestris</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine the structure of microbiome of <italic toggle="yes">M. sylvestris</italic>, in arid regions and evaluate which bacteria are associated with this plant’s drought tolerance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The endosphere was dominated by the genus <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic>, Pseudomonadota, Actinomycetota, Pseudomonadota, Bacillota, Planctomycetota, Chloroflexota,</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Legeay et al. <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Woodland, bushveld, fallow</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the influence of drought on bacteria and their response to different soil water availability</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">High population of Blastocatellia and Vicinamibacteria in loamy sands, while the Acidobacteriia dominated in sandy soils</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidobacteriia, Blastocatellia, Pyrimonadales, Blastocatellales, Vicinamibacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Namibia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Huber et al. <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Capsicum annuum</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To assess the impact of desert farming on plant-microbe association in pepper cultivated in arid conditions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> spp. (68% of the isolates) was mainly recovered from the endosphere, while rhizosphere and the root surrounding soil fractions were dominated by <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic> spp. (61% and 44% respectively)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria, Bacilli, Alpha, Pseudomonas, Beta, Gammaproteobacteria</italic>,</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egypt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Marasco et al. <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Zea mays</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To identify and assess the bacterial strains’ capacity to stimulate plant growth under drought stress</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant improvements in maize vigour index, germination rate, seedling length, height and dry biomass by the combinatorial potential of the identified isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. cereus, B. velezensis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kenya</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Ehinmitan et al. <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Anthoxanthum odoratum, Dactylis glomerata, Leontodon hispidus, Rumex acetosa</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To evaluate contribution of plant communities in the response of bacterial network and community to drought, as well as the resulting consequences for soil functionality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glasshouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drought decreased bacterial richness and evenness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verrucomicrobia, Actinobacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">England</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(de Vries et al. <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Geographical distribution of fungi response to drought</title><p>The reviewed experimental research on fungal diversity during drought also encompassed a broad spectrum of geographical locations with varying weather and experimental setups. They too illustrated the significance of drought-resistant fungi in CSA on a large scale by including regions from Asia, Europe, Australia, America, and Africa (Table <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Temperate regions were the primary subject of several investigations, with Europe receiving particular attention (de Vries et al. <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, Schmidt et al. <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, Lozano et al. <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, Albracht et al. <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>, Maisnam et al. <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>) on various plants under varying experimental setups. These investigations focused on examining temporal shifts in fungi structure and community under drought on different plants. Studies from United States of America (Hawkes et al. <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, Buscardo et al. <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, Carbone et al. <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, Lagueux et al. <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, Basyal and Walker <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>, Yang et al. <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>;) were also explored in the current review. These studies aimed to assess temporal and spatial fungal shifts under different plant species subjected to drought, as well as soil functionality. In the tropical and temperate continental climates of Australia, studies including those by (Hopkins et al. <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, Birnbaum et al. <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and Asia (Wang et al. <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">2024a</xref>,<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>, Andreo-Jimenez et al. <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, Maitra et al. <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) identified fungi with potential for mitigating drought stress under different experimental settings across greenhouse, field and forests. These studies established that fungi are sensitive to drought stress, with more abundance of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF), ectomycorrhizal fungi (ECM), and saprophytes.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Spatial and temporal shifts of soilborne fungi subjected to drought stress on different plant species.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Objective</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conditions</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identified fungi</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Woodland, shrubs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate shifts in the structure of microbial community pre- and post-drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungi were shown to be more sensitive to the prolonged drought and to rainfall treatment than bacteria with Basidiomycota mostly dominant in the reduced rainfall treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascomycota, Basidiomycota, Chytridiomycota, Mortierellomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Maisnam et al. <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eucalyptus marginata, Corymbia calophylla</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To measure the rhizosphere fungal communities in a drought impact gradient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal community composition and abundance of functional groups were altered in the soil underneath the drought-affected tree, with less ECM mycorrhizal fungi and greater levels of AMF and saprotrophs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arbuscular mycorrhiza, ectomycorrhizal fungi, ericoid, saprophytes, endophytes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Hopkins et al. <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteaceae, Fabaceae, Myrtaceae,Ericaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To assess how warming and drying conditions shape soil fungi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">When compared to control plots, soil fungal diversity increased during warming, suggesting that warming had a beneficial impact on fungal diversity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endophytes, ericoid mycorrhizas, yeasts, ectomycorrhizas</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Birnbaum et al. <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grasses, herbs, legumes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To determine the long-term impacts of drought on interactions between fungi and plants</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shifts in AMF and overall fungal community structures brought on by recurring drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Diversispora torrecillas, Penicillium jenensii, Paraglomus</italic> spp.,</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Albracht et al. <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grasses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To assess how different moisture conditions affect overall fungal diversity, community composition and functionality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grassland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Changes in community structure, but richness of communities was not changed and decrease in the relative abundance of pathogens</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sordariomycetes, Agaricomycetes, Eurotiomycetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Schmidt et al. <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Avena barbata, Bromus diandrus, Medicago polymorpha</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To test how soil microbial diversity, composition and co-occurrence relationships are affected by drought and vegetation restoration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal diversity and composition were not significantly impacted by either vegetation restoration or drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States of America</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Yang et al. <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Anthoxanthum odoratum, Dactylis glomerata, Leontodon hispidus, Rumex acetosa</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To evaluate contribution of plant communities in the response of fungal networks and community to drought, as well as the effects of drought on soil fungi and the resulting consequences for soil functioning</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glasshouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal richness and evenness increased during the drought period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascomycota, Glomeromycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">England</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(de Vries et al. <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Andropogon gerardii, Bouteloua curtipendula, B.dactyloides, B. eriopoda, B. gracilis, Schizachyrium scoparium</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To assess the effects of drought on grassland root-associated fungi and to investigate the differences between these grasslands in the fungi linked to the major grasses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greenhouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fungal diversity and abundance in roots were mostly unaltered by drought, but the fungal community makeup was significantly rearranged</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rhizophagus, Podospora, Lophiostoma, Preussia, Cladophialophora, Marasmius, Lachnum, Marchandiomyces, Mortierella, Chaetomium, Monosporascus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Lagueux et al. <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Panicum virgatum</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate how AMF species affect switchgrass physiology and growth during periods of severe drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greenhouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The aboveground biomass of mycorrhizal plants grew more than three times under drought compared to the uninoculated control plants, despite the fact that drought drastically reduced mycorrhizal colonization by about 37%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Claroideoglomus etunicatum</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States of America</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Basyal and Walker <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Schima superba, Castanopsis fargesii, Castanopsis carlesii, Lithocarpus glaber, Hicriopteris glauca</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine the response of AM fungi to drought in different seasons</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drought significantly affected AM fungal extra-radical hyphal density, spore density and root colonization rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glomerales, Diversisporales, Archaeosporales, Paraglomerales</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Maitra et al. <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic> “Qingshui”, “Longdong”, <italic toggle="yes">M. varia</italic> “Gongnong”</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Looking at which microbes are best for alfalfa’s drought resistance and how drought stress alters the endogenous hormone content of the root system</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greenhouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Different alfalfa species promoted different relative abundance of fungi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascomycota, Dothideomycetes, Capnodiales, Cladosporiaceae, <italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium, Cladosporium sphaerospermum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Wang et al. <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">2024a</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Castanopsis fargesii, Castanopsis sclerophylla, Lithocarpus glaber, Schima superba</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate how long-term drought affects the microbial population at various soil depths</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">While Basidiomycota increased with increasing soil depth, Ascomycota relative abundance declined. On fungal species including Chytridiomycota and Rozellomycota, there were notable interactions between soil depth and drought. Even though Kickxellomycota are known to be less abundant in soil, their relative abundance was greatly enhanced by drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basidiomycota, Kickxellomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Wang et al. <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">2024b</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grassland</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine how soil fungi respond to rain seasonal changes in a grassland ecosystem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rainfall levels had a direct impact on fungi, with abundant, varied, and stable communities growing under drought and less abundant, varied, and unstable communities during wetter times</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascomycota, Basidiomycota, Glomeromycota, Chytridiomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States of America</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Hawkes et al. <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grasses, forbs, legumes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To evaluate how plant species (i.e. grasses, forbs, legumes) react to drought in terms of fungal communities and the functional groups linked to their roots</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root characteristic adaptations to water shortage were linked to the fungal response to drought, which was strongly dependent on the fungal group</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Gibberella tricintata, Urocystis agropyri, Powellomyces hirtus, Mortierella minutissima,Mortierella sarnyensis, Trichocladium opacum, Preussia flana-ganii</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Lozano et al. <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Vitis vinifera</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To explore the impact of drought on root-associated fungal communities</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 and 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greenhouse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All three compartments' total fungal composition was considerably altered by drought, with the root endosphere compartment varying from the well-watered control the most.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nectriaceae, Mortierellaceae, Ceratobasidiaceae, Mortierellaceae, Ceratobasidiaceae, Mortierellaceae,</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uruguay</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Carbone et al. <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic> ssp. indica</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To examine how drought affects fungal microbiomes associated with the roots of several rice cultivars and if these alterations may help rice withstand drought</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drought enhanced fungal diversification and changed the makeup of the fungal community associated with roots</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glomeromycota, Ascomycota, Zygomycota, Basidiomycota, Chytridiomycota,</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Philippines</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Andreo-Jimenez et al. <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evergreen rainforest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">To investigate the effects of natural seasonality in an Amazonian rain forest with 14 years of partial throughfall exclusion, with an emphasis on the functional diversity of soil fungi</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drought causes significant changes in fungal diversity and functional group composition, with noticeable rise in dark-septate fungal abundance and a decline in fungal pathogens</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ascomycota, Rozellomycota, Basidiomycota, Mucoromycota, Chytridiomycota, Entomophthoromycota, Glomeromycota, Mortierellomycota</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Buscardo et al. <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl4fn1"><p>AMF: arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi, EMC: ectomycorrhizal fungi</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec4-1"><title>Soil microbial diversity and abundance under drought</title><p>Based on the reviewed studies, a conceptual framework emerges in which plant–microbe interactions under drought stress are mediated by interconnected mechanisms. These include (i) plant-driven root exudation that selectively recruits beneficial microbes, (ii) microbial enhancement of plant stress tolerance through osmolyte production and phytohormone regulation, and (iii) structural modifications such as enhanced root growth that improve water acquisition. While the relative importance of these mechanisms varies across systems, they collectively represent a generalizable pathway through which plants and microbes interact under water-limited conditions.</p><p>Different plant species have shown varying effects of drought on the variety of rhizospheric bacteria, and this diversity can occasionally be influenced by the host plant species, soil conditions, and the intensity of the applied drought (Moore et al. <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Drought, for example, decreased microbial diversity in other plant species, including <italic toggle="yes">Populus</italic> trees (Xie et al. <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), but increased microbial diversity in the rhizosphere of cowpea (Halo et al. <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>). In rice, the co-occurrence network in the rhizosphere became more complicated due to drought circumstances. Bacterial diversity, as shown by the Shannon index, rose while species richness stayed the same (Wu et al. <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Studies such as those by Wu et al. (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>) indicated differences in microbial diversity differences across endosphere, rhizosphere and bulk soil. Drought stress boosted bacterial alpha diversity in cotton rhizospheres, and some bacterial phyla, including Chloroflexi and Gemmatimonadetes, were enriched (Ullah et al. <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Similarly to bacteria dynamics under drought, fungi composition and diversity are also influenced by drought periods and plant species. In a study by Hopkins et al. (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), the rhizospheric soil of <italic toggle="yes">Eucalyptus marginata</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Corymbia calophylla</italic> trees damaged by dryness had a different fungus community composition and functional group abundance, with more AMF and saprotrophs and less ECM. In the drought-affected areas, fungal communities under live and dead plants differed as well; under dead trees, the drought-affected plots had more AMF and saprophytes, but a decline in pathogenic fungal species (Schmidt et al. <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, Buscardo et al. <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Under greenhouse conditions, while fungal diversity and abundance in roots were mostly unaltered by drought, the fungal community composition was significantly rearranged on different grass species subjected to drought stress (Lagueux et al. <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p><p>The plant holobiont is made up of the rhizosphere and endosphere microbes, which are essential for changing the composition of soil nutrients and for facilitating plants tolerating a wide range of biotic and abiotic stressors, including drought. The distinction between rhizosphere and endosphere microbial communities is well established, with each niche hosting structurally and functionally distinct microbiomes (Trivedi et al. <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). This was further supported by Wu et al. (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>), who showed that the dominant bacterial taxa and community structure in the rhizosphere and endosphere of <italic toggle="yes">O. sativa</italic> were significantly different from those in the bulk soil under drought. In this study there were notable enrichment of Gemmatimonadetes, Patescibacteria, and Actinobacteriota, while populations of Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes, and Desulfobacterota, declined in the rhizosphere and endosphere (Wu et al. <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). Similarly, Ullah et al. (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) established differences in bacteria diversity of <italic toggle="yes">G. hirsutum</italic> rhizosphere and bulk soil, where drought treatment reduced the abundance of Streptomyces but increased the abundance of Sphingomonas. Dynamic changes were seen in the rhizosphere communities during the drought treatment. The relative abundance of Actinobacteria and Alphaproteobacteria in the rhizosphere bacterial community increased, while the relative abundance of Betaproteobacteria and Sphingobacteria decreased (Liu et al. <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>).</p><p>Plant growth and overall health have been shown to be impacted by drought-induced alterations in microbial populations. When assessing the impact of desert farming on plant-microbe association in pepper cultivated in arid conditions Marasco et al. (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) discovered that <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> species (68% of the isolates) was mainly recovered from the endosphere, while rhizosphere and the root surrounding soil fractions were dominated by <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella</italic> species (61% and 44%, respectively). When treated with drought after inoculation, the plants’ growth was higher than that of the groups that received regular watering (Xie et al. <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). In yet another study, Peng et al. (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>) established that the primary factor influencing the makeup of microbial communities was drought, which led to a decrease in the abundance of Proteobacteria, Acidobacteriota, and Ascomycota, while it resulted in an increase in Actinobacteriota, Firmicutes, and Basidiomycota. Halo et al. (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>) identified species previously identified in saline environments such as <italic toggle="yes">Adhaeretor mobilis, Halobacteriovorax</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Haliea atlantica, Halocatena pleomorpha, Kangiella koreensis, Marinobacter bryozoorum, Maricaulis maris, Ornithinicoccus halotolerans, Pelagibacterium halotolerans</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Tistlia consotensis</italic>. The species list also includes bacterial species previously identified in desert habitats, such as <italic toggle="yes">Nocardioides</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Pseudonocardia saturnea</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces sediminis</italic>, as well as in the hot spring, such as <italic toggle="yes">Thermochromatium tepidum</italic>.</p><p>In a microbial co-occurrence study de Vries et al. (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) established that drought predominately encourages altering characteristics in networks of soil bacteria more than that of fungal species, and that alterations in bacterial communities have a stronger correlation with soil functioning following recovery than do alterations in fungal communities. In a study by Hopkins et al. (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), along the drought effect gradient, the composition of fungal communities varied considerably, with drought-affected stands having lower levels of diversity. While there was no difference in taxonomic richness and diversity, there was considerable indication of community divergence between dead and living trees. In comparison to surviving trees from the unaffected plots, die-off-impacted plots contained more saprotrophs and AMF and less ECM when analyzed by functional group. Additionally, dead and living tree rhizosphere samples in die-off plots had lower ECM, higher AMF, and saprotrophs and pathogens. Fungal diversity and colonization were mostly resistant to drought, although species relative abundances were rearranged by dryness, changing the makeup of the root fungal community. Of the fungus linked with roots, the grass variety that showed the most decreases under drought had the least amount of reordering. In response to changed precipitation, plants may benefit from a stabilizing mechanism that is provided by the reorganization of the fungal population associated with the roots (Lagueux et al. <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). This implies that rather than plant-associated fungi directly responding to climatic factors, the biggest changes in plant-associated fungi will probably be brought about by changes in plant relative abundance or the extinction of plant species.</p></sec><sec id="sec4-2"><title>Plant species facilitate soil microbial assemblages under drought</title><p>As much as microbes facilitate plant growth, to an equitable degree, plant species also stimulate the establishment of certain microbial communities. Plant-microbial community is facilitated by root exudates, which are also essential for ecosystem response to environmental change (Williams and de Vries <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Under moderate drought, plants often boot carbon allocation to roots and release osmoprotectants like proline, trehalose, and glycine betaine to stabilize cellular functions. As drought intensifies, plant metabolism shifts from primary to secondary metabolites such as flavonoids, caffeic acid, and lignin precursors to protect tissues, counter oxidative stress, and signal beneficial microbes. Specific peptides and antioxidants including acacetin and luteolin accumulate during severe drought to maintain turgor pressure and enhanced drought tolerance. Regardless of recovery, drought exposure boosted host growth in C and N metabolic pathways (amino acids, fatty acids, and phenolic glycosides), according to plant metabolomic analysis. Several metabolites showed a favorable correlation with microbial alpha-diversity linked with roots (Veach et al. <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Compared to irrigated controls, the composition of the soil bacterial community changed when <italic toggle="yes">P. trichocarpa</italic> and drought were present, but only when plants were present did the composition of the soil fungal community change. On the other hand, root bacterial populations altered less with dryness than root fungal communities (Veach et al. <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Likely for increased investment in root growth due to reduction or absence of photosynthetic capacity (Gargallo‐Garriga et al. <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The buildup of organic or amino acid metabolites in the roots, which was higher in plants experiencing drought, may draw microbial endophytes (Andreo-Jimenez et al. <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and provide characteristics that promote plant development (Rolli et al. <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Though they did not identify plant roots exudates, Lozano et al. (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) concluded that there were plant species-specific differences in fungal beta diversity between the control and drought conditions. While mutualistic fungi exhibited the reverse tendency, saprotrophic fungi for some species increased in relative abundance and richness with drought. And while it was minimally impacted by drought, the community structure of pathogenic fungus was specific to plant species.</p><p>The presence or absence of plants play significant roles in the abundance and diversity of soil microbial shift under drought conditions. According to taxonomic study by Ullah et al. (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), the phyla Proteobacteria (31.7%), Actinobacteria (29.6%), Gemmatimonadetes (9.8%), Chloroflexi (9%), Cyanobacteria (5.6%), and Acidobacteria made up the majority of the bacterial community structure in the cotton rhizosphere subjected to drought. Though this study did not identify roots exudate, the diversity and rise in bacteria population on cotton than in fallow means that plants stimulate bacterial composition. A similar trend was observed in other studies including (Dai et al. <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>, Zapata et al. <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>, Halo et al. <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>). Although bacteria from the surrounding soil environment are drawn to root exudates, notable variations in the makeup of microbial communities across various plant species have been discovered. Findings by Ullah et al. (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) further demonstrated that the alpha diversity of the rhizosphere bacterial community is affected differently by cotton roots in drought-affected and normal conditions. Likewise, Wang et al. (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">2024a</xref>) reported that <italic toggle="yes">Medicago</italic> species subjected to drought had different fungal abundance. In their study, Basidiomycota, Tremellomycetes, Filobasidiales, Filobasidiaceae, and <italic toggle="yes">Filobasidium oeirense</italic> increased in <italic toggle="yes">M. sativa</italic> “Qingshui” and decreased in <italic toggle="yes">M. sativa</italic> “Longdong” and <italic toggle="yes">M. varia</italic> “Gongnong”. The relative abundance of Sordariomycetes, Hypocreales, and Nectriaceae decreased in <italic toggle="yes">M. sativa</italic> “Qingshui” and increased in <italic toggle="yes">M. varia</italic> “Gongnong”. On the other hand, Ascomycota, Dothideomycetes, Capnodiales, Cladosporiaceae, <italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Cladosporium sphaerospermum</italic> increased initially before declining and were at their lowest in all <italic toggle="yes">Medicago</italic> species under moderate stress.</p></sec><sec id="sec4-3"><title>Microbial assemblages influence plant adaptability to drought stress</title><p>Though these reviewed studies suggest a shift toward drought-tolerant micro-organisms, there is a general trend of a decline in total bacteria diversity in other studies (Xie et al. <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Nonetheless, microbial diversity does not signify reduced microbial functionality. By reducing diversity and altering the abundance of certain microbial species, drought dramatically changed microbial ecosystems in support of those that facilitate drought resilient (Liu et al. <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Beneficial microbes can encourage the creation of osmolytes, certain exudates, or peroxidase, which eliminates reactive oxygen species that are common during water stress (Allard-Massicotte et al. <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Under drought and salinity stress, plant phytohormone levels, particularly auxins such as indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), may decline; however, this can be compensated by IAA-producing rhizobacteria such as salt-tolerant <italic toggle="yes">Azospirillum brasilense</italic> NH, which enhance plant growth and stress tolerance (Nabti et al. <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Halo et al. (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>) found that the most prevalent genus on cowpea under drought stress was Nocardioides. Because they can break down a variety of chemical substances, including those that are persistent contaminants in the environment, Nocardioides species are significant to the ecosystem health and functionality. Drought-tolerant microbes are renowned for aiding in the natural biodegradation and bioremediation processes by decomposing hydrocarbons and aromatic chemicals. Their ecological relevance is further highlighted by the fact that they may flourish in a variety of settings, including those with low nutrient levels and even some polluted areas. In studies similar the one conducted by Marasco et al. (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), well-irrigated plants that had been inoculated with the rhizobacterial suspensions were abruptly subjected to a twelve-day water stress phase, demonstrating the potential of these species to support CSA. In the same study, control plants suffered significant damage following eight days of water stress, but plants inoculated with rhizobacteria showed increased shoot turgor.</p><p>Through a mutualistic interaction, microbial communities assist plants in fending off and recovering from abiotic challenges, increasing agricultural output and resilience (Liu et al. <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). For example, <italic toggle="yes">Azospirillum</italic> species in the rhizosphere improved plant water-use efficiency and nutrient uptake during drought conditions by producing osmolytes (e.g. proline and trehalose) and by stimulating root growth, thereby enhancing access to water in deeper soil layers (Prisa and Fresco <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Chloroflexi and Gemmatimonadetes are aerobic/anaerobic thermophilic bacteria that thrive in drought environments, as has been extensively described (Ward et al. <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Accordingly, these groups of bacterial phyla may improve their resistance to drought by using chloroflexi and gemmatimonadetes to support a variety of plant physiological processes during drought stress. To ascertain the role of plants in facilitating soil microbiota resilience to water stress, <italic toggle="yes">Populus trichocarpa</italic> colony and bulk soils without plants were subjected to prolonged drought (∼0.03% gravimetric water content), rewetting, and a 12-day recovery phase. Drought stimulation augmented host accumulation in C and N metabolic pathways (amino acids, fatty acids, phenolic glycosides), according to plant metabolomic analysis. In contrast to irrigated controls, the makeup of the soil bacterial community changed in response to <italic toggle="yes">P. trichocarpa</italic> and drought, while the composition of the soil fungal community changed only in response to plant presence (Veach et al. <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Sequences linked to metabolism, signaling transduction, defense mechanisms, and fundamental essential activities were shown to be enriched in the drought-treated rhizosphere, according to metagenomic profiling (Dai et al. <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). This finding may have consequences for plant survival and drought tolerance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Research gaps and prospects</title><p>The findings of this review should be interpreted in light of certain limitations. The included studies represent a wide range of geographic regions, plant species, and experimental conditions, which introduce heterogeneity and may limit direct comparability. Additionally, the relatively small number of studies (n = 31) means that some observations are based on a limited number of cases. As such, the conclusions drawn primarily reflect general trends rather than universally applicable outcomes. The reviewed studies varied considerably in taxonomic resolution, with some identifying microbes at species level, while others reported only genus- or family-level classifications, limiting the ability to accurately infer functional roles. The identification to phyla (Peng et al. <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>, Yang et al. <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>) and genus (Dai et al. <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) level could prove ecotoxic as species from the same genus could have positive and negative impact on the same plants. There are both positive and negative impacts that <italic toggle="yes">Aspergillus</italic> species may have on plants. While some species are plant pathogens, which cause diseases and financial losses, others are helpful, which through a variety of processes promote plant growth and health (Ramatsitsi et al. <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Plant root exudates selectively stimulate specific bacteria and fungi to colonize roots, thereby shaping rhizosphere microbial communities (Hartmann et al. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Moreover, in such studies, it could be argued that less accurate conclusions could be drawn. For instance, the study by Yang et al. (<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>) concluded that both drought and vegetation had no impact of fungi composition. However, this study only identified fungi to phylum level, Ascomycota. Within this phyla hundreds of fungal species have been identified, some pathogenic and some beneficial. As such, though overall composition may not have been significantly impacted, it is possible that there were significant effects of fungi diversity. Species level identification further allows for inoculation of isolates that have been identified to not only tolerate drought but also improve plant growth under drought stress. There have been fewer studies such as thobe by Cao et al. (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>) and Wang et al. (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">2024b</xref>), that have inoculated known drought-tolerant species to increase crop growth. Advancement of research in this area would immensely assist the promotion and application of soil microbes in CSA in regions where water scarcity affects crop productivity. Conversely, cultivating plants, through intercropping, that facilitate sporulation of drought-tolerant microbes could be practiced improving growth of plants that are affected by water scarcity. This is especially true in cases where the inoculated drought-resistant microbes cannot be sustained by the cultivated plant, as it was clear in the current review that different plants promote different groups of microbes.</p><p>The reviewed papers provide an indication that plants can survive drought periods by influencing micro-organisms that live in the rhizosphere. Studies including those by Pivato et al. (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), noted differences in microbial diversity between rhizospheric and bulk soil, indicating that these plants possibly formed a symbiotic relationship with drought-resilient microbes. However, limited studies have explicitly evaluated plant root exudation under drought stress. It is well established that, under stress conditions, plants release specific metabolites that selectively stimulate microbial communities associated with stress mitigation (Hartmann et al. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). For instance, drought elevated the exudation of organic acids in maize, especially malic acid (together with fumaric, malonic, succinic, and oxalic acids (Henry et al. <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), which is a powerful chemoattractant for <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> (Allard-Massicotte et al. <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Through the activation of osmolyte secretion, the beneficial bacterial species <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> promotes drought tolerance in <italic toggle="yes">Phleum pratense</italic> L. (Gagné-Bourque et al. <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas putida</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. amyloliquefaciens</italic> are rhizosphere bacteria in chickpea that mitigate the effects of drought (Kumar et al. <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Although the precise chemical signals mediating these interactions are not fully understood, root exudates are widely recognized as key drivers of plant–microbe interactions, functioning as signaling molecules, chemoattractants, and nutrient sources for beneficial microbes (Hartmann et al. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Plant responses to drought may therefore be partly mediated by species-specific changes in root exudation patterns, which influence the structure and function of associated microbial communities. These plant–microbe interactions can, in turn, affect plant recovery and broader ecosystem functioning. Even though there are still a lot of unanswered questions, the data makes it abundantly evident that changes in root exudation patterns brought on by drought might affect rhizosphere functions and perhaps affect how an ecosystem responds to drought. Through metabolomic profiling of root exudates in conjunction with focused evaluations of bacterial and fungal communities, advancing towards CSA that addresses productivity arid and semi-arid regions could be achieved.</p><p>Limited data on how soil management practices (cover crops, reduced tillage, organic amendments) influence microbial resilience to drought. The incorporation of proper production practices to foster microbial communities that can maintain soil functionality under water stress. By increasing the diversity, quantity, and activity of soil micro-organisms, soil management techniques can greatly increase their resistance to drought. Beneficial micro-organisms’ capacity to tolerate and recover from drought stress can be increased by employing techniques including conservation agriculture, the application of organic amendments, and strategic nutrient management. In other studies, such as Lozano et al. (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), wherein there was considerable abundance of pathogenic fungal species, conservation agriculture could promote beneficial micro-organisms as this system has been reported to promote beneficial soil microbes. For instance, by minimizing soil disturbance through reduced or no-tillage techniques, beneficial microbial populations can thrive in a more stable environment that maintains soil structure, lowers erosion, and conserves moisture (Xia et al. <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The same is true for using cover crops and incorporating crop residue. Crop residues retained on the soil’s surface offer an organic matter supply that supports microbial activity and enhances soil structure, improving microbial resilience and water retention. Cover crops, particularly those with deep roots, can improve soil structure, boost microbial diversity, and promote water penetration, all of which improve drought tolerance (Taskin et al. <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas, Burkholderiales</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Rhizobiales</italic> are some examples of beneficial micro-organisms that are known to increase plant growth and improve drought tolerance and are fostered by conservation agricultural approaches (Kost et al. <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Concluding remarks</title><p>Since water availability is clearly a major limiting factor in plant output, the health, and functionality of agroecosystems may be particularly vulnerable to climate change. Drought is an abiotic stress that modifies the soil environment and impact soil organisms, which is a substantial, concerning, and dangerous circumstance. The activity and functional composition of soil bacteria and fungi that oversee essential ecosystem services and functions are changed. Plant anatomy, physiology, biochemistry, and morphology are all directly impacted by drought. The synergy that exists between plants and microbes can be mediated to improve drought tolerance. It is imperative to note that rhizosphere microbial communities have potential to lessen the detrimental impacts of drought on plants by modifying their structural and functional makeup in response to water shortage. According to the reviewed literature, drought stress dramatically changes the diversity and quantity of epiphytic and rhizosphere bacterial and fungal communities, which affects the soil ecological balance and plant performance. The findings demonstrate how microbial resistance to drought promote plant resilience by mitigating water shortage stress, offering valuable insights for promoting CSA and creating microbial-based techniques to increase crop yields in areas vulnerable to drought. In the face of climate change, in particular, soil microbial populations play a crucial role in promoting resilience and resistance in ecosystems, thereby restoring soil functionality and maintenance of plant health. Microbiomes support plant health, which helps restore ecological processes such as carbon sequestration and nutrient cycling and lessens the impact of climate change. Improved plant resilience to drought stress is another way that microbiomes lessen the need for advanced irrigation systems. These drought-adapted species’ phylogenetic grouping raises the possibility that their capacity to endure drought environments is linked to evolutionary ties. These results demonstrate how the rhizospheric microbiome may contribute to plant drought tolerance, which may have implications for farming methods including the production of biofertilizer for areas that are prone to drought.</p><p>Under drought conditions, microbial diversity and biomass often declines, fragmenting soil microbial networks and reducing ecosystem functionality. Nonetheless, spore-forming and exopolysaccharide-producing bacteria and fungi, such as <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces</italic>, tend to increase in relative abundance due to their enhanced tolerance to osmotic stress. Drought favors drought-resilient bacteria and fungi phyla such as Actinobacteria, Firmicutes, and Chloroflexi, which possess structural and metabolic adaptations for low water environments. Despite reductions in microbial richness, these stress-adapted taxa maintain essential functions such as nutrient cycling, growth promotion, and stress mitigation. Endophytic communities are often more affected than rhizospheric ones, as their survival is closely tied to plant internal physiology and water status. Microbial shifts under drought correlate with changes in plant metabolome profiles, reflecting a coordinated response between plants and microbiomes. Plants dynamically alter the quantity and composition of root exudates in response to drought, with patterns influenced by species identity, drought severity and time. Moreover, plant resistance to drought may be influenced by the prevalence of drought-tolerant ectomycorrhizal species, such as <italic toggle="yes">Cenococcum geophilum</italic>, or the transition of mycorrhizal groups from ectomycorrhiza to arbuscular mycorrhizae fungi. Supporting local and global initiatives for promoting sustainable agriculture to provide food and nutrition security while including essential adaptation and mitigation is the overarching goal of CSA. To achieve this goal, three primary objectives are established: (i) increasing agricultural productivity in a sustainable manner; (ii) adapting and strengthening resilience to climate change at the farm and national levels; and (iii) creating opportunities to lower greenhouse gas emissions from agriculture in comparison to historical trends. It is not implied that every practice used in every site should provide these “threefold wins”, even while CSA strives to achieve all three goals. While these findings highlight important trends, further research across diverse systems is required to strengthen the generalizability of these conclusions.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec9"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Ndivhuwo Ramatsitsi (Conceptualization, Investigation, Writing – original draft), Alen Manyevere (Investigation, Writing – review &amp; editing).</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Funding</title><p>This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ajala</surname>  <given-names>OA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ajibade</surname>  <given-names>FO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Oluwadipe</surname>  <given-names>OR</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Microbial impact on climate-smart agricultural practices</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname>  <given-names>LFR</given-names></string-name></person-group> (eds.). <source>Microbiome under Changing Climate</source>. <publisher-name>Woodhead Publishing: Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>Cambridge (UK), 2022</year>, <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Albracht</surname>  <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenhauer</surname>  <given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Effects of recurrent summer droughts on arbuscular mycorrhizal and total fungal communities in experimental grasslands differing in plant diversity and community composition</article-title>. <source>Front Soil Sci</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>3:1129845</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fsoil.2023.1129845</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Allard-Massicotte</surname>  <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tessier</surname>  <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lécuyer</surname>  <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> early colonization of <italic toggle="yes">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> roots involves multiple chemotaxis receptors</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7:e01664-16</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mbio.01664-16</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5137498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Andreo-Jimenez</surname>  <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vandenkoornhuyse</surname>  <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lê Van</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Plant host and drought shape the root associated fungal microbiota in rice</article-title>. <source>PeerJ</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e7463</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7463</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31565550</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6744933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Azadi</surname>  <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Moghaddam</surname>  <given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Burkart</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Rethinking resilient agriculture: from climate-smart agriculture to vulnerable-smart agriculture</article-title>. <source>J Cleaner Prod</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>319</volume>:<fpage>128602</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2021.128602</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Basyal</surname>  <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname>  <given-names>BJ.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi enhance yield and photosynthesis of switchgrass (<italic toggle="yes">Panicum virgatum</italic> L.) under extreme drought and alters the biomass composition of the host plant</article-title>. <source>Biomass Bioenergy</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>177</volume>:<fpage>106936</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biombioe.2023.106936</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Birnbaum</surname>  <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname>  <given-names>AJM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fontaine</surname>  <given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Soil fungal responses to experimental warming and drying in a Mediterranean shrubland</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>683</volume>:<fpage>524</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.05.222</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31146058</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Bogati</surname>  <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Walczak</surname>  <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>The impact of drought stress on soil microbial community, enzyme activities and plants</article-title>. <source>Agronomy</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agronomy12010189</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Buscardo</surname>  <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname>  <given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Meir</surname>  <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Effects of natural and experimental drought on soil fungi and biogeochemistry in an Amazon rain forest</article-title>. <source>Commun Earth Environ</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43247-021-00124-8</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Cao</surname>  <given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>  <given-names>WX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname>  <given-names>YN</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>An endophytic fungus, <italic toggle="yes">piriformospora indica</italic>, enhances drought tolerance of trifoliate orange by modulating the antioxidant defense system and composition of fatty acids</article-title>. <source>Tree Physiol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>452</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/treephys/tpac126</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36263985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Carbone</surname>  <given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Alaniz</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mondino</surname>  <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Drought influences fungal community dynamics in the grapevine rhizosphere and root microbiome</article-title>. <source>J Fungi</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>686</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof7090686</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8468433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34575724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Chaudhry</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sidhu</surname>  <given-names>GPS.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Climate change regulated abiotic stress mechanisms in plants: a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Rep</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-021-02759-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34351488</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Dai</surname>  <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>  <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname>  <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Effect of drought stress and developmental stages on microbial community structure and diversity in peanut rhizosphere soil</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>2265</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20092265</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31071918</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6540327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>de Souza</surname>  <given-names>YPA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Siani</surname>  <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Albracht</surname>  <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>The effect of successive summer drought periods on bacterial diversity along a plant species richness gradient</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>100:fiae096</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsec/fiae096</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11264299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38955391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>de Vries</surname>  <given-names>FT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname>  <given-names>RI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Soil bacterial networks are less stable under drought than fungal networks</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>3033</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-05516-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30072764</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6072794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ehinmitan</surname>  <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Losenge</surname>  <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mamati</surname>  <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Characterization of drought-tolerant bacterial strain from semiarid soil of kenya for plant growth promotion and drought stress amelioration</article-title>. <source>Int J Agro</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>2025:3965809</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/ioa/3965809</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Engel</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname>  <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Payments for environmental services to promote “climate-smart agriculture”? Potential and challenges</article-title>. <source>Agricultural Economics</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/agec.12307</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gagné-Bourque</surname>  <given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bertrand</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Claessens</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Alleviation of drought stress and metabolic changes in timothy (<italic toggle="yes">Phleum pratense</italic> L.) colonized with <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> B26</article-title>. <source>Front Plant Sci</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>584</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.00584</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27200057</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4854170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Gargallo-Garriga</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sardans</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Pérez-Trujillo</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Warming differentially influences the effects of drought on stoichiometry and metabolomics in shoots and roots</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>207</volume>:<fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13377</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25772030</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Halo</surname>  <given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aljabri</surname>  <given-names>YAS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yaish</surname>  <given-names>MW.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Drought-induced microbial dynamics in cowpea rhizosphere: exploring bacterial diversity and bioinoculant prospects</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>e0320197</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0320197</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40132013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11936235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Hartmann</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schid</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>van Tuinen</surname>  <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Plant-driven selection of microbes</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>321</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-008-9814-y</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Hawkes</surname>  <given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kivlin</surname>  <given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rocca</surname>  <given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Fungal community responses to precipitation</article-title>. <source>Glob Chang Biol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1637</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2010.02327.x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Heikonen</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heino</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jalava</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Climate change threatens crop diversity at low latitudes</article-title>. <source>Nat Food</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>331</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43016-025-01135-w</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40038529</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12018264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Henry</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Doucette</surname>  <given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Norton</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Changes in crested wheatgrass root exudation caused by flood, drought, and nutrient stress</article-title>. <source>J of Env Quality</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>904</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jeq2006.0425sc</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17485723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Hopkins</surname>  <given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ruthrof</surname>  <given-names>KX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fontaine</surname>  <given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Forest die-off following global-change-type drought alters rhizosphere fungal communities</article-title>. <source>Environ Res Lett</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>,<fpage>095006</fpage>, :095006. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/aadc19</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Huber</surname>  <given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sikorski</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Differential response of acidobacteria to water content, soil type, and land use during an extended drought in African Savannah soils</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>13:750456</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.750456</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8874233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35222321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Hussain</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mubeen</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Climate smart agriculture (CSA) technologies</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jatoi</surname>  <given-names>WN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mubeen</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Cheema</surname>  <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname>  <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hashmi</surname>  <given-names>MZ</given-names></string-name></person-group> (eds.), <source>Building Climate Resilience in Agriculture: Theory, Practice and Future Perspective</source>. <publisher-loc>Cham (Switzerland)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <year>2022</year>, <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-79408-8</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Junaid</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gokce</surname>  <given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Global agricultural losses and their causes</article-title>. <source>Bull Biol All Sci Res</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>2024</volume>,<fpage>66</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.54112/bbasr.v2024i1.66</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Kost</surname>  <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Kundel</surname>  <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Conz</surname>  <given-names>RF</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Microbial resistance and resilience to drought under organic and conventional farming</article-title>. <source>Biorxiv</source>. <year>2024</year>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.04.17.589021</pub-id>. <comment>bioRxiv</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Kumar</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yusuf</surname>  <given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname>  <given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas putida</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> alleviates the adverse effect of pesticides and poise soil enzymes activities in chickpea (<italic toggle="yes">Cicer arietinum</italic> L.) rhizosphere</article-title>. <source>Trop Plant Res</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22271/tpr.2017.v4.i3.054</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Lagueux</surname>  <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jumpponen</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Porras-Alfaro</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Experimental drought re-ordered assemblages of root-associated fungi across North American grasslands</article-title>. <source>J Ecol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>776</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2745.13505</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Legeay</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Errafii</surname>  <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ziami</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>The rhizosphere of a drought-tolerant plant species in Morocco: a refuge of high microbial diversity with no taxon preference</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol Rep</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>16:e13254</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1758-2229.13254</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11082428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38725134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Liu</surname>  <given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname>  <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>  <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Response of sugarcane rhizosphere bacterial community to drought stress</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12:716196</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.716196</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8527094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34690961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Lozano</surname>  <given-names>YM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar-Trigueros</surname>  <given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Drought induces shifts in soil fungal communities that can be linked to root traits across 24 plant species</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>232</volume>:<fpage>1917</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.17707</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34480754</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Maisnam</surname>  <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffries</surname>  <given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Szejgis</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Severe prolonged drought favours stress-tolerant microbes in Australian drylands</article-title>. <source>Microb Ecol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>3097</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-023-02303-w</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37878053</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10640424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Maitra</surname>  <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname>  <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>  <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Effect of drought and season on arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi in a subtropical secondary forest</article-title>. <source>Fungal Ecol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.funeco.2019.04.005</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Marasco</surname>  <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Rolli</surname>  <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ettoumi</surname>  <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>A drought resistance-promoting microbiome is selected by root system under desert farming</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e48479</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0048479</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23119032</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3485337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Mazumder</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharya</surname>  <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Lahiri</surname>  <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Rhizobacteria and arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) community in growth management and mitigating stress in millets: a plant-soil microbe symbiotic relationship</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-025-04230-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40220175</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Moore</surname>  <given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname>  <given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Heneghan</surname>  <given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Microbial drivers of plant performance during drought depend upon community composition and the greater soil environment</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e01476</fpage>–<lpage>01422</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.01476-22</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36943043</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10101012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Nabti</surname>  <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sahnoune</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Ghoul</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Restoration of growth of durum wheat (<italic toggle="yes">Triticum durum</italic> var. waha) under saline conditions due to inoculation with the rhizosphere bacterium <italic toggle="yes">Azospirillum brasilense</italic> NH and extracts of the marine alga <italic toggle="yes">ulva lactuca</italic></article-title>. <source>J Plant Growth Regul</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00344-009-9107-6</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Page</surname>  <given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname>  <given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Bossuyt</surname>  <given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>The PRISMA 2020 statement: an updated guideline for reporting systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>372</volume>. <fpage>n71</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n71</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33782057</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8005924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Peng</surname>  <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname>  <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Soil microbial composition, diversity, and network stability in intercropping versus monoculture responded differently to drought</article-title>. <source>Agriculture, Ecosystems &amp; Environment</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>365</volume>:<fpage>108915</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2024.108915</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Philippot</surname>  <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname>  <given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Langenheder</surname>  <given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Microbial community resilience across ecosystems and multiple disturbances</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>85:e00026-20</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mmbr.00026-20</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8139522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33789927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Pivato</surname>  <given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Semblat</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guégan</surname>  <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Rhizosphere bacterial networks, but not diversity, are impacted by pea-wheat intercropping</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>674556</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.674556</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34127925</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8195745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Prisa</surname>  <given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fresco</surname>  <given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Inoculants for plant drought stress tolerance: mechanisms and applications</article-title>. <source>Preprint</source>. <year>2023</year>;<fpage>2023061995</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20944/preprints202306.1995.v1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ramatsitsi</surname>  <given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Khosa</surname>  <given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Mashamaite</surname>  <given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> assessment of eight selected indigenous fungal isolates tolerance to various abiotic stresses and their effects on seed germination</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>80</volume>:<fpage>386</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-023-03507-6</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37875629</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10598106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ritchie</surname>  <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Roser</surname>  <given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Land use: how has global land use changed over the long term?</article-title>. <source>Our World in Data</source>. <year>Global Change Data Lab, Oxford, UK; 2024. (Accessed 12 January 2026)</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/land-use" ext-link-type="uri">https://ourworldindata.org/land-use</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Rolli</surname>  <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Marasco</surname>  <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Vigani</surname>  <given-names>G</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Improved plant resistance to drought is promoted by the root-associated microbiome as a water stress-dependent trait</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.12439</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24571749</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Schmidt</surname>  <given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname>  <given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Otte</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Season-long experimental drought alters fungal community composition but not diversity in a grassland soil</article-title>. <source>Microb Ecol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>468</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-017-1047-2</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28785816</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tang</surname>  <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname>  <given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>  <given-names>S</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Increasing synchrony of extreme heat and precipitation events under climate warming</article-title>. <source>Geophys Res Lett</source>. <year>2025</year>;<volume>52:e2024GL113021</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2024GL113021</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Taskin</surname>  <given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Boselli</surname>  <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorini</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Combined impact of no-till and cover crops with or without short-term water stress as revealed by physicochemical and microbiological indicators</article-title>. <source>Biology</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biology10010023</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33401423</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7824270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Tong</surname>  <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>  <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fensholt</surname>  <given-names>R</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Global area boom for greenhouse cultivation revealed by satellite mapping</article-title>. <source>Nat Food</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>513</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43016-024-00985-0</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38741004</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Trivedi</surname>  <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Leach</surname>  <given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Tringe</surname>  <given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Plant–microbiome interactions: from community assembly to plant health</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Micro</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-020-0412-1</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32788714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ullah</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Akbar</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname>  <given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Microbiome diversity in cotton rhizosphere under normal and drought conditions</article-title>. <source>Microb Ecol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>429</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-018-1260-7</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30196314</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<collab>UN (United Nations)</collab>
</person-group>. <article-title>The global threat of drying lands: regional and global aridity trends and future projections</article-title>. <year>2024. (Accessed 12 January 2026)</year>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.unccd.int/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.unccd.int/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Veach</surname>  <given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname>  <given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname>  <given-names>ZK</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Plant hosts modify belowground microbial community response to extreme drought</article-title>. <source>mSystems</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>5:e00092-20</volume>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/msystems.00092-20</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7329318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32606021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Vives-Peris</surname>  <given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>De Ollas</surname>  <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Gómez-Cadenas</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Root exudates: from plant to rhizosphere and beyond</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Rep</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-019-02447-5</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31346716</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>  <given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Nan</surname>  <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname>  <given-names>Q.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Changes in root endogenous hormone levels and rhizosphere fungi diversity in alfalfa under drought stress</article-title>. <source>Plant Growth Regul</source>. <year>2024a</year>;<volume>102</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10725-023-01062-5</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Wang</surname>  <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname>  <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname>  <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Drought-induced changes in rare microbial community promoted contribution of microbial necromass C to SOC in a subtropical forest</article-title>. <source>Soil Biol Biochem</source>. <year>2024b</year>;<volume>189</volume>:<fpage>109252</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.soilbio.2023.109252</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Ward</surname>  <given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Hemp</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname>  <given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Evolution of phototrophy in the <italic toggle="yes">chloroflexi phylum</italic> driven by horizontal gene transfer</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00260</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29515543</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5826079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Williams</surname>  <given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>de Vries</surname>  <given-names>FT.</given-names></string-name></person-group>  <article-title>Plant root exudation under drought: implications for ecosystem functioning</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>225</volume>:<fpage>1899</fpage>–<lpage>905</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.16223</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31571220</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Wu</surname>  <given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>  <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname>  <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Drought stress increases the complexity of the bacterial network in the rhizosphere and endosphere of rice (<italic toggle="yes">Oryza sativa</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Agronomy</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1662</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agronomy14081662</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Xia</surname>  <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname>  <given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname>  <given-names>L</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Effects of tillage managements and maize straw returning on soil microbiome using 16S rDNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>JIPB</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jipb.12802</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30912294</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Xie</surname>  <given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Dawwam</surname>  <given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Sehim</surname>  <given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Drought stress triggers shifts in the root microbial community and alters functional categories in the microbial gene pool</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>744897</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.744897</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34745045</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8566882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Yang</surname>  <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Loik</surname>  <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname>  <given-names>X</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>Drought and vegetation restoration lead to shifts in soil microbial diversity and co-occurrence networks in California coastal prairie</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>. <year>2024</year>;<volume>512</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>., <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-024-06625-7</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name name-style="western">
<surname>Zapata</surname>  <given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Galindo</surname>  <given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name name-style="western"><surname>Corrales-Ducuara</surname>  <given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>  <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>  <article-title>The diversity of culture-dependent gram-negative rhizobacteria associated with <italic toggle="yes">Manihot esculenta</italic> Crantz plants subjected to water-deficit stress</article-title>. <source>Diversity</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/d13080366</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>