<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2873</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ncomms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Nat Commun</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12923533</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12923533</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12923533</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41565653</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-026-68586-y</article-id><title-group><article-title>Air quality improvement masks global cooling from CO<sub>2</sub> reductions under China’s carbon neutrality policies for half a century</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="B">Bin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_eqcntrb93pmc__">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaochun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_eqcntrb93pmc__">#</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yisheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names initials="D">Da</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="J">Junxi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuqiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Shindell</surname><given-names initials="D">Drew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names initials="SJ">Steven J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="G">Guangxing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names initials="B">Biwu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff11">11</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12">12</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff13">13</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="H">Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff11">11</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12">12</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="K">Kebin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="S">Shuxiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>State Key Laboratory of Regional Environment and Sustainability, School of Environment, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Key Laboratory of Sources and Control of Air Pollution Complex, Ministry of Ecology and Environment, The People’s Republic of China, Beijing, China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Earth System Science, Stanford University, Stanford, CA USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Frontiers Science Center for Deep Ocean Multispheres and Earth System, Ocean University of China, Qingdao, China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Key Laboratory of Marine Environmental Science and Ecology, Ministry of Education, Ocean University of China, Qingdao, China </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Qingdao National Laboratory for Marine Science and Technology, Qingdao, China </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label>State Key Laboratory of Clean Energy Utilization, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label>Environment Research Institute, Shandong University, Qingdao, China </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label>Nicholas School of the Environment, Duke University, Durham, NC USA </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label>10</label>College of Ocean and Earth Sciences, Xiamen University, Xiamen, China </aff><aff id="Aff11"><label>11</label>State Key Joint Laboratory of Environment Simulation and Pollution Control, Re-search Center for Eco-Environmental Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China </aff><aff id="Aff12"><label>12</label>College of Resources and Environment, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China </aff><aff id="Aff13"><label>13</label>Institute of Atmospheric Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn><fn id="_eqcntrb93pmc__"><label>#</label><p>Contributed equally.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><fpage>1914</fpage><page-range>1914</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_Article_68586.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path cd38/12923533/189819f9bf41/41467_2026_Article_68586.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2618512?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Achieving carbon neutrality and improving air quality are pivotal sustainability strategies for the Global South countries. However, their global climate impacts over a realistic timescale remain unclear. Here we evaluate the climate impacts of China’s carbon neutrality and Beautiful China policies using a fully coupled Earth system model and updated future anthropogenic emission scenarios. We find that, for an unexpectedly long time through ~2070, China’s air pollutant reductions can cause a large global surface warming (0.12 ± 0.09 K for 2050–2070) that almost offsets the cooling from concurrent CO<sub>2</sub> emission reduction (0.16 ± 0.05 K for 2050–2070), compared to a business-as-usual scenario. This warming is mainly attributed to reduced SO<sub>2</sub> and organic matter emissions. Moreover, combined air pollutants and CO<sub>2</sub> declines create a striking hemispheric temperature change contrast, because of the stronger aerosol-induced heating in the Northern Hemisphere. Considering that most future air pollutant reductions represent synergistic effects of carbon neutrality policies, the associated inevitable warming effect over decades highlights the importance of exploring more aggressive policies including early carbon neutrality, methane reductions, and negative carbon emissions.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Environmental impact, Atmospheric science</p></sec></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">China’s carbon neutrality and clean-air policies cause global warming from reduced aerosols that nearly offsets cooling from reduced CO2 before 2060, with warming emerging afterwards, calling for early carbon neutrality and more mitigation strategies.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 May 7; Accepted 2026 Jan 12; Collection date 2026.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Earth’s mean temperature increased to more than 1.5 °C above pre-industrial levels for the first time in 2024<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. To limit the continuous warming and avoid more disastrous consequences of climate change, achieving global carbon neutrality by the second half of the century is essential and urgent<sup><xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. Meanwhile, large parts of the world, especially Global South countries like China and India, face grand challenges in alleviating severe aerosol pollution<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>, which causes over three million premature deaths annually<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. Achieving carbon neutrality and improving air quality are thus pivotal strategies for the sustainable development of Global South countries. For example, as one of the large annual emitters of CO<sub>2</sub> and short-lived air pollutants, China has pledged to achieve carbon neutrality by 2060 and fully realize a Beautiful China by 2050. The latter can be interpreted as China should at least meet the World Health Organization’s (WHO) 2005 guideline (10 μg m<sup>−3</sup> for annual mean concentration of fine particulate matter, PM<sub>2.5</sub>) and strive to achieve the 2021 guideline (5 μg m<sup>−3</sup>), the attainment of which requires additional clean air measures beyond carbon neutrality<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>–<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Such regional carbon neutrality and clean air policies, by changing both CO<sub>2</sub> and aerosols, will have complex region- and time-dependent climate impacts. Specifically, compared with the well-mixed CO<sub>2</sub>, the climate impact of aerosol reduction depends strongly on the region where the policies are implemented, because of the large spatial heterogeneity in aerosol compositions, chemical regimes, and topographical and climate characteristics<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. Moreover, the climate impacts of aerosol and CO<sub>2</sub> reductions occur on distinct time scales, with the former manifesting much sooner because of the shorter lifetime of aerosols<sup><xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. It is thus important to quantify the global climate impacts of each region’s carbon neutrality and clean-air policies on a realistic time scale to develop mitigation policies tailored for individual regions.</p><p id="Par4">Previous studies on the climate impacts of decarbonization and clean-air policies have mostly considered the global policies as a whole, with the most well-known being the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 6 (CMIP6)<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. Moreover, the Detection and Attribution Model Intercomparison Project (DAMIP), as part of CMIP6, has worked to separate the contributions of individual forcings (e.g., changes in aerosols and greenhouse gases) to global climate change<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. However, only a couple of studies have examined the impact of regional decarbonization or clean-air policies on global climate change. A previous modeling assessment<sup><xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> showed that the net effect of United States reductions in all emissions consistent with 2 °C warming would avoid 0.03–0.07 °C global warming in 2030 and 0.15–0.25 °C in 2100. Without considering the effect of concurrent air pollutant reductions, a previous study<sup><xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> showed that China’s CO<sub>2</sub> reduction under carbon neutrality would lower global mean temperature by 0.40–0.48 °C by the end of this century compared to scenarios representing less stringent climate policies. In contrast, another study<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> evaluated the climate impacts of China’s aerosol reductions without considering the influence of CO<sub>2</sub> changes. They showed that the aerosol reduction associated with achieving carbon neutrality by 2060 might increase global mean temperature by 0.23 °C under climate equilibrium, which is a hypothetical condition that would not be achieved unless all emissions remained constant for nearly 100 years. Nevertheless, regional CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant emissions will inevitably change simultaneously and progressively, especially under anticipated carbon neutrality and clean air policies. The climate impacts of concurrent regional CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant emission reductions, as well as their temporal evolution over a realistic policy-relevant timescale (e.g., from the present to 2060 and 2100), remain unclear.</p><p id="Par5">Here we employ a comprehensive and fully coupled Earth System Model, the Community Earth System Model version 2 (CESM2), to evaluate the climate impacts of both simultaneous and separate CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant emission reductions in China, under the carbon neutrality and Beautiful China strategies on a realistic timescale in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. In contrast to previous studies, we conduct long-term, fully coupled, transient simulations (representing time-varying radiative forcing in a realistic manner) with full interactions of all key components of the climate system, including dynamic oceans, biogeochemical systems, and chemistry-climate interactions. Unexpectedly, our findings reveal that, for half a century through ~2070, the global surface temperature increase from China’s air pollutant reductions relative to a business-as-usual (BAU) scenario largely offsets the cooling from China’s CO<sub>2</sub> reduction. This contrasts with previous studies that suggested that global or United States decarbonization policies would quickly contribute to temperature decreases<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. Intriguingly, the combined air pollutant and CO<sub>2</sub> reductions create contrasting temperature and precipitation changes in the two hemispheres. The inevitable and persistent offsetting effect underscores the importance of achieving carbon neutrality early, promoting methane reduction, and achieving negative carbon emissions in the long run.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Changes in CO<sub>2</sub> and aerosols for 2050–2070 under control policies</title><p id="Par6">Three emission scenarios for China, developed by a technology-rich provincial-level integrated assessment model<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>, are investigated in this study: (1) a BAU scenario, defined by the climate and air pollution control policies enacted as of 2020, assumes that carbon emissions peak around 2030 and then decline slightly; (2) a carbon neutrality and clean air (CNCA) scenario, which assumes the achievement of carbon neutrality by 2060, followed by negative carbon emissions, along with stricter clean air policies in line with the 2050 Beautiful China vision; and (3) a sensitivity scenario (SENS), which combines the CO<sub>2</sub> emissions from CNCA with the air pollutant emissions from BAU to help isolate the impacts of CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions. The integrated assessment model fully accounts for China’s recent development path and policies and thus realistically reproduces recent and anticipated near-future emission trends, e.g., the constantly increasing CO<sub>2</sub> emissions until about 2030 and the swiftly decreasing emissions of major air pollutants in the previous decade (2010–2020); such trends are not visible in the shared socioeconomic pathways (SSPs) with overall comparable stringency (SSP2-4.5, SSP1-2.6, and SSP1-1.9, see Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>), which show that China’s CO<sub>2</sub> emissions have been decreasing since 2020 but the air pollutant emissions have been decreasing much slower than in reality. For the rest of the world, we use SSP2-4.5, which represents a future with moderate climate policies. For each emission scenario, we average over five ensemble members with small perturbations to the initial conditions derived from historical-era simulations to minimize the impact of internal variability in the climate system.</p><p id="Par7">We first focus our analysis on 2050–2070, a twenty-year period centering around 2060 when China is expected to achieve carbon neutrality. Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the difference in CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden between the CNCA and BAU scenarios (CNCA minus BAU, or CNCA − BAU) for 2050–2070. Global mean CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations are reduced by 23.5 ± 0.7 ppm (mean ± standard deviation), as a result of the year-by-year accumulation of CO<sub>2</sub> emission reduction driven by China’s carbon neutrality goal. The CO<sub>2</sub> concentration reductions are rather uniform globally, except for eastern China where the largest CO<sub>2</sub> emission reduction occurs, as it takes time for CO<sub>2</sub> to disperse evenly around the world. In contrast, air quality improvement in terms of PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden (excluding dust and sea salt) primarily occurs in and near China, with global and China mean reductions of 0.31 ± 0.10 mg m<sup>−2</sup> and 3.74 ± 0.11 mg m<sup>−2</sup>, respectively. The PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden reduction represents a combined effect of the carbon neutrality target and additional end-of-pipe control policies aligned with the Beautiful China vision. Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref> highlights that the implementation of carbon neutrality is responsible for over 80% of the emission reductions in all air pollutants except for volatile organic compounds (VOCs) around 2060.</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Overall and spatial differences in CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden under China’s carbon neutrality and clean air (CNCA) policies with respect to the business-as-usual (BAU) scenario for 2050–2070.</title><p><bold>A, C</bold> Mean differences in global and China (<bold>A</bold>) PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden and (<bold>C</bold>) CO<sub>2</sub> concentration. <bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold> Spatial distribution of the differences in (<bold>B</bold>) PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden and (<bold>D</bold>) CO<sub>2</sub> concentration. The results are averaged over 2050–2070, centered around 2060 when China is expected to achieve carbon neutrality. The calculation of PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden differences excluded dust and sea salt components that almost exclusively originate from natural sources, since differences in these components are not directly tied to mitigation policies. The spatial distributions of the differences in different PM<sub>2.5</sub> chemical components are given in Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>. The raincloud plots are constructed with 25 samples obtained by pairwise differencing of five ensemble members under two scenarios. The thick horizontal line represent median values, the central box indicate the interquartile range (25–75%), the thin vertical lines extending from the box display the data range (excluding outliers), and the width of the violin shape shows the kernel density estimation distribution of the data. The scattered points to the right of the box represent the individual data samples. The numbers on top of the raincloud plots represent mean values. Stippled areas in the spatial maps indicate statistical significance at the 95% confidence level based on a two-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic> test. Coastline boundaries in this and all subsequent figures and Supplementary Figs. were made with Natural Earth. Source data are provided with this paper.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e619" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/5e098d02b5e8/41467_2026_68586_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1057?><?original-width 1442?><?scaled-height 529?><?scaled-width 721?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/0a62ee88eaec/41467_2026_68586_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Global mean changes in climate variables for 2050–2070 due to control policies</title><p id="Par8">We first examine global mean difference in surface temperature (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>), the most commonly used climate metric, between the CNCA and BAU scenarios (CNCA−BAU) for 2050–2070, as well as the differences induced by CO<sub>2</sub> (SENS−BAU) and air pollutant (CNCA−SENS) emission reductions separately. Also shown are the corresponding differences in top-of-atmosphere (TOA) net radiation flux (shortwave + longwave) that are closely related to temperature differences (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>). The CO<sub>2</sub> emission reduction causes a decrease in the net TOA radiation flux and cools the surface by 0.16 ± 0.05 K relative to BAU, consistent with the mitigation of the greenhouse effect of CO<sub>2</sub>. In contrast, the reductions in air pollutant emissions increase the TOA net radiation, warming the surface by 0.12 ± 0.09 K, as a combined effect of aerosol–radiation interaction (ARI) and aerosol-cloud interactions (ACI). ACI likely plays a leading role in causing the temperature changes (see more in Supplementary Note <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>). The global warming from air pollutant reductions can largely offset the climate cooling benefit of CO<sub>2</sub> reduction even by around 2060, when net-zero CO<sub>2</sub> emissions are reached. The combined global effect is an insignificant cooling of −0.03 ± 0.09 K. Note that the magnitude of the above temperature differences is substantial, considering that emission controls are only implemented in a single country.</p><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Global mean differences in key climate variables under China’s carbon neutrality and clean air (CNCA) with respect to the business-as-usual (BAU) scenario for 2050–2070.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>) show the overall differences in (<bold>A</bold>) surface temperature and (<bold>B</bold>) top-of-atmosphere (TOA) net radiation under these policies relative to the BAU scenario (CNCA−BAU), as well as the respective differences induced by emission reductions of CO<sub>2</sub> (SENS − BAU, where SENS denotes sensitivity scenario) and air pollutants (CNCA−SENS). Panel (<bold>C</bold>) shows the Effective Radiative Forcing (ERF) due to the combined and individual emission reductions of air pollutants, including sulfur dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub>), primary organic matter (POM), black carbon (BC), and volatile organic compounds (VOCs). Note that results in (<bold>A</bold>) and (<bold>B</bold>) are derived from fully coupled simulations while those in (<bold>C</bold>) are derived from atmosphere-only simulations (see Methods). Interpretation of the raincloud plots is the same as that in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The numbers on top of the violin plots represent mean values. Source data are provided with this paper.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e684" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/059d040cbc51/41467_2026_68586_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 529?><?original-width 2001?><?scaled-height 176?><?scaled-width 667?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/f6bfea0c1132/41467_2026_68586_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par9">We further investigate how much individual air pollutant contributes to global climate, by quantifying their global mean effective radiative forcing (ERF). The details of additional sensitivity experiments can be found in Methods. Figure <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2C</xref> illustrates that the global mean ERF associated with the emission reductions of SO<sub>2</sub>, primary organic matter (POM), black carbon (BC), and VOCs are 0.045 ± 0.016 W m<sup>−2</sup>, 0.046 ± 0.024 W m<sup>−2</sup>, −0.018 ± 0.020 W m<sup>−2</sup>, and 0.017 ± 0.023 W m<sup>−2</sup>. These results clearly show that SO<sub>2</sub> and POM reductions are the dominant contributors to positive ERF, namely, reductions in sulfate- and POM-induced cooling drive most of the warming effect associated with air pollutant reductions. BC reductions contribute a negative ERF due to the removal of a warming agent, which partly offsets the sulfate- and POM-driven warming. VOC reductions contribute a smaller but non-negligible positive ERF, indicating that the decrease of secondary organic aerosol (SOA) also contributes to the warming effect.</p><p id="Par10">Precipitation is another key climate metric that affects water availability, agriculture, and the overall health of ecosystems. Under CNCA policies, the CO<sub>2</sub> reduction decreases global mean precipitation by 1.84 ± 1.53 mm year<sup>−1</sup> for 2050–2070, while the air pollutant reductions increase global mean precipitation remarkably by 2.28 ± 2.13 mm year<sup>−1</sup> relative to BAU (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>). The larger sensitivity to the air pollution reduction results in a small net precipitation increase for 2050–2070. The changes in precipitation are closely tied to the aforementioned warming and cooling of surface temperature, since global warming (cooling) leads to more (less) evaporation and subsequently more (less) precipitation<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Spatial changes in climate variables for 2050–2070 due to control policies</title><p id="Par11">The spatial pattern of temperature difference has important implications for assessing its regional impacts and developing mitigation and adaptation policies. While the emission reductions occur exclusively in China, the temperature and radiation differences exhibit an obvious global pattern (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A–B,D–E</xref>). A prominent feature is the polar amplification (especially the Arctic amplification), where the mean temperature differences induced by CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions in the Arctic region (−0.30 K and 0.47 K) are 1.9–3.9 times the global average values (−0.16 K and 0.12 K). While polar amplification has been previously reported in climate assessments of global emission changes<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>, our study indicates that such a pattern persists even when only China’s emission reductions are implemented. A likely explanation is that, following either CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions, energy perturbations originating at low- and mid-latitudes can be propagated poleward and get amplified through a positive feedback loop involving incoming energy surplus, sea ice melting, surface albedo, and surface temperature over the Arctic<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–<xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. Such feedback is confirmed by the simulated opposite albedo differences to temperature differences (see Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref>). The stronger Arctic amplification due to air pollutant reductions than that due to CO<sub>2</sub> reduction arises because the concentrated energy perturbations at northern mid-latitudes in the former case enhance poleward energy transport.</p><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Spatial differences in key climate variables under China’s carbon neutrality and clean air (CNCA) policies with respect to the business-as-usual (BAU) scenario for 2050–2070.</title><p><bold>A</bold>–<bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>–<bold>E</bold> Spatial distribution of the differences in (<bold>A–B</bold>) surface temperature and (<bold>D</bold>–<bold>E</bold>) top-of-atmosphere (TOA) net radiation due to emission reductions in (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>D</bold>) CO<sub>2</sub> (SENS−BAU, where SENS denotes sensitivity scenario) and (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>E</bold>) air pollutants (CNCA−SENS). <bold>C</bold>, <bold>F</bold> Meridional distribution of the differences in (<bold>C</bold>) surface temperature and (<bold>F</bold>) TOA net radiation under the CNCA policies relative to BAU (CNCA−BAU), as well as the respective differences induced by emission reductions of CO<sub>2</sub> (SENS−BAU) and air pollutants (CNCA−SENS). Stippled areas in the spatial maps indicate statistical significance at the 95% confidence level based on a two-tailed Student’s t-test. Error bars in the bar charts represent the 95% confidence intervals, also based on a two-tailed Student’s t-test. Source data are provided with this paper.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e807" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/3327f08c23b1/41467_2026_68586_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 848?><?original-width 2000?><?scaled-height 339?><?scaled-width 800?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/3761e88f15d0/41467_2026_68586_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par12">Another important feature is the hemispheric contrast in the temperature differences. Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref> shows the surface temperature differences averaged over different latitude bands in response to China’s CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions relative to BAU. The warming induced by air pollutant reductions is much greater in the Northern Hemisphere (0.22 ± 0.12 K) than in the Southern Hemisphere (0.02 ± 0.09 K), mainly because the dedicated emission reductions in China and the short lifetime of air pollutants result in their localized warming effect in the Northern Hemisphere. In contrast, the cooling effect of CO<sub>2</sub> reduction has a relatively small hemispheric difference, since CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations are much more evenly distributed over the world. The overall CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions result in contrasting temperature responses in the extratropical regions, with a net warming effect in the Northern Hemisphere and a cooling effect in the Southern Hemisphere (both statistically significant with <italic>p</italic>-values of 0.007 and &lt;0.001, respectively). This hemispheric asymmetry is consistent with recent observations of declining fine-mode aerosols globally and a greater trend in absorbed solar radiation (ASR) increase in the Northern Hemisphere relative to the Southern Hemisphere<sup><xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par13">In addition to the global pattern of climate impacts, regional hotspots of positive TOA radiation and surface temperature changes due to air pollutant reductions occur in China and the downwind North Pacific region (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3B, E</xref>), since the short lifespan of aerosols causes their concentration changes to be localized near the source (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1D</xref>, Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>). Below we explain the reasons behind such changes. Figure <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref> indicates that China’s air pollutant reductions cause a large decrease in aerosol optical depth (AOD), contributing to a positive clear-sky TOA radiation change via ARI. Moreover, following the aerosol loading decrease, the cloud droplet number decreases while the cloud droplet radius increases (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B, C</xref>), in line with the aerosol first indirect effect. The cloud water path also increases (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4D</xref>), probably through the aerosol second indirect effect, where the increased droplet radius enhances the collision and coalescence efficiency and fosters precipitation formation, leaving less cloud water in the atmosphere. The altered cloud radiative effect (defined as all-sky minus clear-sky radiative fluxes) by anthropogenic aerosol changes contributes to a positive TOA radiation change (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4F</xref>), which far exceeds the clear-sky radiation change (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4E</xref>). This suggests that ACI dominates over ARI in producing the positive TOA and temperature changes. It occurs both near China, where aerosol changes are greatest, and far downwind over the Pacific, where there are few other sources of particles.</p><fig id="Fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Spatial distribution of changes in aerosol and cloud properties as well as radiation fluxes due to air pollutant reductions for 2050–2070.</title><p>The six panels depict the changes in (<bold>A</bold>) aerosol optical depth, (<bold>B</bold>) cloud droplet number concentration (<bold>C</bold>) cloud droplet radius, (<bold>D</bold>) cloud water path, (<bold>E</bold>) clear-sky net shortwave flux at top-of-atmosphere (TOA), and (<bold>F</bold>) cloud radiative effects at TOA, due to air pollutant emission reductions. Stippled areas indicate statistical significance at the 95% confidence level based on a two-tailed Student’s t-test. Source data are provided with this paper.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e886" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/aa88d9527358/41467_2026_68586_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1522?><?original-width 1999?><?scaled-height 608?><?scaled-width 799?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig4_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/cfbe08c5cca0/41467_2026_68586_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par14">For precipitation differences induced by CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions, hotspots mainly occur over the tropical Pacific (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>A, B). The air pollutant reductions induce a strong precipitation increase in the northern tropics and a decrease in the southern tropics—a more prominent north-south contrast compared to the precipitation changes induced by global air pollutant changes<sup><xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>. Such a precipitation shift occurs because the stronger aerosol-induced heating in the Northern Hemisphere relative to the Southern Hemisphere causes a northward migration of the intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ). A diagnosis of the zonal mean position of the ITCZ following an existing method<sup><xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> confirms that ITCZ is displaced northward by 0.35 degree (statistically significant with a <italic>p</italic>-value of &lt;0.001). Compared to air pollutants, the CO<sub>2</sub> reduction induces a relatively weaker north-south contrast, with moderate precipitation decrease in the northern tropics and increase in the southern tropics, corresponding to a slight 0.14-degree southward displacement of ITCZ (not statistically significant). Averaged over hemispheres, the overall CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5C</xref>) result in a net positive precipitation change in the Northern Hemisphere and a negative precipitation change in the Southern Hemisphere (both statistically significant with <italic>p</italic>-values &lt; 0.001). A more in-depth discussion of the spatial precipitation changes in given in Supplementary Note <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="2"><title>Temporal evolutions of temperature and precipitation responses</title><p id="Par15">From 2015 through 2100, the global CO<sub>2</sub> concentration reduction relative to the BAU scenario due to the CNCA policies (CNCA−BAU) keeps increasing swiftly, while the PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden reduction in China increases rapidly through ~2050 and stabilizes thereafter (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The difference can be explained by the fact that CO<sub>2</sub> concentration hinges on the cumulative emission reduction over many decades, while the concentration of PM<sub>2.5</sub>, a short-lived forcing agent, primarily depends on air pollutant reductions in a given year. After ~2055, the CO<sub>2</sub> concentration reduction continues to grow due to the ongoing accumulation of CO<sub>2</sub> emission reduction and the use of negative carbon technologies; nevertheless, the PM<sub>2.5</sub> reduction stabilizes as the potential for further reducing air pollutants relative to BAU is largely exhausted (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>). Note that the PM<sub>2.5</sub> reduction even slightly decreases after 2075 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>), as air pollutant emissions in BAU continue to decline slowly with time due to gradual decarbonization (1.0–2.5% per year), while the air pollutant emissions in the CNCA scenario remain almost constant due to the limited reduction potential (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>). Accordingly, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref> shows that the global temperature increase driven by air pollutant reductions intensifies until around 2055–2060 and then levels off, while the temperature decrease from CO<sub>2</sub> reduction accelerates over time. The stabilization of air pollutant-induced temperature increase occurs later than the point at which PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden reductions roughly plateau (2045–2050), largely due to the ocean’s thermal inertia and its slow uptake of heat. As a result, before ~2070, the net global temperature difference under CNCA policies relative to BAU is not significantly different from zero, but after ~2070, the net temperature difference becomes significantly negative (<italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.001) and reaches −0.21 K for 2070–2100.</p><fig id="Fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Temporal evolution of climate responses induced by China’s carbon neutrality and clean air (CNCA) policies.</title><p><bold>A</bold> Differences in global mean CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and China mean PM<sub>2.5</sub> burden under the CNCA policies relative to business-as-usual (BAU) (CNCA−BAU). <bold>B</bold> Differences in global mean surface temperature caused by CO<sub>2</sub> reduction (blue, SENS−BAU, where SENS denotes sensitivity scenario), air pollutant reductions (red, CNCA−SENS), and their combined effect (black, CNCA−BAU). The lines represent the mean differences between two scenarios, and the shaded areas indicate one standard deviation of 25 samples obtained by pairwise differencing of five ensembles under the two scenarios. All values shown are 10-year running means. Source data are provided with this paper.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e985" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/6d94329279fd/41467_2026_68586_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 990?><?original-width 1343?><?scaled-height 495?><?scaled-width 671?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_Fig5_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/cd38/12923533/dfa10f43b1b8/41467_2026_68586_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par16">The time evolution of net global precipitation difference (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6A</xref>) closely resembles the trends in surface temperature, where air pollutant reductions drive an intensifying and then stabilizing precipitation increase, and CO<sub>2</sub> reduction drives an accelerating precipitation decrease. Slightly different from temperature, the net difference in global precipitation under CNCA policies relative to BAU remains insignificant until around 2080 (cf. ~2070 for temperature), after which a significant negative difference emerges. This indicates that, compared to temperature, air pollutant reductions tend to have a greater efficiency in increasing precipitation, probably because precipitation can be more directly modified by aerosols via ACI. In China, where the precipitation difference is much larger than the global average, the precipitation increase due to air pollutant reductions significantly outweighs the precipitation decrease from CO<sub>2</sub> reduction throughout the simulation period, resulting in a persistent net precipitation enhancement (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6B</xref>).</p><p id="Par17">The above findings update our understanding on the global climate impacts of regional decarbonization and clean air policies. The key conclusion that warming from air pollutant reductions can largely offset the cooling from CO<sub>2</sub> reductions for about half a century through ~2070 stand in clear contrast to previous studies<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> on the climate impacts of global and United States emission reductions. Specifically, on the global scale, the CMIP6 simulations showed that the differences in radiative forcing or temperature between different SSPs, which broadly reflect the effect of global greenhouse gas (GHG) mitigation or clean air policies, were mostly dominated by GHG reduction, with air pollutant reductions playing a relatively minor role<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. A previous study also revealed that, in the United States, where air pollutant emissions are relatively low, decarbonization policies will quickly contribute to a decrease in temperature before 2030<sup><xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. The stronger and more persistent warming effect of China’s air pollutant reductions than that revealed by CMIP6 global simulations and United States simulations is probably explained by (1) the higher intensity of air pollutant emissions in China as compared to developed countries and (2) the insufficient consideration of China’s aggressive clean air policies in SSPs. Note that this strong pollutant reduction-induced warming is unlikely to be attributed to the uncertainty of aerosol radiative forcing estimate, since the aerosol effective radiative forcing predicted by CESM2 is at a medium level among all CMIP6 models<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par18">The findings have important implications for the optimization of future climate and clean air policies in China. Even aggressive climate policies like carbon neutrality are not sufficient to cool the climate by ~2070 due to the compensating effect of air pollutant reductions, although a significant cooling effect is expected to unfold by 2100. We anticipate that the compensating effect would remain strong regardless of whether additional clean air policies were considered, since the synergistic effect of carbon neutrality, rather than the clean air policies, plays a dominant role (~80%) in reducing the emissions of most air pollutants. Moreover, the quest for Beautiful China represents an indispensable and regret-free policy choice given its drastic public health benefits<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. For these reasons, the clean-air policies should be firmly upheld without delay. To achieve a net cooling effect earlier and with a maximized amplitude, we suggest that carbon neutrality should be achieved as early as possible and that negative carbon technologies be vigorously promoted in the long run, augmented by policies to rapidly reduce methane emissions<sup><xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> (see more in Supplementary Note <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>). Furthermore, future efforts could optimize the combinations of reduction measures across sectors by simultaneously considering climate benefits from reducing GHG and short-lived climate forcers, as well as public health benefits. This approach would ultimately identify the reduction pathway that delivers the greatest climate and health benefits while achieving carbon neutrality and clean air.</p><p id="Par19">More importantly, our study has implications for sustainable development strategies in many other Global South countries that simultaneously grapple with high CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and severe air pollution, as exemplified by India. Ongoing and future climate and clean air policies in these countries or regions are expected to substantially alleviate PM<sub>2.5</sub> pollution<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. The anticipated warming effect could potentially be even larger than that of China, as the relatively lenient control measures currently in place in those countries indicate greater potential for future reductions in air pollutants. The widely used SSPs have not fully accounted for ambitious clean air goals, exemplified by the Beautiful China vision, and potential clean air policies in other Global South countries. In view of the challenges brought by air quality improvement, it is crucial to promote earlier and more stringent GHG reduction strategies worldwide—such as achieving net zero sooner and pursuing negative carbon emissions—to ensure that the temperature targets set by the Paris Agreement are met or the overshoot of those targets is limited in time as much as possible.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="2"><title>Description of the Earth System Model</title><p id="Par20">In this study, we evaluate the climate impacts of carbon neutrality and clean air policies consistent with the Beautiful China vision, using the Community Earth System Model version 2 (CESM2). We conduct fully coupled simulations with all components activated, including the atmosphere, land, ocean, sea-ice, land-ice, river, and wave components. The atmosphere component CAM6 uses a nominal 1° (1.25° in longitude and 0.9° in latitude) horizontal resolution with 32 vertical levels and a model top at 2.26 hPa (about 40 km).</p><p id="Par21">CAM6 incorporates a range of advanced capabilities and new improvements that are directly relevant to the climate impacts of emission reductions. Aerosols are represented using the Modal Aerosol Model version 4 (MAM4)<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> which predicts aerosol compositions, including sulfate, BC, POM, SOA, mineral dust, and sea salt in four lognormal modes (i.e., Aitken, accumulation, coarse, and primary carbon modes). Aerosols are assumed internally mixed within each mode but externally mixed between different modes. Sulfate aerosol is formed from its precursor SO<sub>2</sub> via gas-phase oxidation and aqueous-phase oxidation in bulk cloud water. The SOA formation is parameterized with a single-lumped semivolatile organic gas-phase species called SOAG, regarded as a proxy for the oxidation products of VOCs. The preprocessed surface emissions of SOAG are derived from the emission five primary VOCs, using mass yields of 5% for BIGALK (lumped butanes and larger alkanes), 5% for BIGENE (lumped butenes and larger alkenes), 15% for aromatics, 4% for isoprene, and 25% for monoterpenes, which equivalently simulates the gas-phase oxidation of VOC precursors<sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. SOAG then undergoes condensation and evaporation into/from the Aitken and accumulation modes. BC and POM are emitted into the primary carbon mode and then transferred to the accumulation mode via aging. As with most Earth system models, nitrate and ammonium are not included in the current model, which needs to be improved in future studies. The Rapid Radiative Transfer Model for General circulation models (RRTMG) is used for radiative transfer calculations. ARI is computed online by feeding the optical properties (including scattering, absorption, and asymmetry parameters) estimated by MAM4 to RRTMG to assess shortwave and longwave radiative effects. An updated version of the Morrison-Gettelman cloud microphysics scheme (MG2)<sup><xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> is employed to treat the microphysical processes of stratiform clouds, including ACI. In MG2, aerosol activation follows the parameterization of Abdul-Razzak and Ghan<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>, which converts aerosol number concentrations into cloud droplet number concentrations. This subsequently influences both the droplet size and cloud albedo (the “first indirect effect”) and the efficiency of cloud water converting into rainwater, thereby affecting cloud lifetime and precipitation processes (the “second indirect effect”). Moreover, the mixed-phase ice nucleation has been improved to depend on both aerosols and temperature<sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>–<xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Another major advance is the inclusion of the unified turbulence scheme, Cloud Layers Unified By Binormals (CLUBB)<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>, which provides a uniform treatment of clouds across cloud types.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Scenarios and experimental design</title><p id="Par22">We employ emission scenarios for China developed in our previous study<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> using the GCAM-ABaCAS modeling system, including a BAU scenario (named “NDC-2015” in Sun et al.<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>) and a CNCA scenario (named “NDC-2021-AQE” in Sun et al.<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>). Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref> shows that, in 2060, the emissions of SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>x</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, BC, and organic carbon (OC) under CNCA are 93–97% lower than those under BAU, and VOCs emissions are 78% lower, resulting from a combination of the synergistic effect of carbon neutrality and additional clean air policies. As a result, the population-weighted annual mean PM<sub>2.5</sub> concentration in China under CNCA is estimated to reach 7.3 and 5.3 μg m<sup>−3</sup> by 2050 and 2060, respectively, consistent with the expected improvement under the Beautiful China vision to attain the 2005 WHO guideline (10 μg m<sup>−3</sup>) and approach the 2021 guideline (5 μg m<sup>−3</sup>). Another independent emission projection<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> showed that carbon neutrality and clean-air policies could reduce 2060 emissions of SO<sub>2</sub>, NO<sub>x</sub> and PM<sub>2.5</sub> by 85–90% and VOCs emissions by 63% compared to BAU, broadly consistent with those used in this study. The synergistic effect of carbon neutrality (represented by the difference between the BAU and an intermediate scenario where the carbon neutrality target is implemented but no additional clean air policies are considered, see Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>) contributes over 80% of the emission reductions in SO<sub>2</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, BC, and OC, and 60% of the emission reductions in VOCs.</p><p id="Par23">We conduct fully coupled CESM2 simulations for 2015–2100 for the BAU and CNCA scenarios, as well as a sensitivity scenario (SENS) to separate the individual impacts of CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions. In the SENS scenario, the CO<sub>2</sub> emissions and air pollutant emissions are set to the levels of the CNCA scenario and the BAU scenario, respectively. The total impact of CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutant reductions under carbon neutrality and clean air policies aligned with the Beautiful China vision is obtained by differencing the CNCA and BAU scenarios (CNCA−BAU). The impact of CO<sub>2</sub> reduction is obtained by differencing the SENS and BAU scenarios (SENS−BAU) and that of air pollutant reductions is achieved by differencing the CNCA and SENS scenarios (CNCA−SENS).</p><p id="Par24">For all scenarios (BAU, CNCA, and SENS), the fully coupled CESM2 simulations are transient runs initialized on January 1, 2015. The initial conditions are derived from CESM2 historical-era simulations that used standard SSP2-4.5 historical forcings. For each scenario, five ensemble members are performed with a small initial perturbation to atmospheric temperature, to minimize the impact of internal variability in the climate system. In all simulations, the anthropogenic emissions of CO<sub>2</sub> and air pollutants outside China, as well as global biomass burning emissions follow the default SSP2-4.5 scenario, which represents the medium level within the range of future forcing pathways. The base-year emissions in SSP2-4.5 are obtained from the Community Emissions Data System (CEDS)<sup><xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–<xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. The SSP2-4.5 scenario represents a medium pathway within the range of future forcing trajectories, which we consider to best reflect the most likely future emission trajectory outside China. Most analyses in this study focus on the time around 2060 (represented by the average of 2050–2070 to reduce the influence of internal variability), while the temporal evolution trends until 2100 are also examined.</p><p id="Par25">In addition to the fully coupled simulations, we conduct a separate set of atmosphere-only sensitivity experiments to quantify the contribution of individual air pollutant emission changes to the ERF. These experiments are driven by prescribed present-day monthly sea surface temperatures and sea ice concentrations, allowing the differences between experiments to represent the ERF. The horizontal winds in these experiments are nudged towards reanalysis data in 2010, which helps to identify the ERF within a relatively short simulation time<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>. The simulations are integrated for 10 years with the average of the last 9 years used for ERF estimates. In these experiments, the emissions of SO<sub>2</sub> (together with primary sulfate), POM, BC, and VOCs are sequentially adjusted from their BAU levels to the CNCA levels, with each experiment differing from the previous one by the change of a single pollutant. Therefore, by taking the difference between each pair of adjacent experiments, we can quantify the contribution of each pollutant to ERF. The CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations in all these experiments are prescribed based on the fully coupled simulation results under CNCA and are fed into the model via lower boundary conditions. Other configurations are the same as the fully coupled experiments.</p><p id="Par26">Note that this study has not yet considered the changes in non-CO<sub>2</sub> greenhouse gases (such as methane and nitrous oxide) or ozone due to climate or clean air policies (see more in Supplementary Note <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>). Future studies could further benefit from including these forcing agents for a more comprehensive modeling analysis, although the Chinese government has not set specific targets for non-CO<sub>2</sub> greenhouse gases, and the climate impact of ozone is considered to be smaller compared to CO<sub>2</sub> and aerosols<sup><xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="2"><title>Model evaluations</title><p id="Par27">We compare simulated mean surface temperature for 2015–2020 with MERRA2 reanalysis at a 0.25° × 0.25° resolution. The CESM2 model shows strong agreement with MERRA2 reanalysis data for the global patterns of both temperature and precipitation, with the model effectively capturing major temperature gradients and precipitation features (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">7A–D</xref>). The temperature comparison demonstrates particularly high consistency with an <italic>R</italic>² value of 0.9914, while precipitation shows moderate agreement with an <italic>R</italic>² of 0.7492 (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">7E, F</xref>). CESM2 also performs well in reproducing the overall evolution of global historical temperature in the 20<sup>th</sup> century. Danabasoglu et al.<sup><xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> show that, compared with observational datasets such as HADCRU4.5, GISTEMP and NOAAGlobalTemp, CESM2 successfully captures key multi-decadal evolution of global mean surface temperature change, including the early warming from 1920–1940, the mid-century warming hiatus from 1940–1970, and the accelerated warming after the 1970s (see Fig. 7 of Danabasoglu et al.<sup><xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>).</p><p id="Par28">The performance of CESM2 in simulating aerosol concentrations has been evaluated in previous studies<sup><xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>–<xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup>. We use the same emissions as these studies, i.e., the CEDS (CMIP6) emission inventory, except that we replace the default Chinese emissions with our localized emission inventory derived from the GCAM-ABaCAS system and calibrate it against the ABaCAS-EI. For this reason, we further evaluate simulated concentrations of key PM<sub>2.5</sub> components, including sulfate, BC, and organic aerosol, against observations at more than 40 sites in eastern China—the main polluted region of China. These monitoring sites are distributed in major polluted regions including Beijing–Tianjin–Hebei, Shandong, Henan<sup><xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>, and Shanghai<sup><xref rid="CR53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup>, covering both urban and mountainous areas. At these sites, we analyze online measurements of OC/EC and ionic species using OC/EC analyzers and ion chromatography systems during 2018 and 2019. The observational data sources and detailed measurement methodology are described in previous studies<sup><xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>–<xref rid="CR54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup>. Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">8</xref> shows that simulated concentrations of sulfate, BC, and organic aerosol are generally within a factor of 3, 2, and 2 of the observed values across various sites. The normalized mean biases (NMBs) for the three components are −46%, 12%, and −30%, respectively, indicating reasonable model-measurement agreement. The underestimation of sulfate suggests that the warming effects due to air pollutant reductions could be stronger than our current simulation results. Accordingly, the global surface temperature increase from China’s air pollutant reductions may offset the cooling from China’s CO<sub>2</sub> reduction for an even longer time.</p><p id="Par29">Building on this, we further examine CESM2’s ability to simulate the separate responses to GHG and aerosols—two key forcing factors. Although their individual contributions cannot be directly verified through observations, we can indirectly assess the model by analyzing their roles in different historical phases of global temperature change. From the CESM2 single forcing large ensemble experiments, which isolate historical climate forcings (such as GHG and aerosols), the model reveals the independent effect of each forcing (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> of Simpson et al.<sup><xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup>). The results show that under GHG-only forcing, the model simulates a continuous warming trend, consistent with the physical understanding of GHG as the main driver of warming. Under anthropogenic aerosol-only forcing, the model produces a clear cooling signal, with the strongest cooling in the mid-20<sup>th</sup> century, gradually weakening afterward due to the decrease in aerosol loading. When both GHG warming and aerosol cooling are combined, CESM2 successfully reproduces the phased characteristics of historical temperature change, i.e., mid-20<sup>th</sup>-century warming hiatus and accelerated warming in the late 20<sup>th</sup> century. This indicates that aerosols contributed significantly to the mid-century warming slowdown, while the continued strengthening of GHG impact and the weakening of aerosol impact drove later temperature rise. These results also align with previous attribution studies<sup><xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup>. This suggests that CESM2 can not only reproduce the overall historical temperature curve but also capture the separate effects of GHG and aerosols on temperature change from a physical mechanism perspective. Additionally, the effective radiative forcing of GHG and aerosols simulated by CESM2 falls within the range of the CMIP6 multi-model ensemble<sup><xref rid="CR57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup>, further supporting the reasonableness of its forcing representations. Evaluation of precipitation simulations by CESM2 is given in Supplementary Note <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary information</title>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM1" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path cd38/12923533/5190e5ef9e64/41467_2026_68586_MOESM1_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2706815?><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM2" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path cd38/12923533/2f34484a4218/41467_2026_68586_MOESM2_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2433487?><caption><p>Transparent Peer Review file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="1"><title>Source data</title>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM3" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_MOESM3_ESM.zip" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip"><?cloudpmc-path cd38/12923533/b3f85e066e9d/41467_2026_68586_MOESM3_ESM.zip?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 553758?><caption><p>Source Data</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>S.W., B.Z., H.H., B.C., and K.H. were supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China grant 22188102. B.Z. was supported by the National Key R&amp;D Program of China grant 2022YFC3701000, Task 5. S.W. was supported by the National Key R&amp;D Program of China grant 2022YFC3702905 and the International Joint Mission on Climate Change and Carbon Neutrality. S.W. and B.Z. were also supported by the Tsinghua-Toyota Joint Research Institute Inter-disciplinary Program.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>B.Z., Y.W., and S.W. conceived the study. B.Z., X.W., Y.W., Y.S., D.G., Y.G., J.Z., Y.Z., G.L., and S.W. developed the methods used in this study. B.Z., X.W., Y.W., Y.S., D.G., Q.G., Y.G., J.Z., Y.Z., D.S., S.J.D., G.L., Y.h.W., B.C., H.H., K.H., J.H., and S.W. carried out the research. B.Z. and X.W. wrote the original draft of the manuscript. B.Z., X.W., Y.W., Y.S., D.G., Q.G., Y.G., J.Z., Y.Z., D.S., S.J.D., G.L., Y.h.W., B.C., Z.J., H.H., K.H., J.H., and S.W. revised the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Peer review</title><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="2"><title>Peer review information</title><p id="Par30"><italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks the anonymous reviewers for their contribution to the peer review of this work. A peer review file is available.</p></sec></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>Source Data corresponding to all figures in this paper have been provided in the Source Data file. In addition, the processed datasets, including emission inventories for the Business-As-Usual (BAU) and China Carbon Neutrality and Clean Air (CNCA) scenarios, as well as key model outputs covering the 2050-2069 period with 5 ensemble members, have been deposited in Figshare and are accessible via 10.6084/m9.figshare.30511721. <xref rid="Sec13" ref-type="sec">Source data</xref> are provided with this paper.</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Code availability</title><p>The codes of the CESM2 model used in this study are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm2" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" disp-level="1"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par31">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><p>These authors contributed equally: Bin Zhao, Xiaochun Wang.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="_ci93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="contrib-info" disp-level="1"><title>Contributor Information</title><p>Yuan Wang, Email: yzwang@stanford.edu.</p><p>Shuxiao Wang, Email: shxwang@mail.tsinghua.edu.cn.</p></sec><sec id="sec14" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41467-026-68586-y.</p></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tollefson, J. Earth breaches 1.5 °C climate limit for the first time: what does it mean? <italic>Nature</italic><bold>637</bold>, 769–770 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/d41586-025-00010-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39794429"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tollefson, J. Earth breaches 1.5 °C climate limit for the first time: what does it mean? Nature637, 769–770 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Huang, M.-T. &amp; Zhai, P.-M. Achieving Paris Agreement temperature goals requires carbon neutrality by middle century with far-reaching transitions in the whole society. <italic>Adv. Clim. Chang. Res.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 281–286 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Huang, M.-T. &amp; Zhai, P.-M. Achieving Paris Agreement temperature goals requires carbon neutrality by middle century with far-reaching transitions in the whole society. Adv. Clim. Chang. Res.12, 281–286 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hammer, M. S. et al. Global estimates and long-term trends of fine particulate matter concentrations (1998-2018). <italic>Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>54</bold>, 7879–7890 (2020).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1021/acs.est.0c01764"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32491847"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hammer, M. S. et al. Global estimates and long-term trends of fine particulate matter concentrations (1998-2018). Environ. Sci. Technol.54, 7879–7890 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cohen, A. J. et al. Estimates and 25-year trends of the global burden of disease attributable to ambient air pollution: an analysis of data from the Global Burden of Diseases Study 2015. <italic>Lancet</italic><bold>389</bold>, 1907–1918 (2017).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30505-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5439030"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28408086"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cohen, A. J. et al. Estimates and 25-year trends of the global burden of disease attributable to ambient air pollution: an analysis of data from the Global Burden of Diseases Study 2015. Lancet389, 1907–1918 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sun, Y. et al. Air quality, health, and equity benefits of carbon neutrality and clean air pathways in China. <italic>Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>58</bold>, 15027–15037 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1021/acs.est.3c10076"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11814289"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39133145"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sun, Y. et al. Air quality, health, and equity benefits of carbon neutrality and clean air pathways in China. Environ. Sci. Technol.58, 15027–15037 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cheng, J. et al. A synergistic approach to air pollution control and carbon neutrality in China can avoid millions of premature deaths annually by 2060. <italic>One Earth</italic><bold>6</bold>, 978–989 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cheng, J. et al. A synergistic approach to air pollution control and carbon neutrality in China can avoid millions of premature deaths annually by 2060. One Earth6, 978–989 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shi, X. et al. Air quality benefits of achieving carbon neutrality in China. <italic>Sci. Total. Environ.</italic><bold>795</bold>, 148784 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.148784"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34246132"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shi, X. et al. Air quality benefits of achieving carbon neutrality in China. Sci. Total. Environ.795, 148784 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cheng, J. et al. Pathways of China’s PM<sub>2.5</sub> air quality 2015-2060 in the context of carbon neutrality. <italic>Natl. Sci. Rev.</italic><bold>8</bold>, nwab078 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/nsr/nwab078"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8692930"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34987838"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cheng, J. et al. Pathways of China’s PM2.5 air quality 2015-2060 in the context of carbon neutrality. Natl. Sci. Rev.8, nwab078 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Thornhill, G. D. et al. Effective radiative forcing from emissions of reactive gases and aerosols - a multi-model comparison. <italic>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 853–874 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Thornhill, G. D. et al. Effective radiative forcing from emissions of reactive gases and aerosols - a multi-model comparison. Atmos. Chem. Phys.21, 853–874 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Persad, G. G. &amp; Caldeira, K. Divergent global-scale temperature effects from identical aerosols emitted in different regions. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 3289 (2018).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-018-05838-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6097985"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30120243"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Persad, G. G. &amp; Caldeira, K. Divergent global-scale temperature effects from identical aerosols emitted in different regions. Nat. Commun.9, 3289 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">IPCC. <italic>Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis. Working Group I contribution to the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italic> (Cambridge University Press, 2021).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gao, D. et al. Distinct PM2.5-related near-term climate penalties induced by different clean air measures in China. <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>51</bold>, e2024GL108204.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shindell, D. T., Faluvegi, G., Rotstayn, L. &amp; Milly, G. Spatial patterns of radiative forcing and surface temperature response. <italic>J. Geophys. Res-Atmos.</italic><bold>120</bold>, 5385–5403 (2015).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shindell, D. T., Faluvegi, G., Rotstayn, L. &amp; Milly, G. Spatial patterns of radiative forcing and surface temperature response. J. Geophys. Res-Atmos.120, 5385–5403 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Stjern, C. W. et al. The time scales of climate responses to carbon dioxide and aerosols. <italic>J. Climate</italic><bold>36</bold>, 3537–3551 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Stjern, C. W. et al. The time scales of climate responses to carbon dioxide and aerosols. J. Climate36, 3537–3551 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shindell, D. &amp; Smith, C. J. Climate and air-quality benefits of a realistic phase-out of fossil fuels. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>573</bold>, 408–411 (2019).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-019-1554-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31534245"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shindell, D. &amp; Smith, C. J. Climate and air-quality benefits of a realistic phase-out of fossil fuels. Nature573, 408–411 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dreyfus, G. B., Xu, Y., Shindell, D. T., Zaelke, D. &amp; Ramanathan, V. Mitigating climate disruption in time: A self-consistent approach for avoiding both near-term and long-term global warming. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>119</bold>, e2123536119 (2022).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.2123536119"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9295773"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35605122"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Dreyfus, G. B., Xu, Y., Shindell, D. T., Zaelke, D. &amp; Ramanathan, V. Mitigating climate disruption in time: A self-consistent approach for avoiding both near-term and long-term global warming. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA119, e2123536119 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, Y. et al. Short-lived air pollutants and climate forcers through the lens of the COVID-19 pandemic. <italic>Rev. Geophys.</italic><bold>62</bold>, e2022RG000773 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, Y. et al. Short-lived air pollutants and climate forcers through the lens of the COVID-19 pandemic. Rev. Geophys.62, e2022RG000773 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nazarenko, L. S. et al. Future climate change under SSP emission scenarios with GISS-E2.1. <italic>J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.</italic><bold>14</bold>, e2021MS002871 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nazarenko, L. S. et al. Future climate change under SSP emission scenarios with GISS-E2.1. J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.14, e2021MS002871 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tebaldi, C. et al. Climate model projections from the Scenario Model Intercomparison Project (ScenarioMIP) of CMIP6. <italic>Earth Syst. Dyn.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 253–293 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tebaldi, C. et al. Climate model projections from the Scenario Model Intercomparison Project (ScenarioMIP) of CMIP6. Earth Syst. Dyn.12, 253–293 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gillett, N. P. et al. The Detection and Attribution Model Intercomparison Project (DAMIP v1.0) contribution to CMIP6. <italic>Geosci. Model. Dev.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 3685–3697 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.5194/gmd-9-4521-2016"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5911933"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29697697"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gillett, N. P. et al. The Detection and Attribution Model Intercomparison Project (DAMIP v1.0) contribution to CMIP6. Geosci. Model. Dev.9, 3685–3697 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Xu, C., Zhao, T., Zhang, J., Hua, L. &amp; Tao, L. Impacts of natural and anthropogenic forcings on historical and future changes in global-land surface air temperature in CMIP6-DAMIP simulations. <italic>Clim. Change</italic><bold>177</bold>, 30 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Xu, C., Zhao, T., Zhang, J., Hua, L. &amp; Tao, L. Impacts of natural and anthropogenic forcings on historical and future changes in global-land surface air temperature in CMIP6-DAMIP simulations. Clim. Change177, 30 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shindell, D. T., Lee, Y. &amp; Faluvegi, G. Climate and health impacts of US emissions reductions consistent with 2 °C. <italic>Nat. Clim. Change.</italic><bold>6</bold>, 503–507 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shindell, D. T., Lee, Y. &amp; Faluvegi, G. Climate and health impacts of US emissions reductions consistent with 2 °C. Nat. Clim. Change.6, 503–507 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, L. et al. Mitigation of China’s carbon neutrality to global warming. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 5315 (2022).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-022-33047-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9463144"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36085326"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, L. et al. Mitigation of China’s carbon neutrality to global warming. Nat. Commun.13, 5315 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yang, Y., Zeng, L., Wang, H., Wang, P. &amp; Liao, H. Climate effects of future aerosol reductions for achieving carbon neutrality in China. <italic>Sci. Bull.</italic><bold>68</bold>, 902–905 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.scib.2023.03.048"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37037697"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yang, Y., Zeng, L., Wang, H., Wang, P. &amp; Liao, H. Climate effects of future aerosol reductions for achieving carbon neutrality in China. Sci. Bull.68, 902–905 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Held, I. M. &amp; Soden, B. J. Robust responses of the hydrological cycle to global warming. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 5686–5699 (2006).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Held, I. M. &amp; Soden, B. J. Robust responses of the hydrological cycle to global warming. J. Clim.19, 5686–5699 (2006)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Screen, J. A. &amp; Simmonds, I. The central role of diminishing sea ice in recent Arctic temperature amplification. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>464</bold>, 1334–1337 (2010).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nature09051"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20428168"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Screen, J. A. &amp; Simmonds, I. The central role of diminishing sea ice in recent Arctic temperature amplification. Nature464, 1334–1337 (2010)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shindell, D. &amp; Faluvegi, G. Climate response to regional radiative forcing during the twentieth century. <italic>Nat. Geosci.</italic><bold>2</bold>, 294–300 (2009).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shindell, D. &amp; Faluvegi, G. Climate response to regional radiative forcing during the twentieth century. Nat. Geosci.2, 294–300 (2009)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, Y., Zhang, R. Y. &amp; Saravanan, R. Asian pollution climatically modulates mid-latitude cyclones following hierarchical modelling and observational analysis. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 3098 (2014).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/ncomms4098"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24448316"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, Y., Zhang, R. Y. &amp; Saravanan, R. Asian pollution climatically modulates mid-latitude cyclones following hierarchical modelling and observational analysis. Nat. Commun.5, 3098 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Loeb, N. G. et al. Emerging hemispheric asymmetry of Earth’s radiation. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>122</bold>, e2511595122 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.2511595122"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12519167"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="41021814"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Loeb, N. G. et al. Emerging hemispheric asymmetry of Earth’s radiation. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA122, e2511595122 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yan, X. et al. A global land aerosol fine-mode fraction dataset (2001–2020) retrieved from MODIS using hybrid physical and deep learning approaches. <italic>Earth Syst. Sci. Data</italic><bold>14</bold>, 1193–1213 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yan, X. et al. A global land aerosol fine-mode fraction dataset (2001–2020) retrieved from MODIS using hybrid physical and deep learning approaches. Earth Syst. Sci. Data14, 1193–1213 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Navarro, J. C. A. et al. Future response of temperature and precipitation to reduced aerosol emissions as compared with increased greenhouse gas concentrations. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 939–954 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Navarro, J. C. A. et al. Future response of temperature and precipitation to reduced aerosol emissions as compared with increased greenhouse gas concentrations. J. Clim.30, 939–954 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, P. et al. Aerosols overtake greenhouse gases causing a warmer climate and more weather extremes toward carbon neutrality. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 7257 (2023).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-023-42891-2"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10636203"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37945564"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, P. et al. Aerosols overtake greenhouse gases causing a warmer climate and more weather extremes toward carbon neutrality. Nat. Commun.14, 7257 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zanis, P. et al. Fast responses on pre-industrial climate from present-day aerosols in a CMIP6 multi-model study. <italic>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>20</bold>, 8381–8404 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zanis, P. et al. Fast responses on pre-industrial climate from present-day aerosols in a CMIP6 multi-model study. Atmos. Chem. Phys.20, 8381–8404 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shindell, D. et al. The methane imperative. <italic>Front. Sci.</italic><bold>2</bold>, 1349770 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shindell, D. et al. The methane imperative. Front. Sci.2, 1349770 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ganguly, T., Selvaraj, K. L. &amp; Guttikunda, S. K. National Clean Air Programme (NCAP) for Indian cities: Review and outlook of clean air action plans. <italic>Atmos. Environ. X</italic><bold>8</bold>, 100096 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ganguly, T., Selvaraj, K. L. &amp; Guttikunda, S. K. National Clean Air Programme (NCAP) for Indian cities: Review and outlook of clean air action plans. Atmos. Environ. X8, 100096 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu, X. et al. Description and evaluation of a new four-mode version of the Modal Aerosol Module (MAM4) within version 5.3 of the Community Atmosphere Model. <italic>Geosci. Model. Dev.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 505–522 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liu, X. et al. Description and evaluation of a new four-mode version of the Modal Aerosol Module (MAM4) within version 5.3 of the Community Atmosphere Model. Geosci. Model. Dev.9, 505–522 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu, X. et al. Toward a minimal representation of aerosols in climate models: description and evaluation in the Community Atmosphere Model CAM5. <italic>Geosci. Model. Dev.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 709–739 (2012).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liu, X. et al. Toward a minimal representation of aerosols in climate models: description and evaluation in the Community Atmosphere Model CAM5. Geosci. Model. Dev.5, 709–739 (2012)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gettelman, A. &amp; Morrison, H. Advanced two-moment bulk microphysics for global models. part I: off-line tests and comparison with other schemes. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>28</bold>, 1268–1287 (2015).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gettelman, A. &amp; Morrison, H. Advanced two-moment bulk microphysics for global models. part I: off-line tests and comparison with other schemes. J. Clim.28, 1268–1287 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Abdul-Razzak, H. &amp; Ghan, S. J. A parameterization of aerosol activation 2. Multiple aerosol types. <italic>J. Geophys. Res-Atmos.</italic><bold>105</bold>, 6837–6844 (2000).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Abdul-Razzak, H. &amp; Ghan, S. J. A parameterization of aerosol activation 2. Multiple aerosol types. J. Geophys. Res-Atmos.105, 6837–6844 (2000)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hoose, C., Kristjansson, J. E., Chen, J.-P. &amp; Hazra, A. A Classical-theory-based parameterization of heterogeneous ice nucleation by mineral dust, soot, and biological particles in a global climate model. <italic>J. Atmos. Sci.</italic><bold>67</bold>, 2483–2503 (2010).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hoose, C., Kristjansson, J. E., Chen, J.-P. &amp; Hazra, A. A Classical-theory-based parameterization of heterogeneous ice nucleation by mineral dust, soot, and biological particles in a global climate model. J. Atmos. Sci.67, 2483–2503 (2010)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, Y., Liu, X., Hoose, C. &amp; Wang, B. Different contact angle distributions for heterogeneous ice nucleation in the Community Atmospheric Model version 5. <italic>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 10411–10430 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, Y., Liu, X., Hoose, C. &amp; Wang, B. Different contact angle distributions for heterogeneous ice nucleation in the Community Atmospheric Model version 5. Atmos. Chem. Phys.14, 10411–10430 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shi, X., Liu, X. &amp; Zhang, K. Effects of pre-existing ice crystals on cirrus clouds and comparison between different ice nucleation parameterizations with the Community Atmosphere Model (CAM5). <italic>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1503–1520 (2015).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shi, X., Liu, X. &amp; Zhang, K. Effects of pre-existing ice crystals on cirrus clouds and comparison between different ice nucleation parameterizations with the Community Atmosphere Model (CAM5). Atmos. Chem. Phys.15, 1503–1520 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Golaz, J. C., Larson, V. E. &amp; Cotton, W. R. A PDF-based model for boundary layer clouds. Part I: Method and model description. <italic>J. Atmos. Sci.</italic><bold>59</bold>, 3540–3551 (2002).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Golaz, J. C., Larson, V. E. &amp; Cotton, W. R. A PDF-based model for boundary layer clouds. Part I: Method and model description. J. Atmos. Sci.59, 3540–3551 (2002)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Larson, V. E. CLUBB-SILHS: a parameterization of subgrid variability in the atmosphere. Preprint at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1711.03675" ext-link-type="uri">https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.03675</ext-link> (2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hoesly, R. M. et al. Historical (1750-2014) anthropogenic emissions of reactive gases and aerosols from the Community Emissions Data System (CEDS). <italic>Geosci. Model. Dev.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 369–408 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hoesly, R. M. et al. Historical (1750-2014) anthropogenic emissions of reactive gases and aerosols from the Community Emissions Data System (CEDS). Geosci. Model. Dev.11, 369–408 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46"><named-content content-type="citation-string">McDuffie, E. E. et al. A global anthropogenic emission inventory of atmospheric pollutants from sector- and fuel-specific sources (1970-2017): an application of the Community Emissions Data System (CEDS). <italic>Earth Syst. Sci. Data</italic><bold>12</bold>, 3413–3442 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="McDuffie, E. E. et al. A global anthropogenic emission inventory of atmospheric pollutants from sector- and fuel-specific sources (1970-2017): an application of the Community Emissions Data System (CEDS). Earth Syst. Sci. Data12, 3413–3442 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gettelman, A. et al. Has reducing ship emissions brought forward global warming? <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett</italic>. <bold>51</bold>10.1029/2024gl109077 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gillett, N. P. et al. Constraining human contributions to observed warming since the pre-industrial period. <italic>Nat. Clim. Change.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 207–212 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gillett, N. P. et al. Constraining human contributions to observed warming since the pre-industrial period. Nat. Clim. Change.11, 207–212 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Danabasoglu, G. et al. The Community Earth System Model Version 2 (CESM2). <italic>J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.</italic><bold>12</bold>, e2019MS001916 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Danabasoglu, G. et al. The Community Earth System Model Version 2 (CESM2). J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.12, e2019MS001916 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tilmes, S. et al. Climate forcing and trends of organic aerosols in the community earth system model (CESM2). <italic>J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 4323–4351 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tilmes, S. et al. Climate forcing and trends of organic aerosols in the community earth system model (CESM2). J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.11, 4323–4351 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lu, Z. et al. Radiative Forcing of Nitrate Aerosols From 1975 to 2010 as Simulated by MOSAIC Module in CESM2-MAM4. <italic>J. Geophys. Res-Atmos.</italic><bold>126</bold>, e2021JD034809.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, Y. et al. Construction and application of comprehensive observation network for air pollution in Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei and its surrounding areas. <italic>Res. Environ. Sci.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 1651–1663 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, Y. et al. Construction and application of comprehensive observation network for air pollution in Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei and its surrounding areas. Res. Environ. Sci.32, 1651–1663 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, Q. et al. Traffic, marine ships and nucleation as the main sources of ultrafine particles in suburban Shanghai, China. <italic>Environ. Sci. Atmos.</italic><bold>3</bold>, 1805–1819 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, Q. et al. Traffic, marine ships and nucleation as the main sources of ultrafine particles in suburban Shanghai, China. Environ. Sci. Atmos.3, 1805–1819 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lin, Y. Characterization of particle pollution changes in Dianshan Lake area of Shanghai and its possible impact on ozone. <italic>Environ. Monit. China</italic><bold>40</bold>, 62–69 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lin, Y. Characterization of particle pollution changes in Dianshan Lake area of Shanghai and its possible impact on ozone. Environ. Monit. China40, 62–69 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Simpson, I. R. et al. The CESM2 single-forcing large ensemble and comparison to CESM1: implications for experimental design. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>36</bold>, 5687–5711 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Simpson, I. R. et al. The CESM2 single-forcing large ensemble and comparison to CESM1: implications for experimental design. J. Clim.36, 5687–5711 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Stott, P. A. et al. Observational constraints on past attributable warming and predictions of future global warming. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 3055–3069 (2006).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Stott, P. A. et al. Observational constraints on past attributable warming and predictions of future global warming. J. Clim.19, 3055–3069 (2006)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Smith, C. J. et al. Effective radiative forcing and adjustments in CMIP6 models. <italic>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>20</bold>, 9591–9618 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Smith, C. J. et al. Effective radiative forcing and adjustments in CMIP6 models. Atmos. Chem. Phys.20, 9591–9618 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path cd38/12923533/5190e5ef9e64/41467_2026_68586_MOESM1_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2706815?><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material2_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path cd38/12923533/2f34484a4218/41467_2026_68586_MOESM2_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2433487?><caption><p>Transparent Peer Review file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material3_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_68586_MOESM3_ESM.zip" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip"><?cloudpmc-path cd38/12923533/b3f85e066e9d/41467_2026_68586_MOESM3_ESM.zip?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 553758?><caption><p>Source Data</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>Source Data corresponding to all figures in this paper have been provided in the Source Data file. In addition, the processed datasets, including emission inventories for the Business-As-Usual (BAU) and China Carbon Neutrality and Clean Air (CNCA) scenarios, as well as key model outputs covering the 2050-2069 period with 5 ensemble members, have been deposited in Figshare and are accessible via 10.6084/m9.figshare.30511721. <xref rid="Sec13" ref-type="sec">Source data</xref> are provided with this paper.</p><p>The codes of the CESM2 model used in this study are available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm2" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm2</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec></body></article>