<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">981</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">npgopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Communications Earth &amp; Environment</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Commun Earth Environ</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12979200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12979200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12979200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41835918</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43247-026-03331-3</article-id><title-group><article-title>Reforestation scenarios shape global and regional temperature outcomes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahrenbach</surname><given-names initials="NLS">Nora L S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>De Hertog</surname><given-names initials="SJ">Steven J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Jäger</surname><given-names initials="F">Felix</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names initials="PJ">Peter J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Jnglin Wills</surname><given-names initials="RC">Robert C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Institute for Atmospheric and Climate Science, ETH Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Q-ForestLab, Department of Environment, Ghent University, Ghent, Belgium </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Climate and Global Dynamics Laboratory, National Center for Atmospheric Research, Boulder, CO USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Present Address: Earth Resilience Science Unit, Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research, Potsdam, Germany </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>204</fpage><page-range>204</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="43247_2026_Article_3331.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 93c6/12979200/da7485c64d2d/43247_2026_Article_3331.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 6017925?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Large-scale reforestation is a prominent proposed climate mitigation strategy, but its full temperature impact remains poorly understood. Here, we present a systematic comparison of temperature responses to three distinct reforestation potentials using a fully-coupled Earth System Model. We find that reforestation consistently provides net global cooling, ranging from −0.13<sup>∘</sup>C to −0.25<sup>∘</sup>C, due to carbon uptake partially offset by biogeophysical warming. Crucially, a comparable net global cooling can be achieved with substantially smaller (450 Mha less area) but strategically located reforestation. Reforestation locally cools the tropics but causes albedo-driven warming in higher latitudes, which is often amplified by non-local effects. The different reforestation patterns alone can induce a wide range of non-local effects, showing that planting locations shape the biogeophysical response through atmospheric and oceanic feedbacks. Our findings underscore the importance of climate-smart policies that focus on the geographical placement of reforestation, considering both biogeochemical and biogeophysical effects to maximize cooling benefits.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Climate-change mitigation, Climate and Earth system modelling, Climate-change ecology</p></sec></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Strategic reforestation can achieve similar global cooling with half the forest area, by avoiding reforestation in high latitudes, as revealed by implementing three distinct reforestation scenarios in a fully coupled Earth System Model.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-in-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 Oct 8; Accepted 2026 Feb 12; Issue date 2026.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Limiting global warming to 2 °C or less likely necessitates large-scale carbon dioxide removal strategies in addition to rapid decarbonization<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. While technological carbon dioxide removal methods face cost and scalability barriers<sup><xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, forest-based approaches offer a compelling alternative<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. Afforestation and reforestation are widely recognized for their cost-effectiveness and co-benefits for biodiversity and water quality<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Global commitments like the EU’s Nature Restoration Law<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> underline their policy relevance.</p><p id="Par4">The climate impact of forests includes both biogeochemical (BGC) cooling from carbon sequestration and biogeophysical (BGP) effects driven by changes in albedo, evapotranspiration, and surface roughness<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. BGP effects are highly latitude-dependent: high-latitude reforestation can cause local warming by reducing surface albedo over snow<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>, whereas tropical reforestation typically cools via enhanced evapotranspiration<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Non-local climate effects, mediated by atmospheric and oceanic responses, can further modify the net climate impact<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Given the growing interest in reforestation and to guide policy, various global maps have been developed to identify suitable reforestation areas (which we refer to as “reforestation potentials”) and quantify their carbon sequestration potential<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. However, estimates of both potential area (150 to over 1000 Mha) and carbon uptake until 2100 (130 to 750 GtCO<sub>2</sub>; reducing cumulative emissions excluding from land use under SSP2-4.5 by 4–25%<sup><xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>) vary dramatically. This wide range stems from differing methodologies, from diverse definitions of forests to different decisions about the exclusion of regions like urban or agricultural lands<sup><xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. These choices have been the subject of significant debate [e.g., refs. <sup><xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>]. Despite these uncertainties, reforestation potential maps remain a foundation for political commitments<sup><xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> and IPCC assessments<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>, motivating the need to move beyond simple carbon-only assessments and investigate the full climate response to different reforestation potentials.</p><p id="Par6">Most previous modeling studies investigating the climate response to forest-cover change have used idealized scenarios that simulate a complete global or large-scale latitudinal change in forest area [e.g., refs. <sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>–<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup>], aiming to improve the mechanistic understanding rather than simulating realistic scenarios. However, some recent studies have implemented single reforestation potentials in Earth System Models (ESMs) to better understand carbon and temperature responses to more realistic reforestation patterns. Simulations based on the Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> potential suggest that while large-scale forestation could sequester a large amount of carbon (125 PgC), a substantial portion of this benefit can be offset by biogeophysical effects and disturbance losses<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>. While these authors extrapolated their carbon calculations to other reforestation potentials<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>, they did not investigate the temperature response. Studies focusing on the temperature response to reforestation have produced divergent results. An ESM-based study by Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> estimated an end-of-century global temperature reduction of 0.2 °C, primarily from BGC effects dominating over BGP effects. Similarly, a study implementing the Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> potential in a land-atmosphere model found modest BGP cooling benefits that may even diminish under elevated CO<sub>2</sub> due to nonlocal feedbacks<sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. However, Hasler et al.<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> estimates using radiative kernels that albedo-driven warming can offset up to 80% of the cooling from carbon uptake, especially in drylands and boreal zones, in three reforestation potential scenarios<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>, although they do not consider evaporative cooling effects nor non-local atmospheric responses. While these findings offer valuable context for specific scenarios, a comparison of the biogeophysical and biogeochemical temperature responses across different reforestation potentials, simulated by a fully-coupled ESM, remains absent. Using a fully-coupled ESM is needed to capture the full forest-induced climate response, because ocean circulation changes can modify the non-local responses to forest cover change<sup><xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. This work fills this gap and represents a step toward more comprehensively assessing the potential climate benefits and risks of different reforestation scenarios, which is crucial to estimate the climate change mitigation potential and so to better inform policy.</p><p id="Par7">To understand how temperature responses differ across reforestation scenarios, our study systematically quantifies and compares the global and regional temperature responses to three prominent reforestation potential maps: an upper-bound estimate from Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>, a synthesized perspective from Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>, and a medium-scale estimate from Hurtt et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. We implement these scenarios in a fully-coupled Earth System Model (CESM2; Danabasoglu et al.<sup><xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>), running five-member ensembles from 2015 to 2100 under a warming trajectory close to current policy projections (prescribed SSP2-4.5 atmospheric composition). Our analysis aims to answer three fundamental questions: (1) To what extent do global BGP and BGC temperature responses offset or reinforce each other across reforestation scenarios? (2) How do regional BGP temperature responses compare across scenarios, and what are the contributions of local and non-local effects? (3) Which reforestation areas are most suitable for effective climate change mitigation? We analyze CESM2-simulated BGP temperature changes, approximate the BGC effect using the transient climate response to cumulative emissions (TCRE), and use a moving window regression (MWR) method to disentangle local and nonlocal temperature signals (see “Methods”). Our findings provide crucial insights for climate policy by identifying where reforestation efforts would be most effective to optimize global and regional temperature benefits.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Large variations in reforestation placement across scenarios</title><p id="Par8">Our analysis focuses on three reforestation potentials from Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>, Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>, and Hurtt et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> (hereafter, Bastin, Moustakis and Hurtt reforestation potentials), which we implemented in CESM2 (see Methods). All three datasets identify reforestation opportunities in key regions such as the eastern United States, Amazonia, the Congo rainforest and eastern China, but they diverge markedly in both the magnitude and regional emphasis of the total potential (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a–c</xref>). While the Moustakis and Bastin reforestation potentials are similar in total size (926 Mha and 894 Mha, respectively), the former suggests the largest potential is in the tropics, whereas the latter includes extensive reforestation in northern temperate and polar latitudes. In contrast, the Hurtt scenario is substantially more conservative, with a total area of 440 Mha.</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Implemented reforestation potential patterns.</title><p>Global maps of the (<bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold>) implemented reforestation potential (given as the change in the percentage of grid cell covered by trees) and (<bold>d</bold>–<bold>f</bold>) simulated canopy height changes from 2071 to 2100 for the ensemble mean for each of the three reforestation potentials (Bastin, Moustakis, Hurtt) relative to the baseline. The total implemented reforestation area within the CESM2 model for each reforestation potential dataset is provided in the bottom left of figures (<bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold>).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e434" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/8dbead60f9e4/43247_2026_3331_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 726?><?original-width 1969?><?scaled-height 290?><?scaled-width 787?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/41da956529ad/43247_2026_3331_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par9">These three reforestation potentials were implemented in CESM2 to analyse the corresponding temperature response. The reforestation is implemented as a linear ramp-up in forest cover fraction between 2015 and 2070, after which the resulting land-cover state is held fixed until the end of the simulation in 2100 (see “Methods”). Following the prescribed land-cover change, the target tree cover successfully established in most regions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d–f</xref>), with the exception of some dry areas—specifically the southern Great Plains and central Siberian Plateau in the Bastin and Moustakis scenarios—where the climate conditions limited the growth and persistence of the new forest plant functional types (PFTs). The large variations in total area and geographical placement demonstrate the importance of a systematic comparison of their climate impacts.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Differences in global-mean temperature changes to reforestation potentials</title><p id="Par10">We quantify the influence of reforestation on global-mean near-surface temperature, distinguishing between biogeophysical (<inline-formula id="IEq1"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e447"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>), biogeochemical (<inline-formula id="IEq2"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e462"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) and their combined (<inline-formula id="IEq3"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e477"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGP</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) effects (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The <inline-formula id="IEq4"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e498"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> exhibits strong internal variability across all three datasets; albeit, using a 5-member ensemble helps to reduce the influence of this variability (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). However, a small BGP warming of around 0.09 °C emerges in the Bastin scenario around 2080, which is at the upper bound of baseline variability (grey bar in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>) and is statistically significant when averaged over the ensemble. Contrarily, the Moustakis and Hurtt scenarios show no statistically significant, consistent deviation of <inline-formula id="IEq5"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e520"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> from the baseline until the end of the century.</p><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Biogeophysical, biogeochemical and net global-mean temperature changes.</title><p>Ensemble mean of the global-mean near-surface temperature changes from 2015 to 2100 due to (<bold>a</bold>) simulated biogeophysical effects <inline-formula id="IEq6"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e545"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, (<bold>b</bold>) calculated biogeochemical effect <inline-formula id="IEq7"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e563"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> based on CESM2 TCRE from Amali et al.<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> and (<bold>c</bold>) combined effects <inline-formula id="IEq8"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e586"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGC</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> for the Bastin, Moustakis and Hurtt reforestation potentials compared to the baseline. A 15-year centered rolling mean was applied. Envelopes indicate the standard deviation (computed over 15-year rolling means) for the difference between the reforestation scenario and baseline across the five ensemble members. In (<bold>a</bold>), the grey bar shows the internal variability in the baseline simulation given by the one standard deviation spread across the five ensemble members from 2071 to 2100. Thicker line segments in (<bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold>) show where the response is statistically significant at the 90% level using the two-sample t-test, the thicker lines in (<bold>b</bold>) have been omitted as all years are statistically significant.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e614" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/d9c14eebb98d/43247_2026_3331_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 575?><?original-width 1999?><?scaled-height 230?><?scaled-width 799?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/9bce4825955f/43247_2026_3331_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par11">The <inline-formula id="IEq9"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e620"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, calculated following the methods of Amali et al.<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> and using the TCRE for CESM2 calculated by Arora et al.<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> (see “Methods”), shows significant global-mean cooling for all scenarios, with the rate increasing from mid-century onwards (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). This reflects sustained land carbon uptake by new forests (350 GtCO<sub>2</sub> in the Bastin scenario, 435 GtCO<sub>2</sub> in the Moustakis scenario and 220 GtCO<sub>2</sub> in the Hurtt scenario; Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>), primarily by vegetation, followed by woody debris. This carbon sequestration potential is in the mid-range of total estimates for global sequestration potential from reforestation and would equate to around 5–10 times the present-day annual global CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. By the end of the century (mean over 2086–2100), the Moustakis scenario leads to the most substantial BGC cooling (−0.25 °C), followed by Bastin scenario (−0.22 °C) and Hurtt scenario (−0.13 °C). The sustained cooling trend, which persists after reforestation stops in 2070, suggests that the full BGC effect takes a long time to establish due to sustained carbon uptake of vegetation and woody debris, and has not been realized by the end of the simulations in 2100. A critical implication for our results is that the continued establishment of the BGC effect beyond 2100 would likely cause the long-term total climate efficacy of reforestation to be greater than our end-of-century projections suggest. However, the eventual long-term efficacy beyond 2100 depends also on the balance between this continued carbon sink and potential counteracting processes, such as reduced carbon uptake efficiency due to lower atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and increased carbon losses from climate extremes like droughts.</p><p id="Par12">The combined effect results in a significant net global cooling for all scenarios by the end of the century (2086–2100): −0.25 °C for the Moustakis potential and −0.13 °C for the Bastin and Hurtt potential (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Notably, despite being 450 Mha smaller, the Hurtt potential achieves a net global cooling comparable to the larger Bastin potential, as Bastin’s BGP warming offsets some of its BGC cooling. This highlights the sensitivity of the global temperature response to reforestation potential design and suggests that some scenarios are more suitable for climate change mitigation than others.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Spatial differences in biogeophysical temperature patterns</title><p id="Par13">The spatial patterns of annual-mean near-surface temperature changes at the end of the century from BGP effects reveal both consistent and contrasting responses (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). All three datasets show robust cooling over large areas of tropical (23.5°S–23.5°N) and subtropical (23.5–35° latitude) land, particularly in South America, southern Africa, and East Asia (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a–d</xref>). The Moustakis reforestation potential leads to the largest cooling over Amazonia due to extensive projected reforestation there. This tropical cooling is consistent with enhanced evapotranspiration (increased latent heat flux) and a reduction in shortwave cloud forcing (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>). The cooling also reduces net longwave radiation at the surface (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>). However, some warming is also observed over tropical land, like over Indonesia and western Australia.</p><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Spatial biogeophysical temperature changes.</title><p><bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold> Global maps of the BGP annual-mean near-surface temperature changes for the ensemble mean of the three reforestation potentials relative to the baseline, averaged over 2071–2100. Stippling indicates regions where the response is statistically significant at the 90% significance level using the two-sample t-test with Benjamini–Hochberg correction<sup><xref rid="CR62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup>. <bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold> Average land-only and global temperature changes over the tropics (23.5<sup>∘</sup>S–23.5<sup>∘</sup>N), temperate (23.5<sup>∘</sup>–66.5<sup>∘</sup> in both hemispheres), and polar (66.5<sup>∘</sup>–90<sup>∘</sup> in both hemispheres) regions for the three reforestation datasets relative to the baseline. Error bars represent one standard deviation across the five ensemble members for the difference between the reforestation potential and the baseline.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e714" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/424a2134e6b1/43247_2026_3331_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 822?><?original-width 1992?><?scaled-height 328?><?scaled-width 796?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/7094c01a3056/43247_2026_3331_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par14">In temperate and polar regions, the spatial patterns of temperature change differ across scenarios. In temperate latitudes, we observe cooling over Europe and warming over the United States and Central Asia, leading to net temperate warming for the Bastin and Moustakis scenario, in contrast to a net cooling in the Hurtt scenario (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). In polar regions in the Northern Hemisphere, the Bastin scenario shows pronounced warming due to extensive reforestation. Replacing high-albedo snow and grassland with dark forest canopy decreases surface albedo, strongly increasing net surface shortwave radiation and sensible heat flux (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>). This warming persists year-round, being strongest in spring and summer (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>), even in a warming world. This seasonal signal, peaking in spring and summer, is consistent with prior studies that link this maximum warming to the strongest incident solar radiation in spring and summer, which maximizes the radiative forcing from the albedo change<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the magnitude of cloud changes in our simulations also peaks in summer and spring (similarly to Portmann et al.<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> and Guo et al.<sup><xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>), enhancing the surface warming during those seasons. This warming is also evident in the Moustakis reforestation simulations, albeit attenuated, but is largely absent in the Hurtt scenario (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b–d</xref>).</p><p id="Par15">Our analysis also identifies small, yet significant temperature responses over oceans, including warming over the equatorial Atlantic and Indian Ocean, and cooling over the Norwegian Sea across all datasets. The cooling response and reduction in the heat fluxes (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>) over the Norwegian Sea hint at an ocean circulation response to reforestation, similarly to oceanic changes found by Portmann et al.<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> and Bauer et al.<sup><xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. This oceanic cooling signal likely spreads over nearby land areas in all three scenarios, although it seems to be masked by albedo- and non-local-induced warming in the midlatitudes in the Bastin and Moustakis scenario. When considering combined ocean and land averages, near-zero changes are observed in the tropics, but significant warming (Bastin) and cooling (Hurtt) occur in the Arctic (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e</xref>).</p><p id="Par16">Overall, this highlights that the specific reforestation scenario, even with similar total forestation areas, profoundly influences the spatial patterns of the BGP temperature response.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="2"><title>Trade-offs between local and non-local temperature changes</title><p id="Par17">To further understand the mechanisms driving regional BGP temperature changes, we separate the total temperature response into local and non-local components using the MWR (see “Methods”) method (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The close agreement between the reconstructed total response (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a–c</xref>) and the simulated response (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a–c</xref>) validates this decomposition.</p><fig id="Fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Local and nonlocal temperature changes.</title><p>Global maps of the annual mean (<bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold>) total, (<bold>d</bold>–<bold>f</bold>) local, and (<bold>g</bold>–<bold>i</bold>) non-local near-surface biogeophysical temperature changes for the ensemble mean of the three reforestation potentials relative to the baseline, averaged over 2071–2100. The ensemble-mean temperature signal was decomposed using a Moving Window Regression (MWR) with a 9 × 9 window. The local response (<bold>d</bold>–<bold>f</bold>) is undefined over oceans.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e815" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/850ec97a6638/43247_2026_3331_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1158?><?original-width 1988?><?scaled-height 463?><?scaled-width 795?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig4_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/79ed355492f6/43247_2026_3331_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par18">The local response (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d–f</xref>) reveals consistent spatial patterns across all reforestation scenarios. Cooling is dominant in the tropics and subtropics, while albedo-related warming dominates at higher latitudes. Local tropical and subtropical cooling generally outweighs non-local influences, defining the net temperature change in these zones.</p><p id="Par19">Conversely, the total temperature response in mid- and high-latitudes, and over oceanic regions, is substantially influenced by non-local responses (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4g–i</xref>). These non-local effects, indicative of large-scale atmospheric and oceanic responses, are the primary drivers of the differences in climate response among the reforestation potentials. We observe widespread non-local warming in the Northern Hemisphere in the Bastin and Moustakis scenarios, whereas the Hurtt scenario exhibits widespread non-local cooling. Over the Norwegian Sea, a consistent non-local cooling is found across all three scenarios. This oceanic signal appears to influence adjacent land regions, leading to non-local cooling over Europe, which reinforces the small local cooling effect there.</p><p id="Par20">These findings highlight a complex interplay of local and non-local effects on the temperature response. Local cooling generally dominates in the tropics and subtropics, while higher latitudes are characterized by a combination of local albedo-related warming and varied non-local effects.</p><p id="Par21">Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> provides a regional synthesis of reforestation impacts across IPCC land regions, highlighting the magnitude of the reforestation potential (circle size), the local BGP temperature response (inner circle color), and the total BGP temperature response (outer ring color) from 2071 to 2100. This integrated perspective illustrates the complex interplay between local and non-local BGP effects and the resulting total BGP temperature changes. We identify five distinct types of regional BGP climate response: (1) strong local cooling dominates the total response (e.g., Northeastern South America and the South American monsoon region in the Moustakis scenario); (2) local warming is amplified by non-local effects (e.g., Central North America in all datasets); (3) total temperature change is predominantly driven by non-local effects (e.g., Western and Central Europe in the Hurtt scenario or Northwestern North America in Bastin scenario); (4) local cooling and non-local warming balance, leading to a near-zero total temperature change (e.g., Central Africa in the Moustakis and Bastin scenario) and (5) both local and non-local effects are near-zero (e.g., India in Hurtt and Moustakis scenario).</p><fig id="Fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Synthesis of reforestation potentials and biogeophysical temperature responses.</title><p>Summary figure of end-of-century temperature changes following the (<bold>a</bold>) Bastin, (<bold>b</bold>) Moustakis and (<bold>c</bold>) Hurtt reforestation potentials across IPCC land regions used in AR6<sup><xref rid="CR73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></sup>. The size of each dot per IPCC region shows the reforestation potential area within that region. The color of the inner dot (surrounded by a dashed line) shows the local BGP temperature change, and the color of the outer ring shows the corresponding total BGP ensemble mean temperature change, averaged across the 2071–2100 period. The BGP temperature signal was decomposed using an MWR with a 9 × 9 window. The dot color combinations can be interpreted as follows: (1) Regions with a blue outer circle and similarly colored inner circle indicate that the local cooling dominates the total response; (2) Regions with a slight red inner and dark red outer circle highlight that the local warming is amplified by non-local effects; (3) Regions with a near-zero (white) inner and blue or red colored outer circle indicate that the total temperature change is predominantly driven by non-local effects; and (4) Regions with near-zero (white) outer circles highlight that local and non-local changes are opposite and nearly balance each other out.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e854" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/902a17cad253/43247_2026_3331_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1149?><?original-width 2000?><?scaled-height 460?><?scaled-width 800?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_Fig5_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/93c6/12979200/c80aad3776aa/43247_2026_3331_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par22">This regional synthesis helps to identify high-potential climate mitigation areas. All three datasets show large reforestation potential combined with strong BGP cooling potential in South America (e.g., South American monsoon region) and Africa (e.g., Southeastern Africa) due to evapotranspiration-driven benefits (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>). This agreement is especially apparent when normalizing the local response by reforestation area (a measure of forest sensitivity), yielding values of −2 to −1 °C per Mha for these regions (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>). Reforestation programs in these areas would directly contribute to local temperature reductions due to BGC and BGP cooling, representing a high-potential local climate strategy. Our findings also highlight regions where local BGP cooling is counterbalanced by non-local BGP warming, such as in East Asia in the Bastin and Moustakis reforestation potential (also see Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Reforestation here would still be beneficial, as local BGP cooling could either mitigate non-local BGP warming or, in the absence of such an effect, provide direct local cooling benefits from BGP and BGC effects. Conversely, our analysis highlights regions, particularly in mid- to high-latitudes (e.g., Central North America), where the local BGP warming response is amplified by non-local BGP effects. Reforestation projects in these regions would show no temperature benefits (if the large BGP warming compensates for the BGC cooling) or even become climatically detrimental (if the BGP warming is larger than the BGC cooling).</p><p id="Par23">This regional breakdown demonstrates that the climate efficacy of reforestation is not uniform and emphasizes the critical need for climate-optimized reforestation strategies that account for both BGC and BGP effects. Nonetheless, we cannot quantify in this model setup the remote effects of each regional reforestation, which can only be inferred indirectly from the reforestation potential differences.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">The implementation of large-scale reforestation as an effective climate change mitigation strategy requires a comprehensive understanding of its biogeophysical and biogeochemical temperature effects. Our study provides a systematic comparison of three distinct reforestation potentials within a state-of-the-art, fully-coupled Earth System Model (CESM2). This approach offers a consistent framework to robustly quantify the temperature response to different reforestation strategies. This is a crucial advancement over previous research, which was limited to observations of historical and present-day local impacts [e.g., ref. <sup><xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>], to idealized reforestation simulations [e.g., refs. <sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>] or, when using reforestation potentials, implemented only a single potential in a fully-coupled model<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> or used a land-atmosphere model without ocean coupling<sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. Only this fully-coupled approach allows for the integration of dynamic ocean responses, which are important for characterizing the full global climate response and accurately quantifying the regional balance between local biophysical effects and the atmosphere- and ocean-mediated non-local impacts. For instance, Davin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> demonstrated that incorporating ocean coupling fundamentally alters the simulated BGP land temperature response to deforestation, changing the net land effect from a warming (under fixed oceanic conditions) to a cooling when ocean responses are included.</p><p id="Par25">Our analysis provides a systematic quantification of the global biogeophysical, biogeochemical, and net temperature response to three distinct reforestation potentials. We find a near-zero to slightly positive (0.09 °C) global BGP temperature change, which is consistent with the small global BGP effect to historical deforestation<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>. This BGP warming can partially offset the dominant BGC cooling from carbon sequestration<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>. Our results show robust net global cooling across all scenarios, ranging from −0.13 °C (Bastin, Hurtt) to −0.25 °C (Moustakis) by 2100. The value for the Moustakis scenario is in good agreement with emission-driven simulations from Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>, who reported a cooling of −0.2 °C with the MPI-ESM model and a different emission pathway (SSP5-3.4os). Crucially, our direct comparison of several reforestation potentials allows for the valuable quantitative evidence that similar net global cooling can be achieved with substantially less reforested area (up to 450 Mha) if planting locations are optimized for climate benefits. This highlights that the geographical placement of reforestation can be as, or even more, important than the total area for maximizing cooling benefits.</p><p id="Par26">Our findings also shed light on the regional BGP temperature patterns and the role of non-local effects. Reforestation leads to significant local BGP cooling in the tropics and subtropics due to enhanced evapotranspiration, aligning with previous idealized studies<sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>. However, in higher latitudes, we observe a complex mix of local and non-local BGP warming. This is consistent with previous idealized studies showing strong BGP warming from albedo changes in boreal regions<sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>. Previous criticism of the Bastin reforestation potential by Friedlingsstein et al.<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> mentioned that BGP effects were not considered; we quantify this effect, finding that local BGP warming is further amplified by non-local BGP effects to reach above 1 °C in mid- to high latitudes. Inter-model differences in reforestation effects are often attributed to divergent representation of non-local processes<sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>. However, our work reveals that differences between reforestation patterns alone can induce a wide range of non-local BGP effects. This insight demonstrates that the geographical pattern of planting, via its impact on large-scale climate, is the primary source of divergent temperature outcomes to different reforestation scenarios, potentially even in a multi-model setup.</p><p id="Par27">While our findings offer valuable insights, some uncertainties remain. Firstly, our reliance on a single Earth System Model (CESM2) means we cannot account for inter-model uncertainties. While comparison with previous ESM simulations implementing one of the presented reforestation patterns allows for some contextualization [e.g., refs. <sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>], future work should test the robustness of our findings by repeating this work with additional ESMs, different forcing pathways and additional reforestation potential scenarios. Secondly, CLM5 with prognostic vegetation potentially underestimates the transpiration fraction<sup><xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>. Given that reforestation-induced biophysical cooling is driven by enhanced latent heat flux from increased transpiration, our simulated cooling effects are likely conservative estimates. Importantly, however, CESM2 performs well against observations for BGP impacts of forest cover changes, ranking it highly in the CMIP6 ensemble<sup><xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup>. Thirdly, our approximation of the carbon effect using the TCRE concept<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> does not include aerosol-related effects from reforestation<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and assumes that temperature changes are solely driven by land carbon changes. Furthermore, the TCRE value of CESM2 (2.13 °C EgC<sup>−1</sup>)<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> is at the upper end of the observational (1.0–2.3 °C EgC<sup>−1</sup>)<sup><xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup> and CMIP6 model range (1.32–2.3 °C EgC<sup>−1</sup>)<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. A sensitivity analysis shows that using these lower TCRE values from observations and CMIP6 result in a smaller global-mean net cooling by up to 0.05 °C less (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref>). An additional limitation regarding the calculation of the biogeochemical temperature response based on the TCRE values and the uptake of carbon from land is that this land carbon sequestration might be overestimated, as the atmospheric concentration does not decrease in response to the plant growth, thereby sustaining a higher CO<sub>2</sub> fertilization effect compared to an emission-driven simulation. Finally, our implemented linear afforestation trajectory and the assumption of no other land use and land cover change (LULCC) are simplifications of real-world complexities.</p><p id="Par28">Based on our findings, we suggest shifting from maximizing reforestation area towards climate-smart policies that strategically choose planting locations to maximize cooling benefits [e.g., refs. <sup><xref rid="CR53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="CR54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup>]. Current policies and commitments on the national and international level, such as the Paris Agreement<sup><xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup> or UN Framework for REDD+<sup><xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup>, focus exclusively on forests as sinks for greenhouse gases (BGC effects) and do not consider local and non-local BGP effects following forestation. However, based on our findings, these policies should consider BGP effects in addition to BGC effects, a recommendation that aligns with Windisch et al.<sup><xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. We provide a novel perspective that builds on their work, which was based on observational data under current climate conditions. Our approach assesses local responses under future climate change and demonstrates how non-local responses can outweigh local effects in some regions. This has important policy implications, as it helps explain why local cooling benefits may not be evident in the total climate response and enables the evaluation of reforestation strategies beyond current climate conditions. Our results suggest prioritizing reforestation in the tropics and subtropics, where strong local BGP and BGC cooling offers the greatest direct climate benefit, consistent with prior studies<sup><xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="CR57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup>. Additionally, tropical forests have been shown to have a lower risk of detrimental non-local temperature effects<sup><xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>. Conversely, reforestation in high- and polar-latitude regions can be a counterproductive climate strategy<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>, as reforestation leads to albedo-driven local warming (often further amplified by non-local effects) even in a warming world that can mask or outweigh BGC cooling. Similarly, relying primarily on non-local BGP cooling benefits, such as those in Northern Europe, would be ill-advised for a targeted local adaptation strategy due to their remote and unpredictable nature. While strategic reforestation placement for climate benefits is important, effective policies must also consider societal factors, biodiversity, and ecosystem services to ensure long-term success. Ultimately, while reforestation is one of the only carbon dioxide removal methods readily available at large scale, our simulations show that even ambitious reforestation potentials may only provide a maximum cooling of −0.25 °C. This underscores that it must be considered a complement to, rather than a replacement for, immediate and deep emission reductions to meet global temperature targets.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="2"><title>Reforestation potential maps</title><p id="Par29">This study analyzes the climate response to three distinct reforestation potentials, focusing on their impact on temperature. Our literature review identified 19 global maps for reforestation<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. From these, we selected the datasets by Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>, Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>, and Hurtt et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> for implementation in our simulations (hereafter referred to as Bastin, Moustakis, and Hurtt reforestation potentials). The Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> reforestation potential is based on satellite and ground-based measurements combined with machine learning. The Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> map was chosen for its integrated approach, which synthesizes thousands of Integrated Assessment Model (IAM) scenarios with existing reforestation datasets from Griscom et al.<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> and the Atlas of Forest Landscape Restoration Opportunities (FLRO<sup><xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>), offering a more synthesized and policy-relevant perspective. Both the maps by Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> serve as an upper-bound estimate of global reforestation potential (935 Mha for Moustakis and 900 Mha for Bastin), which is useful to estimate the maximum potential effect that large-scale reforestation could have. The Bastin reforestation potential has drawn notable criticism, including for its widespread reforestation in boreal regions that likely induces BGP warming<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CR58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup>. The geographic differences between our two scenarios, therefore, allow for a comparative analysis of the climate impacts of reforestation placement and provide a means to evaluate some of these previously raised concerns. Lastly, we selected the SSP1-2.6 scenario from Hurtt et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. This scenario is a component of the Land-Use Harmonization version 2 (LUH2) dataset, which is a standard input for climate models, and is derived from the Integrated Assessment Model IMAGE that includes a dynamic vegetation model. The Hurtt reforestation scenario thus serves as an important bridge between established climate community land-use scenarios and the recent ecology- or machine learning-based reforestation potentials. Additionally, we selected this SSP1-2.6 land-use scenario as it is a low warming scenario that is close to the Paris Agreement and represents a medium reforestation potential (around 440 Mha) compared to the other two datasets. Note that the difference in SSPs used for the forcing (SSP2-4.5) and the Hurtt reforestation potential (SSP1-2.6) will not cause any inconsistencies, as we are investigating the climate response to a land-use perturbation, not the socio-economic feasibility of achieving this change in land-use within the SSP2-4.5 world. Table <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> provides detailed information on the methodologies, underlying assumptions, total reforestation area, total carbon uptake, and climatic context for these three selected reforestation potentials<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par30">Other available reforestation potential maps were not selected due to several limiting factors, including practical feasibility, assumed safeguards and availability. Some datasets<sup><xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> assumed an unrealistic absence of human activity, proposing reforestation across all cropland and cultivated grassland areas. Moreover, the dataset by Laestadius et al.<sup><xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> has been critiqued for potentially overestimating the global reforestation potential. A key technical consideration was the unit of measurement: several potential restoration datasets<sup><xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> were provided in units of carbon uptake. This would have necessitated a complex conversion from carbon to a suitable forest input map for CESM2. Furthermore, some datasets<sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> did not have openly available data repositories, and others did not provide estimates at the gridcell level<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. Additionally, the Griscom et al.<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> was not chosen as it is considered in the Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> dataset and the Weber et al.<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> dataset as it has already been implemented in CESM2. The recent datasets from Fesenmyer et al.<sup><xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> and Roebroeck et al.<sup><xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> were published after the completion of our simulations. While the dataset from Fesenmyer et al.<sup><xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> would be valuable for future climate model implementations to represent a lower-bound estimate, exploring such a scenario would require substantial additional computational resources. This is because the resulting weak climate signal, stemming from the small restoration area, would require a larger ensemble size to be reliably separated from natural climate variability.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Implementation of reforestation potential maps</title><p id="Par31">To assess the impact of future reforestation scenarios on the climate, we conducted simulations based on reforestation potentials by Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>, Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>, and Hurtt et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> in comparison to a baseline scenario under SSP2-4.5 forcing. In the baseline scenario, land cover (natural vegetation and cropland) was held constant at the 2015 level for the entire length of the simulation (2015 to 2100).</p><p id="Par32">We then generated a land-use timeseries input for the Community Land Model version 5 (CLM5), the land component of CESM2<sup><xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>, based on the three different reforestation potentials. For the Bastin dataset, we used the reforestation potential rather than the global potential tree cover to avoid the impact of differing climatological tree cover distribution based on satellite- and ground-based data from Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and CLM5. We then followed these steps to generate a land-use timeseries input for CLM5 based on the Bastin reforestation potential: First, we converted the Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> reforestation potential from the original TIFF format into a NetCDF file. The Bastin dataset assumes that grid cells with non-zero reforestation potential are set to 100% land cover, while regions with zero potential or ocean areas contain not-a-number (NaN) values. For integration into CLM5, remapping to the CESM2 resolution necessitated accounting for changes in land fraction. This was achieved by employing the Bastin future risk data (which includes NaN values over oceans and numerical values over land) to construct a land-ocean mask. Applying this mask to the Bastin reforestation potential data preserved NaN values over the ocean, introduced zeroes for land areas with no reforestation potential, and maintained the original reforestation values in all other land grid cells. Next, we conservatively remapped the Bastin dataset from its native resolution (30 arc sec) to the CESM2 resolution of 0.9° latitude × 1.25° longitude. This yielded a land-specific map of Bastin data at CESM2 resolution, to which we applied the CESM2 land-sea mask, ensuring that non-zero reforestation potential was assigned exclusively to land areas within CESM2.</p><p id="Par33">To create a Moustakis input dataset, we used the change in forest fraction data in 2100 at the grid cell level<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. This data contains NaN values over the ocean and values ranging from 0 to 1 reforestation potential over land, expressed as fractions of grid cell area. We divided this potential by the land fraction of MPI to get land-specific values. We then conservatively remapped the data to the resolution of CESM2 and masked the remapped dataset by the land-sea mask from CESM2.</p><p id="Par34">As the third dataset, we created a reforestation potential input file based on the SSP1-2.6 scenario from Hurtt et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. For this, we used the SSP input for the CESM2 model (which is already at CESM2 resolution) and converted the forest cover data to land-specific values. We then calculated the maximum forest cover in every grid cell from 2015 to 2100 to define a reforestation potential. This approach of using the maximum forest cover across the time period, rather than the difference between forest cover in 2100 and 2015, ensured that only reforestation (and no deforestation) was implemented, thereby making this definition of reforestation potential more comparable across datasets.</p><p id="Par35">After creating CLM-resolution maps for all three reforestation potentials, we constructed a land-use timeseries file for CLM5. For this, we calculated a linear reforestation trajectory from 2015 to 2070 for each gridcell, ensuring that the full reforestation potential for each gridcell of each respective dataset was attained by 2070. This method accounts for regional variations in reforestation speed due to unique linear trajectories for each gridcell, reflecting the likely heterogeneous reforestation efforts. To accommodate reforestation, existing vegetation types were removed hierarchically in the following order: shrubs (PFTs 9-11), grasses (PFTs 12-14), and then crops (CFTs) (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S6</xref>). This specific hierarchy was chosen to minimize the reduction of non-irrigated and irrigated cropland. Note that it is assumed that no future expansion of croplands or grazing lands occurs according to our implementation, which could be attributed to shifts in dietary patterns or increased efficiency in existing agricultural practices. Additionally, bare soil, ice-covered regions and urban areas were excluded from reforestation to maintain consistency with the safeguards applied in the reforestation potentials and considering the small likelihood of plant growth in bare soil and ice-covered regions. After the fraction of shrub, grass and cropland was reduced, the original forest fraction is scaled up proportionally to match the projected reforestation potential in that grid cell. Note that reforestation was only implemented in regions where CESM2 already contained forest. In locations where a reforestation potential dataset suggested reforestation but CESM2 did not contain forest historically (i.e., in 2015), land cover was reverted to its original distribution, although adjustment impacted only less than 1% of the grid cells. To investigate equilibration effects after the full forest change is implemented, we extended the simulations beyond 2070 by maintaining full reforestation potential for an additional 30 years, until 2100.</p><p id="Par36">Using this methodology, we successfully implemented around 99% of the Bastin reforestation potential into CESM2. The remaining 1% could not be incorporated due to geographic constraints, as these areas—primarily located in the Canadian Arctic, parts of Greenland and Siberia—were either covered by snow and ice, classified as urban or bare soil, or already fully forested in CESM2. Similarly, we were able to implement over 99% of the Moustakis and Hurtt scenario (Table <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="2"><title>CESM2 model and experimental design</title><p id="Par37">The simulations in this study were performed with the fully-coupled CESM2.1.2 model to capture forest-induced climate response and allow an examination of coupled biosphere-atmosphere-ocean interactions. Previous research has demonstrated robust model performance of CESM2 concerning Leaf Area Index (LAI) sensitivity, albedo, and surface radiation<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>, as well as in simulating temperature and precipitation patterns<sup><xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup>. The model has a horizontal resolution of 0.9° latitude × 1.25° longitude and comprises the Community Atmospheric Model version 6 (CAM6), the Community Land Model version 5 (CLM5), the Parallel Ocean Program version 2 (POP2), the Los Alamos Sea Ice Model (CICE), the Model for Scale Adaptive River Transport (MOSART) and the Land Ice Model (CISM2). The CESM2 model version used here does not allow dynamic changes in vegetation composition. We used the biogeochemical (BGC-Crop) mode in CLM5, as it includes active biogeochemistry and fires, and provides a more physically plausible representation of vegetation dynamics by allowing trees to die if planted outside their suitable climatic regions<sup><xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par38">Each simulation was run from 2015 to 2100 in a concentration-driven mode, driven by the transient forcing of SSP2-4.5 (BSSP245cmip6 compset) with the exception of land use change. In the control simulation, forest cover was held constant at 2015 levels. In the three reforestation simulations, the reforestation potential from Bastin, Moustakis, and Hurtt was linearly increased from 2015 to 2070, followed by 30 years of constant forest cover. Land-use options such as harvesting, grazing, and nitrogen fertilizer usage were set to zero in the control and reforestation simulations, while irrigation could dynamically respond to simulated soil moisture conditions.</p><p id="Par39">To reduce the effect of internal variability and enhance the signal-to-noise ratio, five ensemble members were run for both the control and each reforestation potential simulation. These ensemble members branched off from 2015 from the BHISTcmip6 simulations of the CESM2 Large Ensemble (CESM2-LE<sup><xref rid="CR60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup>). We excluded the BSMBB simulations due to the limited availability of restart files and to maintain consistency with CMIP6 historical simulations. The selection of CESM2-LE ensemble members was based on latitude-weighted sea surface temperatures (SSTs) over the subpolar North Atlantic (SPNA) region (45-65°N, 50°W-0°), averaged over 2010-2014. This index is strongly correlated with the strength of the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC)<sup><xref rid="CR61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup>. Specifically, we chose ensemble members that fell within the 10<sup>th</sup>, 25<sup>th</sup>, 50<sup>th</sup>, 75<sup>th</sup> and 90<sup>th</sup> percentiles of the SPNA SST distribution, corresponding to weak (ensemble members 1251.010), medium-weak (ensemble member 1141.008), medium (ensemble member 1251.005), medium-strong (ensemble members 1281.009) and strong (ensemble member 1021.002) AMOC states, respectively. This approach allows for an assessment of the sensitivity of our results to underlying patterns of oceanic variability while ensuring that the simulations encompass a broad range of possible initial conditions.</p><p id="Par40">The results are presented as the ensemble means, which represent the biogeophysical effects of global reforestation driven by changes in albedo, evapotranspiration and surface roughness. To calculate the ensemble means, we first calculate the difference of each reforestation potential ensemble member from the according baseline ensemble member (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>) and then take the ensemble mean. We present ensemble means to reduce the influence of internal variability, and because the influence of the AMOC initialisation state on the simulated response diminished rapidly, becoming negligible beyond the initial 20 years of simulations. The analysis focused on near-surface air temperature changes. This temperature variable is defined as 2 m above the combined roughness length and displacement height, meaning that the temperature usually lies above the tree canopy in forested areas. CESM2 (and other ESMs) does not have a temperature variable that would capture surface shading effects from trees, which would lead to local cooling effects just below the tree canopy. All spatial maps are shown as a time average over the last 30 years of the simulation (2071–2100), during which forest cover was held constant. The significance of the results has been evaluated using a two-sample t-test with Benjamini-Hochberg correction<sup><xref rid="CR62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,<xref rid="CR63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup>. Stippling in spatial figures shows significant responses at the 90% significance level.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="2"><title>Calculation of the biogeochemical temperature effect of reforestation</title><p id="Par41">Since our simulations are concentration-driven and solely capture the biogeophysical effects of reforestation, we approximate the associated biogeochemical temperature effect based on changes in land carbon stocks. This approximation uses the concept of the transient climate response to cumulative emissions (TCRE)<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="CR64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></sup>. The TCRE quantifies the amount of global warming per unit of cumulative fossil fuel emission at the point of doubling of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration relative to a baseline. A key characteristic of the TCRE is its approximate constancy over time and independence from the specific emission trajectory<sup><xref rid="CR65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup>. To estimate the global-mean near-surface temperature change attributable to the biogeochemical impacts of reforestation (<inline-formula id="IEq10"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1322"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>), we use the following formula from Amali et al.<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>: </p><disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1345" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">BGC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">TCRE</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Land</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></disp-formula><p> where <inline-formula id="IEq11"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1378"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Land</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the total change in the land carbon stock (variable TOTECOSYSC from CESM2) between the baseline and each reforestation scenario and the TCRE value of 2.13 °C EgC<sup>−1</sup> for the CESM2 model is taken from Arora et al.<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. The overbars denote global-mean values. We additionally did a sensitivity test by repeating the calculations with TCRE values based on the observational range identified by the IPCC AR6 (1.0–2.3 °C EgC<sup>−1</sup> with a best estimate of 1.65 °C EgC<sup>−1</sup><sup><xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>) and the CMIP6 ESM range (1.32–2.3 °C EgC<sup>−1</sup><sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>), with the results presented in Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref> and described in the discussion section.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="2"><title>Separation of local and nonlocal signals using Moving Window Regression</title><p id="Par42">We disentangled the local and non-local biogeophysical temperature responses to identify regions that could directly benefit from reforestation versus those primarily influenced by remote climate signals. Local responses arise from in-situ land-atmosphere interactions due to changes in surface properties like roughness, evaporative capacity, and albedo<sup><xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup>. Non-local responses are remotely induced by larger-scale atmospheric or oceanic changes. This separation provides a deeper understanding of the interplay between local surface processes and the large-scale climate system.</p><p id="Par43">Here, we used the MWR method<sup><xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="CR68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup>. This method has been proven effective in extracting the LULCC signal from simulations [e.g., ref. <sup><xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup>] and observations [e.g., ref. <sup><xref rid="CR69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></sup>]. For each grid cell, a linear regression is performed between the near-surface temperature change (climate response) and tree cover fraction change (surface forcing) across surrounding grid cells within a defined window. The intercept of this linear regression represents the non-local signal, which is the climate response that would be present without LULCC in the specific grid cell and is influenced by atmospheric processes. The slope of the regression gives the local signal, which is assumed to be directly related to land cover changes within the grid cell. The total response is then calculated as the sum of the local and non-local signal. The MWR method has proven to provide estimates of local versus non-local temperature responses compatible with estimates from other methods like checkerboard interpolation and spectral decomposition<sup><xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par44">In this study, we used a 9 × 9 grid cell window for the MWR. Consistent with previous literature<sup><xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>, we found that the results are largely insensitive to the window size. Thus, we chose a 9 × 9 window which provides a suitable trade-off between capturing significant trends and accurately explaining the simulated behaviour.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary information</title>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM1" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 93c6/12979200/26831519b01d/43247_2026_3331_MOESM1_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1520551?><caption><p>Transparent Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM2" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 93c6/12979200/0a9bcd142571/43247_2026_3331_MOESM2_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 10690805?><caption><p>Supplementary Material</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Sebastian Schemm and Sonia Seneviratne for the helpful discussion regarding the simulation design. They would like to thank Johan van der Hoogen for his help with questions regarding the Bastin map. They further thank Urs Beyerle for his help with modelling-related questions. Finally, the authors would like to thank the three reviewers for their helpful comments and suggestions. This work was supported by an ETH Zurich Research Grant. N.L.S.F. and R.C.J.W. additionally acknowledge funding from the Swiss National Science Foundation (Award PCEFP2 203376). SJDH acknowledges funding by the Belgian Federal Science Policy Office BELSPO (B2/223/P1/DAMOCO and SR/00/410/AFROCARDS). F.J. acknowledges funding from the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program (ForestNavigator project, grant agreement 101056875), including funding from the Swiss Secretariat for Education, Research and Innovation (SERI).</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>N.L.S.F. conceived the research idea. N.L.S.F., S.J.D.H., and R.C.J.W. designed the study with inputs from F.J. and P.J.L. N.L.S.F. performed the CESM2 simulations and data analysis, visualised the results, and wrote the initial draft. All others contributed to the interpretation and discussion of the results and edited the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Peer review</title><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="2"><title>Peer review information</title><p id="Par45"><italic>Communications Earth and Environment</italic> thanks Lei Zhu, Shijing Liang and Hunter Douglas for their contribution to the peer review of this work. Primary handling editors: Yi Jiao, Mengjie Wang. [A peer review file is available].</p></sec></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>The reforestation potential data are published by Hurtt et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> via the Land Use Harmonization<sup>2</sup> (LUH2) webpage <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://luh.umd.edu/data.shtml" ext-link-type="uri">https://luh.umd.edu/data.shtml</ext-link>, by Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> on the ETH Zurich repository at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.research-collection.ethz.ch/handle/20.500.11850/350258" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.research-collection.ethz.ch/handle/20.500.11850/350258</ext-link> and by Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> on the Zenodo repository at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/records/12533125" ext-link-type="uri">https://zenodo.org/records/12533125</ext-link>. CESM is an open-source model, and the CESM2.1.2 version can be downloaded from the Zenodo repository 10.5281/zenodo.3895328<sup><xref rid="CR71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup>. The reforestation potential files at CESM2 resolution and processed CESM2 output data for this analysis are available via 10.5281/zenodo.16903179<sup><xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Code availability</title><p>The code to produce the figures of this manuscript is available via 10.5281/zenodo.16903179<sup><xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" disp-level="1"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par46">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="sec15" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s43247-026-03331-3.</p></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">IPCC. Summary for policymakers. in (eds Shukla, P. et al.) <italic>Mitigation of climate change. Contribution of working group III to the sixth assessment report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italic> (Cambridge University Press, 2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fuss, S. et al. Negative emissions-Part 2: Costs, potentials and side effects. <italic>Environ. Res. Lett</italic>. <bold>13</bold>, 063002 (2018).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Seddon, N. et al. Global recognition of the importance of nature-based solutions to the impacts of climate change. <italic>Glob. Sustain</italic>. <bold>3</bold>, e15 (2020).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Griscom, B. W. et al. Natural climate solutions. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>114</bold>, 11645–11650 (2017).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1710465114"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5676916"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29078344"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Griscom, B. W. et al. Natural climate solutions. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA114, 11645–11650 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">IPCC. Summary for policymakers. in (eds Shukla, P. et al.) <italic>Climate Change and Land: an IPCC special report on climate change, desertification, land degradation, sustainable land management, food security, and greenhouse gas fluxes in terrestrial ecosystems</italic> (Cambridge University Press, 2019).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">European Commision. Nature restoration law <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/topics/nature-and-biodiversity/nature-restoration-law_en" ext-link-type="uri">https://environment.ec.europa.eu/topics/nature-and-biodiversity/nature-restoration-law_en</ext-link> (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bonan, G. B. Forests and climate change: forcings, feedbacks, and the climate benefits of forests. <italic>Science</italic><bold>320</bold>, 1444–1449 (2008).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.1155121"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="18556546"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bonan, G. B. Forests and climate change: forcings, feedbacks, and the climate benefits of forests. Science320, 1444–1449 (2008)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hasler, N. et al. Accounting for albedo change to identify climate-positive tree cover restoration. <italic>Nat. Commun</italic>. <bold>15</bold>, 2275 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-024-46577-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10965905"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38531896"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Betts, R. A. Offset of the potential carbon sink from boreal forestation by decreases in surface albedo. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>408</bold>, 187–190 (2000).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/35041545"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11089969"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Betts, R. A. Offset of the potential carbon sink from boreal forestation by decreases in surface albedo. Nature408, 187–190 (2000)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kristensen, J. A. et al. Tree planting is no climate solution at northern high latitudes. <italic>Nat. Geosci</italic>. <bold>17</bold>, 1087–1092 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Swann, A. L. S., Fung, I. Y. &amp; Chiang, J. C. H. Mid-latitude afforestation shifts general circulation and tropical precipitation. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>109</bold>, 712–716 (2012).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1116706108"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3271929"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22190490"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Swann, A. L. S., Fung, I. Y. &amp; Chiang, J. C. H. Mid-latitude afforestation shifts general circulation and tropical precipitation. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA109, 712–716 (2012)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bauer, V. M. et al. Impacts of North American forest cover changes on the North Atlantic Ocean circulation. <italic>Earth Syst. Dyn.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 379–409 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bauer, V. M. et al. Impacts of North American forest cover changes on the North Atlantic Ocean circulation. Earth Syst. Dyn.16, 379–409 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Laestadius, L., Maginnis, S., Minnemeyer, S., Saint-Laurent, C. &amp; Sizer, N. Mapping opportunities for forest landscape restoration. <italic>Unasylva</italic><bold>62</bold>, 47–48 (2011).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Laestadius, L., Maginnis, S., Minnemeyer, S., Saint-Laurent, C. &amp; Sizer, N. Mapping opportunities for forest landscape restoration. Unasylva62, 47–48 (2011)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Erb, K. H. et al. Unexpectedly large impact of forest management and grazing on global vegetation biomass. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>553</bold>, 73–76 (2018).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nature25138"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5756473"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="29258288"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Erb, K. H. et al. Unexpectedly large impact of forest management and grazing on global vegetation biomass. Nature553, 73–76 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bastin, J. F. et al. The global tree restoration potential. <italic>Science</italic><bold>365</bold>, 76–79 (2019).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.aax0848"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31273120"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bastin, J. F. et al. The global tree restoration potential. Science365, 76–79 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lewis, S. L., Wheeler, C. E., Mitchard, E. T. A. &amp; Koch, A. Regenerate natural forests to store carbon. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>568</bold>, 25–28 (2019).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/d41586-019-01026-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30940972"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lewis, S. L., Wheeler, C. E., Mitchard, E. T. A. &amp; Koch, A. Regenerate natural forests to store carbon. Nature568, 25–28 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cook-Patton, S. C. et al. Mapping carbon accumulation potential from global natural forest regrowth. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>585</bold>, 545 (2020).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-020-2686-x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32968258"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cook-Patton, S. C. et al. Mapping carbon accumulation potential from global natural forest regrowth. Nature585, 545 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hurtt, G. C. et al. Harmonization of global land use change and management for the period 850-2100 (LUH2) for CMIP6. <italic>Geosci. Model Dev.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 5425–5464 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hurtt, G. C. et al. Harmonization of global land use change and management for the period 850-2100 (LUH2) for CMIP6. Geosci. Model Dev.13, 5425–5464 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Strassburg, B. B. N. et al. Global priority areas for ecosystem restoration. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>586</bold>, 724–729 (2020).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-020-2784-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33057198"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Strassburg, B. B. N. et al. Global priority areas for ecosystem restoration. Nature586, 724–729 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dooley, K. et al. The Land Gap Report 2022 <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.landgap.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.landgap.org</ext-link> (2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Humpenöder, F. et al. Overcoming global inequality is critical for land-based mitigation in line with the Paris Agreement. <italic>Nat. Commun</italic>. <bold>13</bold>, 7453 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-022-35114-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9718475"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36460636"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Walker, W. S. et al. The global potential for increased storage of carbon on land. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>119</bold>, e2111312119 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.2111312119"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9191349"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35639697"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mo, L. et al. Integrated global assessment of the natural forest carbon potential. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>624</bold>, 92–101 (2023).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41586-023-06723-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10700142"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37957399"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mo, L. et al. Integrated global assessment of the natural forest carbon potential. Nature624, 92–101 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Moustakis, Y., Nützel, T., Wey, H. W., Bao, W. &amp; Pongratz, J. Temperature overshoot responses to ambitious forestation in an Earth System Model. <italic>Nat. Commun</italic>. <bold>15</bold>, 8235 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-024-52508-x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11413198"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39300072"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rouhette, T., Escobar, N., Zhao, X., Sanz, M. J. &amp; van de Ven, D. Limits to forests-based mitigation in integrated assessment modelling: global potentials and impacts under constraining factors. <italic>Environ. Res. Lett</italic>. <bold>19</bold>, 114017 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Weber, J. et al. Chemistry-albedo feedbacks offset up to a third of forestation’s CO2 removal benefits. <italic>Science</italic><bold>383</bold>, 860–864 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.adg6196"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38386743"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Weber, J. et al. Chemistry-albedo feedbacks offset up to a third of forestation’s CO2 removal benefits. Science383, 860–864 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bastin, J. F. et al. Global alternatives of natural vegetation cover. <italic>Nat. Commun</italic>. <bold>16</bold>, 6484 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-025-61520-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12267432"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40670344"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fesenmyer, K. A., Cook-Patton, S. C., Griscom, B. W. &amp; Zarin, D. J. Addressing critiques refines global estimates of reforestation potential for climate change mitigation. <italic>Nat. Commun</italic>. <bold>16</bold>, 4572 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-025-59799-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12159164"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40500256"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Roebroek, C. T. J. et al. Potential tree cover under current and future climate scenarios. <italic>Sci. Data</italic><bold>12</bold>, 564 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41597-025-04408-y"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11968939"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40180995"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, Y. et al. Land availability and policy commitments limit global climate mitigation from forestation. <italic>Science</italic><bold>389</bold>, 931–934 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.adj6841"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40875861"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, Y. et al. Land availability and policy commitments limit global climate mitigation from forestation. Science389, 931–934 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fricko, O. et al. The marker quantification of the shared socioeconomic pathway 2: a middle-of-the-road scenario for the 21st century. <italic>Glob. Environ. Change</italic><bold>42</bold>, 251–267 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Fricko, O. et al. The marker quantification of the shared socioeconomic pathway 2: a middle-of-the-road scenario for the 21st century. Glob. Environ. Change42, 251–267 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Veldman, J. W. et al. Where tree planting and forest expansion are bad for biodiversity and ecosystem services. <italic>BioScience</italic><bold>65</bold>, 1011–1018 (2015).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Veldman, J. W. et al. Where tree planting and forest expansion are bad for biodiversity and ecosystem services. BioScience65, 1011–1018 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Friedlingstein, P., Allen, M., Canadell, J. G., Peters, G. P. &amp; Seneviratne, S. I. Comment on “The global tree restoration potential”. <italic>Science</italic><bold>366</bold>, eaay7976 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.aay8060"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31624183"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Trillion Trees. Forests are our gratest hopes <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://trilliontrees.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://trilliontrees.org/</ext-link> (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">IPCC. An IPCC special report on the impacts of global warming of 1.5 °C above pre-industrial levels and related global greenhouse gas emission pathways, in the context of strengthening the global response to the threat of climate change, sustainable development, and efforts to eradicate poverty. in (eds Masson-Delmotte, V. et al.) <italic>Global Warming of</italic> 1.5 °C (Cambridge University Press, 2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Portmann, R. et al. Global forestation and deforestation affect remote climate via adjusted atmosphere and ocean circulation. <italic>Nat. Commun</italic>. <bold>13</bold>, 5569 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-022-33279-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9532392"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36195588"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">De Hertog, S. J. et al. The biogeophysical effects of idealized land cover and land management changes in Earth system models. <italic>Earth Syst. Dyn.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 629–667 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="De Hertog, S. J. et al. The biogeophysical effects of idealized land cover and land management changes in Earth system models. Earth Syst. Dyn.14, 629–667 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Devaraju, N., Bala, G. &amp; Modak, A. Effects of large-scale deforestation on precipitation in the monsoon regions: Remote versus local effects. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>112</bold>, 3257–3262 (2015).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1423439112"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4371945"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25733889"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Devaraju, N., Bala, G. &amp; Modak, A. Effects of large-scale deforestation on precipitation in the monsoon regions: Remote versus local effects. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA112, 3257–3262 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liang, S. et al. Climate mitigation potential for targeted forestation after considering climate change, fires, and albedo. <italic>Sci. Adv.</italic><bold>11</bold>, eadn7915 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/sciadv.adn7915"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11980826"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40203095"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kan, F. et al. Diminished biophysical cooling benefits of global forestation under rising atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>. <italic>Nat. Commun</italic>. <bold>16</bold>, 4410 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-025-59547-y"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12075575"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40360539"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Danabasoglu, G. et al. The Community Earth System Model Version 2 (CESM2). <italic>J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.</italic><bold>12</bold>, e2019MS001916 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Danabasoglu, G. et al. The Community Earth System Model Version 2 (CESM2). J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.12, e2019MS001916 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Amali, A. A. et al. Biogeochemical versus biogeophysical temperature effects of historical land-use change in CMIP6. <italic>Earth Syst. Dyn.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 803–840 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Amali, A. A. et al. Biogeochemical versus biogeophysical temperature effects of historical land-use change in CMIP6. Earth Syst. Dyn.16, 803–840 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Arora, V. K. et al. Carbon-concentration and carbon-climate feedbacks in CMIP6 models and their comparison to CMIP5 models. <italic>Biogeosciences</italic><bold>17</bold>, 4173–4222 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Arora, V. K. et al. Carbon-concentration and carbon-climate feedbacks in CMIP6 models and their comparison to CMIP5 models. Biogeosciences17, 4173–4222 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Davin, E. L. &amp; de Noblet-Ducoudre, N. Climatic impact of global-scale deforestation: radiative versus nonradiative processes. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>23</bold>, 97–112 (2010).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Davin, E. L. &amp; de Noblet-Ducoudre, N. Climatic impact of global-scale deforestation: radiative versus nonradiative processes. J. Clim.23, 97–112 (2010)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Guo, J., Liu, Y. &amp; Hu, Y. Climate response to vegetation removal on different continents. <italic>J. Geophys. Res. Atmos</italic>. <bold>129</bold>, e2023JD039531 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Windisch, M. G., Davin, E. L. &amp; Seneviratne, S. I. Prioritizing forestation based on biogeochemical and local biogeophysical impacts. <italic>Nat. Clim. Change</italic><bold>11</bold>, 867 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Windisch, M. G., Davin, E. L. &amp; Seneviratne, S. I. Prioritizing forestation based on biogeochemical and local biogeophysical impacts. Nat. Clim. Change11, 867 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Luo, X. et al. Local and nonlocal biophysical effects of historical land use and land cover changes in CMIP6 models and the intermodel uncertainty. <italic>Earths Future</italic><bold>12</bold>, e2023EF004220 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu, S. et al. Local and non-local biophysical impacts of deforestation on global temperature during boreal summer: CMIP6-LUMIP multimodel analysis. <italic>J. Geophys. Res. Atmos</italic>. <bold>128</bold>, e2022JD038229 (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lawrence, D. M. ea The community land model version 5: description of New Features, Benchmarking, and Impact of Forcing Uncertainty. <italic>J. Adv. Model Earth Syst.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 4245–4287 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lawrence, D. M. ea The community land model version 5: description of New Features, Benchmarking, and Impact of Forcing Uncertainty. J. Adv. Model Earth Syst.11, 4245–4287 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Luo, X. et al. An evaluation of cmip6 models in representing the biophysical effects of deforestation with satellite-based observations. <italic>J. Geophys. Res. Atmos</italic>. <bold>128</bold>, e2022JD038198 (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Boysen, L. R. et al. Global climate response to idealized deforestation in CMIP6 models. <italic>Biogeosciences</italic><bold>17</bold>, 5615–5638 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Boysen, L. R. et al. Global climate response to idealized deforestation in CMIP6 models. Biogeosciences17, 5615–5638 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Arias, P. A. et al. Technical summary. in <italic>Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</italic>, 33–144 (Cambridge University Press, 2021).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Weatherall, A. et al. Defining climate-smart forestry. in <italic>Climate-Smart Forestry in Mountain Regions</italic>, Vol. 40, 35–58 (Springer, 2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Seymour, F., Wolosin, M. &amp; Gray, E. Not just carbon: capturing all the benefits of forests for stabilizing the climate from local to global scales 10.46830/wrirpt.19.00004 (2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">United Nations. Paris agreement <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/english_paris_agreement.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/english_paris_agreement.pdf</ext-link> [last accessed: 20.11.2025] (2015).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">REDD+. Redd+ resources <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://unfccc.int/topics/land-use/workstreams/redd/redd-resources" ext-link-type="uri">https://unfccc.int/topics/land-use/workstreams/redd/redd-resources</ext-link> [last accessed: 20.11.2025] (2015).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lawrence, D., Coe, M., Walker, W., Verchot, L. &amp; Vandecar, K. The unseen effects of deforestation: biophysical effects on climate. <italic>Front. For. Glob. Change</italic><bold>5</bold>, 756115 (2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Veldman, J. W. et al. Comment on “The global tree restoration potential”. <italic>Science</italic><bold>366</bold>, eaay7976 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.aay7976"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31624182"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Meehl, G. A., Shields, C., Arblaster, J. M., Annamalai, H. &amp; Neale, R. Intraseasonal, seasonal, and interannual characteristics of regional monsoon simulations in CESM2. <italic>J. Adv. Model Earth Syst</italic>. <bold>12</bold>, e2019MS001962 (2020).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rodgers, K. B. et al. Ubiquity of human-induced changes in climate variability. <italic>Earth Syst. Dynam.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1393–1411 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rodgers, K. B. et al. Ubiquity of human-induced changes in climate variability. Earth Syst. Dynam.12, 1393–1411 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Deser, C. et al. Effects of macro vs. micro initialization and ocean initial-condition memory on the evolution of ensemble spread in the CESM2 large ensemble. <italic>Clim. Dyn</italic>. <bold>63</bold>, 62 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00382-024-07553-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11668834"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39726716"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Benjamini, Y. &amp; Hochberg, Y. Controlling the false discovery rate - A practical and powerful approach to multiple testing. <italic>J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B Stat. Methodol.</italic><bold>57</bold>, 289–300 (1995).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Benjamini, Y. &amp; Hochberg, Y. Controlling the false discovery rate - A practical and powerful approach to multiple testing. J. R. Stat. Soc. Ser. B Stat. Methodol.57, 289–300 (1995)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wilks, D. S. "the stippling shows statistically significant grid points” how research results are routinely overstated and overinterpreted, and what to do about it. <italic>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>97</bold>, 2263+ (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wilks, D. S. &#34;the stippling shows statistically significant grid points” how research results are routinely overstated and overinterpreted, and what to do about it. Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.97, 2263+ (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gillett, N. P., Arora, V. K., Matthews, D. &amp; Allen, M. R. Constraining the ratio of global warming to cumulative CO2 emissions using CMIP5 simulations. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 6844–6858 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gillett, N. P., Arora, V. K., Matthews, D. &amp; Allen, M. R. Constraining the ratio of global warming to cumulative CO2 emissions using CMIP5 simulations. J. Clim.26, 6844–6858 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zickfeld, K., Arora, V. K. &amp; Gillett, N. P. Is the climate response to CO<sub>2</sub> emissions path dependent? <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett</italic>. <bold>39</bold>, L05703 (2012).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lejeune, Q., Seneviratne, S. I. &amp; Davin, E. L. Historical land-cover change impacts on climate: comparative assessment of LUCID and CMIP5 multimodel experiments. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 1439–1459 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lejeune, Q., Seneviratne, S. I. &amp; Davin, E. L. Historical land-cover change impacts on climate: comparative assessment of LUCID and CMIP5 multimodel experiments. J. Clim.30, 1439–1459 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gao, L. et al. Localization or globalization? Determination of the optimal regression window for disaggregation of land surface temperature. <italic>IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sens.</italic><bold>55</bold>, 477–490 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gao, L. et al. Localization or globalization? Determination of the optimal regression window for disaggregation of land surface temperature. IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sens.55, 477–490 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lejeune, Q., Seneviratne, S. I. &amp; Davin, E. L. Historical deforestation locally increased the intensity of hot days in northern mid-latitudes. <italic>Nat. Clim. Change</italic><bold>8</bold>, 386 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lejeune, Q., Seneviratne, S. I. &amp; Davin, E. L. Historical deforestation locally increased the intensity of hot days in northern mid-latitudes. Nat. Clim. Change8, 386 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Baker, J. C. A. &amp; Spracklen, D. V. Climate benefits of intact Amazon forests and the biophysical consequences of disturbance. <italic>Front. For. Glob. Change</italic><bold>2</bold>, 47 (2019).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Jäger, F., Schwaab, J., Bukenberger, M., De Hertog, S. J. &amp; Seneviratne, S. I. Spectral decomposition and signal separation of climate responses to land cover changes. <italic>J. Geophys. Res. Atmos</italic>. <bold>130</bold>, e2024JD042698 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Danabasoglu, G. et al. CESM-release-cesm2.1.2 (release-cesm2.1.2). <italic>Zenodo</italic>10.5281/zenodo.3895328 (2020).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fahrenbach, N. L. S., De Hertog, S. J., Jäger, F., Lawrence, P. &amp; Jnglin Wills, R. Reforestation scenarios shape global and regional temperature outcomes. <italic>Zenodo</italic>10.5281/zenodo.16903179 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Iturbide, M. et al. An update of IPCC climate reference regions for subcontinental analysis of climate model data: definition and aggregated datasets. <italic>Earth Syst. Sci. Data</italic><bold>12</bold>, 2959–2970 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Iturbide, M. et al. An update of IPCC climate reference regions for subcontinental analysis of climate model data: definition and aggregated datasets. Earth Syst. Sci. Data12, 2959–2970 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 93c6/12979200/26831519b01d/43247_2026_3331_MOESM1_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1520551?><caption><p>Transparent Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material2_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="43247_2026_3331_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 93c6/12979200/0a9bcd142571/43247_2026_3331_MOESM2_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 10690805?><caption><p>Supplementary Material</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The reforestation potential data are published by Hurtt et al.<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> via the Land Use Harmonization<sup>2</sup> (LUH2) webpage <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://luh.umd.edu/data.shtml" ext-link-type="uri">https://luh.umd.edu/data.shtml</ext-link>, by Bastin et al.<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> on the ETH Zurich repository at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.research-collection.ethz.ch/handle/20.500.11850/350258" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.research-collection.ethz.ch/handle/20.500.11850/350258</ext-link> and by Moustakis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> on the Zenodo repository at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/records/12533125" ext-link-type="uri">https://zenodo.org/records/12533125</ext-link>. CESM is an open-source model, and the CESM2.1.2 version can be downloaded from the Zenodo repository 10.5281/zenodo.3895328<sup><xref rid="CR71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup>. The reforestation potential files at CESM2 resolution and processed CESM2 output data for this analysis are available via 10.5281/zenodo.16903179<sup><xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup>.</p><p>The code to produce the figures of this manuscript is available via 10.5281/zenodo.16903179<sup><xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec></body></article>