<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2873</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ncomms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Nat Commun</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13287610</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13287610</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13287610</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">42331792</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-026-74157-y</article-id><title-group><article-title>Patterns, drivers, and trends of urban cooling demand across global cities</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names initials="N">Nilabhra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Anand</surname><given-names initials="P">Prashant</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names initials="A">Ansar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgescu</surname><given-names initials="M">Matei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Niyogi</surname><given-names initials="D">Dev</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Santamouris</surname><given-names initials="M">Mattheos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Artificial Intelligence and Human-Building Interaction Lab, Department of Architecture and Regional Planning, Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur, Kharagpur, India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Geography, Lalbaba College, University of Calcutta, Kolkata, India </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>School of Geographical Sciences and Urban Planning, Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Geography, National University of Singapore, Singapore, Singapore </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences, Jackson School of Geosciences, University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Fariborz Maseeh Department of Civil, Architectural, and Environmental Engineering, Cockrell School of Engineering, University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX USA </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label>School of Built Environment, University of New South Wales, Sydney, New South Wales Australia </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><fpage>5455</fpage><page-range>5455</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_Article_74157.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b390/13287610/456f430ad28c/41467_2026_Article_74157.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 13162538?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Urban cooling demand (UCD) is shaped by the three-dimensional evolution of cities, where climate, morphology, and demographic pressures interact to determine thermal energy needs. However, urbanization is driving heterogeneous volumetric growth, spanning horizontal expansion, vertical densification, and infilling, whose combined effects on UCD remain poorly quantified. Here, we analyse 88 Indian and 52 global cities from 2003 to 2023 and reveal a divergence in UCD trajectories driven by growth typologies. Cities undergoing extensive, irregular expansion exhibit the fastest relative increases in UCD despite lower initial demand, whereas medium-sized cities sustain the highest absolute demand. Compact urban forms show moderated trends, indicating structural thermal advantages. Across regions, volumetric growth, particularly vertical development and volumetric densification, is strongly associated with UCD and exhibits substantial explanatory power after climate, suggesting that urban form is  an important consideration in climate-responsive and energy-efficient urban transitions.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Environmental impact, Environmental health</p></sec></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">The authors show that city growth patterns strongly shape future cooling demand, with sprawling and vertically densifying cities showing the fastest rise, highlighting critical risks for energy demand, heat exposure, and climate-resilient urban planning.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 Jul 5; Accepted 2026 May 26; Collection date 2026.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Cities are considered as fundamental units of climate change adaptation and mitigation<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. Urbanization-induced development of cities drives multi-scale environmental change<sup><xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>, including global warming<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. The physical expansion of urban built forms, growth pattern of cities, and the associated CO<sub>2</sub> emissions from this development collectively drive local and regional warming, compounding the rise in global temperatures<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. As urban areas continue to warm, city-wide annual indoor cooling needs, henceforth called urban cooling demand (UCD), are expected to rise<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. However, beyond the rate or scale of urbanization, the impact of different spatial development patterns on UCD at city scale remains underexplored. While recent Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) assessment reports highlight the role of urban structure, form, and the relationships between physical elements, spaces, and activities in shaping urban energy use<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>, there is limited quantitative understanding of their collective influence on cooling demand.</p><p id="Par4">The evolution of cities and their built form is shaped by a complex interplay of socio-economic and environmental factors<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. The scope of our study is limited to the physical evolution of cities and built-forms. Urban built forms evolve through three key processes that reshape city volume: (i) lateral or horizontal expansion, where the urban fringe is developed into engineered landscapes<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>; (ii) structural development, which includes vertical growth, as taller buildings replace shorter ones<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>, and infilling<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> which occurs via a transition from open spaces to built infrastructure; (iii) and demographic densification, where changes in population density influence the extent and form of growth<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Collectively and through time, these changes shape urban volumetric changes. The resulting processes, henceforth called volumetric growth, define patterns of urban growth, which characterize the structure and function of cities<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. These processes also collectively impact surface energy dynamics<sup><xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>, creating temperature differentials within and around urban areas<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. In hot and humid as well as semi-arid regions, such temperature variations adversely affect urban quality of life by causing fluctuations in cooling energy demand<sup><xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> and can pose significant health risks<sup><xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Moreover, these concerns are compounded by socio-economic disparities, resulting in a disproportionate heat burden on city dwellers<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Despite over 13,000 cities worldwide experiencing such temperature variations and extreme heat stress<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>,<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> there is limited scientific understanding and empirical evidence on how different components of city-volumetric growth interact to shape UCD. Addressing this knowledge gap is essential for developing effective adaptation and mitigation strategies tailored to the diverse urban growth trajectories observed globally.</p><p id="Par5">Remote sensing and numerical modelling studies focused on lateral expansion of cities, attributing 20–50% of warming and up to 75% of cooling demand to urbanization<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. Spatial density of built forms is identified as a driver of cooling demand<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. However, studies rarely provide an integrated understanding of UCD variations across multiple cities, with particular focus on the relative roles of city size (lateral and vertical extent both), built-ground coverage (indicator of compactness as well as imperviousness), and population density growth together. Recently, Zhou et al.<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> Frolking et al.<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> highlighted vertical development as a critical yet overlooked factor in urbanization assessment studies that necessitate further study to ascertain their contribution to UCD. Numerical models often consider urban parameters: such as lateral expansion (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>H</italic></sub>), vertical development (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>V</italic></sub>) which shape urban canyon depths, built-ground coverage reflecting compactness as well as the share of impervious cover in urban cores (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>IR</italic></sub>), and population density (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub>) in a simplified form or based on Local Climate Zone classifications, which do not adequately capture the actual volumetric growth dynamics of urban areas<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. While there are recent attempts to capture the detailed impact of <inline-formula id="IEq1"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e398"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> on heat and cold exposure studies<sup><xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>, integrating observation-based high-resolution actual volumetric data increases computational complexity<sup><xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>, limiting large-scale assessments and leading to inconsistencies in intra-city UCD analysis<sup><xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–<xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. Addressing these gaps is crucial for accurately quantifying city-scale structural growth impact on UCD.</p><p id="Par6">In this study, we quantitatively examine the relationship between UCD and key indicators of city-scale volumetric growth (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>) for 88 Indian and 52 globally prominent cities. Leveraging high-resolution satellite and reanalysis datasets from 2003–2023, harmonized to a common spatial resolution of ~1 km and spatially aggregated within urban boundaries, we incorporate indicators such as varied measures of vertical expansion, lateral urban spread, infill densification, population density, vegetation cover, and road network intensity; dimensions that collectively characterize the evolving urban form. Our study advances and complements prior works in two key aspects, which we test in form of two hypotheses: (1) that the trajectory of volumetric growth, shaped by geomorphological factors and historical contingencies surrounding the growth of cities, influences UCD; and (2) that vertical expansion and volumetric densification have a stronger impact on UCD than horizontal expansion, particularly in rapidly developing cities coming under lower-middle income as well as high and upper-middle income classification, following the World Bank income classification of countries<sup><xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>. We classify these cities into four typologies based on shared volumetric growth characteristics, with additional stratifications based on regional and climatic factors. Using a humidity-weighted Cooling Degree Days (CDD-hum) approach as a proxy for UCD, derived using reanalysis meteorological data (ERA5-and), we capture monthly-to-annual demand dynamics with high temporal coherence (R ≈ 0.7–0.9, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) (see methods). This approach proves especially useful for Indian cities, where fine-resolution cooling energy data remain sparse. Our findings demonstrate that typology-specific growth patterns, when analysed alongside climatic and morphological context, exert a measurable influence on UCD trajectories. Prior global studies have already identified India, alongside Indonesia and China, as regions with rising UCD<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. With nearly 8% of Indian households currently equipped with air conditioning (AC), projections indicate a six-fold increase in ACs over the next two decades<sup><xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. The methodological framework and findings present here are thus not only critical for understanding the drivers of UCD in Indian cities, but also offer a broader lens to compare urban cooling demand trajectories across cities of Global South with lower-middle income, providing a foundation for future regional and global assessments of climate-responsive urbanization.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Patterns of annual UCD and its trends</title><p id="Par7">Our analysis of UCD across 2003 to 2023 shows that approximately 90% of analyzed Indian cities, situated in hot-humid, composite and semi-arid regions, such as Kolkata, Delhi, Chennai, and Jaipur, experience a substantial cooling demand, with mean CDD-hum of 1963 ± 78.46 °C-year (mean ± standard error). This translates to an average of 273 ± 1 days requiring cooling, with 22 °C base temperature. When the base temperature is increased to 28 °C, the CDD-hum decreases by 58% (821.86 ± 38 °C-year), with a corresponding reduction in cooling-demand days to 146 ± 5 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">20</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">22</xref>). Cities situated in cold climatic zones, primarily in the southern, western Himalayan foothills including Srinagar and Imphal, exhibit markedly lower cooling demands, with CDD-hum ranging from 82 to 438 °C-years and only 50 to 150 warmer days annually. Regionally, eastern coastal cities exhibit the highest demand (2514 ± 224 °C-year, with 22°C base temperature), exceeding western coastal and inland regions, despite similar climate classifications (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>). The estimated CDD-hum across 52 global cities also showed an overall increase of 1.12 ± 0.12% in cooling demand over the past two decades (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, the mean CDD-hum value remained significantly lower (~741.82 ± 99 °C-years) compared to that observed in Indian cities. Days requiring cooling generally fell within the range of 120 or more, as unlike Indian cities, many western cities also have a substantial reliance on space heating. Similar to Indian cities, the major coastal and inland cities across Asia did not exhibit significant differences in UCD. In contrast, pronounced regional variations were observed in the United States and Europe. Specifically, US inland cities exhibited significantly higher UCD values compared to their coastal counterparts, whereas in Europe, coastal cities showed relatively higher UCD than inland cities (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Patterns and trends of UCD across 88 Indian cities over the past two decades, modelled using humidity-weighted Cooling Degree Days (CDD-hum) with a base temperature of 22–28 °C.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Shows the average CDD-hum (°C-year) over the period 2003–2023, while <bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold> illustrate the linear (°C-year/year) and log-linear trends (%/year) of CDD-hum, respectively, based on ordinary least squares regression. Bubble size represents the relative magnitude of values across cities. Bubble edge colour represents volumetric city typology in panels <bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold> and regional setting in panels <bold>d</bold>–<bold>f</bold>. Boxplots in the first three panels (<bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold>) of the first row represent the distribution of trends across different volumetric city typologies (Type-I to Type-IV), while those in the last three panels (<bold>d</bold>–<bold>f</bold>) represent the distribution across regional settings of cities. Boxplots summarize distributions across volumetric typologies (Type I–IV) in <bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold> and across regional settings in <bold>d</bold>–<bold>f</bold>. Boxplots indicate the median (centre line), interquartile range (IQR; 25th–75th percentiles), whiskers extending to 1.5×IQR, and points beyond whiskers as outliers. <bold>d</bold>–<bold>f</bold> replicate panels <bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold>, respectively, with colour coding representing regional groupings: East Coast (EC), West Coast (WC), Indo-Gangetic Plain (IG), South and Western Himalayan Foothills and the North-Eastern Hill Region  (SH), Interior Peninsular/Deccan Plateau (DP), and Central and Western India (CI). The administrative boundary of India used in this study was obtained from the Survey of India, Online maps Portal<sup><xref rid="CR142" ref-type="bibr">142</xref></sup>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e559" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/3287f54318d7/41467_2026_74157_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEED_LOADING?><?original-height 1904?><?original-width 2000?><?scaled-height 762?><?scaled-width 800?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/ce9d69251ff0/41467_2026_74157_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Patterns and trends of UCD across 52 global cities (excluding Indian cities) over the past two decades, modelled using humidity-weighted Cooling Degree Days (CDD-hum) with a base temperature of 20 °C.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Shows the average CDD-hum (°C-year), while <bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold> show the linear (°C-year/year) and log-linear (%/year) trends, respectively based on ordinary least squares regression. Bubble size represents the relative magnitude across cities, and edge colour represents volumetric city typology. First column of boxplots in <bold>a</bold>–<bold>c</bold> represents continental distributions (Asia (ASIA), Australia (AUS), Europe (EUR), and United States (US)); while corresponding second column also show volumetric typology-based distributions (Type-I to Type-IV). Boxplots indicate the median (centre line), interquartile range (IQR; 25th–75th percentiles), whiskers extending to 1.5×IQR, and points beyond whiskers as outliers. The administrative boundary of global countries used in this study was obtained from the World Bank Official Boundaries portal<sup><xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e586" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/07792207dd82/41467_2026_74157_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEED_LOADING?><?original-height 1709?><?original-width 1997?><?scaled-height 683?><?scaled-width 798?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/8010e3a8defd/41467_2026_74157_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The estimated values of CDD-hum across the other Global cities and their rising trends per annum in the time period 2003–2023</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Metric -estimated over time period 2003-2023</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Representative Global Cities</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type-I city</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type-II city</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type-III city</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type-IV city</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">CDD-hum average values (°C-year)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average CDD-hum (20 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">741.82 ±  98.83 (Median: 521.03)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">861.81 ± 1 65.57 (Median: 636.68)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">797.39 ±  180.33 (Median: 597.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">442.01 ±  75.66 (Median: 362.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">404.71 ±  132.42 (Median: 407.88)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days &gt; 20 °C (days/year)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">122 ± 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133 ± 4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">131 ± 4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91 ± 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82 ± 4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">CDD-hum rising trend (°C-year per annum), observed over representative cities</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDD-hum overall trend (°C-year) in simple linear regression (20 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.46 ± 0.62 (Median: 4.14)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.97 ± 1.13 (Median: 4.28)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.98 ± 1.02 (Median: 4.16)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.39 ± 0.64 (Median: 3.75)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.84 ± 1.36 (Median: 4.35)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDD-hum overall trend (%) in Log-linear regression (20 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12 ± 0.12 (Median: 0.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.07 ± 0.20 (Median: 0.82)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17 ± 0.21 (Median: 0.80)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86 ± 0.28 (Median: 0.64)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53 ± 0.37 (Median: 1.39)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p16"><p>The values are shown as mean ± standard error format. The cities are grouped into four typologies based on their volumetric characteristics.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p id="Par8">The group of type-I and type-II cities together, characterized by high population densities and extensive to medium volumetric expansion, exhibit the higher CDD-hum values and exceedance durations (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Type-II cities, which undergo rapid vertical densification alongside continuous horizontal expansion at a faster pace than type-I cities, in India, display the highest cooling energy demands. Interestingly, despite their substantial built-up volumes, type-I cities exhibit CDD-hum levels comparable to smaller cities (type-III, type-IV). Among cities outside India, Type-I cities exhibited substantially higher UCD as well as higher warming days, followed by Type-II cities, while Type-III and Type-IV cities recorded nearly half the demand observed in Type-I cities. Although the number of global cities outside India included in the analysis is relatively limited, making it difficult to draw definitive conclusions, the markedly greater lateral spread observed in Type-I global cities (Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">20</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">21</xref>) appears to be a key contributing factor to their elevated UCD levels, in addition to the influence of background climate conditions (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The estimated values of CDD-hum across the Indian cities and their rising trends per annum within the time period 2003–2023</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Metric-estimated over time period 2003-2023</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Indian Cities</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Overall</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type-I city</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type-II city</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type-III city</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Type-IV city</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">CDD-hum average values (°C-year)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average CDD-hum (22 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1963 ± 78.46 (Median: 2199.30)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1842.00 ± 226.71 (Median: 1814.24)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2087.46 ± 122.55 (Median: 2245.81)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2019.71 ± 143.13 (Median: 2199.44)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1937.87 ± 143.13 (Median: 2038.17)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Average CDD-hum (28 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">821.86 ± 38.08 (Median: 839.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">731.29 ± 143.33 (Median: 721.47)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">872.98 ± 66.14 (Median: 981.94)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">808.75 ± 67.00 (Median: 859.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">804.70 ± 75.00 (Median: 874.37)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days &gt; 22 °C (days/year)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">273 ± 1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">265 ± 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">270 ± 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">266 ± 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">258 ± 2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Days &gt; 28 °C (days/year)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146 ± 5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140 ± 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">154 ± 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146 ± 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">140 ± 2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">CDD-hum rising trend (°C-year per annum)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDD-hum overall trend (°C-year/year) in simple linear regression (22 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.38 ± 0.89 (Median: 3.92)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.54 ± 6.25 (Median: 6.46)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.87 ± 1.15 (Median: 4.94)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.93 ± 1.13 (Median: 2.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.05 ± 1.75 (Median: 4.26)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDD-hum overall trend (%) in Log-linear regression (22 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36 ± 0.05 (Median: 0.22)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57 ± 0.30 (Median: 0.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34 ± 0.08 (Median: 0.23)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34 ± 0.10 (Median: 0.15)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.34 ± 0.08 (Median: 0.20)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDD-hum overall trend (°C-year/year) in simple linear regression (28 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.30 ± 0.32 (Median: 2.25)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.43 ± 1.06 (Median: 3.50)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.51 ± 0.50 (Median: 2.52)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.27 ± 0.62 (Median: 2.17)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.01 ± 0.65 (Median: 2.13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CDD-hum overall trend (%) in Log-linear regression (28 °C)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49 ± 0.08 (Median: 0.33)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.53 ± 0.12 (Median: 0.49)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.40 ± 0.05 (Median:0.40)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.63 ± 0.21 (Median: 0.31)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.39 ± 0.09 (Median: 0.30)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p12"><p>The values are shown as mean ± standard error format. The cities are grouped into four typologies based on their volumetric characteristics.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p id="Par9">Analysis of trends of rise in CDD-hum for Indian cities showed a consistent upward trend, with an average annual increase, under the assumption of a linear increase, of 6.4 ± 0.9 °C-year (mean ± standard error). Considering the background climate and regional settings, Indian cities exhibited distinct trends in the rise of CDD-hum (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Cities located in the foothills of the southern and western Himalayas exhibited the highest relative rise in CDD-hum, followed by those on the east coast and then the west coast. Cities situated in the Indo-Gangetic Plain and the Deccan Plateau showed moderate increases, both in terms of absolute rise and log-linear relative-trends. While absolute increases reflect the total growth in cooling demand, relative increases capture proportional changes, enabling meaningful comparisons across regions with differing baseline conditions. For global cities, the Australian cities showed comparable trends in the relative rise in CDD-hum to Indian cities (~0.2–0.3% per annum). Cities experiencing warm and humid conditions (typically concentrated in southern Asian coastal as well as inland regions) showed similar trends of CDD-hum rise as Indian cities facing comparable climatic conditions (~0.4–0.7%). European cities showed the highest rise in CDD-hum (~2.5–5%), primarily due to the rapid impact of global warming in last two decades on temperate regions across European countries<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. However, in absolute terms, the values are around 5 °C-year, significantly lower than those observed in the US and Asia (~5–10 °C-year) (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par10">Volumetric classification-specific trends in CDD-hum indicate distinct cooling demand rise patterns. In Indian cities under study, type-I cities exhibit the highest average rate of increase, at 3.4 ± 1 to 11.5 ± 6 °C-year per annum, followed by Type-II (~5.8 ± 1.1 °C-year/year). Type-III and type-IV cities display comparable trends, with type-III cities showing less variability around the mean compared to type-IV cities (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">20</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">22</xref> and Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The log-linear trend for the increase in CDD-hum across all the cities showed a rise of ~3.5% per decade, except type-I cities (~6% per decade). For global cities, outside India, the trend in absolute increase of CDD-hum is highest for type-I, II (~6 ± 1 °C-year per annum) cities followed by type-III and type-IV (~3-4 °C-year per annum). The majority of inland Asian cities, which primarily fall under the Type-I classification, also showed a comparable rise in UCD to Type-I cities in India. While the patterns of CDD-hum rise in absolute terms for global cities outside India and Indian cities are similar, global cities (~0.9–1.5%) exhibit a significantly higher relative increase in CDD-hum compared to Indian cities across all typologies (~0.2–0.5%) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Bivariate and semi-partial correlation of built-urbanization</title><p id="Par11">Indicators of volumetric growth of cities, representing urbanization trends, showed statistically significant correlation with the city-wide rising trends of CDD-hum as well as the 20-year average of annual CDD-hum (henceforth as avg. CDD-hum). Using both Pearson correlation coefficients and Spearman rank correlations, we assessed the linear and monotonic (non-linear) relationships (with significance level <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.1 and <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between actual and relative increases in CDD-hum, avg. CDD-hum and various indicators of city volumetric growth (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and see Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">31</xref>).</p><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Bivariate Pearson correlations between urban volumetric indicators and rising CDD-hum trends across Indian cities.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Correlations with the absolute increase in CDD-hum; <bold>b</bold> correlations with the relative increase. Statistical significance is denoted as <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.1 (*) and <italic>p </italic>&lt; 0.05 (**), based on two-sided tests. Colours represent the four volumetric typologies (Type-I to Type-IV), and the grey bars indicate overall correlations across all cities. Y-axis labels denote urban volumetric indicators grouped under broader dimensions of urban structural change: lateral extent (LAT. EXT.), population (POP.), infilling (INFILL), vertical expansion (VER. EXT.), volumetric growth (VOL. GROW.), volumetric densification (DENSIFIC.), consolidation, green cover (GREEN), land surface temperature (LST), anthropogenic heat (AH), and GDP. Detailed urban variable definitions are provided in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>. Correlations are computed after excluding values beyond 1.5×IQR for each variable to limit the influence of extreme observations on Pearson estimates; corresponding full-dataset results are shown in Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref> and yield consistent pattern.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e924" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/98a70fc0ed64/41467_2026_74157_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEED_LOADING?><?original-height 2496?><?original-width 1742?><?scaled-height 997?><?scaled-width 696?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/df7e37cc9d10/41467_2026_74157_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par12">Cities expanding horizontally - lateral expanse of built-up exhibit a positive linear correlation with rising CDD-hum trends (R ~ 0.–0.8) for Indian cities (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>). The annual increase in lateral extent of the built environment (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>H</italic></sub>↑) and related metrics further reinforce this relationship, highlighting the role of urban sprawl and population-rise driven lateral expansion of cities in exacerbating cooling demand across all city types over time. These effects are most pronounced in both Indian as well as Global Type-I and Type-II cities (Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">28</xref>). In contrast, smaller cities (Type-III and IV together) show weaker associations, reflecting slower lateral expansion and reduced contributions from the increase in lateral extent. Interestingly, Type-IV cities, characterized by compact urban development, indicated a weak negative correlation between (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>H</italic></sub>↑) and CDD-hum trends when analysed separately. These cities also exhibit a weak negative correlation between CDD-hum trends and log(<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub>), further supporting the idea that small, compact cities undergoing moderate expansion may reflect a temporary reduction in urban density-related thermal effects. This suggests that within certain limits, lateral growth in Type-IV cities could initially help mitigate cooling demand by balanced lateral and vertical compactness. However, this effect likely diminishes as expansion progresses, eventually leading to heat accumulation, beyond a critical threshold. The lateral expansion indicators also showed a moderate, nonlinear, and positive association with the rise in CDD-hum, with the effect most pronounced in megacities across both lower-middle income as well as high and upper-middle income regions under study (Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">26</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">28</xref>).</p><p id="Par13">City Infilling, greenery reduction, road network in tandem with lateral expansion - Infilling as well as the measure of imperviousness exhibit a moderate positive correlation with the rising trends of CDD-hum. The rate of average increment in urban infilling across the lateral expanse of cities, represented by <inline-formula id="IEq2"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e969"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> showed a stronger positive correlation (R ~ 0.3-0.7, p &lt; 0.1)  in both linear as well as in nonlinear association measures (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>). These observations are most pronounced in Type-I and Type-II cities, while for Type-III, and IV cities, such a relationship was not apparent when metrics were correlated separately. For Indian cities, urban consolidation around city cores, defined as the city lateral expanse combined with logarithm of population density, infilling in cities, consistently exhibit the strong positive correlations with the annual increase in CDD-hum (R &gt; 0.45), highlighting the role of overall urban infilling and population driven built form development, increasing the cooling demand requirement (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">28</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">The relative densification of urban patches expressed in terms of (<italic>increase in C</italic><sub><italic>H</italic></sub>
<italic>per capita</italic>) demonstrated negative correlation with CDD-hum rise across the globe (R ~ −0.25 to −0.65). The rise of green cover showed a moderate negative correlation, with the effect most pronounced in Type-I and Type-II cities (R ~ –0.2 to –0.45), indicating that a reduction in greenery and densification of lands contributes to the rise in UCD in overall. This impact was evident in both linear and nonlinear association analyses. Furthermore, indices measuring road network characteristics across cities showed a moderate to strong positive linear association with the rise in CDD-hum (R ~ 0.4–0.6). Expansion of road networks contributes to increased impervious surface coverage, making it a potential city-scale driver of the observed CDD-hum trends (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">28</xref>).</p><p id="Par15">Cities expanding vertically - When analysing the vertical rise of cities, data is often organized into percentiles to understand the distribution of building height thresholds, rather than taking averages within the city-lateral extent<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. The lowest 25% of building heights fall into the <inline-formula id="IEq3"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1034"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> percentile, representing areas with the shortest buildings, such as residential or commercial neighborhood, or older parts of the city. From the 25<sup>th</sup>−50<sup>th</sup> percentile, categorized as <inline-formula id="IEq4"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1057"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, includes mid-rise buildings like larger residential complexes or smaller office buildings. The <inline-formula id="IEq5"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1077"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, percentile encompasses the middle to upper range of building heights, featuring taller office buildings, high-rise residential complexes, and significant commercial developments. Finally, the highest 25% of building heights are represented by <inline-formula id="IEq6"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1094"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>75</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, and include the tallest skyscrapers, major commercial centers, and high-density urban developments. The vertical rise in cities across all the major percentile distributions (<inline-formula id="IEq7"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1113"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) showed moderate to strong positive correlations (R ~ 0.2-0.6) with relative increase of CDD-hum (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">28</xref>), with this trend evident for Indian as well as Global Type-I cities. Further, our analysis across global and Indian cities shows a negative linear correlation between the quartile coefficient of dispersion (QCD) and rising CDD-hum trends (R ≈ –0.36 ). Physically, the QCD reflects the variability in building heights across a city, with higher values indicating a more uneven vertical profile variability within a city. Our observation here, suggests that greater vertical heterogeneity is associated with reduced cooling demand, but not for all the cities, specifically this effect is most prominent in smaller, compact Indian cities. For instance, a city with uniform building heights tends to show a steeper increase in CDD-hum compared to one with a more varied high rise, implying that diverse vertical form may be associated with reduced increase in temperature-related cooling demand within the urban extent of such cities.</p><p id="Par16">To observe the trends of possible vertical growth associated with horizontal urban expansion and infilling as well as increases in population density, the measures (e.g., <inline-formula id="IEq8"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1143"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq9"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1174"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,(<inline-formula id="IEq10"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1204"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) is examined. Initially urban population densities were used for 3D urban representation<sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. By combining the vertical rise of cities with horizontal expansion and infilling, as well as changes in population density, these metrics indirectly assess how vertical growth complements lateral densification in both built and demographic terms. This approach allows for an indirect understanding of how cities balance vertical development with horizontal expansion, providing insights into the dynamics of urban densification. Our results indicate moderate to strong correlation (R &gt; 0.45–0.75, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.1) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">31</xref>), suggesting that increased building heights across cities contribute to increased cooling demand, likely due to altered airflow, heat retention, and shifts in the surface energy balance of urban facets. This impact is again both valid in linear and nonlinear association measure, making this metric as one of the possible determinants of UCD variations in cities in association with metrics such as <inline-formula id="IEq11"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1248"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula id="IEq12"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1262"><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></inline-formula> or compactness.</p><p id="Par17">Volumetric expansion of cities tandem with population-driven densification - The gross volumetric measure of cities, estimated by city lateral expansion multiplied by inter-quartile height distribution <inline-formula id="IEq13"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1278"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> shows a strong positive correlation (R ~ 0.7) with rising trend of CDD-hum, both in absolute as well as relative terms. For global cities under study, the impact is diminished. The overall growth rate of city volume in terms of <inline-formula id="IEq14"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1307"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> also resulted in a similarly strong positive correlation across the entire set of cities (R ~ 0.6). These effects are particularly pronounced in larger cities, where expansive urban form and vertical growth contribute significantly to rising UCD, as also noted from last discussions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">13</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">19</xref>). The volumetric densification of cities defined in terms of <inline-formula id="IEq15"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1347"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula id="IEq16"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1377"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. showed a contrasting relation with avg. CDD-hum for Indian cities and Global cities. In case of Indian cities, the observed correlation is moderately negative (R ~ −0.2–0.5) whereas for Global cities its moderate to positively strong (R ~ 0.6) (Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">29</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">31</xref>).</p><p id="Par18">Semi-partial correlation controlled for city-lateral expansion and population density - The semi-partial correlation of built-urbanization indicators, while controlling for urban lateral expansion and population density, is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> for Indian cities and in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> for global cities. The horizontal axis (Bivariate Correlation) represents the direct correlation between each indicator and the trends of CDD-hum. The vertical axis (Semi-Partial Correlation) shows the additional explanatory power of each indicator after accounting for urban lateral expansion and population density. This highlights the strength of the linear correlation between CDD-hum trends and the remaining urbanization indicators, particularly city vertical growth. Several indicators provide additional explanations over city size and population density alone. Among these, the annual rise in built area multiplied by the IQR of vertical expanse of cities, <inline-formula id="IEq17"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1407"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> exhibits the strongest semi-partial correlation, suggesting its potential as the second most influential positive determinant in CDD-hum trends in Indian cities. Interestingly the relative densification or consolidations in Indian cities expressed in terms of <inline-formula id="IEq18"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1449"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq19"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1467"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> or, <inline-formula id="IEq20"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1499"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and green coverage can act as moderate attributors of CDD-hum rise reduction. In case of Global cities (excluding Indian cities) city vertical rise <inline-formula id="IEq21"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1534"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the strongest attributor in CDD-Hum rise where as, <inline-formula id="IEq22"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1558"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq23"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1593"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> act as second most important positive attributor. In terms of strong impacting factor, the city infilling in combination with log of population density <inline-formula id="IEq24"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e1624"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be potential choice for these cities (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">32</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">35</xref>).</p><fig id="Fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>The semi-partial correlation between rising trends of CDD-hum for Indian cities, controlling for city area and population density.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Shows the Semi-partial Pearson correlations with absolute and relative CDD-hum trends respectively, controlling for city area and population density. <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Shows the semi-partial Spearman rank correlations, controlling for the same variables and for same target variables. The vertical axis shows the semi-partial correlation coefficient, while the horizontal axis shows the corresponding bivariate (uncontrolled) correlation. Statistical significance is denoted as <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.1 (*) and <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (**), based on two-sided tests. Grouped y-axis labels represent broader dimensions of urban structural change, including lateral extent (LAT.), population (POP.), infilling (INFIL.), vertical expansion (VER.), volumetric growth (VOL. GROW.), densification (DENSIFIC.), consolidation (COND.), green cover (GREEN), land surface temperature (LST), anthropogenic heat (AH), and economic activity (GDP). Detailed features and their definitions under each broad categorization are provided in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1687" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/383cfd625d64/41467_2026_74157_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEED_LOADING?><?original-height 2016?><?original-width 1996?><?scaled-height 806?><?scaled-width 798?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig4_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/e95ee5ca4d83/41467_2026_74157_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><fig id="Fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>The semi-partial correlation between rising trends of CDD-hum for global cities (excluding Indian cities), controlling for city area and population density.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Shows the Semi-partial Pearson correlations with absolute and relative CDD-hum trends respectively, controlling for city area and population density. <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Shows the semi-partial Spearman rank correlations, controlling for the same variables and for same target variables. The vertical axis shows the semi-partial correlation coefficient, while the horizontal axis shows the corresponding bivariate (uncontrolled) correlation. Statistical significance is denoted as <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.1 (*) and <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (**), based on two-sided tests. Grouped y-axis labels represent broader dimensions of urban structural change, including lateral extent (LAT.), population (POP.), infilling (INFIL.), vertical expansion (VER.), volumetric growth (VOL. GROW.), densification (DENSIFIC.), consolidation (COND.), green cover (GREEN), land surface temperature (LST), anthropogenic heat (AH), and economic activity (GDP). Detailed urban features and their definitions under each broad categorization are provided in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1717" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/8600b1252bef/41467_2026_74157_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEED_LOADING?><?original-height 2016?><?original-width 1996?><?scaled-height 806?><?scaled-width 798?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig5_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/556f6a71b1df/41467_2026_74157_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Modelling attempt for cross-city UCD trends</title><p id="Par19">Linear regression models including Least Absolute Shrinkage and Selection Operator (LASSO), Elastic Net, and Bayesian Ridge regression methods<sup><xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> were employed to identify interpretable indicators of city-scale urbanization which can be potential predictors for cross city UCD estimation (see Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, model cluster 1,3,5,7). Further, methods such as Random Forest (RF) and Extreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost)<sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> were also implemented to evaluate the dynamic non-linear relationship between urbanization indicators and cross-city variability in UCD (model cluster 2,4,6,8). The cross-country variability in UCD in the models were accessed using two separate target variables: two-decade average of annual UCD (model 1,2 and 3,4) and annual rise in UCD (model 5,6 and 7,8), given same set of input feature spaces. When the rising trend of CDD-hum was used as the target variable, the models exhibited limited generalizability (R² ~0.4–0.7, CV MSPE ~ 0.94–1.5) (see Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Indicators of city vertical expanse, along with indicators of volumetric growth, densification, and green cover reduction, showed a relatively modest but noticeable influence alongside climatic and contextual impact. In contrast, when average CDD-hum was used as the target variable, the models performed substantially better (R² ~ 0.8–0.9, CV MSPE ~ 0.05–0.13). Across all the models the influence of urbanization was less dominant than that of warming days, which largely reflect the combined effects of climate and regional setting across all the models (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">36</xref>). Here in models, targeting average CDD-hum, urbanization indicators related to volumetric expansion, height distribution measures, retained substantial importance, suggesting that the three-dimensional characteristics of urban form may be the second most important predictors of UCD variability after climate. For a detailed summary of the relative importance of urbanization, climate, and regional setting indicators, see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">7</xref>. Future work should focus on improving model accuracy and enhancing applicability for robust cross-city UCD prediction.</p><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Summary of Cross-city average UCD and its trends prediction attempts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="7" rowspan="1">Cross-city prediction of average CDD-hum</th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Input feature space<sup>a</sup></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model clusters abbreviation</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model type</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range of within sample goodness of fit (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup><italic>)</italic></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Range of out-of-Sample goodness of fit (<italic>OS</italic>_<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CV-RMSE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">CV-MSPE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Direct city-wide area averaged annual climate variables and/or indirect climate variables, and variables indicating urban growth</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model cluster 1, 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Linear models</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.86–0.90</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.64–0.74</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.27-0.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08–0.13</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model cluster 2, 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-linear models</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91–0.99</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.76–0.85</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.22-0.28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05–0.10</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1"><bold>Cross-city prediction of rising trend of CDD-hum</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Input feature space</bold><sup>a</sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Model clusters abbreviation</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Model type</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Within sample goodness of fit (</bold><bold><italic>R</italic></bold><sup>2</sup><bold><italic>)</italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Out-of-Sample goodness of fit (</bold><bold><italic>OS</italic></bold><bold>_</bold><bold><italic>R</italic></bold><sup>2</sup><bold>)</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>CV-RMSE</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>CV-MSPE</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Direct city-wide area averaged annual climate variables and/or indirect climate variables, and variables indicating urban growth</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model cluster 5,7</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Linear models</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56–0.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.14–0.22</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.2-2.24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3 −1.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model cluster 6,8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-linear models</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.71–0.95</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23–0.43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.95-2.35</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.94–1.27</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p31"><p><sup>a</sup>Please refer Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>,<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6</xref>,<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">7</xref> for further details of model input features.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig6" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Relative importance of urbanization indicators, climate, and regional setting in predicting annual mean CDD-hum and its rising trend.</title><p>Models were trained using 20 years of data from 140 cities (88 Indian cities and 52 global cities). <bold>a</bold> Shows the contribution of all explanatory variables, including climate and regional context, to average CDD-hum. <bold>b</bold> Presents the influence of urbanization indicators, excluding climate variables from relative comparison, on urban cooling demand. <bold>c</bold> Shows the contribution of all explanatory variables, including climate and regional context, to rising trends of CDD-hum.<bold> d</bold> Presents the influence of urbanization indicators, excluding climate variables from relative comparison, on rising trend of urban cooling demand. Dots show model-iteration feature importance; circles indicate mean ± standard error. Grouped y-axis labels denote broader dimensions of urban structural change: lateral extent (LAT.), population (POP.), infilling (INFIL.), vertical rise (VER.), volumetric growth (VOL. GROW.), densification (DENSIFIC.), consolidation (COND.), green cover (GREEN), land surface temperature (LST), anthropogenic heat (AH), and economic activity (GDP). Direct climate variables include relative humidity (RH), solar radiation, 2 m air temperature (T2M), and wind speed (WS), while indirect climate proxies are represented by exceedance days requiring cooling (WARM DAYS). Detailed urban features and their definitions under each broad categorization are provided in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1778" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig6_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/61e3701599d1/41467_2026_74157_Fig6_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEED_LOADING?><?original-height 2136?><?original-width 2000?><?scaled-height 854?><?scaled-width 800?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig6_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/12ecf8eceacc/41467_2026_74157_Fig6_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par20">Our work demonstrates that cooling energy demand in cities not only depend on regional setting and background climate of city, city size, but rather emerges from the interaction between horizontal expansion, vertical development, infilling, and population density alongside regional-climatic setting (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). These findings are consistent with previous large-scale urban studies<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>–<xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>, highlighting the broader regional influence of urban form on cooling demand. By jointly examining the average CDD-hum values and their temporal trends, the synergistic impact of built volumetric development and regional climate can be understood through two conceptual, exploratory thought experiments initially. The first is: if two cities share a similar regional climate and setting (for example, both are inland or both coastal), will their built form influence cooling demand in the same way? For instance, among Indo-Gangetic Plain inland cities, classified under the same composite climate zone by Bureau of Energy efficiency (BEE)<sup><xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>, there is notable intra-regional variation in CDD-hum trends. Cities such as Bareilly, Aligarh, Kanpur, Lucknow, and Patna, all categorized as Type-II cities, exhibit a moderate CDD-hum rise ranging from 5 to 10 °C per year. In contrast, cities like Delhi (Type-I), Jhansi (Type-III), Jabalpur, and Satna show a much wider spread, with increases ranging from over 20 °C per year to as low as 5 °C per year, which cannot be fully explained by city setting or regional background climate in long-term analysis. A similar degree of variability is seen in coastal cities, which typically fall under the warm and humid climate zone according to BEE<sup><xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup>. There are also significant variations in CDD-hum rise in those cities that cannot be explained by a single, uniform background climate. Chennai (Type-I), Kochi and Puducherry (Type-II), Thoothukudi, Cuttack (Type-III), Bhubaneswar, Rajahmundry, and Visakhapatnam (Type-IV) show a wide range of CDD-hum rise, varying from 5 to 18 °C per year. Further, the second thought experiment is, does cities with distinct climatic conditions but with similar volumetric profiles exhibit comparable UCD levels or not. For example, under Type-II cities, Patna (Indo-Gangetic Plain, Composite), Jaipur (western India, arid and dry), and Puducherry (eastern coast, hot and humid) all report similar annual UCD values (~2100–2800 °C-years) and comparable rates of increase (~0.13–0.16% per annum), highlighting the possible role of urban built form in modulating cooling demand, given the background climate and contextual settings of the three aforementioned cities are completely different. Bivariate and semi-partial correlation analyses support these observations and indicates that the extent and spatial configuration of volumetric built structures, specifically the volumetric expanse and growth of cities, vertical rise and infill driven consolidation, volumetric densification significantly contribute to variations in cooling energy demand across cities in lower-middle income as well as high and upper-middle income regions.</p><fig id="Fig7" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Conceptual representation of city volumetric growth trajectories and diverging urban cooling demand patterns.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Shows the representative city forms. <bold>b</bold> Shows the ranges of average annual UCD and its rate of rise across the respective city types. <bold>c</bold> Shows the characteristic volumetric growth patterns in these cities, which may act as key drivers of rising UCD, second to climate.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1993" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig7_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/1eb73d9c8951/41467_2026_74157_Fig7_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status NEED_LOADING?><?original-height 2335?><?original-width 1982?><?scaled-height 933?><?scaled-width 792?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_Fig7_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/b390/13287610/893df369113d/41467_2026_74157_Fig7_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par21">Although background climate remains the dominant driver, both linear and nonlinear correlation analysis as well as cross-city models of annual average UCD further established that volumetric urban expansion can play second most important role in driving UCD, beside climate. Elaborating on previous studies<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>, our findings emphasizes the increasing relevance of three-dimensional urban form, in explaining cross-city variability in UCD. By incorporating a comprehensive set of 65 indicators of volumetric growth into the prediction of cross-city average UCD and its trends, this study advances prior work by further highlighting relative importance of vertical expansion, population growth, volumetric densification, and consolidation, independent of climatic and geographic factors, shaping UCD (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Unlike earlier studies that treated urbanization as a single aggregated effect<sup><xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>, this approach provides a more granular perspective of various indicators of urbanization contribute in city wide cooling needs. The need for this granular observation can be understood by another thought experiment: cities with comparable urbanization patterns in terms of lateral expansion or population size can also exhibit substantial differences in CDD-hum values and trends (e.g.- Delhi and Kolkata). Conversely, cities with highly distinct spatial extents or population distributions can exhibit similar UCD patterns at the city-grid scale, resembling those of much larger urban centres (e.g.- Bhuvaneswar and Cuttack in comparison to Type-I cities). This emphasizes the necessity of accounting for the relative contributions of city-scale volumetric alterations; encompassing urbanization scale, spatial density, and vertical expansion- when assessing urban cooling needs or related mitigation strategies at such scales. For instance, planning electricity grid expansions based solely on factors such as horizontal city growth or population changes may result in significant miscalculations of cooling demand in cities with apparently similar urbanization characteristics. In combination with the bi-variate and multi-variate analyses, the modelling clusters show that city volumetric growth, particularly vertical expansion and its heterogeneous spatial distribution (see Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>–<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">23</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">36</xref>) together with the lateral extent and its annual increment, strongly contributes to both the yearly average city-wide cooling demand and the rise in UCD. A notable insight emerges when comparing the performance of models predicting average UCD and those predicting the annual rate of change in UCD using the same feature set. Across both linear and nonlinear clusters, model accuracy was consistently higher for average UCD. This pattern suggests that volumetric indicators of city structural change, are effective predictors of area-averaged cooling demand when considered in relation to a city’s current physical form, past urbanization trajectory, and prevailing climate. However, these indicators appear less capable of capturing the temporal dynamics of UCD, which are influenced by short-term dynamics such as rapid increases in air-conditioning adoption, socio-economic transitions, or the accelerating nonlinear effects of global warming, which may play a stronger role in driving annual trends than climate variables and volumetric growth indicators alone, as the latter represent relatively long-term processes that are better reflected in decade-scale trends rather than year-to-year variability. Nevertheless, these results, in conjunction with prior studies<sup><xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>, highlight the imperative to investigate inter-city UCD variability driven by diverse urbanization trajectories. Such variability not only influences regional and global climate dynamics but also presents substantial challenges for large-scale, generalized mitigation strategies.</p><p id="Par22">Once we looked into the role of volumetric growth alongside climate in driving UCD across cities, following is further detailed, typology specific discussion of the UCD variability and how past developmental trends in cities across lower-middle income region as well as high and upper-middle income region is shaping the cooling needs. The observed CDD-hum values and trends across the cities are in agreement with the previous global studies like Staffell et al.<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>, Deroubaix et al.<sup><xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> Scoccimarro et al.<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> and regional studies like Ukey et al.<sup><xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>.  However, while these studies focused on broader scales or limited city samples, our research provides city-level analyses, enabling a more detailed characterization of urban-scale trends. These combined observations of average annual CDD-hum values and their increasing trends suggest that cities with high volumetric expansion and relatively larger population densities, such as Type-I and Type-II cities, are more susceptible to accelerated UCD. Notably, major metropolitan areas like Delhi and Kolkata, along with many rapidly growing Type-II cities<sup><xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>–<xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>, exhibit extensive urban footprints and higher population shares, further reinforcing this trend. Compared to smaller, less densely populated, and less volumetrically spread cities classified as Type-III and Type-IV, these larger urban centres are more likely to experience intensified UCD in the coming years. This distinction highlights the role of urban form and demographic factors in shaping cooling energy demands. Furthermore, when examining the increasing frequency of days with elevated cooling requirements, Type-I cities consistently rank highest. This result underscores the tendency of high-density urban environments to experience persistently rising heat conditions, emphasizing the critical need for targeted mitigation strategies in these rapidly expanding urban regions.</p><p id="Par23">Though Type-I Indian cities exhibit the highest increasing trend in CDD-hum, their overall yearly average CDD-hum values over the past two decades remain lower than those of Type-II cities. This distinction may arise from fundamental differences in urban growth dynamics. Type-I cities in India, including major metropolitan centres such as Kolkata, Delhi, and Mumbai, have experienced near-saturation within their core areas due to extensive infilling, particularly post-2010<sup><xref rid="CR53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="CR54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup>. As a result, their horizontal expansion has significantly slowed compared to Type-II cities, where lateral growth and infilling continue at a more pronounced pace. This divergence in urban form is directly reflected in their respective CDD-hum trends. While Type-I cities exhibit lower absolute CDD-hum values, they demonstrate a steeper rate of increase in yearly CDD-hum, indicative of accelerating cooling demand. A key driver behind this trend can be the significant vertical expansion witnessed in Type-I cities over recent decades, as substantiated by global studies on urban densification<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. The ongoing transition from horizontal sprawl to vertical growth, driven by development regulations such as higher permissible Floor Space Index (FSI) in metropolitan regions<sup><xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup>, has intensified urban heat retention, thereby amplifying the cooling energy demand in larger cities. Apart from climate and built form, several associated confounding factors driven by demographics and increasing built volumes may contribute to the rising need for UCD in such cities. Factors such as higher adoption of per capita indoor space cooling in high density cities or megacities with higher GDP<sup><xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="CR57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup>, and the rise in anthropogenic emissions linked to expanded air conditioning use<sup><xref rid="CR58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup>, although not systematically explored in this study, may also influence the higher rate of UCD increase observed in tier-I cities.</p><p id="Par24">Type-II Indian cities continue to experience both lateral expansion and infilling, leading to higher baseline CDD-hum values but a relatively slower rate of increase. This comparison between Type-I and Type-II cities suggests a stronger link between vertical urban growth and rising CDD-hum trends. Specifically, the measure of <inline-formula id="IEq25"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2091"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">75,100</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>↑</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for Type-I and Type-II cities, along with the semi-partial correlation analysis, highlights this indicator as the significant contributing factor of increasing CDD-hum. This alignment reinforces the idea that volumetric growth, where cities are growing up rather than growing out, is emerging as a key factor in shaping rising urban cooling demand. The findings suggest that future urban climate responses will need to account for this shift, as vertical densification continues to reshape the thermal characteristics of cities. Previous studies, such as Liu et al.<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>, Shen et al.<sup><xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> and Sethi et al.<sup><xref rid="CR60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup>, typically employed a top-down approach that focused on urban horizontal expanse or population share as independent metrics in linear attribution models for warming trends or UCD variabilities. However, this study, which spans 20 years and empirically analysed 88 cities coming under lower-middle income and 52 cities coming majorly under high and upper-middle income, with globally available vertical expanse data, emphasizes the importance of considering city-wide vertical expanse in attribution models. Also, the degree of correlation decreases as the base temperature shifts from 22 °C to 28 °C. A lower base temperature suggests greater reliance on mechanical cooling in urban built spaces, while a higher base temperature indicates a greater dependence on mixed-mode cooling, likely due to the lower overall penetration of air conditioning in Indian cities. While causality cannot be firmly established, the reduced (increasing) influence of city form on CDD-hum at higher (lower) base temperatures may point to a growing role of urban morphology in shaping future thermal stress where mechanical space cooling will be more frequent.</p><p id="Par25">Among Type-III and Type-IV cities, despite their smaller urban volumes and lower population shares, Type-IV cities exhibit CDD-hum values and increased cooling demand intensity comparable to Type-I cities. This suggests that compact urban developments can significantly contribute to UCD, even with moderate growth. In contrast, Type-III cities show the lowest UCD and growth rates, reinforcing the link between lower built-up density and reduced cooling demand. A weak negative correlation between CDD-hum trends and <inline-formula id="IEq26"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2135"><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in Type-IV cities further indicates that moderate lateral expansion may initially dilute urban density effects, temporarily mitigating cooling demand. However, as expansion progresses, this effect weakens, eventually leading to heat accumulation if built-up density surpasses a critical threshold. For both Type-III and Type-IV cities, vertical densification and volumetric expansion exhibit weak to moderate negative correlations with CDD-hum trends, suggesting that while regional temperature increment will drive higher cooling needs, built urbanization plays a less dominant role in these city types compared to the more vertically expanding Type-I and Type-II cities. Previous studies have also highlighted the role of city compactness as well as urban densification in contributing urban-building energy demand but many of such studies limited by study scale both in temporal as well as spatial has sometimes conflicting results. Like Tewari et al.<sup><xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> reported a relative rise in overall UCD with urban spatial density whereas Güneralp et al.<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> reported a relative fall in overall energy usage. In contrast, this study try to provide more detailed empirical evidence across one forty global cities with diverse urbanization characteristics. It examines various quantitative measures of urban density- both in terms of population distribution and built form, and their contribution to localized temperature differentials, which in turn increase UCD for Type-I and Type-II cities. For rest two typologies the observations are in alignment with Güneralp et al.<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par26">To summarize (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), beyond typology-specific patterns, the influence of volumetric densification and vertical growth on annual UCD appears to be both region-specific and shaped by lower-middle income to high and upper-middle income based regional distinction. In Indian cities, where population-driven densification has been dominant over the past two decades, vertical development is associated with a reduction in annual average UCD for cities having similar growth trajectories (except mega-cities), potentially due to more compact living conditions and reduced surface exposure. In contrast, many high to upper-middle income global cities, particularly in the U.S. and Europe exhibit greater lateral expansion and higher vertical thresholds but lower population densities. In these contexts, vertical densification is often linked to increased annual UCD, likely reflecting elevated per capita energy use and greater surface heat retention. All these observations, underscores the limitations of broad, one-size-fits-all heat mitigation approaches<sup><xref rid="CR61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup> and reinforces the necessity for localized, data-driven strategies tailored to distinct urban morphologies. Our findings also prompt a reconsideration of how urbanization is conceptualized at the city scale - not merely as a physical transformation but as a complex interplay of built form and socio-economic dynamics. Historically, major classical structures of urbanization models, such as Burgess’s<sup><xref rid="CR62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup>, Hoyt’s models<sup><xref rid="CR63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup> to allometric scaling approach<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>, and many geo-spatial top-down approaches exploring UCD or related urban temperature anomalies, have primarily focused on horizontal expansion while overlooking the role of built-up volumetric growth<sup><xref rid="CR64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></sup>. Our work demonstrates the need to integrate the third dimension of urban volumetric alteration and development alongside socio-economic aspects of urbanization into contemporary urban planning frameworks, as vertical densification alongside infilling emerges as a crucial but often underexplored factor in shaping urban climate responses. This critical factor needed be taken into account when addressing future urban cooling demands, influenced both by the direct effects of urban volumetric expansion and the broader impacts of greenhouse gas emissions. Our city typology-based framework may serve as an base model applicable to other rapidly growing regions, including Asia and, in the coming decades, significant areas of Africa. We also acknowledge that, although the observations highlight the importance of incorporating urban volumetrics in city-scale assessments of aggregated energy or heat mitigation potential, the findings should be interpreted as indicative rather than absolute patterns. Since the CDD-hum metric is derived from hourly meteorological variables available in the ERA5-Land dataset, regional biases due to the underrepresentation of detailed urban effects present in the original data are also reflected in our computations. Furthermore, although the modelling framework attempts to separate urban influences from broader climatic effects, the estimation of CDD-hum and its rising trends derived directly from ERA5-Land inherently carries the background synoptic climate signal alongside the urban impact. It is also important to note that the current UCD framework relies on ambient, grid-level annual population distributions combined with CDD-hum estimates. As such, it does not explicitly resolve intra-annual shifts in population distribution or activity patterns. Transient shocks, such as those observed during the COVID-19 pandemic, which altered the spatial and functional distribution of cooling demand (for example, reduced commercial usage and increased residential demand), may therefore introduce additional uncertainty in the estimates. However, given the annual aggregation of the analysis, such effects are expected to have limited influence on the overall spatial patterns and long-term trends reported here. These limitations point to a clear direction for future work, where multi-scale UCD frameworks integrating time-resolved population dynamics and activity-based demand modelling could further refine both intra-city and inter-city assessments of cooling demand.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par27">We employ a top-down integrated framework (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>), combining high-resolution satellite imagery and reanalysis datasets harmonized to a common spatial resolution of ~1 km and spatially aggregated within urban boundaries from study period 2003 to 2023. First, we introduce a simple city classification approach, that can be globally adopted using open-source urban geo-spatial data, enabling further investigations into the impacts of volumetric features on inter-city UCD variability. Then we analysed the co-determinacy of key indicators of city-scale built-urbanization, including <inline-formula id="IEq27"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2196"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>,<inline-formula id="IEq28"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2207"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>,<inline-formula id="IEq29"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2218"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq30"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2229"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula id="IEq31"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2242"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, both individually and in combination, influencing rising UCD trends.</p><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="2"><title>City volumetrics data and context</title><p id="Par28">Key city-scale features of volumetric alteration like - city lateral extent (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>H</italic></sub>) and lateral shape irregularity (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>A</italic></sub>), vertical expansion (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>V</italic></sub>), population density (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub>), and infilling in city cores which also indicate the imperviousness share in terms of actual built-up ground coverage (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>IR</italic></sub>) are measured and recorded for the cities under assessment. For further details, refer to Supplementary Discussion and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>,<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6</xref>.</p><p id="Par29">Lateral extent, infilling and population data- To estimate the major lateral urban extents (e.g.-<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>H</italic></sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>A</italic></sub>, <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>IR</italic></sub>) of global cities, we employed the city cluster boundary dataset from the (GUB) data<sup><xref rid="CR65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup>, supplemented with additional urban boundary data<sup><xref rid="CR60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup> for Indian cities. This GUB dataset integrates global artificial impervious area product (GAIA)<sup><xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup> to capture the extent of urbanized land patches across the globe. GAIA-GUB boundaries represent the contiguous impervious footprint of urban agglomerations, capturing built-up structures such as buildings and pavements, rather than administrative or municipal limits, capturing both city centres and peripheral built-up areas that functionally delineate urban lateral extent<sup><xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup> expressed in km<sup>2</sup>. Representative city-centre coordinates were used to identify the corresponding urban extents for each city. The urban-boundary dataset was subsequently aligned to the common analysis grid using nearest-neighbour method. To capture the annual urban lateral growth, yearly land cover types of MODIS data-MCD12Q1 were also used in this study, rather than relying directly upon the GUB dataset. For each city cluster, the pixels classified as urban and built-up areas (e.g., class 13) by MODIS land cover product were defined as urban lateral extent following past approaches<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CR68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup>. To cross validate the ranges of lateral expansion data and its growth trends, Global Human Settlement Layer (GHSL) data<sup><xref rid="CR69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup> is also used which specifically record the city names. It also provided us with the additional features of urban lateral expansion (e.g.- per capita built ground coverage and the yearly rise in per capita ground coverages specific to that urban city cluster).</p><p id="Par30">Additionally, <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>A</italic></sub> is defined as the ratio of the city’s maximum Feret’s diameter to its minimum Feret’s diameter<sup><xref rid="CR68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,<xref rid="CR71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,<xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup> (Feret ratio). Feret’s diameter represents the distance between two parallel tangents to an object along a specific direction.We derived an equivalent ellipse for each city boundary using a principal component–based approach and computed the Feret ratio as the ratio of the major to minor axis lengths. This anisometry measure also reflects the long-term lateral expansion pattern of a city. For instance, a value close to one indicates monocentric radial growth, while values greater than one suggest linear expansion in a particular direction<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CR73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></sup>. Urban imperviousness ratio (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>IR</italic></sub>) was estimated as the proportion of built-up ground coverage, representing impervious areas excluding urban road networks, relative to the total urban lateral land cover within the urban core area. The urban core was defined as the area within an approximate 5-km radius around the city centre, delineated and surrounded by the oldest functional urban units, which may include commercial business districts or early residential patches<sup><xref rid="CR74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>–<xref rid="CR76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></sup>. This metric serves as a proxy for city infilling, capturing both building and paved surface densities within the central urban fabric. For this purpose, initially Google-Open Buildings V3 Polygons data set is used<sup><xref rid="CR77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,<xref rid="CR78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref></sup> alongside GHSL built-up coverage data for urban centers<sup><xref rid="CR69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,<xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par31">The population dataset for the period 2003–2023 was sourced from the Oak Ridge National Laboratory LandScan dataset<sup><xref rid="CR79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref></sup>. These datasets (<italic>C</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub>), offers a 1 km global ambient population distribution (24-hour average and measure of unit is people per m<sup>2</sup>) by disaggregating census data through advanced spatial modelling that accounts for daily mobility and activity patterns also<sup><xref rid="CR80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,<xref rid="CR81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></sup>. For estimating population density growth, the compound annual growth rate (CAGR) method was used<sup><xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>, where <inline-formula id="IEq32"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2426"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <italic>r</italic> denotes the growth rate expressed as a percentage. The yearly pixel specific population values are multiplied with that pixel specific CDD-hum data to generate population weighted cooling degree days estimation, a more accurate form of urban cooling demand proxy in urban studies which is also adapted in our study. See Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref> for further details on the additional lateral growth trend indicators used in the subsequent analyses.</p><p id="Par32">Vertical and volumetric growth- The <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>V</italic></sub> metric measures the vertical rise of cities within the average urban extent of cities and is a key parameter for assessing volumetric urban growth. For this purpose, we used two types of vertical-structure data: gross rise (<inline-formula id="IEq33"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2464"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) and net vertical rise (<inline-formula id="IEq34"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2476"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>), both sourced from GHS Built-Up Height (R2023) dataset<sup><xref rid="CR82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref></sup>. The gross dataset represents the vertical rise of built form within each urban pixel, weighted by the full pixel area, indicating amount of built cubic meters per unit pixel, whereas the net dataset represents the average height of built surfaces. Both datasets were resampled to a 1 km × 1 km grid covering each city’s urban boundary and finally were area aggregated. Quartile-based metrics were then derived from the resampled values to quantify the intra-city distribution and spatial variability of building heights<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. From both data set, the first quantile <inline-formula id="IEq35"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2497"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>,<inline-formula id="IEq36"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2510"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (25<sup>th</sup> percentile) and third quantile <inline-formula id="IEq37"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2525"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq38"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2538"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (75<sup>th</sup> percentile) are the major variables (in m) estimated apart from recording the <inline-formula id="IEq39"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2554"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq40"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2567"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (50<sup>t</sup><sup>h</sup> percentile) and highest rise value (<inline-formula id="IEq41"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2583"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq42"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2597"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>). Further, measures like area averaged mean values of each percentile distribution (i.e. <inline-formula id="IEq43"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2612"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, or <inline-formula id="IEq44"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2631"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>), quartile coefficient of dispersion (QCD), are recorded to observe additional understanding of city vertical rise distribution (see Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>). QCD reflects the degree of variation in built-up heights across a city, while normalizing these variations so that cities with different average building heights can be compared meaningfully<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. Apart from city lateral spread and vertical growth, gross volumetric expanse of city-built spaces is collected directly from the GHSL datasets and averaged over the study period using the available data. The annual increment in city volume is also recorded for the available period under study. Some proxy measures of urban consolidation<sup><xref rid="CR83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref></sup> and urban concentration<sup><xref rid="CR84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></sup> using the various combination of lateral growth, infilling and vertical growth measure metrics, are also used in bi-variate analysis and modelling studies.</p><p id="Par33">Roads, green cover and other urbanization indicators- City road data, including total road length in kilometres and overall road network density in meters per square meter, is collected directly from the GHSL datasets and averaged over the study period using the available data. Data on urban green cover and its changes, which reflect shifts in open areas beyond built-up development, were collected from both the GHSL-Urban Centre Database (UCDB) list and cross-verified using MODIS-EVI datasets (MOD13A2.061) from 2003 to 2023, considering green cover as another key factor influencing urban temperature rise, which can be potential impactor of cooling demand also<sup><xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. In addition to urban volumetrics data, data on urban surface warming trends is also gathered as an additional record of urbanization indicator. MODIS datasets (2003–2023) were primarily used, where land surface temperature (MYD11A2, Aqua LST) datasets were mapped along the city extents for past two decades to record the warming trend (in °C/year). Alongside surface temperature, separately the city-scale area-averaged anthropogenic heating flux<sup><xref rid="CR85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref></sup> (in W/m<sup>2</sup>) is also sourced. Surface temperature and anthropogenic heating is a primary contributor and indicator of surface energy balance, which directly impact urban-climate and thus also impact cooling. Apart from these, regional-scale determinants of economic activity such as gross domestic product (in ppp) for urban centres <inline-formula id="IEq45"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2677"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which ultimately influence city energy demand and overall city-scale affordability<sup><xref rid="CR86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>–<xref rid="CR88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref></sup>, are also collected.</p><p id="Par34">Further, it is important to note that the majority of urban built volumetric datasets are sourced from the GAIA and GHSL project. Previous studies covering both global and Indian cities have successfully employed these datasets for city-scale analyses and have demonstrated their applicability and reasonable accuracy for urban research <sup><xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="CR89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>–<xref rid="CR91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, the findings should be interpreted in light of the limitations inherent to global open-source datasets, and future studies would benefit from the integration of additional locally validated datasets where available.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="2"><title>Clustering of cities</title><p id="Par35">After compiling the full set of urban volumetric indicators, we classified cities into four distinct morphological profiles using cluster analysis: (1) Large cities, high population density, high vertical development, high built-ground coverage, irregular city shape (Type-I), (2) Medium cities, high population density, moderate vertical development, high to moderate built-ground coverage, irregular city shape (Type-II), (3) Medium to Small cities, medium population density, moderate vertical development, moderate built-ground coverage, irregular city shape (Type-III), and (4) Smaller cities, low to medium population density, low vertical development, low built-ground coverage, compact city shape (Type-IV) (Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>,<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref>,<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par36">A k-means clustering algorithm was used to classify Indian cities by applying varied combinations of weightage to the volumetric urban features. To account for heterogeneity in units and magnitudes among volumetric indicators (e.g., km², %, people km<sup>−2</sup>, etc.), volumetric indicators were first standardized using Z-score normalization. This feature scaling converts the feature space into a dimensionless form with zero mean and unit variance, thereby ensuring balanced contribution of all variables in the clustering<sup><xref rid="CR92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></sup>. Potential collinearity among variables was assessed using a pairwise Pearson correlation matrix. Strong correlations (|r| &gt;0.8) were limited and primarily observed among percentile-based vertical rise indicators; in such cases, the contribution of one variable was moderately reduced prior to clustering to limit over-representation of closely related features. Next, multiple combinations of relative feature weighting and the corresponding clustering outcomes were examined. The optimal number of clusters, identified as four, was determined using a two-step approach. First, we reviewed clustering numbers adopted in past studies involving such urban features and city-scale climate-driven analytics addressing urban form and function, which identified clustering cities into 3-4 types<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CR91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref></sup>. Based on this evidence, we began with K equal to three and evaluated five stages of relative weight combinations as described in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>. Given the moderate sample size of cities in this study compared with global datasets, the selection of K was not determined solely by numerical metrics. We therefore conducted additional sensitivity analyses using higher and lower values of K (e.g., K + 1, K + 2, K-1, and K-2) to ensure that the clusters remained interpretable in terms of volumetric characteristics. The Silhouette score, Davies Bouldin index and the elbow method were employed<sup><xref rid="CR93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,<xref rid="CR94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></sup> to verify whether the chosen cluster range fell within an acceptable optimal window, as shown in Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par37">The final selection of four clusters was consistent with previous work showing that typologies based on equal weighting of volumetric indicators, or on greater emphasis on lateral expansion followed by vertical expansion, generate the most meaningful groups for comparative urban analysis as highlighted in Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">2</xref>. In the Indian context, the four-cluster typology also corresponded well with the Tier-I city classification used in the House Rent Allowance (HRA) norms issued by the Ministry of Finance in 2017<sup><xref rid="CR95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref></sup>, which categorises cities based on population and cost of living. This correspondence is important because Tier-I cities, often regarded as megacities, also exhibit the highest volumetric composition driven by highest rate of urbanization in last two decades and represent locations where development is approaching saturation compared with the more rapidly evolving Tier-II cities<sup><xref rid="CR96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,<xref rid="CR97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref></sup>. As four clusters were identified as optimal and provided the most interpretable distinctions across the urbanisation indicators used in this study, the 52 global cities were also categorised into the four typologies (Type-I to Type-IV) based on their dominant volumetric characteristics. The placement of representative global cities within these typologies aligns with the Globalization and World Cities (GaWC) classification tiers<sup><xref rid="CR98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></sup>, as well as with the volumetric expansion patterns documented for each city (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref>). Given the limited number of global cities in our dataset, adopting GaWC tiers as a reference ensured meaningful interpretation<sup><xref rid="CR99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>–<xref rid="CR101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref></sup>, whereas relying solely on automated clustering could have produced unstable or distorted groupings. We acknowledge, however, that future studies with a larger sample of global cities may employ fully automated clustering at the global scale, in which case the use of GaWC tiers may no longer be necessary.</p><p id="Par38">The sole motivation behind this clustering was to capture a broader dynamics of cities structural growth beyond its allometric scaling<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. Previous studies on city-wide warming trends<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> and cooling demand<sup><xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> have primarily categorized cities based on population size or lateral expansion, overlooking critical variations in urban volumetric structure that influence temperature differentials<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. Most existing city-classifications rely on allometric scaling, where cities are categorized by population share or horizontal extent alone<sup><xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>, reflecting long-term urban evolution and self-organization<sup><xref rid="CR102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref></sup>. While such approaches are valuable for understanding macro-scale urban dynamics, they may not fully capture disparities in energy demand, which largely depend on a city’s overall volumetric massing and floor area coverage<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. The classification framework adopted here addresses this limitation by integrating built development characteristics<sup><xref rid="CR103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref></sup>, offering a more comprehensive representation of cities’ physical dimensions alongside their allometric growth patterns. This clustering is further updated by incorporating city-wide daytime and nighttime surface warming trends. Surface warming patterns in cities acts as a major indicator of surface energy alternations<sup><xref rid="CR104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref></sup>, which in term can inform observations on the inter-city cooling demand variations<sup><xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="CR105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref></sup>. Another reason of considering warming trends along volumetric growth features for clustering was to consider the background climatic effect<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>. Regional and background climate-based classifications were also explored for cities across both the Indian subcontinent and globally. Indian cities were grouped into six regional zones named as East Coast (EC), West Coast (WC), Indo-Gangetic Plain (IG), South and Western Himalayan Foothills and the North-Eastern Hill Region (SH), Interior Peninsular or Deccan Plateau (DP), and Central as well as Western India (CI). This classification is based on the initial seven homogeneous climate zones delineated by the Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology (IITM), Pune, and was further refined following studies like<sup><xref rid="CR106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>–<xref rid="CR108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref></sup>. For global cities, due to the smaller sample size, a simplified classification was used, categorizing them as either coastal or inland, in addition to their grouping through volumetric clustering.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Estimation of UCD</title><p id="Par39">Cooling degree days (CDD) as indicators of UCD- Our cooling degree days approach is an aggregated level (top-down) cooling demand prediction method in urban grids. Use of CDD  is one of the most widely used method for urban scale demand predictions due to its high spatio-temporal granularity as well as requirement of reduced computational expense, relative to other approaches<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> (see Supplementary Note 1). In simpler terms, the cooling degree approach measures how much and for how long the outdoor air temperature remains higher than a given base temperature<sup><xref rid="CR109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref></sup>.The base temperature refers to the threshold beyond which mechanical cooling becomes necessary. It varies depending on regional climate conditions, occupancy preferences, building construction design, and energy flow dynamics within buildings. Various base temperatures (e.g., 18 °C, 21 °C, 24 °C, etc.) have been utilized globally, tailored to the spatiotemporal scale of assessments and often demonstrating a significant positive correlation between outdoor temperatures and actual energy demand profiles (see Supplementary Note 1). Before exploring the details of base temperature specifications, suitable for our study regions, here is a summarized outline of annual CDD measures-systematically followed in this study:</p><disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2860" display="block"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>365</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> &gt;   = <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub>; <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> is the external temperature and <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub> is the base temperature. Currently all the climate parameters are of hourly resolution. As we are to count the CDD for the entire city regions more appropriate representation of this approach would be as equation ii, where <inline-formula id="IEq46"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2937"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> represent the cooling degree days, calculated over the certain period of time in the grid specification l.</p><disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e2953" display="block"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>365</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></disp-formula><p id="Par40">Equation (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>) represents the sensible component of the cooling degree days measure, where other micro-climate parameters are not included. This approach is widely adopted in global studies, such as Deroubaix et. al.<sup><xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>, Yalew et. al.<sup><xref rid="CR110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref></sup>, Ruijven et. al.<sup><xref rid="CR111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref></sup> as a climate-driven energy demand indicator. However, the majority of these studies focus on regional or national scales. In our study, we aim to explore cooling demand dynamics at a much finer spatial scale within city boundaries, necessitating a region-specific modification of Cooling Degree Days (CDDs). Considering India’s predominantly hot and humid climate, where both sensible and latent heat significantly influence thermal comfort, particularly the humidity-induced warming effect, the CDD equation is updated to incorporate additional microclimatic parameters.</p><p id="Par41">The heat index updated perceived outdoor temperature measure- Many previous studies modified this degree days methods (Eq. <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>) where the <inline-formula id="IEq47"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3030"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is weighted with other urban micro-climate data (e.g.- relative humidity, solar radiation, windspeed data etc.)<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> to obtain the perceived temperature <inline-formula id="IEq48"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3050"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values, which in term improves the accuracy of model. There are many established indices as well as recent researches that tries to derive the perceived temperature measure<sup><xref rid="CR112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref></sup>. Among these the humidity weighted-heat index approach, adapted by Scoccimarro et. al.<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>, building-adjusted internal temperature (BAIT)-index derived by Staffell, Pfenninger, and Johnson<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> were found compatible with the current study scale and scope. For this study covering Indian cities, the heat index definition provided by the IEA and used in the studies of Scoccimarro et. al.<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> is used, where the modified perceived outdoor temperature is defined as (Eq. <xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3089" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∓</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></disp-formula><p id="Par42">Here <inline-formula id="IEq49"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3252"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is calculated in °F with values of the used scaling factors: <italic>C</italic><sub>0</sub> = −42.379; <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub> = 2.04901523; <italic>C</italic><sub>2</sub> = 10.14333127; <italic>C</italic><sub>3</sub> = −0.22475541; <italic>C</italic><sub>4</sub> = −6.83783 * 10<sup>−3</sup>; <italic>C</italic><sub>5</sub> = −5.481717 * 10<sup>−2</sup>;<italic>C</italic><sub>6</sub> = 1.22874 * 10<sup>−3</sup>; <italic>C</italic><sub>7</sub> = 8.5282 * 10<sup>−4</sup>; <italic>C</italic><sub>8</sub> = −1.99 * 10<sup>−6</sup>. The equation−3 is said to be valid for <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic>,<italic>l</italic></sub> ≥ 26.67 °C and <italic>RH</italic> ≥ 40%, else <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic>,<italic>l</italic></sub> can be used in place of <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>pe</italic>,<italic>l</italic></sub>. While proceeding with rest of the steps of CDD calculation, the perceived temperature values are converted to °C from °F, maintaining the continuity with the cooling degree days definition. In this study, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>pe</italic>,<italic>l</italic></sub> is calculated for each grid points with all other microclimate parameters resampled at a consistent spatial resolution (~1 km x 1 km). To ensure temporal resolution compatibility, the same reanalysis dataset, ERA5-Land (detailed applicability of this dataset is explained in the following sub-section), is used throughout the calculation. Relative Humidity (RH) is not directly available in the dataset and is derived from dew point temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>dew</italic></sub>) and external temperature <inline-formula id="IEq50"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3362"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> using the Arden Buck equations<sup><xref rid="CR113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref></sup> (Eq. <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>). Here the used balance point values are noted as-<italic>r</italic><sub>1</sub> = 17.052 and <italic>r</italic><sub>2</sub> = 240.97 from<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>.</p><disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3400" display="block"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula><p id="Par43">The final CDD which is typically the humidity weighted CDD and henceforth called ‘CDD-hum’ is calculated following Eq. <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref> for each 1 km x 1 km grid cells covering eighty plus cities in India. Though the approach is adapted by Scoccimarro et. al. (2024), the heat index used here connects to the Steadman’s model of human thermoregulation derived on 1979<sup><xref rid="CR114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref></sup> and updated over time following its applicability range<sup><xref rid="CR115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref></sup>. This method was found to be more relevant for recording the compound impact of microclimate parameters, particularly the combined effect of outdoor temperature and relative humidity, which are primary contributors to heating-related physiological sensations. Another suitable index could be the BAIT approach; however, its application in the current study has a noted limitation. Specifically, BAIT closely follows outdoor actual temperature but exhibits lower daily variability due to temporal smoothing. It is generally higher than temperature during spring and lower in autumn months due to differences in solar irradiance relative to temperature. Consequently, recording CDD in the Indian context using BAIT would result in a smoothed impact, potentially failing to capture the actual warming effects or the rise in cooling demand. This limitation is particularly pronounced in studies like these focusing on developing yet rapidly urbanizing cities, where validation datasets may be limited. Also, Scoccimarro et. al.<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> has highlighted the applicability of the Eq. <xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref> in cities like India where the predominant meso-climatic condition remains hot and humid in many rapidly urbanizing cities and thus the final CDD-hum calculations with perceived temperatures are defined through Eq. <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref>:</p><disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3504" display="block"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>365</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula><p id="Par44"><inline-formula id="IEq51"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3567"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is calculated on a yearly basis across the urban boundaries of each city, representing the cumulative annual sum of positive hourly exceedances of perceived temperature <inline-formula id="IEq52"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3583"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> above the base temperature (expressed as CDD in °C-year and the total number of days where <italic>CDD</italic><sub><italic>t</italic>,<italic>l</italic></sub> &gt; 0)</p><p id="Par45">City-scale CDD-hum estimation - As our study is on city-scale, to further enhance the CDD calculations by accounting for the regional-scale impact of urbanization, a widely practiced approach is to weight the cooling degree days by the population densities<sup><xref rid="CR116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref></sup>. Population values were derived from the clipped population raster within each city boundary, following which the population-weighted mean of the extracted annual CDD-hum values within the same city extent was calculated. The region-aggregated CDD-hum is therefore defined as in Eq. <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref>.</p><disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3622" display="block"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <inline-formula id="IEq53"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3704"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the annual aggregated CDD-hum value for region <italic>r</italic> at the selected threshold temperature <italic>t</italic>. <inline-formula id="IEq54"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3727"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the extracted annual CDD-hum values within the city extent, <inline-formula id="IEq55"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3745"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the population density values derived from the clipped population raster, and <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> denotes the total number of valid extracted values within region <italic>r</italic>. The denominator represents the total population aggregated over the entire city boundary. Along with the CDD-hum values in terms of °C-year, the number of days for which the perceived temperature exceeds the threshold temperature is also recorded as <inline-formula id="IEq56"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3770"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, represented as an area-averaged indicator to assess the relative intensity of warming days within cities.</p><p id="Par46">Base point temperature choice suiting the study scale- The determination of preferred base point temperatures <inline-formula id="IEq57"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3798"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> rely upon list of built system as well as occupant characteristics like the building-users’ behavioural preferences, building thermal inertia to outdoor micro-climatic influences, etc. Previous studies have adapted many systematic methods like by a three-parameter cooling (3PC) regression analysis plotting using actual building energy usage data <inline-formula id="IEq58"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3814"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, outdoor temperature <inline-formula id="IEq59"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3831"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to count on the inflection point that can give the range for the base point measure. In such approaches, the base point preferences are set to vary across building archetypes and with regional variability in both meso- and microscale urban climates, as well as socio-physiological acclimatization<sup><xref rid="CR117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref></sup>. The International Energy Agency (IEA) and similar studies<sup><xref rid="CR118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>–<xref rid="CR120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref></sup> typically adopt a base temperature range of 18–26 °C for CDD calculations at global or country-wide scales. Region-specific studies, particularly in the Asia-Pacific and Middle East (APME) regions, provide further insights into variability. For instance, Bhatnagar et al. (2018)<sup><xref rid="CR121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref></sup> documented base temperature ranges of 6.8 °C to 28.6 °C for large hotels and 8.7 °C to 28.1 °C for office buildings within the Indian subcontinent. Specifically, for this study, a base temperature range of 22–28 °C was chosen for Indian cities, with the lower limit derived from previous global studies such as Kennard et al. (2022)<sup><xref rid="CR122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref></sup> and the upper limit based on the findings of study<sup><xref rid="CR121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref></sup>. The consideration of the 22 to 28 °C range can also reflect increasing city-wide mechanical cooling penetration as the base temperature decreases. The lower base temperatures are typically associated with buildings with higher cooling dependence and tighter comfort expectations, often characteristic of mechanically conditioned environments. For global cities outside India, a base temperature of 20 °C as a standardized reference was adopted as the cooling threshold, consistent with previous globally validated studies like Staffell, Pfenninger, and Johnson<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="2"><title>CDD-hum and its pattern with actual UCD</title><p id="Par47">M Santamouris<sup><xref rid="CR123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref></sup> has highlighted - the practice of simple linear or non-linear models to estimate the actual cooling demand from the CDD and also noted the usage of CDD as the simple yet reliable method to indicate cooling demand especially the air-conditioning usage and its penetration. Among many models mentioned in literature, Isaac et.al.<sup><xref rid="CR124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref></sup> showed that unit energy consumption of cooling is in direct proportionate with CDD values. Staffell, Pfenninger, and Johnson<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> has also used a simple linear model to directly correlate the CDD with actual energy demand in their multiscale energy demand modelling approach. In our study, the estimation of Urban Cooling Demand (UCD) is currently based on CDD-hum calculations. A direct quantification of UCD in Terajoules (TJ) or equivalent measures like million units (MU) would require extensive city-wide data on cooling energy consumption, which is currently limited in terms of temporal scope. Ideally, cooling energy data for urban building stocks should be computed and compared for a more accurate assessment. However, due to the focus on rapidly developing cities across India with limited real time open-data repository, curating accurate city-wide energy consumption data is challenging. However, to validate whether the estimated CDD-hum and their trends align with actual energy consumption increases, state-specific actual energy demand data was empirically correlated with the estimated CDD-hum.</p><p id="Par48">For Indian cities, the annual total electricity supply data (in million units, MU) was sourced from the India Climate and Energy Dashboard, while monthly energy data (in million units, MU) was obtained from the Central Electricity Authority. Digitally recorded monthly data from 2020 to 2022 was available and used to assess its correlation with monthly CDD-hum measures (°C-year). The data was collected for six states- Delhi NCR, West Bengal, Puducherry, Tripura, Kerala, and Goa. Although the data is state-level, certain regions, such as Delhi NCR, Goa, and Puducherry, primarily represent city-scale energy demand due to their comparable lateral expansion with respect to the pool of cities taken under study. Additionally, we sourced Kolkata’s annual energy demand data (in MU) for the past five years from the Report on Power Survey of India. The taken set of six representative urban boundaries also covers all the city profiles taken under study. Since CDD-hum values are measured in °C-year and energy demand in MU, normalization was performed for each representative case using mean-max normalization. Post-normalization, both variables were plotted in the same time series to observe their monthly variability patterns and long-term (yearly) trends. A strong positive correlation (R ~ 0.7, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) was observed between CDD-hum and energy demand, indicating high temporal coherence throughout the study period. Similarly, CDD and electricity consumption data from global cities, particularly from U.S. cities and Singapore, were compared with our estimated CDD-hum models, which also showed a moderate to strong positive correlation (R ~ 0.5 to 0.96, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Further details are provided in Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">7</xref>–<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">19</xref>. This pattern matching provides further confidence in the adapted methodology as the energy demand peaks and downfalls was in alignment with the observed CDD-hum trends also over the time-period. It is important to note that while total electricity and peak demand account for residential, industrial, and commercial usage, the residential sector contributes approximately 60–85%<sup><xref rid="CR125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref></sup> and is the primary driver of demand variations, particularly due to cooling needs. Although the humidity-weighted CDD derived using Equation 6 exhibits a strong positive correlation with actual energy demand trends, incorporating city-level scaling factors from Equation 3 would yield more precise CDD-hum estimates as a proxy for UCD. Further when we noticed the trends of rising demand in both cases (i.e. actual energy demand values and CDD-hum) the CDD-hum was noticed to show supressed trend (slopes approximately 20–40% lower) than actual energy demand rise. However, given the scope of this study and the significant positive trend observed across all representative cases, we proceed with Eq. <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref> as the proxy for UCD. Future refinements can integrate city-specific adjustments once finer-resolution actual demand data becomes available for scaling factor calibration. Trends in CDD-hum were estimated over 2003–2023, using the longest contiguous interval with an increasing slope for each city. Simple linear and log-linear regression were used to quantify absolute (°C-year/year) and relative (%/year) changes, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="2"><title>Re-analysis dataset and its applicability</title><p id="Par49">For CDD calculations, gridded re-analysis meteorological data were sourced from ERA5-Land, specifically 2m-surface air temperature <inline-formula id="IEq60"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3918"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and dew point temperature <inline-formula id="IEq61"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e3935"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The ERA5-Land data resolution is ~9 km and is resampled to 1 km resolution matching all other city-scale volumetric growth feature datasets. The reanalysis datasets ERA5-Land used in this study is produced using the Integrated Forecasting System (IFS) Cy41r2, which is reported to not contain sophisticated urban parameterizations<sup><xref rid="CR126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref></sup>. But some of the recent studies also record that ERA5-Land has capability to record the urban impact<sup><xref rid="CR127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>,<xref rid="CR128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref></sup> as a mass of observations (from stations, satellites, radars, etc.) are assimilated in the ERA5 reanalysis dataset, and the state-of-the-art data assimilation technologies (such as 4D-Var) have significantly improved the quality of the ERA5 simulations<sup><xref rid="CR129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref></sup>. Sussman et al.<sup><xref rid="CR130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref></sup> utilized ERA5-Land to investigate urbanization impacts in regions across India, highlighting its applicability in analysing urban impacts in warming studies. Taking observation from weather station data around urban centres for Indian cities, it is estimated that though the urban impact might be underestimated in pixel level, the area-averaged air temperature and humidity data remains in good temporal agreement (R = 0.82-0.97) (see Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6</xref>). These findings provide confidence to our study in using ERA5-Land for UCD estimation in this study. Though this reanalysis data based UCD proxy method proves especially robust for Indian cities, it is also important to acknowledge here that, employing ERA5-Land introduces inherent limitations, given its original spatial resolution, though resampled to 1 km, which restricts the ability to capture fine-scale heat exchange processes to capture more detailed localized (intra-urban) cooling requirements. These limitations could result in a partial depiction or underrepresentation of microclimatic variability, as phenomena such as heat retention in urban canyons, mutual shading, or wind wake effects generated by dense high-rise developments within cities might not be fully captured<sup><xref rid="CR131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, given that this study targets city-scale aggregated patterns to evaluate relative changes in cooling demand associated with urbanization, the applied CDD-hum remain suitable for the intended comparative assessment<sup><xref rid="CR131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>–<xref rid="CR135" ref-type="bibr">135</xref></sup>. This current approach offers valuable insights into mesoscale variations in thermal demand, and recognizes that higher-resolution, downscaled, or urban-parameterized datasets could strengthen future analyses by representing intra-urban heterogeneity and detailed urban microclimate dynamics more explicitly<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CR136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="2"><title>Bivariate correlations and Semi-partial correlations</title><p id="Par50">Both Pearson correlation and Spearman rank correlation are measured to evaluate the relationships between variables. Pearson correlation quantifies the linear association between two variables, with the correlation coefficient ranging from −1 to 1. A value of 1 (or −1) indicates a perfect positive (or negative) linear relationship, whereas a value of 0 indicates the absence of linear association. For a bivariate data {(x<sub>1</sub>, y<sub>1</sub>), …, (x<sub>n</sub>, y<sub>n</sub>)}, the correlation <inline-formula id="IEq62"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e4008"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be defined by:</p><disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e4034" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>XY</italic></sub> and <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>X</italic></sub>, <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>Y</italic></sub> denote the sample covariance and standard deviations. In addition, the Spearman rank correlation was calculated as a non-parametric measure of association, which assesses how well the relationship between two variables can be described by a monotonic function, including potentially nonlinear relationships. Unlike Pearson correlation, Spearman correlation is computed using the ranked values of the observations rather than the raw data, and similarly ranges from −1 to 1.The Spearman correlation coefficient <inline-formula id="IEq63"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e4097"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is given by:</p><disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="d33e4123" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mo mathsize="big">∑</mml:mo><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the difference between the ranks of each pair (x<sub>n</sub>, y<sub>n</sub>), and n is the number of observations. Together, these two correlation measures provide a comprehensive understanding of the relationships in such analysis, Pearson capturing linear dependencies, and Spearman capturing monotonic trends, even in the presence of non-linearity<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. Given heterogeneity in city size and growth, extreme values can disproportionately influence correlation estimates. To mitigate this, outliers were identified using the 1.5×IQR criterion and excluded prior to analysis. Correlations were computed on the filtered dataset and also repeated on the full dataset as a sensitivity check to ensure robustness. To further isolate the independent contribution of individual predictors, semi-partial correlation analysis was performed. Specifically, each predictor variable was first regressed against the selected correlated covariates using linear regression, and the resulting residuals, representing the unique variance in the predictor after removing shared effects, were subsequently correlated with the response variable using two-sided Pearson correlation analysis for linear association and for non-linear spearman analysis was used. This approach enables the assessment of the independent association between each predictor and the target variable while accounting for shared variance with control covariates. Further details on the correlation techniques used in such studies are available in previous works<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="CR137" ref-type="bibr">137</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="2"><title>Modelling attempt for cross-city UCD prediction</title><p id="Par51">The dataset used in this study is heterogeneous and relatively small, which limits its suitability for developing a universally generalizable model or for deriving country- or continent-specific cross-city UCD patterns. However, despite these constraints, the dataset provides meaningful indications of how various indicators of volumetric growth driven by urbanization influence city-wide UCD. Both nonlinear and linear modelling approaches were employed, seemingly applicable in such scale of study of human-climate-city interaction<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>. Nonlinear machine learning (ML) models such as Random Forest (RF) and Extreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost) were implemented to capture complex interactions and potential non-additive effects among urban variables following previous studies<sup><xref rid="CR138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref></sup>. In parallel, linear models including Lasso, Elastic Net and Ridge regression methods were utilized to identify interpretable predictors with regularization, suitable for high-dimensional feature spaces<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par52">Modelling was performed using the combined dataset comprising Indian and global cities, incorporating a comprehensive suite of urbanization indicators as input features. These indicators capture both annual changes and yearly averaged measures of city form and land-cover dynamics (built and unbuilt), vertical development, densification, consolidation, infilling, road infrastructure expansion, and GDP-based measures representing city-scale economic growth, as detailed in Supplementary Tables <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>. In addition to these urbanization indicators, city-wide, area-averaged annual climate variables were also included. As the derivation of UCD relies strongly on CDD-hum, the modelling framework was divided into two categories to distinguish the influence of purely urbanization-driven effects from those more strongly controlled by climate (see Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">6</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">7</xref>). In the first category (model clusters 1–2 and 5–6), only 65 urbanization indicators were used, along with indirect measures of background climatic conditions. To capture this background-regional climate influences without relying on direct meteorological inputs, long-term trends in LST and the frequency of warming days (i.e. yearly total number of days requiring cooling of indoors) were included as proxies. In the second category (model clusters 3–4 and 7–8), direct climate variables, specifically annual, area-averaged values of 2-m air temperature, humidity, wind speed and solar radiation, were also incorporated with existing feature space. These variables are expected to enhance prediction accuracy because UCD is strongly climate dependent. However, it is important to note that although UCD estimation is ultimately aggregate from the pixel-level to city scale, inclusion of direct climate conditions, even if they are area-averaged annual values, they can exert a strong influence on UCD independent of urbanization indicators. This provides the rationale for evaluating two distinct model categories: one capturing only urbanization-driven effects (with indirect climatic proxies) and another that explicitly incorporates direct climate variables. The target variable in the models was the observed two-decade average of annual UCD (model 1,2 and 3,4) and annual rise in UCD (model 5,6 and 7,8). As detailed out in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref>, total 65 various features of urban volumetric change are used and many of the features might be correlated and not completely independent of each other. Given this potential multicollinearity issues among predictor variables, Variance Inflation Factor (VIF) was computed, and features with VIF &gt; 10 were iteratively removed prior to modelling to address multicollinearity, which is considered an acceptable threshold for such city-scale energy and climate analytics applications. Each models, where applicable, was evaluated using K-fold cross-validation (K = 10), a technique that partitions the dataset into training and test folds to assess model generalizability<sup><xref rid="CR139" ref-type="bibr">139</xref></sup>. Model performance was assessed using within-sample goodness-of-fit (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>), out-of-sample goodness-of-fit (<italic>OS</italic>_<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) under cross-validation, and the coefficient of variation of fold-wise root mean squared error (CV-RMSE). Here, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>OS</italic>_<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>quantify the explained variance for the training and held-out test samples, respectively. We also included the estimation of coefficient of variation of fold-wise mean squared prediction error (CV-MSPE)<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="CR140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref></sup>. Together, these models provide an indicative assessment of the relevance and predictive power of urbanization indicators in explaining cross-city variability in climate-driven increment in cooling demand. Further details on the relative importance of the input features are presented in the Results section titled Modelling attempt for cross-city UCD trends, as well as in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. A more comprehensive and higher-accuracy modelling framework is a key directive for future research, particularly with larger and more globally representative datasets.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15" disp-level="2"><title>Reporting summary</title><p id="Par53">Further information on research design is available in the <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Nature Portfolio Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary information</title>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM1" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b390/13287610/78ad1e47e909/41467_2026_74157_MOESM1_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 9177358?><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM2" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b390/13287610/47c059d35a7d/41467_2026_74157_MOESM2_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1666357?><caption><p>Reporting Summary</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM3" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_MOESM3_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b390/13287610/8840f0c7fa86/41467_2026_74157_MOESM3_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1940070?><caption><p>Transparent Peer Review file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>N.M. acknowledges the Ph.D. research scholarship provided by IIT Kharagpur. P.A. acknowledges support from the SRIC grant No. IIT/SRIC/AR/MWS/2021-2022/057, which supported the development of the AI-HBI Research Lab infrastructure at the Department of Architecture and Regional Planning, IIT Kharagpur, where the research was conceived. D.N. acknowledges support from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) through the National Integrated Heat Health Information System under grants NA21OAR4310146 and NOAA/CPO #100007298; the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) through the Disasters Science: Austin CARES and Power AI projects under grants 80NSSC25K7417 and 80NSSC26K0190; the U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) under award 60NANB24D235; and the U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) through the Urban Integrated Field Laboratory – Community Research on Climate and Urban Science (CROCUS) under grant DE-SC0023226. D.N. and M.S. acknowledge support from the U.S. National Science Foundation (NSF) under grant 2413827.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>N.M. conceived and designed the initial study, conducted the research, performed data analysis, and wrote the original draft. P.A. coordinated the study, refined the research design, and contributed to writing, review, editing, and supervision. A.K. contributed to the refinement of the study design and scope, and provided review and guidance. M.G. contributed to the enhancement of the study design and scope, and provided review, editing, and guidance. D.N. contributed to the review and refinement of the study design and scope and strategic guidance. M.S. contributed to review and editing, provided strategic guidance and overall supervision.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Peer review</title><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="2"><title>Peer review information</title><p id="Par54"><italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks Guglielmina Mutani and the other anonymous reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work. A peer review file is available.</p></sec></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data used in the current study are available in the public domain as listed below: City lateral extent data can be accessed from the MODIS Land Cover Type dataset (MCD12Q1.v061) available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://lpdaac.usgs.gov/products/mcd12q1v061/" ext-link-type="uri">https://lpdaac.usgs.gov/products/mcd12q1v061/</ext-link>. Further, city urban area shapefiles can be accessed from the updated Global Urban Boundary (GUB) dataset portal at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data-starcloud.pcl.ac.cn/iearthdata/map?id=14&amp;r_id=14" ext-link-type="uri">https://data-starcloud.pcl.ac.cn/iearthdata/map?id=14&amp;r_id=14</ext-link> and for Indian cities the urban boundary shapefiles used in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44284-024-00074-0" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nature.com/articles/s44284-024-00074-0</ext-link> is used which can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/SSoumyaS/Shape_Files/tree/main/India_boundary" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/SSoumyaS/Shape_Files/tree/main/India_boundary</ext-link>. For infilling estimation, Google Open Buildings V3 polygons data can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://sites.research.google/gr/open-buildings/" ext-link-type="uri">https://sites.research.google/gr/open-buildings/</ext-link> and can be used alongside GHSL built-up datasets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_bu.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_bu.php</ext-link>). The GHS Built-Up data can be accessed through the Copernicus GHSL dataset portal, including GHS Urban Centre Database (UCDB) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_ucdb_2024.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_ucdb_2024.php</ext-link>), GHS Built Height (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_buH2023.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_buH2023.php</ext-link>), and GHS Built Volume (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_buV2023.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_buV2023.php</ext-link>). Anthropogenic emissions datasets can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://urbanclimate.tse.ens.titech.ac.jp/category/dataset/" ext-link-type="uri">https://urbanclimate.tse.ens.titech.ac.jp/category/dataset/</ext-link>. The population dataset for the period 2003–2023 can be sourced from the Oak Ridge National Laboratory LandScan dataset (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://landscan.ornl.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://landscan.ornl.gov/</ext-link>). MODIS datasets (2003–2023) can be accessed through the Google Earth Engine platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/modis" ext-link-type="uri">https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/modis</ext-link>) and also directly through NASA Earth data catalogue pages such as <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/data/catalog/lpcloud-myd21c1-061" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/data/catalog/lpcloud-myd21c1-061</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/data/catalog/lpcloud-myd21c2-061" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/data/catalog/lpcloud-myd21c2-061</ext-link>. For CDD calculations, gridded re-analysis meteorological data can be sourced from ERA5-Land available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets" ext-link-type="uri">https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets</ext-link>. State-specific energy demand data for Indian cities can be accessed through the Central Electricity Authority dashboard at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cea.nic.in/dashboard/?lang=en" ext-link-type="uri">https://cea.nic.in/dashboard/?lang=en</ext-link>. For Singapore demand data it can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ema.gov.sg/resources/statistics/load-demand-centre" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ema.gov.sg/resources/statistics/load-demand-centre</ext-link> and for US cities region specific cooling degree days data can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.eia.gov/totalenergy/data/browser/index.php?tbl=T01.12#/?f=A" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eia.gov/totalenergy/data/browser/index.php?tbl=T01.12#/?f=A</ext-link>. The administrative boundary maps for India and the world can be sourced from the Survey of India geoportal (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/" ext-link-type="uri">https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/</ext-link>),product code: OVSF/1M/7 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/Digital_Product_Show.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/Digital_Product_Show.aspx</ext-link>) and the World Bank Official Boundaries dataset (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://datacatalog.worldbank.org/search/dataset/0038272/world-bank-official-boundaries" ext-link-type="uri">https://datacatalog.worldbank.org/search/dataset/0038272/world-bank-official-boundaries</ext-link>), respectively.</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Code availability</title><p>The majority of the geo-spatial data collection and preliminary analysis was done using google earth engine platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://code.earthengine.google.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://code.earthengine.google.com/</ext-link>) coupled with python based google Collab platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://colab.research.google.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://colab.research.google.com/</ext-link>). The visualization and further detailed analysis of data were performed using Python, with the Spyder platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.spyder-ide.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.spyder-ide.org/</ext-link>) utilized as the integrated development environment (IDE). Source codes can be accessed from 10.5281/zenodo.19346583<sup><xref rid="CR141" ref-type="bibr">141</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" disp-level="1"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par55">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="sec17" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41467-026-74157-y.</p></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Georgescu, M., Morefield, P. E., Bierwagen, B. G. &amp; Weaver, C. P. Urban adaptation can roll back warming of emerging megapolitan regions. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</italic><bold>111</bold>, 2909–2914 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1322280111"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3939866"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="24516126"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Grimm, N. B. et al. Global change and the ecology of cities. <italic>Sci. (80-.).</italic><bold>319</bold>, 756–760 (2008).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.1150195"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="18258902"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Grimm, N. B. et al. Global change and the ecology of cities. Sci. (80-.).319, 756–760 (2008)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC). Technical Summary. <italic>Clim. Chang. 2021 – Phys. Sci. Basis</italic> 35–144 (2023) 10.1017/9781009157896.002.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Georgescu, M., Moustaoui, M., Mahalov, A. &amp; Dudhia, J. Summer-time climate impacts of projected megapolitan expansion in Arizona. <italic>Nat. Clim. Chang. 2012 31</italic><bold>3</bold>, 37–41 (2012).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Georgescu, M., Moustaoui, M., Mahalov, A. &amp; Dudhia, J. Summer-time climate impacts of projected megapolitan expansion in Arizona. Nat. Clim. Chang. 2012 313, 37–41 (2012)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mondal, N. et al. Systematic review of the efficacy of data-driven urban building energy models during extreme heat in cities: Current trends and future outlook. <italic>Build. Simul. 2024 175</italic><bold>17</bold>, 695–722 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mondal, N. et al. Systematic review of the efficacy of data-driven urban building energy models during extreme heat in cities: Current trends and future outlook. Build. Simul. 2024 17517, 695–722 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Güneralp, B. et al. Global scenarios of urban density and its impacts on building energy use through 2050. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</italic><bold>114</bold>, 8945–8950 (2017).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1606035114"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5576775"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28069957"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Güneralp, B. et al. Global scenarios of urban density and its impacts on building energy use through 2050. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.114, 8945–8950 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bettencourt, L. M. A. The origins of scaling in cities. <italic>Sci. (80-.)</italic><bold>340</bold>, 1438–1441 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.1235823"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23788793"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bettencourt, L. M. A. The origins of scaling in cities. Sci. (80-.)340, 1438–1441 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, X., Wang, X., Zhang, J. &amp; Wu, L. Allometric scaling, size distribution and pattern formation of natural cities. <italic>Palgrave Commun.</italic><bold>2015</bold>, 1–11 (2015).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, X., Wang, X., Zhang, J. &amp; Wu, L. Allometric scaling, size distribution and pattern formation of natural cities. Palgrave Commun.2015, 1–11 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Frolking, S., Milliman, T., Seto, K. C. &amp; Friedl, M. A. A global fingerprint of macro-scale changes in urban structure from 1999 to 2009. <italic>Environ. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 024004 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Frolking, S., Milliman, T., Seto, K. C. &amp; Friedl, M. A. A global fingerprint of macro-scale changes in urban structure from 1999 to 2009. Environ. Res. Lett.8, 024004 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Novotný, J., Chakraborty, S. &amp; Maity, I. Urban expansion of the 43 worlds’ largest megacities: A search for unified macro-patterns. <italic>Habitat Int</italic>. <bold>129</bold>, 102676 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Novotný, J., Chakraborty, S. &amp; Maity, I. Urban expansion of the 43 worlds’ largest megacities: A search for unified macro-patterns. Habitat Int. 129, 102676 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Frolking, S., Mahtta, R., Milliman, T., Esch, T. &amp; Seto, K. C. Global urban structural growth shows a profound shift from spreading out to building up. <italic>Nat. Cities</italic><bold>19</bold>, 555–566 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Frolking, S., Mahtta, R., Milliman, T., Esch, T. &amp; Seto, K. C. Global urban structural growth shows a profound shift from spreading out to building up. Nat. Cities19, 555–566 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liou, Y. A., Tran, D. P. &amp; Nguyen, K. A. Spatio-temporal patterns and driving forces of surface urban heat island in Taiwan. <italic>Urban Clim.</italic><bold>53</bold>, 101806 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liou, Y. A., Tran, D. P. &amp; Nguyen, K. A. Spatio-temporal patterns and driving forces of surface urban heat island in Taiwan. Urban Clim.53, 101806 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Schorcht, M., Jehling, M. &amp; Krüger, T. Where are cities under pressure? – An indicator for measuring the impact of building changes on urban density. <italic>Ecol. Indic.</italic><bold>149</bold>, 110142 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Schorcht, M., Jehling, M. &amp; Krüger, T. Where are cities under pressure? – An indicator for measuring the impact of building changes on urban density. Ecol. Indic.149, 110142 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Santamouris, M. Recent progress on urban overheating and heat island research. Integrated assessment of the energy, environmental, vulnerability and health impact. Synergies with the global climate change. <italic>Energy Build.</italic><bold>207</bold>, 109482 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Santamouris, M. Recent progress on urban overheating and heat island research. Integrated assessment of the energy, environmental, vulnerability and health impact. Synergies with the global climate change. Energy Build.207, 109482 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhao, L., Lee, X., Smith, R. B. &amp; Oleson, K. Strong contributions of local background climate to urban heat islands. <italic>Nat 2014 5117508</italic><bold>511</bold>, 216–219 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nature13462"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25008529"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhao, L., Lee, X., Smith, R. B. &amp; Oleson, K. Strong contributions of local background climate to urban heat islands. Nat 2014 5117508511, 216–219 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Santamouris, M. On the energy impact of urban heat island and global warming on buildings. <italic>Energy Build</italic><bold>82</bold>, 100–113 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Santamouris, M. On the energy impact of urban heat island and global warming on buildings. Energy Build82, 100–113 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Santamouris, M. Urban overheating and its impact on human beings. <italic>Mitig. Adapt. Urban Overheating Impact Warmer Cities Clim. Energy, Heal. Environ. Qual. Econ. Qual. Life</italic> 1–21 (2024) 10.1016/B978-0-443-13502-6.00001-4.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hsu, A., Sheriff, G., Chakraborty, T. &amp; Manya, D. Disproportionate exposure to urban heat island intensity across major US cities. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1–11 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-021-22799-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8149665"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34035248"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hsu, A., Sheriff, G., Chakraborty, T. &amp; Manya, D. Disproportionate exposure to urban heat island intensity across major US cities. Nat. Commun.12, 1–11 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu, Z. et al. Surface warming in global cities is substantially more rapid than in rural background areas. <italic>Commun. Earth Environ.</italic><bold>3</bold>, 1–9 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liu, Z. et al. Surface warming in global cities is substantially more rapid than in rural background areas. Commun. Earth Environ.3, 1–9 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tuholske, C. et al. Global urban populationexposure to extreme heat. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</italic><bold>118</bold>, e2024792118 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.2024792118"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8521713"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34607944"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lin, Y., Jim, C. Y., Deng, J. &amp; Wang, Z. Urbanization effect on spatiotemporal thermal patterns and changes in Hangzhou (China). <italic>Build. Environ.</italic><bold>145</bold>, 166–176 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lin, Y., Jim, C. Y., Deng, J. &amp; Wang, Z. Urbanization effect on spatiotemporal thermal patterns and changes in Hangzhou (China). Build. Environ.145, 166–176 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang, H. et al. Analysis of land use/land cover change, population shift, and their effects on spatiotemporal patterns of urban heat islands in metropolitan Shanghai, China. <italic>Appl. Geogr.</italic><bold>44</bold>, 121–133 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhang, H. et al. Analysis of land use/land cover change, population shift, and their effects on spatiotemporal patterns of urban heat islands in metropolitan Shanghai, China. Appl. Geogr.44, 121–133 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Grigoraș, G. &amp; Urițescu, B. Land Use/Land Cover changes dynamics and their effects on Surface Urban Heat Island in Bucharest, Romania. <italic>Int. J. Appl. Earth Obs. Geoinf.</italic><bold>80</bold>, 115–126 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Grigoraș, G. &amp; Urițescu, B. Land Use/Land Cover changes dynamics and their effects on Surface Urban Heat Island in Bucharest, Romania. Int. J. Appl. Earth Obs. Geoinf.80, 115–126 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tewari, M., Salamanca, F., Martilli, A., Treinish, L. &amp; Mahalov, A. Impacts of projected urban expansion and global warming on cooling energy demand over a semiarid region. <italic>Atmos. Sci. Lett.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 419–426 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tewari, M., Salamanca, F., Martilli, A., Treinish, L. &amp; Mahalov, A. Impacts of projected urban expansion and global warming on cooling energy demand over a semiarid region. Atmos. Sci. Lett.18, 419–426 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhou, Y. et al. Satellite mapping of urban built-up heights reveals extreme infrastructure gaps and inequalities in the Global South. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</italic><bold>119</bold>, e2214813119 (2022).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.2214813119"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9674218"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36343227"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhou, Y. et al. Satellite mapping of urban built-up heights reveals extreme infrastructure gaps and inequalities in the Global South. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.119, e2214813119 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sun, Y. et al. Urban Morphological Parameters of the Main Cities in China and Their Application in the WRF Model. <italic>J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.</italic><bold>13</bold>, e2020MS002382 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sun, Y. et al. Urban Morphological Parameters of the Main Cities in China and Their Application in the WRF Model. J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.13, e2020MS002382 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Broadbent, A. M., Krayenhoff, E. S. &amp; Georgescu, M. The motley drivers of heat and cold exposure in 21st century US cities. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</italic><bold>117</bold>, 21108–21117 (2020).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.2005492117"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7474622"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32817528"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Broadbent, A. M., Krayenhoff, E. S. &amp; Georgescu, M. The motley drivers of heat and cold exposure in 21st century US cities. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.117, 21108–21117 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Khan, A. &amp; Santamouris, M. On the local warming potential of urban rooftop photovoltaic solar panels in cities. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 1–19 (2023).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-023-40280-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10511547"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37730834"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Khan, A. &amp; Santamouris, M. On the local warming potential of urban rooftop photovoltaic solar panels in cities. Sci. Rep.13, 1–19 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, Y. et al. Green spaces provide substantial but unequal urban cooling globally. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1–13 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-024-51355-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11369290"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39223143"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, Y. et al. Green spaces provide substantial but unequal urban cooling globally. Nat. Commun.15, 1–13 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Jay, O. et al. Reducing the health effects of hot weather and heat extremes: from personal cooling strategies to green cities. <italic>Lancet</italic><bold>398</bold>, 709–724 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S0140-6736(21)01209-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34419206"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Jay, O. et al. Reducing the health effects of hot weather and heat extremes: from personal cooling strategies to green cities. Lancet398, 709–724 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Romanello, M. et al. The 2022 report of the Lancet Countdown on health and climate change: health at the mercy of fossil fuels. <italic>Lancet</italic><bold>400</bold>, 1619–1654 (2022).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S0140-6736(22)01540-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7616806"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36306815"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Romanello, M. et al. The 2022 report of the Lancet Countdown on health and climate change: health at the mercy of fossil fuels. Lancet400, 1619–1654 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">World Bank Official Boundaries - World Bank Data Catalog. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://datacatalog.worldbank.org/search/dataset/0038272/world-bank-official-boundaries" ext-link-type="uri">https://datacatalog.worldbank.org/search/dataset/0038272/world-bank-official-boundaries</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Scoccimarro, E. et al. Country-level energy demand for cooling has increased over the past two decades. <italic>Commun. Earth Environ.</italic><bold>4</bold>, 1–17 (2023).37325084
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Scoccimarro, E. et al. Country-level energy demand for cooling has increased over the past two decades. Commun. Earth Environ.4, 1–17 (2023).37325084"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">MoEFCC. India Cooling Action Plan (ICAP). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.iea.org/policies/7455-india-cooling-action-plan-icap" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.iea.org/policies/7455-india-cooling-action-plan-icap</ext-link> (2019).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sherman, P., Lin, H. &amp; McElroy, M. Projected global demand for air conditioning associated with extreme heat and implications for electricity grids in poorer countries. <italic>Energy Build</italic><bold>268</bold>, 112198 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sherman, P., Lin, H. &amp; McElroy, M. Projected global demand for air conditioning associated with extreme heat and implications for electricity grids in poorer countries. Energy Build268, 112198 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Staffell, I., Pfenninger, S. &amp; Johnson, N. A global model of hourly space heating and cooling demand at multiple spatial scales. <italic>Nat. Energy</italic><bold>8</bold>, 1328–1344 (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Welch, R. Monitoring urban population and energy utilization patterns from satellite Data. <italic>Remote Sens. Environ.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 1–9 (1980).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Welch, R. Monitoring urban population and energy utilization patterns from satellite Data. Remote Sens. Environ.9, 1–9 (1980)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tumminia, G. et al. A New Approach to Model the Effect of Climate Change on the Building Sector: a Climate Models Data Fusion. 10.26868/25222708.2019.210243.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mohan, R. &amp; Pachauri, N. An ensemble model for the energy consumption prediction of residential buildings. <italic>Energy</italic><bold>314</bold>, 134255 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mohan, R. &amp; Pachauri, N. An ensemble model for the energy consumption prediction of residential buildings. Energy314, 134255 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Teng, Y. et al. Dynamic correlation analysis of sectoral electricity consumption and urban carbon concentration using machine learning models. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1–14 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-025-94201-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11929772"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40121275"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Teng, Y. et al. Dynamic correlation analysis of sectoral electricity consumption and urban carbon concentration using machine learning models. Sci. Rep.15, 1–14 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rahman, M. M. Do population density, economic growth, energy use and exports adversely affect environmental quality in Asian populous countries? <italic>Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.</italic><bold>77</bold>, 506–514 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rahman, M. M. Do population density, economic growth, energy use and exports adversely affect environmental quality in Asian populous countries? Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.77, 506–514 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Haberl, H. et al. Built structures influence patterns of energy demand and CO2 emissions across countries. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 1–10 (2023).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-023-39728-3"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10317978"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37400457"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Haberl, H. et al. Built structures influence patterns of energy demand and CO2 emissions across countries. Nat. Commun.14, 1–10 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Krayenhoff, E. S., Moustaoui, M., Broadbent, A. M., Gupta, V. &amp; Georgescu, M. Diurnal interaction between urban expansion, climate change and adaptation in US cities. <italic>Nat. Clim. Chang.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 1097–1103 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Krayenhoff, E. S., Moustaoui, M., Broadbent, A. M., Gupta, V. &amp; Georgescu, M. Diurnal interaction between urban expansion, climate change and adaptation in US cities. Nat. Clim. Chang.8, 1097–1103 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string"> BEE. ECBC. vol. 6 51–66 <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://repositorio.unan.edu.ni/2986/1/5624.pdf%0A" ext-link-type="uri">http://repositorio.unan.edu.ni/2986/1/5624.pdf%0A</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://fiskal.kemenkeu.go.id/ejournal%0A" ext-link-type="uri">http://fiskal.kemenkeu.go.id/ejournal%0A</ext-link>, 10.1016/j.cirp.2016.06.001%0A, 10.1016/j.powtec.2016.12.055%0A, 10.1016/j.ijfatigue.2019.02.006%0A (2017).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu, X. et al. Global Mapping of Three-Dimensional (3D) Urban Structures Reveals Escalating Utilization in the Vertical Dimension and Pronounced Building Space Inequality. <italic>Engineering</italic>10.1016/J.ENG.2024.01.025 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liu, X. et al. Global Mapping of Three-Dimensional (3D) Urban Structures Reveals Escalating Utilization in the Vertical Dimension and Pronounced Building Space Inequality. Engineering10.1016/J.ENG.2024.01.025 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ghanbari, M., Arabi, M., Georgescu, M. &amp; Broadbent, A. M. The role of climate change and urban development on compound dry-hot extremes across US cities. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 3509 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-023-39205-x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10267174"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37316472"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, C. et al. Impacts of climate change, population growth, and power sector decarbonization on urban building energy use. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 6434 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-023-41458-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10584859"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37852971"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Deroubaix, A. et al. Large uncertainties in trends of energy demand for heating and cooling under climate change. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1–8 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-021-25504-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8408235"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34465790"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Deroubaix, A. et al. Large uncertainties in trends of energy demand for heating and cooling under climate change. Nat. Commun.12, 1–8 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ukey, R. &amp; Rai, A. C. Impact of global warming on heating and cooling degree days in major Indian cities. <italic>Energy Build</italic><bold>244</bold>, 111050 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ukey, R. &amp; Rai, A. C. Impact of global warming on heating and cooling degree days in major Indian cities. Energy Build244, 111050 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Government of India. THE ALL INDIA SERVICES (HOUSE RENT ALLOWANCE) RULES, 1977. D P &amp; AR Notification No. 20019/1/75-AIS(II) dated 4.1.1977 <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://dopt.gov.in/sites/default/files/Revised_AIS_Rule_Vol_I_Rule_22.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://dopt.gov.in/sites/default/files/Revised_AIS_Rule_Vol_I_Rule_22.pdf</ext-link> (1977).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string"><italic>Recommendations of the Sixth Central Pay Commission – Decision of Government relating to grant of Dearness Allowance to Central Government servants</italic>. (Ministry of Finance Department of Expenditure).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Government of India, M. of F. HRA and Cities Classification as per Census 2001. 2(21)/E.II(B)/2004 <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doe.gov.in/files/circulars_document/18_11_2004.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://doe.gov.in/files/circulars_document/18_11_2004.pdf</ext-link> (2004).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bhatia, S. Y., Patil, G. R. &amp; Buddhiraju, K. M. Spatiotemporal Land Use Patterns of an Unplanned Metropolitan Region: An Urban Density Based Approach. <italic>Appl. Spat. Anal. Policy</italic><bold>17</bold>, 1569–1604 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bhatia, S. Y., Patil, G. R. &amp; Buddhiraju, K. M. Spatiotemporal Land Use Patterns of an Unplanned Metropolitan Region: An Urban Density Based Approach. Appl. Spat. Anal. Policy17, 1569–1604 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bharath, H. A., Chandan, M. C., Vinay, S. &amp; Ramachandra, T. V. Modelling urban dynamics in rapidly urbanising Indian cities. <italic>Egypt. J. Remote Sens. Sp. Sci.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 201–210 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bharath, H. A., Chandan, M. C., Vinay, S. &amp; Ramachandra, T. V. Modelling urban dynamics in rapidly urbanising Indian cities. Egypt. J. Remote Sens. Sp. Sci.21, 201–210 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">IDFC Institute. India Infrastructure Report 2018: Making Housing Affordable. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://artha.global/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/idfc_institute_housing_report-1.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://artha.global/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/idfc_institute_housing_report-1.pdf</ext-link> (2018).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pavanello, F. et al. <italic>Air-conditioning Adapt. cooling deficit Emerg. economies</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1–11 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-021-26592-2"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8578436"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34753905"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pavanello, F. et al. Air-conditioning Adapt. cooling deficit Emerg. economies12, 1–11 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Colelli, F. P., Wing, I. S. &amp; De Cian, E. Air-conditioning adoption and electricity demand highlight climate change mitigation–adaptation tradeoffs. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 1–12 (2023).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-023-31469-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10023814"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36932168"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Colelli, F. P., Wing, I. S. &amp; De Cian, E. Air-conditioning adoption and electricity demand highlight climate change mitigation–adaptation tradeoffs. Sci. Rep.13, 1–12 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Duan, S., Luo, Z., Yang, X. &amp; Li, Y. The impact of building operations on urban heat/cool islands under urban densification: A comparison between naturally-ventilated and air-conditioned buildings. <italic>Appl. Energy</italic><bold>235</bold>, 129–138 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Duan, S., Luo, Z., Yang, X. &amp; Li, Y. The impact of building operations on urban heat/cool islands under urban densification: A comparison between naturally-ventilated and air-conditioned buildings. Appl. Energy235, 129–138 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shen, P., Zhao, S., Ma, Y. &amp; Liu, S. Urbanization-induced Earth’s surface energy alteration and warming: A global spatiotemporal analysis. <italic>Remote Sens. Environ.</italic><bold>284</bold>, 113361 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shen, P., Zhao, S., Ma, Y. &amp; Liu, S. Urbanization-induced Earth’s surface energy alteration and warming: A global spatiotemporal analysis. Remote Sens. Environ.284, 113361 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sethi, S. S. &amp; Vinoj, V. Urbanization and regional climate change-linked warming of Indian cities. <italic>Nat. Cities</italic><bold>1</bold>, 402–405 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sethi, S. S. &amp; Vinoj, V. Urbanization and regional climate change-linked warming of Indian cities. Nat. Cities1, 402–405 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Santamouris, M. The Impact and Influence of Mitigation Technologies on Heat-Related Mortality in Overheated Cities. 155–169 (2022) 10.1007/978-981-19-4707-0_7.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kearsley, G. W. Teaching Urban Geography: The Burgess Model. <italic>N. Z. J. Geogr.</italic><bold>75</bold>, 10–13 (1983).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hoyt, H. Recent Distortions of the Classical Models of Urban Structure. <italic>Land Econ.</italic><bold>40</bold>, 199 (1964).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hoyt, H. Recent Distortions of the Classical Models of Urban Structure. Land Econ.40, 199 (1964)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Xu, Z. et al. Global consistency of urban scaling evidenced by remote sensing. (2025) 10.1093/pnasnexus/pgaf037.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/pnasnexus/pgaf037"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11823829"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39949656"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, X. et al. Mapping global urban boundaries from the global artificial impervious area (GAIA) data. <italic>Environ. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 094044 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, X. et al. Mapping global urban boundaries from the global artificial impervious area (GAIA) data. Environ. Res. Lett.15, 094044 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gong, P. et al. Annual maps of global artificial impervious area (GAIA) between 1985 and 2018. <italic>Remote Sens. Environ.</italic><bold>236</bold>, 111510 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gong, P. et al. Annual maps of global artificial impervious area (GAIA) between 1985 and 2018. Remote Sens. Environ.236, 111510 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chakraborty, T. C. et al. Large disagreements in estimates of urban land across scales and their implications. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1–15 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-024-52241-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11502887"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39448573"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chakraborty, T. C. et al. Large disagreements in estimates of urban land across scales and their implications. Nat. Commun.15, 1–15 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhou, B., Rybski, D. &amp; Kropp, J. P. The role of city size and urban form in the surface urban heat island. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 1–9 (2017).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-017-04242-2"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5500494"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28684850"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhou, B., Rybski, D. &amp; Kropp, J. P. The role of city size and urban form in the surface urban heat island. Sci. Rep.7, 1–9 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Schiavina, M. et al. GHSL Data Package 2023. Publications Office of the European Union, Luxembourg 10.2760/098587 (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pesaresi, M. et al. Advances on the Global Human Settlement Layer by joint assessment of Earth Observation and population survey data. <italic>Int. J. Digit. Earth</italic><bold>17</bold>, 2390454 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pesaresi, M. et al. Advances on the Global Human Settlement Layer by joint assessment of Earth Observation and population survey data. Int. J. Digit. Earth17, 2390454 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chen, Y. Derivation of the functional relations between fractal dimension of and shape indices of urban form. <italic>Comput. Environ. Urban Syst.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 442–451 (2011).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chen, Y. Derivation of the functional relations between fractal dimension of and shape indices of urban form. Comput. Environ. Urban Syst.35, 442–451 (2011)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chen, Y. Normalizing and classifying shape indexes of cities by ideas from fractals. <italic>Chaos, Solitons Fractals</italic><bold>154</bold>, 111653 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chen, Y. Normalizing and classifying shape indexes of cities by ideas from fractals. Chaos, Solitons Fractals154, 111653 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bettencourt, L. M. A., Lobo, J., Helbing, D., Kühnert, C. &amp; West, G. B. Growth, innovation, scaling, and the pace of life in cities. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</italic><bold>104</bold>, 7301–7306 (2007).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.0610172104"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC1852329"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17438298"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bettencourt, L. M. A., Lobo, J., Helbing, D., Kühnert, C. &amp; West, G. B. Growth, innovation, scaling, and the pace of life in cities. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.104, 7301–7306 (2007)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Xian, G. et al. The effects of urban land cover dynamics on urban heat Island intensity and temporal trends. <italic>GIScience Remote Sens.</italic><bold>58</bold>, 501–515 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Xian, G. et al. The effects of urban land cover dynamics on urban heat Island intensity and temporal trends. GIScience Remote Sens.58, 501–515 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yang, M. et al. Mitigating urban heat island through neighboring rural land cover. <italic>Nat. Cities</italic><bold>1</bold>, 522–532 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yang, M. et al. Mitigating urban heat island through neighboring rural land cover. Nat. Cities1, 522–532 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhan, W. et al. Urban-Rural Gradient in Urban Heat Island Variations Responsive to Large-Scale Human Activity Changes During Chinese New Year Holiday. <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>49</bold>, e2022GL100689 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhan, W. et al. Urban-Rural Gradient in Urban Heat Island Variations Responsive to Large-Scale Human Activity Changes During Chinese New Year Holiday. Geophys. Res. Lett.49, e2022GL100689 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sirko, W. et al. Continental-Scale Building Detection from High Resolution Satellite Imagery. (2021).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Open Buildings V3 Polygons | Earth Engine Data Catalog | Google for Developers. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/GOOGLE_Research_open-buildings_v3_polygons" ext-link-type="uri">https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/GOOGLE_Research_open-buildings_v3_polygons</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR79"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Adams, D. S. et al. LandScan mosaic enables high-resolution gridded population estimates with explicit uncertainty. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 44493 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-025-28125-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12738844"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="41444299"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Adams, D. S. et al. LandScan mosaic enables high-resolution gridded population estimates with explicit uncertainty. Sci. Rep.15, 44493 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lebakula, V. et al. LandScan Global 30 Arcsecond Annual Global Gridded Population Datasets from 2000 to 2022. <italic>Sci. Data</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1–16 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41597-025-04817-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11933676"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40128284"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lebakula, V. et al. LandScan Global 30 Arcsecond Annual Global Gridded Population Datasets from 2000 to 2022. Sci. Data12, 1–16 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dobson, J. E., Bright, E. A., Coleman, P. R., Durfee, R. C. &amp; Worley, B. A. LandScan: a global population database for estimating populations at risk. <italic>Photogramm. Eng. Remote Sens.</italic><bold>66</bold>, 849–857 (2000).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Global Human Settlement - GHSL Homepage - European Commission. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/index.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/index.php</ext-link> (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR83"><named-content content-type="citation-string">McLoughlin, B. Urban consolidation and urban sprawl: A question of density. <italic>Urban Policy Res</italic>. <bold>9</bold>, 148–156 (1991).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="McLoughlin, B. Urban consolidation and urban sprawl: A question of density. Urban Policy Res. 9, 148–156 (1991)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR84"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Frick, S. A. &amp; Rodríguez-Pose, A. Change in urban concentration and economic growth. <italic>World Dev.</italic><bold>105</bold>, 156–170 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Frick, S. A. &amp; Rodríguez-Pose, A. Change in urban concentration and economic growth. World Dev.105, 156–170 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR85"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Varquez, A. C. G., Kiyomoto, S., Khanh, D. N. &amp; Kanda, M. Global 1-km present and future hourly anthropogenic heat flux. <italic>Sci. Data</italic><bold>8</bold>, 1–14 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41597-021-00850-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7900113"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33619279"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Varquez, A. C. G., Kiyomoto, S., Khanh, D. N. &amp; Kanda, M. Global 1-km present and future hourly anthropogenic heat flux. Sci. Data8, 1–14 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR86"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Davis, L. W. &amp; Gertler, P. J. Contribution of air conditioning adoption to future energy use under global warming. <italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</italic><bold>112</bold>, 5962–5967 (2015).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1423558112"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4434761"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25918391"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Davis, L. W. &amp; Gertler, P. J. Contribution of air conditioning adoption to future energy use under global warming. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.112, 5962–5967 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR87"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sivak, M. Potential energy demand for cooling in the 50 largest metropolitan areas of the world: Implications for developing countries. <italic>Energy Policy</italic><bold>37</bold>, 1382–1384 (2009).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sivak, M. Potential energy demand for cooling in the 50 largest metropolitan areas of the world: Implications for developing countries. Energy Policy37, 1382–1384 (2009)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR88"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Stern, D. I. The role of energy in economic growth. <italic>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</italic><bold>1219</bold>, 26–51 (2011).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05921.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21332491"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Stern, D. I. The role of energy in economic growth. Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.1219, 26–51 (2011)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR89"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kundu, D. et al. Spatial Structures and Trends of Cities in Europe and Asia: A Joint Methodological Approach Based on the Global Human Settlement Layer. <italic>Environ. Urban. ASIA</italic><bold>11</bold>, 195–217 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kundu, D. et al. Spatial Structures and Trends of Cities in Europe and Asia: A Joint Methodological Approach Based on the Global Human Settlement Layer. Environ. Urban. ASIA11, 195–217 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kundu, D. et al. India and Europe/Germany. Spatial Structures and Trends. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orlis.difu.de/handle/difu/255739" ext-link-type="uri">https://orlis.difu.de/handle/difu/255739</ext-link> (2019) (accessed 10 June 2026).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR91"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yang, L. et al. Urban development pattern’s influence on extreme rainfall occurrences. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1–9 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-024-48533-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11088619"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38734684"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yang, L. et al. Urban development pattern’s influence on extreme rainfall occurrences. Nat. Commun.15, 1–9 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR92"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wongoutong, C. The impact of neglecting feature scaling in k-means clustering. <italic>PLoS One</italic><bold>19</bold>, e0310839 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0310839"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11623793"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39642177"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wongoutong, C. The impact of neglecting feature scaling in k-means clustering. PLoS One19, e0310839 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR93"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rousseeuw, P. J. Silhouettes: A graphical aid to the interpretation and validation of cluster analysis. <italic>J. Comput. Appl. Math.</italic><bold>20</bold>, 53–65 (1987).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rousseeuw, P. J. Silhouettes: A graphical aid to the interpretation and validation of cluster analysis. J. Comput. Appl. Math.20, 53–65 (1987)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR94"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Davies, D. L. &amp; Bouldin, D. W. A Cluster Separation Measure. <italic>IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell.</italic><bold>PAMI-1</bold>, 224–227 (1979).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21868852"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Davies, D. L. &amp; Bouldin, D. W. A Cluster Separation Measure. IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell.PAMI-1, 224–227 (1979)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Orders &amp; Circulars | DEPARTMENT OF Expenditure. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doe.gov.in/orders-circulars/32" ext-link-type="uri">https://doe.gov.in/orders-circulars/32</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR96"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chaudhuri, G. &amp; Shrobona, K. arkun-S. en Defining Urban India: Finding Order in Chaos. <italic>Curr. Landsc. Ecol. Rep.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 171–180 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chaudhuri, G. &amp; Shrobona, K. arkun-S. en Defining Urban India: Finding Order in Chaos. Curr. Landsc. Ecol. Rep.8, 171–180 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR97"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shukla, A., Jain, K., Ramsankaran, R. A. A. J. &amp; Rajasekaran, E. Understanding the macro-micro dynamics of urban densification: A case study of different sized Indian cities. <italic>Land use policy</italic><bold>107</bold>, 105469 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shukla, A., Jain, K., Ramsankaran, R. A. A. J. &amp; Rajasekaran, E. Understanding the macro-micro dynamics of urban densification: A case study of different sized Indian cities. Land use policy107, 105469 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">. Globalization and World Cities Research Network | UIA Yearbook Profile | Union of International Associations. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://uia.org/s/or/en/1100054103" ext-link-type="uri">https://uia.org/s/or/en/1100054103</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR99"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tian, L. et al. Analyzing world city network by graph convolutional networks. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 18933 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-024-69494-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11327301"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39147920"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tian, L. et al. Analyzing world city network by graph convolutional networks. Sci. Rep.14, 18933 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR100"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Das, S. P. City connectivity via global intra-firm linkages: An analysis of Indian cities. <italic>J. Int. Dev.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 312–330 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Das, S. P. City connectivity via global intra-firm linkages: An analysis of Indian cities. J. Int. Dev.35, 312–330 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Carta, S. &amp; Gonzalez, M. Mapping Connectedness of Global Cities: α, β and γ tiers. (2013).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR102"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Uhl, J. H., Connor, D. S., Leyk, S. &amp; Braswell, A. E. A century of decoupling size and structure of urban spaces in the United States. <italic>Commun. Earth Environ.</italic><bold>2</bold>, 1–14 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s43247-020-00082-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8716013"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34970647"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Uhl, J. H., Connor, D. S., Leyk, S. &amp; Braswell, A. E. A century of decoupling size and structure of urban spaces in the United States. Commun. Earth Environ.2, 1–14 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mondal, N., Deb, C., Anand, P. &amp; Mahdavi, A. Urban cooling demand benchmarking based on built-urbanization. 375–387 (2024) 10.1145/3671127.3699678.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR104"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Frayssinet, L. et al. Modeling the heating and cooling energy demand of urban buildings at city scale. <italic>Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.</italic><bold>81</bold>, 2318–2327 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Frayssinet, L. et al. Modeling the heating and cooling energy demand of urban buildings at city scale. Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.81, 2318–2327 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR105"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Xiong, J. et al. Predicting the response of heating and cooling demands of residential buildings with various thermal performances in China to climate change. <italic>Energy</italic><bold>269</bold>, 126789 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Xiong, J. et al. Predicting the response of heating and cooling demands of residential buildings with various thermal performances in China to climate change. Energy269, 126789 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR106"><label>106.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR106"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yang, X., shen, C., Ullah, I., Curio, J. &amp; Chen, D. Evaluating heat stress and occupational risks in the Southern Himalayas under current and future climates. <italic>npj Clim. Atmos. Sci. 2024 71</italic><bold>7</bold>, 1–12 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yang, X., shen, C., Ullah, I., Curio, J. &amp; Chen, D. Evaluating heat stress and occupational risks in the Southern Himalayas under current and future climates. npj Clim. Atmos. Sci. 2024 717, 1–12 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR107"><label>107.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR107"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dash, S. K. &amp; Mamgain, A. Changes in the Frequency of Different Categories of Temperature Extremes in India. <italic>J. Appl. Meteorol. Climatol.</italic><bold>50</bold>, 1842–1858 (2011).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Dash, S. K. &amp; Mamgain, A. Changes in the Frequency of Different Categories of Temperature Extremes in India. J. Appl. Meteorol. Climatol.50, 1842–1858 (2011)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR108"><label>108.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR108"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kumar, R. &amp; Kuttippurath, J. Long-term changes in tropospheric temperature in India: Insights from radiosonde measurements, reanalysis data and CMIP6 model projections. <italic>Atmos. Res.</italic><bold>309</bold>, 107583 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kumar, R. &amp; Kuttippurath, J. Long-term changes in tropospheric temperature in India: Insights from radiosonde measurements, reanalysis data and CMIP6 model projections. Atmos. Res.309, 107583 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR109"><label>109.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Principles of Heating, Ventilating, and Air Conditioning. ASHRAE <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ashrae.org/technical-resources/bookstore/principles-of-heating-ventilating-and-air-conditioning" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ashrae.org/technical-resources/bookstore/principles-of-heating-ventilating-and-air-conditioning</ext-link> (2009).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR110"><label>110.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR110"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yalew, S. G. et al. Impacts of climate change on energy systems in global and regional scenarios. <italic>Nat. Energy</italic><bold>5</bold>, 794–802 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yalew, S. G. et al. Impacts of climate change on energy systems in global and regional scenarios. Nat. Energy5, 794–802 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR111"><label>111.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR111"><named-content content-type="citation-string">van Ruijven, B. J., De Cian, E. &amp; Sue Wing, I. Amplification of future energy demand growth due to climate change. <italic>Nat. Commun. 2019 101</italic><bold>10</bold>, 1–12 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-019-10399-3"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6591298"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31235700"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="van Ruijven, B. J., De Cian, E. &amp; Sue Wing, I. Amplification of future energy demand growth due to climate change. Nat. Commun. 2019 10110, 1–12 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR112"><label>112.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lanzante, J. R. A New Heat Stress Index For Climate Change Assessment. <italic>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc</italic>. <bold>1</bold>, (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR113"><label>113.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR113"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Buck, A. L. New Equations for Computing Vapor Pressure and Enhancement Factor on JSTOR. <italic>J. Appl. Meteorol.</italic><bold>20</bold>, 1527–1532 (1981).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Buck, A. L. New Equations for Computing Vapor Pressure and Enhancement Factor on JSTOR. J. Appl. Meteorol.20, 1527–1532 (1981)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR114"><label>114.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">The Assessment of Sultriness. Part I: A Temperature-Humidity Index Based on Human Physiology and Clothing Science in: Journal of Applied Meteorology and Climatology Volume 18 Issue 7 (1979). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/apme/18/7/1520-0450_1979_018_0861_taospi_2_0_co_2.xml?tab_body=pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/apme/18/7/1520-0450_1979_018_0861_taospi_2_0_co_2.xml?tab_body=pdf</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR115"><label>115.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR115"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lu, Y. C. &amp; Romps, D. M. Extending the Heat Index. <italic>J. Appl. Meteorol. Climatol.</italic><bold>61</bold>, 1367–1383 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lu, Y. C. &amp; Romps, D. M. Extending the Heat Index. J. Appl. Meteorol. Climatol.61, 1367–1383 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR116"><label>116.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR116"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Spinoni, J. et al. Changes of heating and cooling degree-days in Europe from 1981 to 2100. <italic>Int. J. Climatol.</italic><bold>38</bold>, e191–e208 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Spinoni, J. et al. Changes of heating and cooling degree-days in Europe from 1981 to 2100. Int. J. Climatol.38, e191–e208 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR117"><label>117.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR117"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shin, M. &amp; Do, S. L. Prediction of cooling energy use in buildings using an enthalpy-based cooling degree days method in a hot and humid climate. <italic>Energy Build</italic><bold>110</bold>, 57–70 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shin, M. &amp; Do, S. L. Prediction of cooling energy use in buildings using an enthalpy-based cooling degree days method in a hot and humid climate. Energy Build110, 57–70 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR118"><label>118.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">ANSI/ASHRAE Standard 169−2013 Climatic Data for Building Design Standards. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://shop.iccsafe.org/ansi-ashrae-standard-169-2013-climatic-data-for-building-design-standards.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://shop.iccsafe.org/ansi-ashrae-standard-169-2013-climatic-data-for-building-design-standards.html</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR119"><label>119.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR119"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Walsh, A., Cóstola, D. &amp; Labaki, L. C. Validation of the climatic zoning defined by ASHRAE standard 169-2013. <italic>Energy Policy</italic><bold>135</bold>, 111016 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Walsh, A., Cóstola, D. &amp; Labaki, L. C. Validation of the climatic zoning defined by ASHRAE standard 169-2013. Energy Policy135, 111016 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR120"><label>120.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR120"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hao, Z., Zhang, X., Xie, J., Yin, K. &amp; Liu, J. Balance point temperature and heating degree-days in different climate conditions for building energy efficiency applications. <italic>Build. Environ.</italic><bold>216</bold>, 109013 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hao, Z., Zhang, X., Xie, J., Yin, K. &amp; Liu, J. Balance point temperature and heating degree-days in different climate conditions for building energy efficiency applications. Build. Environ.216, 109013 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR121"><label>121.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR121"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bhatnagar, M., Mathur, J. &amp; Garg, V. Determining base temperature for heating and cooling degree-days for India. <italic>J. Build. Eng.</italic><bold>18</bold>, 270–280 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bhatnagar, M., Mathur, J. &amp; Garg, V. Determining base temperature for heating and cooling degree-days for India. J. Build. Eng.18, 270–280 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR122"><label>122.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR122"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kennard, H., Oreszczyn, T., Mistry, M. &amp; Hamilton, I. Population-weighted degree-days: The global shift between heating and cooling. <italic>Energy Build</italic><bold>271</bold>, 112315 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.enbuild.2022.112315"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10502910"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37719455"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kennard, H., Oreszczyn, T., Mistry, M. &amp; Hamilton, I. Population-weighted degree-days: The global shift between heating and cooling. Energy Build271, 112315 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR123"><label>123.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR123"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Santamouris, M. Cooling the buildings – past, present and future. <italic>Energy Build</italic><bold>128</bold>, 617–638 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Santamouris, M. Cooling the buildings – past, present and future. Energy Build128, 617–638 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR124"><label>124.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR124"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Isaac, M. &amp; van Vuuren, D. P. Modeling global residential sector energy demand for heating and air conditioning in the context of climate change. <italic>Energy Policy</italic><bold>37</bold>, 507–521 (2009).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Isaac, M. &amp; van Vuuren, D. P. Modeling global residential sector energy demand for heating and air conditioning in the context of climate change. Energy Policy37, 507–521 (2009)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR125"><label>125.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">India Climate &amp; Energy Dashboard. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://iced.niti.gov.in/" ext-link-type="uri">https://iced.niti.gov.in/</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR126"><label>126.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR126"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nogueira, M. et al. Assessment of the Paris urban heat island in ERA5 and offline SURFEX-TEB (v8.1) simulations using the METEOSAT land surface temperature product. <italic>Geosci. Model Dev.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 5949–5965 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nogueira, M. et al. Assessment of the Paris urban heat island in ERA5 and offline SURFEX-TEB (v8.1) simulations using the METEOSAT land surface temperature product. Geosci. Model Dev.15, 5949–5965 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR127"><label>127.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR127"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, C. et al. Urbanization-Induced Increases in Heavy Precipitation are Magnified by Moist Heatwaves in an Urban Agglomeration of East China. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>36</bold>, 693–709 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, C. et al. Urbanization-Induced Increases in Heavy Precipitation are Magnified by Moist Heatwaves in an Urban Agglomeration of East China. J. Clim.36, 693–709 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR128"><label>128.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR128"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yu, X. et al. Asymmetrical Shift Toward Less Light and More Heavy Precipitation in an Urban Agglomeration of East China: Intensification by Urbanization. <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>49</bold>, e2021GL097046 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yu, X. et al. Asymmetrical Shift Toward Less Light and More Heavy Precipitation in an Urban Agglomeration of East China: Intensification by Urbanization. Geophys. Res. Lett.49, e2021GL097046 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR129"><label>129.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR129"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hersbach, H. et al. The ERA5 global reanalysis. <italic>Q. J. R. Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>146</bold>, 1999–2049 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hersbach, H. et al. The ERA5 global reanalysis. Q. J. R. Meteorol. Soc.146, 1999–2049 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR130"><label>130.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR130"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sussman, H. S., Dai, A. &amp; Roundy, P. E. The controlling factors of urban heat in Bengaluru, India. <italic>Urban Clim.</italic><bold>38</bold>, 100881 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sussman, H. S., Dai, A. &amp; Roundy, P. E. The controlling factors of urban heat in Bengaluru, India. Urban Clim.38, 100881 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR131"><label>131.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR131"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Smith, E., Grant, N., Luo, X. &amp; Diaz, D. Evaluating the ability of gridded climate datasets to capture temperature and precipitation trends and extremes. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1–11 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-025-97570-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11993658"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40221507"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Smith, E., Grant, N., Luo, X. &amp; Diaz, D. Evaluating the ability of gridded climate datasets to capture temperature and precipitation trends and extremes. Sci. Rep.15, 1–11 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR132"><label>132.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR132"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gibb, R. et al. Interactions between climate change, urban infrastructure and mobility are driving dengue emergence in Vietnam. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 1–15 (2023).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-023-43954-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10713571"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38081831"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Gibb, R. et al. Interactions between climate change, urban infrastructure and mobility are driving dengue emergence in Vietnam. Nat. Commun.14, 1–15 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR133"><label>133.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR133"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shah, A., Sugathan, A., Malghan, D., Kim, R. &amp; Subramanian, S. V. Spatiotemporal changes in heat stress exposure in India, 1981-2023. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 1–11 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-025-64840-x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12569015"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="41152285"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shah, A., Sugathan, A., Malghan, D., Kim, R. &amp; Subramanian, S. V. Spatiotemporal changes in heat stress exposure in India, 1981-2023. Nat. Commun.16, 1–11 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR134"><label>134.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR134"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhao, Q. et al. Global, regional, and national burden of mortality associated with non-optimal ambient temperatures from 2000 to 2019: a three-stage modelling study. <italic>Lancet Planet. Heal.</italic><bold>5</bold>, e415–e425 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2542-5196(21)00081-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34245712"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhao, Q. et al. Global, regional, and national burden of mortality associated with non-optimal ambient temperatures from 2000 to 2019: a three-stage modelling study. Lancet Planet. Heal.5, e415–e425 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR135"><label>135.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR135"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yan, Y., Xu, Y. &amp; Yue, S. A high-spatial-resolution dataset of human thermal stress indices over South and East Asia. <italic>Sci. Data</italic><bold>8</bold>, 1–14 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41597-021-01010-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8410920"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34471140"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yan, Y., Xu, Y. &amp; Yue, S. A high-spatial-resolution dataset of human thermal stress indices over South and East Asia. Sci. Data8, 1–14 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR136"><label>136.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR136"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Georgescu, M., Broadbent, A. M. &amp; Krayenhoff, E. S. Quantifying the decrease in heat exposure through adaptation and mitigation in twenty-first-century US cities. <italic>Nat. Cities</italic><bold>1</bold>, 42–50 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Georgescu, M., Broadbent, A. M. &amp; Krayenhoff, E. S. Quantifying the decrease in heat exposure through adaptation and mitigation in twenty-first-century US cities. Nat. Cities1, 42–50 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR137"><label>137.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cohen, J., Cohen, P., West, S. G. &amp; Aiken, L. S. Applied Multiple Regression/Correlation Analysis for the Behavioral Sciences, Third Edition. <italic>Appl. Mult. Regression/Correlation Anal. Behav. Sci. Third Ed</italic>. 1–704 (2013) 10.4324/9780203774441/APPLIED-MULTIPLE-REGRESSION-CORRELATION-ANALYSIS-BEHAVIORAL-SCIENCES-JACOB-COHEN-PATRICIA-COHEN-STEPHEN-WEST-LEONA-AIKEN/RIGHTS-AND-PERMISSIONS.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR138"><label>138.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR138"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Camps-Valls, G. et al. Artificial intelligence for modeling and understanding extreme weather and climate events. <italic>Nat. Commun.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 1–14 (2025).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41467-025-56573-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11850610"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39994190"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Camps-Valls, G. et al. Artificial intelligence for modeling and understanding extreme weather and climate events. Nat. Commun.16, 1–14 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR139"><label>139.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR139"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, X. &amp; Yao, R. Modelling heating and cooling energy demand for building stock using a hybrid approach. <italic>Energy Build</italic><bold>235</bold>, 110740 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, X. &amp; Yao, R. Modelling heating and cooling energy demand for building stock using a hybrid approach. Energy Build235, 110740 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR140"><label>140.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR140"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Anand, P. et al. Occupancy-based energy consumption modelling using machine learning algorithms for institutional buildings. <italic>Energy Build</italic><bold>252</bold>, 111478 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Anand, P. et al. Occupancy-based energy consumption modelling using machine learning algorithms for institutional buildings. Energy Build252, 111478 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR141"><label>141.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mondal, N. City-wide Cooling Degree Days Analysis and Plotting. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/records/19346583" ext-link-type="uri">https://zenodo.org/records/19346583</ext-link> 10.5281/ZENODO.19346583.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR142"><label>142.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Survey of India. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/Product_NewSpecification.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/Product_NewSpecification.aspx</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b390/13287610/78ad1e47e909/41467_2026_74157_MOESM1_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 9177358?><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material2_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b390/13287610/47c059d35a7d/41467_2026_74157_MOESM2_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1666357?><caption><p>Reporting Summary</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material3_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41467_2026_74157_MOESM3_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><?cloudpmc-path b390/13287610/8840f0c7fa86/41467_2026_74157_MOESM3_ESM.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1940070?><caption><p>Transparent Peer Review file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The data used in the current study are available in the public domain as listed below: City lateral extent data can be accessed from the MODIS Land Cover Type dataset (MCD12Q1.v061) available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://lpdaac.usgs.gov/products/mcd12q1v061/" ext-link-type="uri">https://lpdaac.usgs.gov/products/mcd12q1v061/</ext-link>. Further, city urban area shapefiles can be accessed from the updated Global Urban Boundary (GUB) dataset portal at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data-starcloud.pcl.ac.cn/iearthdata/map?id=14&amp;r_id=14" ext-link-type="uri">https://data-starcloud.pcl.ac.cn/iearthdata/map?id=14&amp;r_id=14</ext-link> and for Indian cities the urban boundary shapefiles used in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44284-024-00074-0" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nature.com/articles/s44284-024-00074-0</ext-link> is used which can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/SSoumyaS/Shape_Files/tree/main/India_boundary" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/SSoumyaS/Shape_Files/tree/main/India_boundary</ext-link>. For infilling estimation, Google Open Buildings V3 polygons data can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://sites.research.google/gr/open-buildings/" ext-link-type="uri">https://sites.research.google/gr/open-buildings/</ext-link> and can be used alongside GHSL built-up datasets (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_bu.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_bu.php</ext-link>). The GHS Built-Up data can be accessed through the Copernicus GHSL dataset portal, including GHS Urban Centre Database (UCDB) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_ucdb_2024.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_ucdb_2024.php</ext-link>), GHS Built Height (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_buH2023.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_buH2023.php</ext-link>), and GHS Built Volume (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_buV2023.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://human-settlement.emergency.copernicus.eu/ghs_buV2023.php</ext-link>). Anthropogenic emissions datasets can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://urbanclimate.tse.ens.titech.ac.jp/category/dataset/" ext-link-type="uri">https://urbanclimate.tse.ens.titech.ac.jp/category/dataset/</ext-link>. The population dataset for the period 2003–2023 can be sourced from the Oak Ridge National Laboratory LandScan dataset (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://landscan.ornl.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://landscan.ornl.gov/</ext-link>). MODIS datasets (2003–2023) can be accessed through the Google Earth Engine platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/modis" ext-link-type="uri">https://developers.google.com/earth-engine/datasets/catalog/modis</ext-link>) and also directly through NASA Earth data catalogue pages such as <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/data/catalog/lpcloud-myd21c1-061" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/data/catalog/lpcloud-myd21c1-061</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/data/catalog/lpcloud-myd21c2-061" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.earthdata.nasa.gov/data/catalog/lpcloud-myd21c2-061</ext-link>. For CDD calculations, gridded re-analysis meteorological data can be sourced from ERA5-Land available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets" ext-link-type="uri">https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets</ext-link>. State-specific energy demand data for Indian cities can be accessed through the Central Electricity Authority dashboard at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cea.nic.in/dashboard/?lang=en" ext-link-type="uri">https://cea.nic.in/dashboard/?lang=en</ext-link>. For Singapore demand data it can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ema.gov.sg/resources/statistics/load-demand-centre" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ema.gov.sg/resources/statistics/load-demand-centre</ext-link> and for US cities region specific cooling degree days data can be accessed from <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.eia.gov/totalenergy/data/browser/index.php?tbl=T01.12#/?f=A" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.eia.gov/totalenergy/data/browser/index.php?tbl=T01.12#/?f=A</ext-link>. The administrative boundary maps for India and the world can be sourced from the Survey of India geoportal (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/" ext-link-type="uri">https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/</ext-link>),product code: OVSF/1M/7 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/Digital_Product_Show.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://onlinemaps.surveyofindia.gov.in/Digital_Product_Show.aspx</ext-link>) and the World Bank Official Boundaries dataset (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://datacatalog.worldbank.org/search/dataset/0038272/world-bank-official-boundaries" ext-link-type="uri">https://datacatalog.worldbank.org/search/dataset/0038272/world-bank-official-boundaries</ext-link>), respectively.</p><p>The majority of the geo-spatial data collection and preliminary analysis was done using google earth engine platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://code.earthengine.google.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://code.earthengine.google.com/</ext-link>) coupled with python based google Collab platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://colab.research.google.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://colab.research.google.com/</ext-link>). The visualization and further detailed analysis of data were performed using Python, with the Spyder platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.spyder-ide.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.spyder-ide.org/</ext-link>) utilized as the integrated development environment (IDE). Source codes can be accessed from 10.5281/zenodo.19346583<sup><xref rid="CR141" ref-type="bibr">141</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec></body></article>