<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Sci Rep</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12891732</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12891732</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12891732</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41545467</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-026-35482-w</article-id><title-group><article-title>Near future projections of tropical cyclone tracks over the Bay of Bengal using high resolution CMIP6 models</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Adsul</surname><given-names initials="R">Rushikesh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names initials="VK">Vineet Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names initials="A">Anant</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Gnanaseelan</surname><given-names initials="C">C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Climate Variability and Prediction, Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Ministry of Earth Sciences, Pune, 411 008 India </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>5567</fpage><page-range>5567</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2026_Article_35482.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 6dd6/12891732/563b042b3c5f/41598_2026_Article_35482.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 5256353?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="unstructured"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Future changes in tropical cyclone (TC) characteristics play a critical role in shaping the impacts and risks associated with climate change. In this study, we analyzed the near-future projections (2015–2050) by the high-resolution CMIP6-HighResMIP models and assessed the projected changes in the TC track characteristics in the Bay of Bengal. The multi model mean projects a northward shift in TC tracks in the near-future under the SSP5-8.5 scenario. The projected increasing number of north-northeastward TCs tracks and decline in west-northwestward moving TCs are primarily driven by strong background upper-level winds steering (southerly) over the Bay of Bengal without any significant contribution from other processes. These upper-level wind changes are caused by increase in the wave activity along the subtropical westerly jet axis, mainly originating from the western Mediterranean region and propagating downstream across the Indian subcontinent. The findings highlight the poleward shift in the projected TC tracks due to change in large scale wave dynamics in the subtropics. The study emphasizes the need for improved understanding of large-scale atmospheric dynamics influencing TC steering in a changing climate. Considering the nature of projected TC tracks, present study speculates its adverse impacts on the Bay of Bengal rim countries and advocates for future disaster preparedness associated with the TCs. The study further highlights the urgent need of more number of high-resolution models and their projections for accurate future projections of TC.</p><sec id="sec1" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-026-35482-w.</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group1" xml:lang="en" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Tropical cyclone track, Bay of Bengal, CMIP6-HighResMIP near-future projection</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group2" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Climate sciences, Natural hazards</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2025 Apr 21; Accepted 2026 Jan 6; Collection date 2026.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Tropical cyclones (TCs) are the most destructive weather systems which often lead to devastating loss of life and property in the coastal regions. TC induced socio-economic damages upon their landfall are primarily driven by TC-induced strong winds, heavy rain, and massive storm surges<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. TC genesis location and their tracks are the key factors in influencing the TC landfall densities. Given the significant threat that TCs pose to human society, understanding their response to anthropogenic climate change is critical for improving future planning and preparedness in high-risk regions.</p><p id="Par3">High-resolution climate models are increasingly being employed globally to simulate future projections of TC characteristics with greater accuracy<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. These climate models, despite having certain sensitivities related to model physics and the design of the dynamical core, demonstrate a substantial ability to accurately represent various aspects of observed TC climatology. Not only these models effectively capture geographical distributions of TCs, but also simulate the seasonal patterns, and inter-annual variations of TCs well<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–<xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>. Notably significant improvements have been observed in the simulation of various TC characteristics in the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 6 (CMIP6) compared to the previous version (CMIP5) models. CMIP5 models often have coarser grid spacing ranging from 100 to 400 km, resulting in underestimation of TC frequency, misrepresentation of intensity of TCs (category 4 and 5 TCs) and bias in the TC tracks<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. The CMIP6 models with grid spacing finer than 100 km have more realistic simulations of TC frequency and their spatial distribution<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. The CMIP6 models ability to simulate high intensity TCs is mainly attributed to their finer resolution<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. As the model resolution increases, the need for convective parameterization diminishes, allowing for a more accurate representation of fine scale processes of TCs<sup><xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">With the advancement in climate models, a significant progress has been achieved in understanding the future changes in TC activity<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. The global TC frequency is projected to decrease with the global warming<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. The potential reasoning behind the projected changes in TC genesis frequency is linked with the changes in the surface enthalpy fluxes, increase in static stability of the atmospheric column and increase in mid-tropospheric saturation deficit<sup><xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. Previous studies have shown that with the global warming, changes in deep convection and increased wind shear would cause more unfavourable environment for the global TC formation<sup><xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>. Though the climate models are projecting a decrease in TC frequency, there are large variations in the projected TC tracks in different ocean basins<sup><xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The north Indian Ocean (including the Arabian Sea and the Bay of Bengal) accounts for 6% of the global TC frequency<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. Out of these nearly 2/3rd of the TCs forms in the Bay of Bengal<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. Annually, the Bay of Bengal has two TC seasons i.e., the pre-monsoon season which is from April–early June and the post–monsoon season which is from October–December<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. Though the frequency of TC in this basin is significantly less as compared to other ocean basins, there were several devastating TCs in the past<sup><xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. Most of the previous studies on TC future projection in Bay of Bengal focussed only on the changes in the TC frequency in a global warming scenario<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>–<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. Under global warming scenario, previous studies using the atmospheric general circulation model and CMIP5 projects a decrease in TC frequency in the Bay of Bengal and an increase in the Arabian Sea<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. This projected decrease in TC frequency is associated with the projected decrease in the vertical updraft<sup><xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> and projected decrease in the low-level relative vorticity in the basin<sup><xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. However, comprehensive understanding on how the TC tracks and their landfall locations are going to change in a global warming scenario is lacking. Given the societal implications, it is essential to investigate the impact of climate change on TC track changes. Therefore, this study aims to analyze near-future projections of TC tracks in the Bay of Bengal using high-resolution CMIP6 (HighResMIP) models.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Evaluation of HighResMIP models performance at simulating TC track density</title><p id="Par6">We initially carried out an assessment of the available HighResMIP models historical simulations in their ability to realistically capture the TC tracks in the north Indian Ocean during the post-monsoon season (October–December). For a comparison of model simulated TC tracks with the observed TC track we have carried out the analysis for the period 1979–2014. The observed cumulative TC track density in north Indian Ocean during the post-monsoon season is widespread with highest TC density concentrated near the east coast of India (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). From the analysis, we see that the TC track density in the Bay of Bengal is significantly higher than the Arabian Sea (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Since the TC track density is directly a function of TC frequency, our results are in line with previous studies which highlight that during the post-monsoon season, higher frequency of TCs is observed in the Bay of Bengal compared to the Arabian Sea<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>.</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Spatial distribution of TC cumulative track density (color) and standard deviation of TC track density (contour) for the post-monsoon season (October–December) in (<bold>a</bold>) observation (1979–2014) and (<bold>b–p</bold>) CMIP6 HighResMIP historical simulations (1979–2014). The figure is created using Python (Version: 3.10.9) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/</ext-link>.–</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e346" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/09e0b42dc4da/41598_2026_35482_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1099?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 366?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/f20394581ae9/41598_2026_35482_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par8">In order to identify the HighResMIP model skills for simulating the TCs in this basin, we have analyzed the spatial pattern of cumulative TC track density as simulated by different models (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b-p). From the spatial analysis of the TC track cumulative density, it is seen that MPI-ESM1-2-HR, ECMWF-IFS-MR, HadGEM3-GC31-MM and MPI-ESM1-2-XR fail to simulate TCs in the entire north Indian Ocean. It is shown in previous studies that MPI models both at low-resolution and high-resolution fail to simulate TCs in the northern hemisphere as well as in the South Indian Ocean<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">On the other hand, CMCC-CM2-VHR4, FGOALS-f3-H, ECMWF-IFS-HR, CNRM-CM6-1-HR and HadGEM3-GC31-HM models simulate TCs with moderate skill in the Arabian Sea and Bay of Bengal. Out of these models, the CMCC-CM2-VHR4 and FGOALS-f3-H model show highest TC track density between 5°N-13°N in the Arabian Sea and Bay of Bengal and the TC track density decreases poleward in both the models. Furthermore, the standard deviation in TC track density highlights that the regions of maximum TC occurrence also exhibit the greatest interannual variability, consistent with expectations and in line with the observed patterns. The HadGEM3-GC31-HM model exhibits pattern similar to CMCC-CM2-VHR4 and FGOALS-f3-H with higher TC track density mainly confined to the lower latitudes, however the magnitude is lower than the two models and is closer to the observed pattern. In the HadGEM3-GC31-HM model the interannual variability as shown by the standard deviation of the TC track density is similar to the observation. In contrast, both the CNRM-CM6-1-HR and ECMWF-IFS-HR models simulate the highest TC track density north of 15°N in the Bay of Bengal. However, the magnitude of TC track density in both models is lower compared to observations. In the Arabian Sea, the CNRM-CM6-1-HR model shows a more uniform distribution of TC track density across the basin, albeit with a lower magnitude than observed, while the ECMWF-IFS-HR model exhibits a concentration of TC tracks in the southwestern part of the basin.</p><p id="Par10">Based on the TC cumulative track density and the interannual variability in the TC tracks, we also carried out Taylor diagram analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, b). Similar Taylor diagram analysis is done for the TC cumulative genesis density and the interannual variability of the TC genesis (Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>), following the methodology of<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>. Based on TC track density, it is found that ECMWF-IFS-HR and BCC-CSM2-HR models have the highest correlation coefficient with the observation (<italic>r</italic> = 0.66 and <italic>r</italic> = 0.63 respectively). However, the standard deviation of TC track density is significantly less in the BCC-CSM2-HR as compared to the observation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Thus, its Taylor skill score is only 0.15. On the other hand, the Taylor skill score of ECMWF-IFS-HR is 0.62 which is the 2nd highest among all the models. HadGEM3-GC31-HM and MPI-ESM1-2-XR also display a correlation coefficient close to 0.6. The Taylor skill score of MPI-ESM1-2-XR is 0.01. On the other hand, HadGEM3-GC31-HM model has standard deviation in the TC track density close to the observation and the root mean square error 0.88 resulting in a high Taylor skill score of 0.80, which is also the highest among all the models. The FGOALS-f3-H and CMCC-CM2-VHR4 models on the other hand have the Taylor skill scores of 0.46 and 0.42 respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c), which is the third and fourth highest among all the models. The Taylor skill scores of other models are less than 0.2. So, HadGEM3-GC31-HM, ECMWF-IFS-HR, FGOALS-f3-H and CMCC-CM2-VHR4 models have higher Taylor skill score as compared to the other models with HadGEM3-GC31-HM as the best performing model (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). Additionally, we analyzed TC genesis locations, which provide complementary information to track density by indicating where TCs form—an important factor influencing their subsequent tracks. Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>a–c presents the Taylor skill score analysis of TC genesis density, showing that models such as CMCC-CM2-HR4, CNRM-CM6-1-HR, EC-Earth3P-HR, BCC-CSM2-HR, and HadGEM3-GC31-HH perform reasonably well, with Taylor skill scores above 0.4. Based on both TC track and TC genesis assessments, we find that only the HadGEM3-GC31-HM, ECMWF-IFS-HR, FGOALS-f3-H, and CMCC-CM2-VHR4 models perform well in simulating both genesis locations and track density. Since, the future projections of the ECMWF-IFS-HR model are not available, considering the availability of the future projections, we have selected three best performing models (HadGEM3-GC31-HM, FGOALS-f3-H and CMCC-CM2-VHR4) for further analysis.</p><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Taylor Diagram comparing the (<bold>a</bold>) Cumulative TC track density, (<bold>b</bold>) Temporal standard deviation of annual TC track density, and (<bold>c</bold>) Taylor skill score analysis (purple for the TC cumulative track density and blue for the standard deviation of TC track density) for different HighResMIP high-resolution historical simulation (1979–2014) against the observations (IBTrACS). The figure is created using Python (Version: 3.10.9) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/</ext-link>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e418" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/4fcb3cfccd33/41598_2026_35482_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1510?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 503?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/4bc545d7549a/41598_2026_35482_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Future projection of TC tracks</title><p id="Par12">We analyzed the historical simulation (1979–2014) and future projection (2015–2050) of the TC track density by the three best selected models and their multi model mean (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). We have binned the TC track points in a 2.5° × 2.5° box. In order to see the projected changes in the TC track density in the near-future, we have calculated the difference in the cumulative TC track density between the future projection and historical simulation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c, f, i, l). In the Arabian Sea, the multi-model mean (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>l) projects a basin-wide decrease in TC track density, indicating an overall decline in TC frequency, with particularly notable decreases south of 15°N where there is stronger inter-model agreement. While these results are of interest, especially given their potential relevance for the region, our primary focus in this study is on the TC track changes in the Bay of Bengal due to higher TC frequency in this basin. Therefore, the Arabian Sea is not examined in detail here, but the projected decreases are acknowledged as an important finding that merits further investigation in future work.</p><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Historical simulation (1979–2014, left) and future projection (2015–2050, center) of TC cumulative track density by HADGEM3-GC31-HM, FGOALS-f3-H, CMCC-CM2-VHR4 model and the last row denotes the multi model mean of all the three models during the post-monsoon season. The right column shows the difference in the TC cumulative track density between the historical simulations and the future projections, where hatching represent that the difference between the two periods is statistically significant at 95% confidence interval and “+” in the multi model mean represents that all the three models agree with the changes in the TC track density in the near future projections. The figure is created using Python (Version: 3.10.9) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/</ext-link>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e446" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/984537eca8a8/41598_2026_35482_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1594?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 531?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/9aa1fbf7ff5c/41598_2026_35482_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par14">In the Bay of Bengal, FGOALS-f3-H model shows an increase in the TC track density in the northern parts of the Bay of Bengal (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>f) and decrease in TC track density in the southern Bay of Bengal, which is statistically significant at the 90% confidence level. The HadGEM3-GC31-HM shows increase in the TC track density in the northern parts of the basin and decrease in the southern part of the basin (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c), but the change in TC tracks is less robust as compared to the FGOALS-f3-H. The CMCC-CM2-VHR4 projects a non-significant increase in the TC track density, with a weaker magnitude as compared to the other two models (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>i). Previous studies show that there are two distinct TC tracks in the Bay of Bengal<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. Some TCs travel in a north-northeastward direction, while others move west-northwestward. Here only those TCs are considered which made landfall over land areas. Based on the multi model mean we can see that the TCs travelling in north-northeastward direction are projected to increase from 21.2% in the historical simulation to 31.5% in the future projection which is statistically significant at the 90% confidence level (<italic>p</italic> = 0.09) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In order to increase the confidence in our findings, we have computed the percentage of TC points north of 15°N (including landfall and non-landfall TCs) (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>) during the historical simulation and the future projection. It can be seen that due to more north-northeastward travelling TCs in the future projection for all the three models (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) there is an increase in the TC points north of 15°N as compared to the historical simulation (Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). The multi-model mean projects a northward shift in TC tracks (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>l; Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and S1), this projection is primarily supported by statistically significant changes at 90% confidence level in the FGOALS-f3-H and CMCC-CM2-VHR4 models (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The HadGEM3-GC31-HM also indicates a northward shift, though it is statistically insignificant (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Nonetheless, all the three models are consistent in projecting the northward shift, which enhances confidence in the multi-model mean projection.</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Historical simulation (1979–2014) and future projection (2015–2050) of the percentage of TCs (only those TCs which are making landfall) moving in west-northwestward direction, north-northeastward direction in different HighResMIP CMIP6 models. Last column denotes the difference in the percentage of TCs moving in north-northeastward direction and west-northwestward direction between the historical simulation and future projection in different models. Last row denotes the multi model mean (MMM) of all the three models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Model</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Historical (1979–2014)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Future (2015–2050)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Future minus historical</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">North-northeastward (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">West-northwestward (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">North-northeastward (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">West-northwestward (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">North-northeastward (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">West-northwestward (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HadGEM3-GC31-HM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.55)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">− 0.8 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.93)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FGOALS-f3-H</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.6</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.1)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">− 5.7 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.47)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMCC-CM2-VHR4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.9</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58.1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.5 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.04)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">− 10.9 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.15)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MMM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.3 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.09)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">− 5.8 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.38)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par16">The changes in the TC cumulative track density in a given basin might be influenced by TC frequency<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. Our analysis, based on the multi model mean from CMIP6-HighResMIP experiments, indicates that the projected TC frequency in the near future over the Bay of Bengal during the post-monsoon season is expected to be 2.4 TC/year which is marginally less, compared to the historical period (2.6 TC/year). However, the projected decrease in the TC frequency is not significant (<italic>p</italic> = 0.27). This finding aligns with projections from both CMIP5 and CMIP6 models, which indicate a decline in TC frequency over the Bay of Bengal, though with a greater magnitude of decrease compared to our results<sup><xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup>. Further, it confirms that the projected shift in TC track density in this basin is independent of variations in TC frequency.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="2"><title>Mechanism driving the poleward shift in TC tracks</title><p id="Par17">Previous studies have shown that TC tracks are modulated by the TC genesis location<sup><xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> and the upper-level atmospheric background winds<sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>. An analysis of the historical simulation and the future projections of the TC genesis latitude shows that FGOALS-f3-H model is projecting a poleward shift of 1.8° when comparing the future projections with the historical simulation, which is statistically significant at 99% confidence level (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In contrast, the other two models do not indicate any significant change in TC genesis latitude (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), highlighting considerable inter-model variability. The multi model mean projects a modest poleward shift of 0.4° as compared to the historical simulation; however, this change is not statistically significant (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). These findings underscore the inconsistency in the projected latitudinal shift of TC genesis and highlights that the projected changes in the TC tracks cannot be explained by the changes in the TC genesis latitude. This insignificant change in the TC genesis latitude as projected by the model, is in contrast to western North Pacific where the TC genesis location shows a more robust poleward shift in a global warming scenario<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>.</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>TC genesis latitude (°N) in the historical simulation (1979–2014) and future projection (2015–2050) by different CMIP6 HighResMIP models and their multi model mean (MMM). The last column denotes the difference in the TC genesis latitude between the future projection and historical simulation. The p-value denotes the statistical significance using two-tailed student’s <italic>t</italic>-test.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Historical (1979–2014) (°N)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Future (2015–2050) (°N)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Difference (future-historical) (°N)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HadGEM3-GC31-HM</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.8 ± 2.8</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7 ± 2.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">− 0.1 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.89)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FGOALS-f3-H</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.2 ± 2.5</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.0 ± 2.2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMCC-CM2-VHR4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.1 ± 2.2</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.1 ± 3.0</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.99)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MMM</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7 ± 1.7</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.1 ± 1.8</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.4 (<italic>p</italic> = 0.28)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par19">We analyzed the historical simulations and future projections of upper-level winds (250 hPa) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) to understand the background steering. The analysis of multi model mean of wind differences indicates a statistically significant (90% confidence level) enhancement of westerly winds over the western and central Bay of Bengal, along with an enhancement of southerly wind over the northern part of the basin (north of 17°N) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>l; the regions with statistical significance at 90% confidence level are marked with hatching). Although this enhancement of southerly wind is not statistically significant it contributes to the development of a cyclonic circulation that restricts TC from moving westward and instead steers them northward. The individual model analysis reveals that all the three models are projecting a change towards a cyclonic circulation in the upper-level winds over the Indian subcontinent with statistically significant enhanced westerlies (90% confidence level) over western Bay of Bengal and non—significant southerlies over the northern Bay of Bengal, with more clear signature in the HadGEM-3-GC31-HM and CMCC-CM2-VHR4 models (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c, f, i). At the mid-level (500 hPa) too there is southerly/southeasterly wind change in the northern parts of the Bay of Bengal. However, enhancement of westerly winds over the western and the central Bay of Bengal is less prominent and not significant as compared to the upper levels (Figure S2). Whereas the change, in the winds at the lower level (700 hPa), is too weak and statistically insignificant to influence the track of TCs (Figure S3). The changes in the upper-level winds as projected by the multi model mean resemble to the anomalous wind pattern which is observed during north-northeastward moving TCs with enhanced southerlies over the northern part of the basin<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. In the observations these anomalous southerlies are associated with an anomalous cyclonic circulation centered over Indian landmass<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. Thus, the model projection of the strengthening of westerlies at the upper-level over the western and central Bay of Bengal, coupled with enhanced southerlies over the northern Bay of Bengal manifest with the cyclonic circulation acts as a barrier to the west-northwestward movement of TCs toward the east coast of India. As a result, the models project a poleward shift in TC tracks.</p><fig id="Fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Historical simulation (1979–2014, left) and future projection (2015–2050, center) of winds (vector, m s<sup>− 1</sup>) and meridional winds (color, m s<sup>− 1</sup>) at 250 hPa by HADGEM3-GC31-HM, FGOALS-f3-H, CMCC-CM2-VHR4 model and the last row denotes the multi-model mean (MMM) of all the three models during the post-monsoon season. Right column denotes the difference in the winds (vectors, m s<sup>− 1</sup>) and meridional winds (color, m s<sup>− 1</sup>) between the historical simulation and the future projection. The hatching in the last column denotes the areas where the difference in the meridional winds is significant at 90% confidence interval using the two-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic>-test. The figure is created using Python (Version: 3.10.9) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/</ext-link>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e798" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/e12e97c66f61/41598_2026_35482_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1748?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 582?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig4_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/d17cd43a1cbe/41598_2026_35482_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par21">The presence of anomalous cyclonic circulation over the Indian subcontinent in the upper levels along the subtropical westerly jet path is due to the presence of a Rossby wave train travelling from west to east along the jet axis and is consistent with the previous studies<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>–<xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup>. Meridional winds are generally used as a proxy of atmospheric wave in the mid to upper levels<sup><xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup>. Figure <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d shows the multi model mean of the difference in the future projections and historical simulations of winds and meridional winds at the upper-level for a wider region. It can be seen that starting from the eastern Atlantic (near 40°N, 20°W), throughout the subtropical westerly jet axis to east Asia (near 150°E) there is a wave pattern with alternating southerly and northerly winds (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). This alternating change in the wind pattern is associated with a cyclonic and anticyclonic changes in the wind all along the jet axis with cyclonic wind change over the Indian subcontinent. To further validate the consistency of the changes in the wind pattern among different models, we conducted a pattern correlation analysis of the meridional winds between each individual model and the multi-model mean. The results show statistically significant (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) correlations: 0.72 for HadGEM3-GC31-HM, 0.77 for FGOALS-f3-H, and 0.79 for CMCC-CM2-VHR4. These correlations indicate that, despite some regional differences, overall, the change in the wind pattern is consistent with the multi model mean (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a-d). This projected change in the wind pattern resembles the observed Rossby wave pattern with its origin at the jet entrance region over the western Mediterranean region<sup><xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> and influencing the upper-level winds over Indian subcontinent.</p><fig id="Fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Difference in winds (vector, m s<sup>− 1</sup>) and meridional winds (color, m s<sup>− 1</sup>) at 250 hPa between the future projection (2015–2050) and historical simulation (1979–2014) by (a) HadGEM-GC31-HM (b) FGOALS-f3-H (c) CMCC-CM2-VHR4 and (d) Multi Model mean (MMM) during the post-monsoon season. The figure is created using Python (Version: 3.10.9) <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.python.org/downloads/release/python-3109/</ext-link>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e850" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/1a1c7c8eed1a/41598_2026_35482_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1858?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 619?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_Fig5_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/6dd6/12891732/6c3cf61296a8/41598_2026_35482_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="1"><title>Summary and discussion</title><p id="Par23">TCs upon landfall make significant socio-economic impact and so understanding the TC track characteristics are very important. In order to understand how the TC tracks are going to change in the near-future, we have analyzed the near-future projections of TC tracks using the high-resolution CMIP6-HighResMIP model projections. Using the CMIP6-HighResMIP best performing multi-model ensemble, we found that the models are projecting a northward shift in the TC tracks in the near future (2015–2050) under the SSP5-8.5 scenario. The projected change in TC tracks is primarily driven by changes in upper-level steering winds, whereas variations in TC genesis locations play only a minimal role. The upper-level winds are projected to evolve in a way that provides stronger southerly steering over the Bay of Bengal, leading to an increase in northward-moving TCs and a decrease in west-northwestward-moving TCs.</p><p id="Par24">These changes in the upper-level wind pattern are associated with the enhanced wave activity along the sub-tropical westerly jet axis originating from the western Mediterranean region and travelling downstream across the Indian subcontinent. The source of origin of this wave activity in the upper levels are the perturbations caused by the north Atlantic Oscillation and the formation of anomalous convergence zone over the Mediterranean region near the subtropical westerly jet entrance region<sup><xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup>. Previous studies show that this atmospheric Rossby wave propagates eastward along the subtropical jet and induces alternating anomalous convergence and divergence zones along the jet axis<sup><xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup>. The subtropical westerly jet provides a favourable waveguide for the downstream propagation of the wave<sup><xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup>. This meridionally trapped wave along the subtropical westerly jet axis is also called as South Asia jet wave train<sup><xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup>. The signature in the projected winds by the multi model mean is most dominant at the upper levels and is consistent with the observational evidence which shows that the wave propagation along the subtropical westerly jet axis is most prominent at the upper level (200–300 hPa)<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. Thus, it can be concluded that the projected changes in the wind pattern over Indian subcontinent and the Bay of Bengal which is altering the TC tracks is due to the changes in the extratropical wave activity. The projection of poleward migration of TC track in this basin with the CMIP6-HighResMIP is consistent with the projection of poleward migration of TC tracks in the western North Pacific<sup><xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">Previous case studies suggest that sea surface temperature (SST), vertical wind shear, and lapse rate can also partially influence TC tracks<sup><xref rid="CR53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="CR54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup>. Our analysis based on multi model mean shows that although SST is projected to warm significantly with the most rapid warming over the southern and central Bay of Bengal (Figure S4 a-c) the TC tracks shift northward, indicating that SST is not the dominant driver in the changes in TC tracks. Similarly, vertical wind shear increases across the basin without a clear north–south gradient (Figure S4 d-f), and lapse rate shows weaker increases over the northern Bay of Bengal compared to other regions (Figure S4 g-i); yet, TC tracks shift northward. These results suggest that none of these factors primarily explain the projected poleward shift, reinforcing the conclusion that upper-level winds play the key role.</p><p id="Par26">It is important to note that the CMIP6-HighResMIP framework currently provides projections only for the SSP5-8.5 scenario and is limited up to 2050. Consequently, a direct comparison with CMIP5 projections for the late 21st century is not feasible. To assess long-term trends and potential shifts in TC characteristics under evolving climate conditions, HighResMIP experiments, extending to the end of the 21st century, are required. The current results are based on the best available three CMIP6-HighResMIP models. The study highlights the potential of high-resolution global models for TC projection. However, participation of more number of high-resolution models are essential for realistic simulation of the TC activity in the north Indian Ocean and increase the confidence in the future projections. As the current findings are based on SSP5-8.5 scenario which is the most aggressive global warming scenario, and so may have some uncertainties in the near-future as well<sup><xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup>. Thus, future research should include additional global warming scenarios (which are less aggressive) to evaluate the robustness of these projections and explore potential nonlinear responses of TC activity to increasing greenhouse gas concentrations and far-future projections. Moreover, regional downscaling techniques and high-resolution modeling will further improve our understanding of TC track density changes, providing critical insights for disaster preparedness and climate adaptation strategies in the Bay of Bengal as well as global ocean region.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="2"><title>Observational and reanalysis data</title><p id="Par27">Observational TC data for the north Indian Ocean during the period 1979–2014 is obtained from the India Meteorological Department (IMD) as archived in the International Best Track Archive for Climate Stewardship version 4 (IBTrACSv4)<sup><xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup>. North Indian Ocean TCs which have their genesis between 0–22°N and 78°E–100°E are taken as the Bay of the Bengal TCs and the TCs which have their genesis between 0–22°N and 50°E–78°E are considered as the Arabian Sea TCs.</p><p id="Par28">In the north Indian Ocean, TCs occur mainly in the pre-monsoon season from April–early June and the post-monsoon season from October–December<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="CR57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup>. In this study, we focus only on the post-monsoon season TCs due to the higher number of TCs in this season as compared to the pre-monsoon season<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>. We have considered the TCs which have their genesis in the post-monsoon season (October–December) and removed the TCs which have their genesis in September and their decay in October. The selection of season is consistent with previous studies<sup><xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CR58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup>. By excluding September TCs that are decaying in October, we ensure that our analysis isolates TCs forming under post-monsoon season only. As the atmospheric conditions especially the wind pattern significantly differs between the September and post-monsoon season, mixing the two seasons likely to dilute the signature of the changes in winds in the historical simulation and the future projection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="2"><title>HighResMIP CMIP6 simulations</title><p id="Par29">In this study, we utilize climate model simulations from HighResMIP, a component of CMIP6—the World Climate Research Programme’s latest initiative to coordinate climate simulations at a high temporal and spatial resolutions of past and future climates from worldwide modeling centers<sup><xref rid="CR60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref></sup>. The HighResMIP experiment is chosen as previous studies have shown that the high-resolution models perform better in the realistic simulation of TC as compared to the low-resolution models<sup><xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CR61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></sup>. Most of the HighResMIP CMIP6 model grid spacing ranging from 25 to 100 km which is higher than the standard CMIP6 model resolutions. A detail of all the HighResMIP models and their temporal and spatial resolutions is provided in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. We selected HigResMIP Tier 2 experiment which is ocean-atmosphere coupled simulations, covering a period from 1950 to 2050<sup><xref rid="CR62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup>. The ocean-atmosphere coupling is crucial for a realistic representation of various TC characteristics in the model<sup><xref rid="CR63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>–<xref rid="CR65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup>. We used Hist-1950 for historical simulation, which are initialized using the ERA-20 C dataset, representing 20th -century conditions, and are given the daily sea surface temperature and sea ice forcings. For the future projections, we have used the HighResMIP-future experiment which has a temporal extent from 2015 to 2050. The HighResMIP future forcing for the period 2015–2050 is same as CMIP6 SSP5-8.5 high fossil fuel usage scenario<sup><xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup>. The SSP5-8.5 scenario combines a shared socioeconomic pathway driven by fossil fuel development with Representative Concentration Pathway 8.5, which has a radiative forcing of 8.5 W m<sup>− 2</sup>. In order to maintain consistency with the number of years available for future projections, we restricted the analysis of historical simulation for the period 1979–2014.</p><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>CMIP6 HighResMIP models, their grid spacing, temporal resolution and their modeling centers which are used in our study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMIP6-HighResMIP models</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Grid spacing and temporal resolution</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Institution</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMCC-CM2-VHR4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 km, 6 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Euro-Mediterranean Center on Climate Change, Italy</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ECMWF-IFS-HR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 km, 6 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European center for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts, UK</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">FGOALS-f3-H</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25 km, 6 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chinese Academy of Sciences, China</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HadGEM3-GC31-HM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 km, 3 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met Office Hadley Center, UK</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CNRM-CM6-1_HR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 km, 6 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">National Center for Meteorological Research, France</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EC-Earth3P-HR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 km, 6hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EC-Earth Consortium, Europe</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ECMWF-IFS-LR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 km, 6hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European center for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts, UK</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MPI -ESM1-2-XR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 km, 6 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max Plank Institute for Meteorology, Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BCC-CSM2-HR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 km, daily</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beijing Climate Center, China</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ECMWF-IFS-MR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 km, daily</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">European center for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts, UK</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HadGEM3-GC31-HH</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">50 km, daily</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met Office Hadley Center, UK</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EC-Earth3P</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 km, 6 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">EC-Earth Consortium, Europe</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MPI -ESM1-2-HR</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 km, 6 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Max Plank Institute for Meteorology, Germany</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HadGEM3-GC31-MM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 km, daily</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Met Office Hadley Center, UK</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CMCC-CM2-HR4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100 km, 6 hourly</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Euro-Mediterranean Center on Climate Change, Italy</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="2"><title>Methodology</title><p id="Par31">We selected all those models which have spatial grid spacing equal to or finer than 100 km and temporal resolution of at least 24 h (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Most of them provide the required variables at 6 hourly interval, except BCC-CSM2-HR, ECMWF-IFS-MR, HadGEM3-GC31-MM and HadGEM3-GC31-HH models, which provide at 24 h. To maintain consistency among the models, we selected only the first member of each model even if they have multiple ensemble members. Further, ECMWF-IFS-HR, ECMWF-IFS-LR and ECMWF-IFS-MR models have only historical simulations and do not have future projections, so in our study these models are only used for historical studies in comparison with observation but are not used for the future projection of TCs in the basin.</p><p id="Par32">TCs in the model data are identified using the Centre National de Recherches Meteorologiques (CNRM) TC tracking and detection algorithm<sup><xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup>. We selected the CNRM algorithm based on its demonstrated superior skill in realistically capturing TCs over the north Indian Ocean compared to other commonly used algorithms, such as the University of Zaragoza (UZ) and Okubo-Weiss-Zeta (OWZ) algorithms<sup><xref rid="CR68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup>. The CNRM algorithm shows the highest probability of TC frequency detection. Furthermore, analysis of TC track errors reveals that approximately 65% of TC positions identified by the CNRM algorithm exhibit a track error of less than 50 km, indicating the lowest track error among the evaluated algorithms. A comprehensive comparison of various TC detection and tracking algorithms will be reported in a separate study. Our findings are consistent with those of Bell et al. (2018)<sup><xref rid="CR69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></sup>, who reported that while the OWZ algorithm performs well in detecting TCs across several ocean basins, its effectiveness in accurately capturing TC tracks and durations in the north Indian Ocean is notably limited.</p><p id="Par33">To identify the location of TC, the CNRM algorithm utilises sea level pressure, wind, temperature and relative vorticity at different levels. TC detection in this algorithm is based on following criteria:</p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par35">The sea level pressure must be lower than surrounding, the region of pressure minimum indicates the system’s centre.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par36">Relative vorticity (ζ<sub>850hPa</sub>) ≥ 1.5 × 10<sup>− 4</sup> s<sup>− 1</sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par37">U850 hPa ≥ 5 m s<sup>− 1</sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par38">The sum of the temperature anomalies averaged over the 700, 500, 300 hPa pressure levels ≥ 1 K.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par39">Difference in temperature anomaly (850 hPa minus 300 hPa) ≤ 1 K.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par40">Difference in wind speed (300 hPa minus 850 hPa) ≤ 5 m s<sup>− 1</sup>.</p></list-item></list>
<p id="Par41">Where, ζ<sub>850hPa</sub> is the relative vorticity at 850 hPa. U850 is the wind speed at 850 hPa. Similar to the methodology of Singh et al. (2024)<sup><xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup>, we define the TC genesis as the first time when the maximum surface wind speed of a system reaches 35 knots (~ 17.5 m s<sup>− 1</sup>). The TCs which have their genesis east of 100°E are also removed from the analysis. Further, we show the TC tracks only for the timespan when TCs have maximum wind speed ≥ 35 knots. This threshold is chosen to emphasize TC tracks corresponding to systems that have reached at least tropical storm intensity, which has a threshold of 35 knots<sup><xref rid="CR71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup>. TC points in the initial and the dissipation stage with wind speeds below 35 knots are excluded from the analysis because, in observations, the initial wind speed of the system varies—some begin at 20 knots, others at 25 or 30 knots. This inconsistency leads to non-uniform identification of TC genesis locations based on the first recorded point. To address this and ensure consistency, we apply a uniform threshold of 35 knots in the observation and the model and include only those TCs which qualifies as a tropical storm or stronger intensity. After detecting the TC, if a TC is weakening to an intensity lower than 35 knots and regaining its intensity again ≥ 35 knots, then a relaxation criterion is applied to avoid any breaks in TC tracks. This relaxation criteria using the relative vorticity threshold of 2.5 × 10<sup>− 4</sup> at 850 hPa, helps to reconstruct full TC life cycle and reconnect fragmented tracks resulting from temporary weakening<sup><xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup>. In our study we classified north-northeastward moving TCs as those making landfall along the coast of Myanmar, Bangladesh or West Bengal, India. Conversely, west-northwestward moving TCs are defined as those making landfall along the east coast of India (Odisha, Andhra Pradesh, Tamil Nadu or the coast of Sri Lanka). From the TC track analysis mentioned in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">2</xref>, TCs that dissipated in the open ocean without making landfall were excluded as in Singh et al.<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. The vertical wind shear in the model historical simulations and future projections is computed as the magnitude of vector difference in the winds between 200 hPa and 850 hPa levels<sup><xref rid="CR73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></sup>. The mid-tropospheric lapse rate is computed as the change in atmospheric temperature/km between 500 and 700 hPa.</p><p id="Par42">To assess the skill of best performing models, we compared the track of simulated model TCs in the historical period (1979–2014) with the observations. This approach increases our confidence in the model projections. We have utilized the Taylor Diagram analysis<sup><xref rid="CR74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></sup>, which is a widely used technique for evaluating the performance of models against a chosen reference dataset<sup><xref rid="CR75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,<xref rid="CR76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></sup>. This method is widely utilized for its ability to concisely summarize key statistical metrics, including correlation, centered root-mean-square difference and the variance. It helps in understanding the statistical relationship between the model dataset and an observation dataset. The correlation coefficient is a crucial metric in Taylor diagram which is used to quantify spatial or temporal similarity between datasets. The root mean square difference is used to identify the difference in the two fields. The standard deviation is utilized to estimate the variation in the data. All these statistical methods are clubbed together and visualized in a single Taylor diagram. Additionally Taylor skill score is utilized to rank the models based on their accuracy and closeness to observation<sup><xref rid="CR74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></sup>. A Taylor skill score value closer to 1 indicate higher agreement between the model and the observation. The statistical significance of the results in this study are carried out using the two-tailed Student’s <italic>t</italic>-test.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p>
<supplementary-material id="MOESM1" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path 6dd6/12891732/2449c59d77c4/41598_2026_35482_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2192588?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge the Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Pune and Ministry of Earth Sciences, Government of India for providing support. Authors are thankful to the reviewers for providing insightful suggestions and comments. Support from the “Deep Ocean Mission” programme of the Ministry of Earth Sciences, Government of India is also acknowledged. We thank Mrs. Ganadhi Mano Kranthi from Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Pune, India for scientific discussions.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>R.A: Conceptualization; methodology; investigation; software; data curation; formal analysis; visualization; writing—original draftV.K.S: Methodology; formal analysis; visualization; writing—original draft and editing.A.P: Methodology; supervision; writing-—review and editing. C.G: Conceptualization; methodology; supervision; project administration; funding acquisition; writing—review and editing.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>The TC data is obtained from the India Meteorological Department (IMD) as archived in the IBTrACS dataset and is available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/ibtracs/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/ibtracs/</ext-link>. The data of reanalysis winds at 250 hPa is obtained from European Center for Medium Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) fifth-generation global atmospheric reanalysis (ERA5) dataset and is available at (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets" ext-link-type="uri">https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets</ext-link>) . The CMIP6 HighResMIP historical simulation and future projection data is openly available at (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.ceda.ac.uk/badc/cmip6/data/CMIP6/HighResMIP" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.ceda.ac.uk/badc/cmip6/data/CMIP6/HighResMIP</ext-link>). The variables in the CMIP6-HighResMIP models are available at (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.ceda.ac.uk/badc/cmip6/data/CMIP6/HighResMIP" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.ceda.ac.uk/badc/cmip6/data/CMIP6/HighResMIP</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="FPar5" disp-level="2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par43">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cai, Y. et al. Enhanced predictability of rapidly intensifying tropical cyclones over the Western North Pacific associated with snow depth changes over the Tibetan plateau. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 2093–2110 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cai, Y. et al. Enhanced predictability of rapidly intensifying tropical cyclones over the Western North Pacific associated with snow depth changes over the Tibetan plateau. J. Clim.35, 2093–2110 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhao, H. et al. A statistical intraseasonal prediction model of extended boreal summer Western North Pacific tropical cyclone genesis. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 2459–2478 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhao, H. et al. A statistical intraseasonal prediction model of extended boreal summer Western North Pacific tropical cyclone genesis. J. Clim.35, 2459–2478 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Camargo, S. J. &amp; Wing, A. A. Tropical cyclones in climate models. <italic>WIREs Clim. Chang.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 211–237 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Camargo, S. J. &amp; Wing, A. A. Tropical cyclones in climate models. WIREs Clim. Chang.7, 211–237 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Roberts, M. J. et al. Projected future changes in tropical cyclones using the CMIP6 HighResMIP multimodel ensemble. <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>47</bold>, eGL088662 (2020). </named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1029/2020GL088662"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7507130"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32999514"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Roberts, M. J. et al. Projected future changes in tropical cyclones using the CMIP6 HighResMIP multimodel ensemble. Geophys. Res. Lett.47, eGL088662 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kreussler, P. et al. Tropical cyclone integrated kinetic energy in an ensemble of highresmip simulations. <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>48</bold>, e2020GL090963 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kreussler, P. et al. Tropical cyclone integrated kinetic energy in an ensemble of highresmip simulations. Geophys. Res. Lett.48, e2020GL090963 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Roberts, M. J. et al. Impact of model resolution on tropical cyclone simulation using the HighResMIP–PRIMAVERA multimodel ensemble. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>33</bold>, 2557–2583 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Roberts, M. J. et al. Impact of model resolution on tropical cyclone simulation using the HighResMIP–PRIMAVERA multimodel ensemble. J. Clim.33, 2557–2583 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Song, K., Zhao, J., Zhan, R., Tao, L. &amp; Chen, L. Confidence and uncertainty in simulating tropical cyclone Long-Term variability using the CMIP6-HighResMIP. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 6431–6451 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Song, K., Zhao, J., Zhan, R., Tao, L. &amp; Chen, L. Confidence and uncertainty in simulating tropical cyclone Long-Term variability using the CMIP6-HighResMIP. J. Clim.35, 6431–6451 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Camargo, S. J. Global and regional aspects of tropical cyclone activity in the CMIP5 models. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 9880–9902 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Camargo, S. J. Global and regional aspects of tropical cyclone activity in the CMIP5 models. J. Clim.26, 9880–9902 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Vidale, P. L. et al. Impact of stochastic physics and model resolution on the simulation of tropical cyclones in climate GCMs. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>34</bold>, 4315–4341 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Vidale, P. L. et al. Impact of stochastic physics and model resolution on the simulation of tropical cyclones in climate GCMs. J. Clim.34, 4315–4341 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Walsh, K. J. E. et al. Hurricanes and climate: the U.S. CLIVAR working group on hurricanes. <italic>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>96</bold>, 997–1017 (2015).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Walsh, K. J. E. et al. Hurricanes and climate: the U.S. CLIVAR working group on hurricanes. Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.96, 997–1017 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Knutson, T. et al. Tropical cyclones and climate change assessment: Part2: projected response to anthropogenic warming. <italic>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>101</bold>, E303–E322 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Knutson, T. et al. Tropical cyclones and climate change assessment: Part2: projected response to anthropogenic warming. Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.101, E303–E322 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chand, S. S. et al. Declining tropical cyclone frequency under global warming. <italic>Nat. Clim. Chang.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 655–661 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chand, S. S. et al. Declining tropical cyclone frequency under global warming. Nat. Clim. Chang.12, 655–661 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Walsh, K. J. E. et al. Tropical cyclones and climate change. <italic>Trop. Cyclone Res. Rev.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 240–250 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Walsh, K. J. E. et al. Tropical cyclones and climate change. Trop. Cyclone Res. Rev.8, 240–250 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sugi, M. &amp; Yoshimura, J. Decreasing trend of tropical cyclone frequency in 228-year high-resolution AGCM simulations. <italic>Geophys Res. Lett</italic><bold>39</bold> (2012). </named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Vecchi, G. A. et al. Tropical cyclone sensitivities to CO2 doubling: roles of atmospheric resolution, synoptic variability and background climate changes. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>53</bold>, 5999–6033 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Vecchi, G. A. et al. Tropical cyclone sensitivities to CO2 doubling: roles of atmospheric resolution, synoptic variability and background climate changes. Clim. Dyn.53, 5999–6033 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhao, M., Held, I. M. &amp; TC-Permitting, G. C. M. Simulations of hurricane frequency response to sea surface temperature anomalies projected for the Late-Twenty-First century. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>25</bold>, 2995–3009 (2012).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhao, M., Held, I. M. &amp; TC-Permitting, G. C. M. Simulations of hurricane frequency response to sea surface temperature anomalies projected for the Late-Twenty-First century. J. Clim.25, 2995–3009 (2012)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yoshida, K., Sugi, M., Mizuta, R., Murakami, H. &amp; Ishii, M. Future changes in tropical cyclone activity in High-Resolution Large-Ensemble simulations. <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>44</bold>, 9910–9917 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yoshida, K., Sugi, M., Mizuta, R., Murakami, H. &amp; Ishii, M. Future changes in tropical cyclone activity in High-Resolution Large-Ensemble simulations. Geophys. Res. Lett.44, 9910–9917 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Grossmann, I. &amp; Morgan, M. G. Tropical cyclones, climate change, and scientific uncertainty: what do we know, what does it mean, and what should be done? <italic>Clim. Change</italic>. <bold>108</bold>, 543–579 (2011).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Grossmann, I. &amp; Morgan, M. G. Tropical cyclones, climate change, and scientific uncertainty: what do we know, what does it mean, and what should be done? Clim. Change. 108, 543–579 (2011)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Knutson, T. R. et al. Tropical cyclones and climate change. <italic>Nat. Geosci.</italic><bold>3</bold>, 157–163 (2010).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Knutson, T. R. et al. Tropical cyclones and climate change. Nat. Geosci.3, 157–163 (2010)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh, V. K. &amp; Roxy, M. K. A review of ocean-atmosphere interactions during tropical cyclones in the North Indian ocean. <italic>Earth Sci. Rev.</italic><bold>226</bold>, 103967 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Singh, V. K. &amp; Roxy, M. K. A review of ocean-atmosphere interactions during tropical cyclones in the North Indian ocean. Earth Sci. Rev.226, 103967 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Deshpande, M. et al. Changing status of tropical cyclones over the North Indian ocean. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>57</bold>, 3545–3567 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Deshpande, M. et al. Changing status of tropical cyclones over the North Indian ocean. Clim. Dyn.57, 3545–3567 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Balaguru, K., Taraphdar, S., Leung, L. R. &amp; Foltz, G. R. Increase in the intensity of Postmonsoon Bay of Bengal tropical cyclones. <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>41</bold>, 3594–3601 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Balaguru, K., Taraphdar, S., Leung, L. R. &amp; Foltz, G. R. Increase in the intensity of Postmonsoon Bay of Bengal tropical cyclones. Geophys. Res. Lett.41, 3594–3601 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sahoo, B. &amp; Bhaskaran, P. K. Assessment on historical cyclone tracks in the Bay of Bengal, East Coast of India. <italic>Int. J. Climatol</italic>. <bold>36</bold>, 95–109 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sahoo, B. &amp; Bhaskaran, P. K. Assessment on historical cyclone tracks in the Bay of Bengal, East Coast of India. Int. J. Climatol. 36, 95–109 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wahiduzzaman, M., Oliver, E. C. J., Wotherspoon, S. J. &amp; Holbrook, N. J. A Climatological model of North Indian ocean tropical cyclone genesis, tracks and landfall. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>49</bold>, 2585–2603 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wahiduzzaman, M., Oliver, E. C. J., Wotherspoon, S. J. &amp; Holbrook, N. J. A Climatological model of North Indian ocean tropical cyclone genesis, tracks and landfall. Clim. Dyn.49, 2585–2603 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bacmeister, J. T. et al. Projected changes in tropical cyclone activity under future warming scenarios using a high-resolution climate model. <italic>Clim. Change</italic>. <bold>146</bold>, 547–560 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bacmeister, J. T. et al. Projected changes in tropical cyclone activity under future warming scenarios using a high-resolution climate model. Clim. Change. 146, 547–560 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bell, S. S., Chand, S. S., Tory, K. J., Ye, H. &amp; Turville, C. North Indian ocean tropical cyclone activity in CMIP5 experiments: Future projections using a model-independent detection and tracking scheme. <italic>Int. J. Climatol</italic>. <bold>40</bold>, 1–14 (2020). </named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bell, S. S., Chand, S. S., Tory, K. J., Ye, H. &amp; Turville, C. North Indian ocean tropical cyclone activity in CMIP5 experiments: Future projections using a model-independent detection and tracking scheme. Int. J. Climatol. 40, 1–14 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Jyoteeshkumar Reddy, P., Sriram, D., Gunthe, S. S. &amp; Balaji, C. Impact of climate change on intense Bay of Bengal tropical cyclones of the post-monsoon season: a Pseudo global warming approach. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>56</bold>, 2855–2879 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Jyoteeshkumar Reddy, P., Sriram, D., Gunthe, S. S. &amp; Balaji, C. Impact of climate change on intense Bay of Bengal tropical cyclones of the post-monsoon season: a Pseudo global warming approach. Clim. Dyn.56, 2855–2879 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sugi, M., Murakami, H. &amp; Yoshimura, J. A reduction in global tropical cyclone frequency due to global warming. <italic>SOLA</italic><bold>5</bold>, 164–167 (2009).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sugi, M., Murakami, H. &amp; Yoshimura, J. A reduction in global tropical cyclone frequency due to global warming. SOLA5, 164–167 (2009)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tory, K. J., Chand, S. S., McBride, J. L., Ye, H. &amp; Dare, R. A. Projected changes in Late-Twenty-First-Century tropical cyclone frequency in 13 coupled climate models from phase 5 of the coupled model intercomparison project. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 9946–9959 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tory, K. J., Chand, S. S., McBride, J. L., Ye, H. &amp; Dare, R. A. Projected changes in Late-Twenty-First-Century tropical cyclone frequency in 13 coupled climate models from phase 5 of the coupled model intercomparison project. J. Clim.26, 9946–9959 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Murakami, H., Sugi, M. &amp; Kitoh, A. Future changes in tropical cyclone activity in the North Indian ocean projected by high-resolution MRI-AGCMs. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>40</bold>, 1949–1968 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Murakami, H., Sugi, M. &amp; Kitoh, A. Future changes in tropical cyclone activity in the North Indian ocean projected by high-resolution MRI-AGCMs. Clim. Dyn.40, 1949–1968 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh, O. P., Khan, A., Rahman, M. S. &amp; T. M. &amp; Changes in the frequency of tropical cyclones over the North Indian ocean. <italic>Meteorol. Atmos. Phys.</italic><bold>75</bold>, 11–20 (2000).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Singh, O. P., Khan, A., Rahman, M. S. &amp; T. M. &amp; Changes in the frequency of tropical cyclones over the North Indian ocean. Meteorol. Atmos. Phys.75, 11–20 (2000)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pall, P. et al. Assessing South Indian ocean tropical cyclone characteristics in highresmip simulations. <italic>Int. J. Climatol</italic>. <bold>44</bold>, 4792–4808 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pall, P. et al. Assessing South Indian ocean tropical cyclone characteristics in highresmip simulations. Int. J. Climatol. 44, 4792–4808 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shan, K. &amp; Yu, X. Enhanced Understanding of Poleward migration of tropical cyclone genesis. <italic>Environ. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 104062 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shan, K. &amp; Yu, X. Enhanced Understanding of Poleward migration of tropical cyclone genesis. Environ. Res. Lett.15, 104062 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shan, K. &amp; Yu, X. Variability of tropical cyclone landfalls in China. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>34</bold>, 9235–9247 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Shan, K. &amp; Yu, X. Variability of tropical cyclone landfalls in China. J. Clim.34, 9235–9247 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh, V. K., Roxy, M. K. &amp; Deshpande, M. Role of subtropical Rossby waves in governing the track of cyclones in the Bay of Bengal. <italic>Q. J. R Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>148</bold>, 3774–3787 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Singh, V. K., Roxy, M. K. &amp; Deshpande, M. Role of subtropical Rossby waves in governing the track of cyclones in the Bay of Bengal. Q. J. R Meteorol. Soc.148, 3774–3787 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bell, S. S. et al. Projections of Southern hemisphere tropical cyclone track density using CMIP5 models. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>52</bold>, 6065–6079 (2019).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bell, S. S. et al. Projections of Southern hemisphere tropical cyclone track density using CMIP5 models. Clim. Dyn.52, 6065–6079 (2019)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Fahad, A. A. et al. The role of tropical Easterly jet on the Bay of bengal’s tropical cyclones: observed climatology and future projection. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>36</bold>, 5825–5840 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Fahad, A. A. et al. The role of tropical Easterly jet on the Bay of bengal’s tropical cyclones: observed climatology and future projection. J. Clim.36, 5825–5840 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yonekura, E. &amp; Hall, T. M. ENSO effect on East Asian tropical cyclone landfall via changes in tracks and genesis in a statistical model. <italic>J. Appl. Meteorol. Climatol</italic>. <bold>53</bold>, 406–420 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yonekura, E. &amp; Hall, T. M. ENSO effect on East Asian tropical cyclone landfall via changes in tracks and genesis in a statistical model. J. Appl. Meteorol. Climatol. 53, 406–420 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Daloz, A. S. &amp; Camargo, S. J. Is the Poleward migration of tropical cyclone maximum intensity associated with a Poleward migration of tropical cyclone genesis? <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>50</bold>, 705–715 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Daloz, A. S. &amp; Camargo, S. J. Is the Poleward migration of tropical cyclone maximum intensity associated with a Poleward migration of tropical cyclone genesis? Clim. Dyn.50, 705–715 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wu, L. &amp; Wang, B. Assessing impacts of global warming on tropical cyclone tracks. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 1686–1699 (2004).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wu, L. &amp; Wang, B. Assessing impacts of global warming on tropical cyclone tracks. J. Clim.17, 1686–1699 (2004)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pattanaik, D. R. &amp; Rama Rao, Y. V. Track prediction of very severe cyclone ‘Nargis’ using high resolution weather research forecasting (WRF) model. <italic>J. Earth Syst. Sci.</italic><bold>118</bold>, 309–329 (2009).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pattanaik, D. R. &amp; Rama Rao, Y. V. Track prediction of very severe cyclone ‘Nargis’ using high resolution weather research forecasting (WRF) model. J. Earth Syst. Sci.118, 309–329 (2009)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wang, P. et al. Future changes and uncertainty in tropical cyclone genesis over the Western North pacific: insights from the dynamic genesis potential index using CMIP6 models. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>63</bold>, 99 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wang, P. et al. Future changes and uncertainty in tropical cyclone genesis over the Western North pacific: insights from the dynamic genesis potential index using CMIP6 models. Clim. Dyn.63, 99 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li, C. &amp; Sun, J. Role of the subtropical Westerly jet waveguide in a Southern China heavy rainstorm in December 2013. <italic>Adv. Atmos. Sci.</italic><bold>32</bold>, 601–612 (2015).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li, C. &amp; Sun, J. Role of the subtropical Westerly jet waveguide in a Southern China heavy rainstorm in December 2013. Adv. Atmos. Sci.32, 601–612 (2015)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Song, J., Li, C. &amp; Zhou, W. High and low latitude types of the downstream influences of the North Atlantic Oscillation. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>42</bold>, 1097–1111 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Song, J., Li, C. &amp; Zhou, W. High and low latitude types of the downstream influences of the North Atlantic Oscillation. Clim. Dyn.42, 1097–1111 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sun, Y. et al. A recent reversal in the Poleward shift of Western North Pacific tropical cyclones. <italic>Geophys. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>45</bold>, 9944–9952 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sun, Y. et al. A recent reversal in the Poleward shift of Western North Pacific tropical cyclones. Geophys. Res. Lett.45, 9944–9952 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wirth, V., Riemer, M., Chang, E. K. M. &amp; Martius, O. Rossby wave packets on the midlatitude waveguide-A review. <italic>Mon. Weather Rev.</italic><bold>146</bold>, 1965–2001 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wirth, V., Riemer, M., Chang, E. K. M. &amp; Martius, O. Rossby wave packets on the midlatitude waveguide-A review. Mon. Weather Rev.146, 1965–2001 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Watanabe, M. Asian jet waveguide and a downstream extension of the North Atlantic Oscillation. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 4674–4691 (2004).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Watanabe, M. Asian jet waveguide and a downstream extension of the North Atlantic Oscillation. J. Clim.17, 4674–4691 (2004)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Miaoqing, S., Yihui, D. &amp; Zunya, W. Relationship between Rossby wave propagation in Southern branch of westerlies and the formation of the Southern branch trough in wintertime. <italic>J. Appl. Meteorol. Sci.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 731–740 (2008).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Miaoqing, S., Yihui, D. &amp; Zunya, W. Relationship between Rossby wave propagation in Southern branch of westerlies and the formation of the Southern branch trough in wintertime. J. Appl. Meteorol. Sci.19, 731–740 (2008)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ding, F. &amp; Li, C. Subtropical Westerly jet waveguide and winter persistent heavy rainfall in South China. <italic>J. Geophys. Res.</italic><bold>122</bold>, 7385–7400 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ding, F. &amp; Li, C. Subtropical Westerly jet waveguide and winter persistent heavy rainfall in South China. J. Geophys. Res.122, 7385–7400 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Branstator, G. Circumglobal teleconnections, the jet stream waveguide, and the North Atlantic Oscillation. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 1893–1910 (2002).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Branstator, G. Circumglobal teleconnections, the jet stream waveguide, and the North Atlantic Oscillation. J. Clim.15, 1893–1910 (2002)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Huang, S., Li, X. &amp; Wen, Z. Characteristics and possible sources of the intraseasonal South Asian jet wave train in boreal winter. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>33</bold>, 10523–10537 (2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Huang, S., Li, X. &amp; Wen, Z. Characteristics and possible sources of the intraseasonal South Asian jet wave train in boreal winter. J. Clim.33, 10523–10537 (2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tang, Y., Huangfu, J., Huang, R. &amp; Chen, W. Simulation and projection of tropical cyclone activities over the Western North Pacific by CMIP6 highresmip. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 7771–7794 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tang, Y., Huangfu, J., Huang, R. &amp; Chen, W. Simulation and projection of tropical cyclone activities over the Western North Pacific by CMIP6 highresmip. J. Clim.35, 7771–7794 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mandal, M., Mohanty, U. C., Sinha, P. &amp; Ali, M. M. Impact of sea surface temperature in modulating movement and intensity of tropical cyclones. <italic>Nat. Hazards</italic>. <bold>41</bold>, 413–427 (2007).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mandal, M., Mohanty, U. C., Sinha, P. &amp; Ali, M. M. Impact of sea surface temperature in modulating movement and intensity of tropical cyclones. Nat. Hazards. 41, 413–427 (2007)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Corbosiero, K. L. &amp; Molinari, J. The relationship between storm Motion, vertical wind Shear, and convective asymmetries in tropical cyclones. <italic>J. Atmos. Sci.</italic><bold>60</bold>, 366–376 (2003).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Corbosiero, K. L. &amp; Molinari, J. The relationship between storm Motion, vertical wind Shear, and convective asymmetries in tropical cyclones. J. Atmos. Sci.60, 366–376 (2003)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pielke, R. Jr, Burgess, M. G. &amp; Ritchie, J. Plausible 2005–2050 emissions scenarios project between 2°C and 3°C of warming by 2100. <italic>Environ. Res. Lett.</italic><bold>17</bold>, 24027 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pielke, R. Jr, Burgess, M. G. &amp; Ritchie, J. Plausible 2005–2050 emissions scenarios project between 2°C and 3°C of warming by 2100. Environ. Res. Lett.17, 24027 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Knapp, K. R. et al. The international best track archive for climate stewardship (IBTrACS). <italic>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>91</bold>, 363–376 (2010).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Knapp, K. R. et al. The international best track archive for climate stewardship (IBTrACS). Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.91, 363–376 (2010)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Balaji, M., Chakraborty, A. &amp; Mandal, M. Changes in tropical cyclone activity in North Indian ocean during satellite era (1981–2014). <italic>Int. J. Climatol</italic>. <bold>38</bold>, 2819–2837 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Balaji, M., Chakraborty, A. &amp; Mandal, M. Changes in tropical cyclone activity in North Indian ocean during satellite era (1981–2014). Int. J. Climatol. 38, 2819–2837 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mondal, M. et al. Spatio-temporal behaviours of tropical cyclones over the Bay of Bengal basin in last five decades. <italic>Trop. Cyclone Res. Rev.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 1–15 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mondal, M. et al. Spatio-temporal behaviours of tropical cyclones over the Bay of Bengal basin in last five decades. Trop. Cyclone Res. Rev.11, 1–15 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tiwari, G., Kumar, P. &amp; Tiwari, P. The appraisal of tropical cyclones in the North Indian ocean: An overview of different approaches and the involvement of earth’s components. <italic>Front. Earth Sci.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 823090 (2022). </named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tiwari, G., Kumar, P. &amp; Tiwari, P. The appraisal of tropical cyclones in the North Indian ocean: An overview of different approaches and the involvement of earth’s components. Front. Earth Sci.10, 823090 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Eyring, V. et al. Overview of the coupled model intercomparison project phase 6 (CMIP6) experimental design and organization. <italic>Geosci. Model. Dev.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 1937–1958 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Eyring, V. et al. Overview of the coupled model intercomparison project phase 6 (CMIP6) experimental design and organization. Geosci. Model. Dev.9, 1937–1958 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu, J., Yuan, C. &amp; Luo, J. J. Impacts of model resolution on responses of Western North Pacific tropical cyclones to ENSO in the HighResMIP-PRIMAVERA ensemble. <italic>Front. Earth Sci.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 1169885 (2023). </named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liu, J., Yuan, C. &amp; Luo, J. J. Impacts of model resolution on responses of Western North Pacific tropical cyclones to ENSO in the HighResMIP-PRIMAVERA ensemble. Front. Earth Sci.11, 1169885 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Haarsma, R. J. et al. High resolution model intercomparison project (HighResMIP ~ v1.0) for CMIP6. <italic>Geosci. Model. Dev.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 4185–4208 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Haarsma, R. J. et al. High resolution model intercomparison project (HighResMIP ~ v1.0) for CMIP6. Geosci. Model. Dev.9, 4185–4208 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bell, R., Strachan, J., Vidale, P. L., Hodges, K. &amp; Roberts, M. Response of tropical cyclones to idealized climate change experiments in a global high-resolution coupled general circulation model. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 7966–7980 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bell, R., Strachan, J., Vidale, P. L., Hodges, K. &amp; Roberts, M. Response of tropical cyclones to idealized climate change experiments in a global high-resolution coupled general circulation model. J. Clim.26, 7966–7980 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Scoccimarro, E. et al. Tropical cyclone interaction with the ocean: the role of High-Frequency (Subdaily) coupled processes. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 145–162 (2017).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Scoccimarro, E. et al. Tropical cyclone interaction with the ocean: the role of High-Frequency (Subdaily) coupled processes. J. Clim.30, 145–162 (2017)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Vincent, E. M., Emanuel, K. A., Lengaigne, M., Vialard, J. &amp; Madec, G. Influence of upper ocean stratification interannual variability on tropical cyclones. <italic>J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.</italic><bold>6</bold>, 680–699 (2014).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Vincent, E. M., Emanuel, K. A., Lengaigne, M., Vialard, J. &amp; Madec, G. Influence of upper ocean stratification interannual variability on tropical cyclones. J. Adv. Model. Earth Syst.6, 680–699 (2014)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66"><named-content content-type="citation-string">O’Neill, B. C. et al. The scenario model intercomparison project (ScenarioMIP) for CMIP6. <italic>Geosci. Model. Dev.</italic><bold>9</bold>, 3461–3482 (2016).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="O’Neill, B. C. et al. The scenario model intercomparison project (ScenarioMIP) for CMIP6. Geosci. Model. Dev.9, 3461–3482 (2016)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chauvin, F., Royer, J. F. &amp; Déqué, M. Response of hurricane-type vortices to global warming as simulated by ARPEGE-Climat at high resolution. <italic>Clim. Dyn.</italic><bold>27</bold>, 377–399 (2006).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Chauvin, F., Royer, J. F. &amp; Déqué, M. Response of hurricane-type vortices to global warming as simulated by ARPEGE-Climat at high resolution. Clim. Dyn.27, 377–399 (2006)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tory, K. J., Dare, R. A., Davidson, N. E., McBride, J. L. &amp; Chand, S. S. The importance of low-deformation vorticity in tropical cyclone formation. <italic>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 2115–2132 (2013).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Tory, K. J., Dare, R. A., Davidson, N. E., McBride, J. L. &amp; Chand, S. S. The importance of low-deformation vorticity in tropical cyclone formation. Atmos. Chem. Phys.13, 2115–2132 (2013)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bell, S. S., Chand, S. S., Tory, K. J. &amp; Turville, C. Statistical assessment of the OWZ tropical cyclone tracking scheme in ERA-Interim. <italic>J. Clim.</italic><bold>31</bold>, 2217–2232 (2018).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bell, S. S., Chand, S. S., Tory, K. J. &amp; Turville, C. Statistical assessment of the OWZ tropical cyclone tracking scheme in ERA-Interim. J. Clim.31, 2217–2232 (2018)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh, V. K., Kim, H. J. &amp; Moon, I. J. Seasonal differences in tropical cyclone—induced sea surface cooling in the Western North Pacific. <italic>Q. J. R Meteorol. Soc.</italic><bold>150</bold>, 447–461 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Singh, V. K., Kim, H. J. &amp; Moon, I. J. Seasonal differences in tropical cyclone—induced sea surface cooling in the Western North Pacific. Q. J. R Meteorol. Soc.150, 447–461 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Deng, E. et al. Increasing Temporal stability of global tropical cyclone precipitation. <italic>Npj Clim. Atmos. Sci.</italic><bold>8</bold>, 11 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Deng, E. et al. Increasing Temporal stability of global tropical cyclone precipitation. Npj Clim. Atmos. Sci.8, 11 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bourdin, S., Fromang, S., Dulac, W., Cattiaux, J. &amp; Chauvin, F. Intercomparison of four algorithms for detecting tropical cyclones using ERA5. <italic>Geosci. Model. Dev.</italic><bold>15</bold>, 6759–6786 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bourdin, S., Fromang, S., Dulac, W., Cattiaux, J. &amp; Chauvin, F. Intercomparison of four algorithms for detecting tropical cyclones using ERA5. Geosci. Model. Dev.15, 6759–6786 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Singh, V. K., Roxy, M. K. &amp; Deshpande, M. Role of warm ocean conditions and the MJO in the genesis and intensification of extremely severe cyclone Fani. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 3607 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-021-82680-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7878906"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33574374"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Singh, V. K., Roxy, M. K. &amp; Deshpande, M. Role of warm ocean conditions and the MJO in the genesis and intensification of extremely severe cyclone Fani. Sci. Rep.11, 3607 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Taylor, K. E. Summarizing multiple aspects of model performance in a single diagram. <italic>J. Geophys. Res. Atmos.</italic><bold>106</bold>, 7183–7192 (2001).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Taylor, K. E. Summarizing multiple aspects of model performance in a single diagram. J. Geophys. Res. Atmos.106, 7183–7192 (2001)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR75"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ngoma, H. et al. Evaluation of precipitation simulations in CMIP6 models over Uganda. <italic>Int. J. Climatol</italic>. <bold>41</bold>, 4743–4768 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ngoma, H. et al. Evaluation of precipitation simulations in CMIP6 models over Uganda. Int. J. Climatol. 41, 4743–4768 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Randriatsara, H. H. R. H. et al. Performance evaluation of CMIP6 highresmip models in simulating precipitation over Madagascar. <italic>Int. J. Climatol</italic>. <bold>43</bold>, 5401–5421 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Randriatsara, H. H. R. H. et al. Performance evaluation of CMIP6 highresmip models in simulating precipitation over Madagascar. Int. J. Climatol. 43, 5401–5421 (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2026_35482_MOESM1_ESM.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path 6dd6/12891732/2449c59d77c4/41598_2026_35482_MOESM1_ESM.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2192588?><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The TC data is obtained from the India Meteorological Department (IMD) as archived in the IBTrACS dataset and is available at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/ibtracs/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/ibtracs/</ext-link>. The data of reanalysis winds at 250 hPa is obtained from European Center for Medium Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) fifth-generation global atmospheric reanalysis (ERA5) dataset and is available at (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets" ext-link-type="uri">https://cds.climate.copernicus.eu/datasets</ext-link>) . The CMIP6 HighResMIP historical simulation and future projection data is openly available at (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.ceda.ac.uk/badc/cmip6/data/CMIP6/HighResMIP" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.ceda.ac.uk/badc/cmip6/data/CMIP6/HighResMIP</ext-link>). The variables in the CMIP6-HighResMIP models are available at (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://data.ceda.ac.uk/badc/cmip6/data/CMIP6/HighResMIP" ext-link-type="uri">https://data.ceda.ac.uk/badc/cmip6/data/CMIP6/HighResMIP</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec></body></article>