<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">51</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmcnurs</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Nursing</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>BMC Nurs</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13235141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13235141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13235141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">42237339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12912-026-04812-8</article-id><title-group><article-title>Climate change-related stress and premenstrual symptoms among nursing students: the moderating role of climate change awareness and the mediating role of eco-anxiety</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Aly</surname><given-names initials="NAEFM">Nagah Abd El-Fattah Mohamed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shanawany</surname><given-names initials="SM">Safaa M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanem</surname><given-names initials="MA">Maha Abdelhamied</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Fayad</surname><given-names initials="EMAEK">Elham Mohamed Abd El Kader</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotfy</surname><given-names initials="WM">Wael M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Nursing Administration, Faculty of Nursing, Matrouh University, Mersa Matrouh, Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Forensic Medicine and Clinical Toxicology, Faculty of Medicine, Alexandria University, Alexandria, Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Psychiatric Nursing and Mental health, Faculty of Nursing, Alexandria University, Alexandria, Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Community Health Nursing, Faculty of Nursing, Matrouh University, Mersa Matrouh, Egypt </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>3</day><month>6</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><fpage>505</fpage><page-range>505</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12912_2026_Article_4812.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path e1be/13235141/126264c9a78a/12912_2026_Article_4812.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 2685196?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1"><title>Abstract</title><sec id="sec1" disp-level="2"><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Nursing students are future nurses. They are more susceptible to the physiological and psychological implications of climate change because of their participation in climate activities.</p></sec><sec id="sec2" disp-level="2"><title>Aim</title><p id="Par2">To assess the relationships among nursing students’ climate change awareness, climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety; and the associations between their climate change-related stress and their eco-anxiety and premenstrual syndrome.</p></sec><sec id="sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par3">A cross-sectional correlational study was conducted on a convenience sample of 400 female nursing students at Matrouh University via self-report questionnaires about climate change knowledge and awareness, perceived stress, eco-anxiety and premenstrual syndrome. The data were collected from January 2022 to June 2025. Hierarchical multiple regression analysis was performed to analyze the effects of the mediating and moderating variables.</p></sec><sec id="sec4" disp-level="2"><title>Results</title><p id="Par4">Nursing students demonstrated satisfactory levels of knowledge and high levels of awareness of climate change. High climate change awareness among nursing students was coupled with moderate (53.2%) to severe (28.6%) climate change-related stress, whereas 54.9% of the students experienced moderate (46.2%) to severe (8.7%) levels of eco-anxiety. Regression analysis revealed that the relationship between nursing students’ climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety was moderated via climate change awareness as a moderating factor. Eco-anxiety played a mediating role in the relationship between climate change-related stress and premenstrual syndrome among nursing students.</p></sec><sec id="sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par5">Nursing students suffer from mental stress related to climate change, including climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety, due to increased climate change awareness. Climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety increased the prevalence of premenstrual syndrome among nursing students.</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group1" xml:lang="en" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Climate change, Knowledge, Awareness, Stress, Eco-anxiety, Premenstrual syndrome, Nursing, Students</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2026 Mar 27; Accepted 2026 May 15; Collection date 2026.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par6">Climate change is a significant global challenge and poses an existential threat to the health and well-being of humans [<xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Climate change impacts on human health outcomes include increases in mortality and morbidity due to natural disasters and extreme weather events; increases in the frequency and intensity of food-, water-, and vector-borne infectious diseases; the exacerbation of chronic diseases; and increases in mental health problems and stressors [<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The World Health Organization (WHO) predicts that climate-sensitive diseases will cause approximately 250,000 extra deaths between 2030 and 2050, with the greatest impacts being felt by the most vulnerable populations [<xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. </p><p id="Par7">Climate change is perceived as among the greatest potential threats to women’s health in the twenty-first century [<xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Women are among the most vulnerable population segments in the face of climate change in many areas. Those living in regions with low economic and social status are even more affected by the negative consequences of climate change [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Various climate‐related events, such as extreme heat and increased average seasonal temperatures, poor air quality, and natural disasters, have a negative impact on mental health, significantly affect sexual and reproductive health outcomes and increase the mortality rates of women [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. </p><p id="Par8">Women may encounter various emotional problems that affect their mental and menstrual health. One of these negative emotions appears to be climate stress and climate change anxiety [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Women are more susceptible to the development of climate-related stress, worry and anxiety than men are [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Climate change induces a variety of stressors, including extreme weather events, food insecurity, and biodiversity loss. These stressors, coupled with social unrest and uncertainty about the future, can lead to feelings of anxiety, sadness, hopelessness, and helplessness [<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. </p><p id="Par9">Stress and anxiety resulting from individual and environmental factors cause women to become vulnerable to changes in menstrual cycle length and/or negative changes in symptoms [<xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Climate stress and eco-anxiety can influence hormonal fluctuations, neurotransmitter levels, and overall physiological functioning, which can affect premenstrual syndrome (PMS) symptoms. Climate stress and eco-anxiety can affect the hypothalamic‒pituitary‒adrenal axis, which plays a role in regulating the levels of hormones, including those involved in the menstrual cycle. Thus, climate stress and eco-anxiety influence women’s hormonal cycles and are expected to increase the incidence and intensity of premenstrual syndrome (PMS) [<xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. </p><p id="Par10">Similarly, in female nursing students, climatic changes can directly or indirectly lead to a range of mental and menstrual health problems [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. As nurses, they feel that they have a degree of social responsibility and a professional role in avoiding and minimizing health risks and hazards associated with climate change in community settings. In health care settings, they also play a role in educating patients about the effects of climate change on health [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. </p><p id="Par11">Increasing nursing students’ awareness and knowledge of climate change and its consequences can heighten their emotional and cognitive response [<xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. They are disproportionately distressed and concerned about climate change, often experiencing strong emotional reactions, even if they have not yet been directly impacted [<xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. </p><p id="Par12">Studies have shown that exposure to climate-related events is associated with greater climate change awareness, knowledge, stress and anxiety [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–<xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Recent research has revealed a complex relationship between stress, anxiety and PMS, with stress and anxiety acting as both risk factors for and consequences of premenstrual symptoms [<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. </p><p id="Par13">In this respect, a well-developed understanding of the associations between female nursing students’ awareness and knowledge of climate change and their mental and menstrual health is critical for developing effective strategies for addressing the consequences of climate change for women’s health. Understanding these associations is also critical for developing effective mental and menstrual health interventions to meet women’s health needs in the context of climate challenges [<xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. </p><p id="Par14">Some studies have focused mainly on the level of awareness of climate change and its association with climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety among nursing students and medical students [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]; however, very little attention has been given to exploring the translation of climate change-related stress into climate change anxiety among nursing and medical students, and they have not focused on climate change awareness as a moderating factor in the relationship between nursing students’ climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. </p><p id="Par15">High worries about the environment and eco-anxiety are also associated with more severe PMS [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. However, there is a paucity of research regarding the effects of mental health problems related to climate change on PMS and women’s health in the literature [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. </p><p id="Par16">Although there has been increasing interest in the consequences of climate change for women’s psychological, sexual and reproductive health worldwide and in Egypt, studies exploring the relationships among knowledge about climate change, eco-anxiety and PMS remain limited [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Additionally, to our knowledge, no studies examining the relationships among awareness of climate change, climate stress, eco-anxiety and PMS in female nursing students have been conducted. Therefore, the present study aims to address this gap.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>General objective</title><p id="Par17">The present study aimed to assess the relationships among nursing students’ climate change awareness, climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety; and the associations between their climate change-related stress and their eco-anxiety and premenstrual syndrome through the following:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par18">Investigating relationships between female nursing students’ awareness and knowledge about climate change and their impact on women’s health, and their climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">Identifying the relationship between nursing students’ climate change-related stress and their eco-anxiety.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par20">Exploring the moderating role of female nursing students’ awareness of climate change in the relationship between their climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par21">Identifying relationships between climate change-related stress, eco-anxiety and PMS among female nursing students.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par22">Exploring the mediating role of nursing students’ eco-anxiety in the relationships between their climate change-related stress and PMS.</p></list-item></list><p id="Par23"><bold>Operational definitions</bold>:</p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par25"><bold>Climate change-related stress</bold> refers to perceived climate stress and involves a range of negative mental, emotional and physical distress responses to climate change, which are often triggered by climate change events and threats. It can manifest as frustration, anger or nervousness, fear, worry, hopelessness, helplessness and sadness about environmental changes and their future impacts [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par26"><bold>Eco-anxiety</bold> refers to anxiety related to climate change. It is characterized by chronic fear of environmental doom, persistent worries and continuous stress that stem from climate change threats and the inadequacy of climate action [<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par27"><bold>Premenstrual syndrome (PMS)</bold> is a disruptive group of emotional and physical symptoms that regularly occur during the luteal phase of a woman’s menstrual cycle, which is the phase between ovulation and the onset of menstruation [<xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p></list-item></list>
<sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Theories and hypotheses framework (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>)</title><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Conceptual framework of the present study</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e635" xlink:href="12912_2026_4812_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1be/13235141/6dcfafd82e83/12912_2026_4812_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1206?><?original-width 2976?><?scaled-height 302?><?scaled-width 744?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="12912_2026_4812_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1be/13235141/611751703765/12912_2026_4812_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><sec id="FPar1" disp-level="3"><title>H1</title><p id="Par28">Female nursing students’ awareness of and knowledge about climate change and its impact on women’s health are positively associated with their climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety.</p><p>Climate change affects human health, including mental health and well-being [<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The increased occurrence and intensity of extreme weather events, such as heat waves and floods, can produce and intensify mental health stressors [<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Awareness and knowledge of current climate impacts and impending risks, coupled with perceived inaction, can contribute to the mental and physiological health burden of climate change [<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. </p><p>Awareness and knowledge of climate change can lead to stress and anxiety through direct experience of extreme weather and indirect exposure via media and general concern about the future. Experiencing traumatic events, such as hurricanes, floods and wildfires, and repeatedly seeing or reading about environmental devastation, scientific reports and slow action by environmental institutions cause significant psychological trauma and stressors [<xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. As a result of the rising climate crisis, it becomes apparent that the more people feel helpless in their ability to take action, the more they experience a sense of stress, hopelessness and anxiety [<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. </p><p>According to the transactional model of stress and coping and in the context of climate change, exposure to environmental stressors serves as the initiating condition (primary appraisal), which has been hypothesized to increase awareness of climate-related threats. This awareness can influence individuals’ emotional responses (e.g., stress and anxiety) both directly and indirectly through their coping strategies, such as meaning-focused or problem-focused coping [<xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. </p><p>Recent studies in different countries revealed that medical and nursing students with greater awareness and knowledge of climate change were more likely to experience psychological distress, climate-related stress, eco-anxiety and hopelessness [<xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–<xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. </p></sec><sec id="FPar2" disp-level="3"><title>H2</title><p id="Par33">Nursing students’ climate change-related stress is positively associated with their eco-anxiety.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3" disp-level="3"><title>H3</title><p id="Par34">Female nursing students’ awareness will moderate the relationship between female nursing students’ climate change-related stress and their eco-anxiety, and this relationship will be stronger when their perceptions of climate change are acceptable or high.</p><p>The transactional model of stress and coping (1984), appraisal (1990) and analysis of Pihkala (2020) theories provide a helpful framework for understanding how awareness of climate change is associated with climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety. These theories are based on the stress response mechanism [<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. </p><p>According to the transactional model of stress and coping theory (1984), stress is a dynamic process arising from the interaction between individuals and their environment. This theory has also been used to understand individuals’ emotional response to climate change and how an individual’s evaluation of a climate stressor affects their coping strategies and ways to respond to it [<xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. </p><p>When individuals are exposed to information about climate change, they may perceive it as a significant threat to their well-being, and the environment serves as an initiating condition (primary appraisal), which has been hypothesized to increase awareness of climate-related threats such as climate stressors. They also appraise climate change as a distant threat that reflects a transactional process in which their cognitive evaluation of the situation influences their emotional response (secondary appraisal). This awareness can influence individuals’ emotional responses (e.g., stress) both directly and indirectly through assessing their coping resources and strategies for addressing the perceived threats that lead to mental health stressors known as climate change-related stress. Persistent and continuous climate change-related stress can cause eco-anxiety (reappraisal). These factors contribute to variations in climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety levels [<xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. </p><p>According to appraisal theory (1990), stress is viewed as an emotional response to perceived danger or threat. This may imply that individuals may perceive climate change as a significant threat that triggers emotional responses leading to persistent mental health stressors known as climate change-related stress, especially when they are exposed to information about its potential impacts, which may result in heightened eco-anxiety [<xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. </p><p>In the context of the theory of analysis of Pihkala (2020) [<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], knowledge and awareness of climate change and its consequences can lead to many emotional responses and persistent climate change-related stress, leading to eco-anxiety. Awareness about climate change and its effects can cause a variety of emotions, including guilt, sadness, and anger, all of which contribute to the stress and anxiety associated with climate change. Stress and anxiety can frequently be exacerbated by the constant onslaught of unsettling news about environmental loss and deterioration or the uncertainty of the future, coupled with a sense of hopelessness. Eco-anxiety and climate change-related stress are terms used to describe this condition [<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. </p><p>Recent studies in different countries revealed that medical and nursing students with greater awareness and knowledge of climate change were more likely to experience psychological distress, climate-related stress, eco-anxiety and hopelessness [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–<xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. </p></sec><sec id="FPar4" disp-level="3"><title>H4</title><p id="Par41">Female nursing students’ climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety are positively associated with their PMS.</p><p>The increased occurrence and intensity of extreme weather events, such as heat waves and floods, can produce and intensify mental health stressors [<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. As a result of climate stress, feelings of worry, sadness, hopelessness and helplessness are exacerbated. These feelings have long been associated with the development of anxiety [<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. </p><p>Climate anxiety is a stressor that can affect one’s behavior, mood, lifestyle, cognitive function, physical health and/or psychological well-being [<xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Hormonal imbalance can also be induced by climate stress and eco-anxiety, which may affect menstrual health.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5" disp-level="3"><title>H5</title><p id="Par44">The relationship between female nursing students’ climate change-related stress and PMS is mediated by their eco-anxiety.</p><p>Exacerbating climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety due to changes in dopamine and serotonin levels resulting from the effects of extreme heat is more prevalent in women. Women are more susceptible to the development of climate-related stress, worry and anxiety [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Numerous studies have highlighted that gender inequality, in particular, exacerbates the severity of the negative effects of climate change on women’s health [<xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Furthermore, previous studies have indicated a correlation between relative humidity and mental health outcomes, including depression, stress, anxiety, and suicide attempts, particularly in women [<xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. </p><p>The stress and anxiety associated with climate change can affect PMS both directly and indirectly [<xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Stress induces a hormonal imbalance that regulates the menstrual cycle, leading to disruptions in the menstrual cycle and PMS, affecting fertility and overall well-being [<xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–<xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. This hormonal imbalance can exacerbate PMS symptoms or make them more challenging to manage [<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. </p><p>Therefore, climate change-related stress, along with eco-anxiety, can trigger worsening menstrual symptoms, disrupt menstrual health, be a significant predictor of PMS and potentially exacerbate PMS symptoms for up to two subsequent cycles [<xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="CR46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. A study reported that higher levels of climate change anxiety are linked to a greater prevalence and severity of PMS symptoms. Increasing stress can worsen PMS symptoms and even heighten premenstrual symptoms for up to two subsequent cycles [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. </p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="1"><title>Materials &amp; methods</title><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Study settings</title><p id="Par49">This study was carried out at the Faculty of Nursing at Matrouh University, which is located on the Mediterranean coast. Like all coastal cities, coastal cities are exposed to sea level rise, intensified storm surges and coastal erosion and face great challenges in managing the significant growth of climate change exposure.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="2"><title>Study design</title><p id="Par50">This was a cross-sectional correlational study, and causality cannot be inferred.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="2"><title>Study sampling and participants</title><p id="Par51">Cochran’s formula (1963) [<xref rid="CR48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] (n = z<sup>2</sup> p (1-p)/d<sup>2</sup>) was employed to estimate samples via a 5% margin of error (d) and 95% confidence level (Z). According to the students’ registration records at Matrouh University, approximately 50% of the total nursing students (p) registered were females. The minimum required sample size was 385, and the actual sample size was 400 female nursing students.</p><p id="Par52">A convenience sample of female students enrolled from the first academic year to the final academic year and internship students were eligible to participate in the study.</p><p id="Par53">The study sample was chosen on the basis of the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The inclusion criteria consisted of female nursing students who were willing to participate in the study and who signed informed consent forms. The exclusion criteria included female nursing students with diagnosed endocrine disorders, psychiatric conditions and hormone-related medications; students who were unwilling to participate in the study; and those who did not provide informed consent.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="1"><title>Study tools</title>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par55"><bold>Demographic tool</bold>: The control variables used to remove extraneous influences included nursing students’ demographic characteristics, such as age, marital status and place of residence.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par56"><bold>Menstrual tool: Menstrual variables</bold> included menstrual characteristics, such as age at menarche, amount, rhythm, duration, interval, and physical and psychological changes before menstruation.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par57"><bold>Climate change awareness scale</bold>: This scale was developed by Lopez and Malay (2019) [<xref rid="CR49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] on the basis of Ezeudu (2016) [<xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] to measure climate change awareness among nursing students. It is composed of 15 items ranked on a five-point Likert scale ranging from strongly disagree (1) to strongly agree (5). The total score was 75 and was classified as very low awareness (15–27 points), low (28–39 points), moderate (40–51 points), high (52–63 points), or extremely high awareness (64–75 points).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par58"><bold>Knowledge scale of women’s health impacts on climate change</bold>: Fifteen items were adopted from the studies of Mekawy (2023) [<xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] (5 items), Saglam &amp; Sahin. (2024) [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] (6 items) and Er et al. (2024) [<xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] (4 items) to evaluate nursing students’ knowledge of the impact of climate change on women’s health. The answers of the nursing students were between yes (1) and no. (0), and I do not think I am affected (0.5). The total score was 12 points. The nursing students were considered satisfied when the total score was 9 points (≥ 60%).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par59"><bold>Perceived Stress Scale (PSS-10)</bold>: The modified PSS-10 was developed by ‏Cohen et al. (1983) [<xref rid="CR53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and consists of 10 items on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from never (0) to very often (4). The tool was used to measure how often the nursing students experienced feelings of stress or strain related to climate change in the past month.</p></list-item></list>
<p id="Par60">To estimate the level of perceived stress, the responses of the nursing students to the negative items were scored from never (0) to very often (4), and the responses of the nursing students to the positively phrased items (typically items 4, 5, 7, and 8) were reversed, where “0” became “4,” “1” became “3,” and so forth. These reversed scores, along with the scores of the remaining items, are then summed to calculate the total score. The total scores ranged from 0 to 40 and were classified as follows: (a) low stress (scores ranging from 0 to 13), moderate stress (scores ranging from 14 to 26) and high stress (scores ranging from 27 to 40).</p>
<list list-type="label"><list-item><label>(6).</label><p id="Par62"><bold>Eco-anxiety scale</bold>: A 13-point scale was developed by Türkarslan (2023) [<xref rid="CR54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] to evaluate climate anxiety symptoms experienced within the past two weeks‏ among nursing students. Each item is scored on a four-point Likert scale (0 = not at all to 3 = nearly every day). According to Schwaab et al. (2022) [<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], scores range from 0 to 39, with higher scores reflecting higher levels of anxiety. The cutoff points for anxiety were 0–7 (minimal), 8–15 (mild anxiety), 16–24 (moderate), and 25 − 9 (severe). Schwaab et al. (2022 [<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] scores linked anxiety and climate change and accurately reflected the level of climate anxiety among nursing students in an Egyptian study [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><label>(7).</label><p id="Par63"><bold>Premenstrual symptoms scale</bold>: A 14-point Likert scale (1 = not at all, 4 = severe) was developed by Choijiljav et al. (2024) [<xref rid="CR55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] to assess the level of premenstrual symptoms in the past one to three months among nursing students from their perspective. The total score ranged between 14 and 56 points and was classified according to Steiner et al.’s criteria (2003) [<xref rid="CR56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] as not having PMS (0–14 points), mild PMS (15–28 points), moderate PMS (29–42 points), or severe PMS (≥ 43 points).</p></list-item></list>
</sec><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="1"><title>Validity and reliability measures</title><p id="Par64">To ensure that the study tools were applicable to Egyptian nursing students, psychometric tests were established through validity (face and content validity) and reliability measures (interrater, test-retest and consistency reliabilities). The study tools were assessed by five experts for face and content validation. The experts evaluated the relevance of each item of the study tools. They were asked if all the items were clearly worded and would not be misinterpreted. They were also asked to provide their suggestions and comments for the addition or omission of items.</p><p id="Par65">According to the experts’ comments, no adjustments or modifications were needed, and the study tools were found to be clear and understandable. Agreement and consensus among experts regarding importance, appropriateness and clarity were estimated for interrater reliability via the content validity index (CVI). An average CVI of each item ≥ 0.80 indicated that the questionnaire had high content validity [<xref rid="CR57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The study tools were translated into Arabic and back-translated into English by researchers.</p><p id="Par66">Test‒retest reliability was assessed via a pilot study. Forty nursing students (10% of the sample size) were included to ensure the applicability of the study in terms of the understandability and relevance of the items and to estimate the time required to complete the study tools. Forty nursing students completed the same study tools repeatedly at two different times. Those students were later excluded from the study.</p><p id="Par67">Test–retest reliability was assessed after three weeks in the same 40 nursing students. The test-retest reliability was 0.89 for knowledge of women’s health impacts of climate change, 0.84 for climate change awareness, 0.76 for perceived stress, 0.86 for eco-anxiety, and 0.79 for premenstrual symptoms. The internal consistency reliability was evaluated via Cronbach’s alpha coefficient and was 0.89 for the knowledge scale of women’s health impacts from climate change, 0.78 for the perceived stress scale, 0.83 for the climate anxiety scale and 0.95 for the premenstrual symptom scale.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="1"><title>Data collection</title><p id="Par68">The data were collected from the study nursing students via seven self-report tools. The researchers met the nursing students in lecture rooms to explain the objectives of the study and how to fill out the questionnaires, answer any doubts, and address any queries about the questionnaire and study. The data were collected from January 2022 to June 2025 and from Saturday to Thursday between 9 am and 2 pm. This period was considered a suitable time for the nursing students to complete the study tools. Study tools were distributed among 425 students at the beginning of lectures in the lecture rooms under the guidance of the researchers. The researchers collected the completed questionnaires at the end of the nursing students’ lectures and reviewed each collected questionnaire for completeness. Four hundred completed questionnaires were returned, and the response rate was 94.1%. To increase the response rate, researchers wrote the questionnaire in simple and clear Arabic and provided book notes and pens to increase the response rate among nursing students.</p><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="2"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par69">SPSS version 27 was used to analyze the data. The percentage, mean, and standard deviation were employed to describe personal characteristics (demographic and menstrual characteristics) and knowledge variables, dependent variables (premenstrual symptoms), independent variables (climate stress), a mediating variable (climate anxiety) and a moderating variable (climate change awareness). The relationships between the dependent and independent variables and test‒retest reliability were evaluated via Pearson correlation coefficient analyses. Interconsistency reliability was analyzed via Cronbach’s alpha.</p><p id="Par70">Hierarchical multiple regression analysis was used to analyze the effects of the mediating and moderating variables. Thresholds of R<sup>2</sup> are 0.02 (small), 0.15 (medium), and 0.35 (large). The bootstrapping repeated sampling method was used to sample 5000 times to obtain the path coefficients of the mediation model and ensure the mediating effect. The moderation effect and conditional effects were estimated via the SPSS PROCESS macro v4.3. The interaction effect of the moderating analysis was presented via simple slope analysis and graphical presentation.</p><p id="Par71">The data were analyzed without including control variables in the regression analysis. Nursing students’ demographic characteristics (such as age, marital status, and place of residence) were measured and controlled to avoid the effects of their demographic characteristics on the results. The data were analyzed without including age, marital status, or place of residence in the analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="2"><title>Demographic and menstruation characteristics</title><p id="Par72">Among the 400 nursing students, 97.5% were between 19 and 23 years of age, 95.5% were identified as single with no history of previous marriage, and 55.8% resided in urban areas. In addition, the nursing students acquired their information from media platforms (54.2%) and the nursing curriculum (25.0%) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Personal and menstrual characteristics of the nursing students (<italic>n</italic> = 400)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No. (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Amount</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold>:</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scant</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (4.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≤ 18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6 (1.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">356 (89.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19–23</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">390 (97.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heavy</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28 (7.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥ 24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4 (1.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Rhythm</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Marital status</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Regular</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274 (68.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Single</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">382 (95.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Irregular</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126 (31.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Married</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14(3.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Interval (days)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Divorced</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4(1.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≤ 24</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101 (25.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Place of residence</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25–34</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">253(63.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urban</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">223 (55.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35–44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (6.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rural</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177 (44.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">≥ 45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20 (5.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Source of climate change information *</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Duration days</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nursing curriculum</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100(25.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1–5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">274 (68.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Conference</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10 (2.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6–10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">126(31.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mass media</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">217 (54.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Physical changes before menstruation</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Website</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73 (18.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">346 (86.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age at menarche (Years)</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No.</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54 (13.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9–12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">112(28.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Psychological changes before menstruation</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13–16</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">244 (61.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">386 (96.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17–20</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44 (11.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14 (3.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p78"><p>*Not mutually exclusive</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p id="Par73">Among the same 400 students, 61.0% were aged at menarche between 13 and 16 years, 68.5% had a regular rhythm for one to five days, 89.0% had a moderate amount of menstruation, and 63.2% had an interval of 25–34 days. A total of 86.5% of the nursing students experienced physical changes before menstruation, whereas 96.5% experienced psychological changes (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="2"><title>Descriptive statistics, relationships and comparisons</title><p id="Par75">The nursing students had a high level of climate change awareness (70.5%) and a satisfactory level of knowledge of the impacts of climate change (73.7%) on women’s health. A total of 81.7% of the nursing students were exposed to moderate (53.0%) or high levels of stress (28.7%), with an overall mean score of 26.01 ± 5.43%, whereas 54.9% of the students were exposed to moderate (46.2%) or severe levels of anxiety (8.7%), with an overall mean score of 24.11 ± 6.08%.</p><p id="Par76">Additionally, 83.0% of them exhibited moderate to severe PMS, with an overall mean score of 39.22 ± 4.06. Climate stress was positively correlated with eco-anxiety (<italic>r</italic>=.62, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). Climate change awareness was positively correlated with climate stress (<italic>r</italic> = .66, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) and eco-anxiety (<italic>r</italic> = .48, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). Additionally, knowledge had a significant positive relationship with climate stress (<italic>r</italic> = .64, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) and eco-anxiety (<italic>r</italic> = .38, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01) (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Descriptive analysis and relationships between study variables among the nursing students (<italic>n</italic> = 400)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Climate change</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Prevalence/<break/>Level</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">No. (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Scores</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Relationships</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Min–Max</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">1- Awareness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Very low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2(0.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">15–75</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">52.66 ± 17.82</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26 (6.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90 (22.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">282 (70.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">5- Knowledge</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Satisfactory</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">295 (73.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2–15</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">8.35 ± 2.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Unsatisfactory</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">105 (26.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">7- Stress</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mild</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73(18.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">6–40</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">26.01 ± 5.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.66**</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.64**</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">212 (53.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Severe</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115 (28.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">10- Anxiety</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Minimal</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">65(16.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">0–39</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">24.11 ± 6.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.48**</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.38*</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">0.62**</td><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mild</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">115(28.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">185 (46.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Severe</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35 (8.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">14- PMS*</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Present</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">332 (83.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">14–56</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">39.22 ± 4.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.58**</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.46**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Absent</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68(17.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p83"><p>*Present (moderate to severe), absent (mild or not at all)</p><p>** Significant at ≤ 0.05</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p id="Par78">An independent sample t-test revealed differences between the present PMS group and the absence of PMS groups of nursing students in terms of the mean scores of climate stress (mean ± SD = 26.01 ± 5.43 and 16.64 ± 5.12, respectively; t = 2.881, <italic>p</italic>&lt; .05) and anxiety (mean ± SD= 24.11 ± 6.08 and 18.85 ± 5.20, respectively; t = 6.331, <italic>p</italic>&lt; .05) (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of nursing students’ climate stress and anxiety between the present and absent PMS groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">PMS</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Climate stress<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 400)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Min–Max</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">t test<break/>(Sig.)</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Climate anxiety<break/>(<italic>n</italic> = 400)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mean ± SD</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Min–Max</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">t test<break/>(Sig.)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low<break/>No. (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate<break/>No. (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Severe<break/>No.<break/>(%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Minimal<break/>No. (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mild<break/>No. (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate<break/>No. (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Severe<break/>No. (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Present</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17 (2.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">372 (62.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>121</p><p>(20.2)</p></td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">6–40</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26.01 ± 5.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2.881 (0.007)<bold>*</bold></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21(3.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27 (4.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">327(54.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">139 (23.2)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.11 ± 6.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0–39</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><p>6.331</p><p>(0.000)<bold>*</bold></p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Absent</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (2.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74(12.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0(0.0)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.64 ± 5.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9 (1.5)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16 (2.7)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41(6.8)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20(3.3)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.85 ± 5.20</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p92"><p>*<italic>p-</italic>value was considered significant at ≤ 0.05</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="Sec15" disp-level="2"><title>Regression analysis of the moderation effect</title><p id="Par80">The final hierarchical regression analysis in Model 1 revealed a significant impact of climate stress on climate anxiety (Beta = 0.62, <italic>p</italic> ≤ .01). <bold>In Model 2</bold>, climate change awareness added to the model significantly (<italic>β</italic> = 0.38) and predicted eco-anxiety, and this model explained 55.8% of the eco-anxiety.</p><p id="Par81"><bold>In Model 3</bold>, a positive direct effect of climate change awareness on climate anxiety was found when it interacted with climate stress (Beta = 0.32, <italic>p</italic> ≤ .01) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The effects of increasing climate change awareness on eco-anxiety when interacting with climate stress are shown in Model 3 (B=0.29, <italic>R</italic> = 66.3%, F = 40.307, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). An increase in R<sup>2</sup> and a positive statistically significant F test were shown in models 1, 2 and 3 (<italic>R</italic> = 38.9%, F = 83.693, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>= 55.8%, F = 62.446, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01 and <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>= 66.3%, F = 40.307, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01, respectively). Therefore, climate change awareness had a positive moderating effect on the correlation between climate stress and anxiety (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>; Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Results of the moderating test</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Model</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Climate anxiety</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B (SE)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">t (sig.)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic>R</italic> square</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F test (sig.)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Climate stress</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56 (0.10)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.904(0.000)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.389</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83.693 (0.000)**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Climate stress</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.50 (0.08)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.113 (0.000)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.558</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">62.446(0.000)**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Climate change awareness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.38 (0.05)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.39**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.797(0.006)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Climate stress</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.57 (0.13)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.59**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.302 (0.000)</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.663</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">40.307 (0.000)**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Climate change awareness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35 (0.09)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">. 35**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.725(0.000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><p>Interaction</p><p>(Climate stress * Climate change awareness)</p></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29 (07)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.32**</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.073 (0.000)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p99"><p>Unstandardized Coefficients: B and Std. Error (SE); Path Coefficients: Beta (β) **<italic>p</italic> values were significant at ≤ 0. 01</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Summaries of the mediating and moderating analyses</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1826" xlink:href="12912_2026_4812_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1be/13235141/f4f4027825a0/12912_2026_4812_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2251?><?original-width 2976?><?scaled-height 563?><?scaled-width 744?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="12912_2026_4812_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1be/13235141/f46159aebbf5/12912_2026_4812_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec16" disp-level="2"><title>Regression analysis of the mediation effect</title><p id="Par83">Hierarchical regression analyses illustrated in the <bold>first model</bold> in the mediating analysis that climate stress significantly affected eco-anxiety (β = 0.62; <italic>p</italic> <bold>≤</bold> 0. 01) and PMS (β = 0.58; <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01). Climate stress significantly predicted eco-anxiety (B= 0.56, F = 83.693, p <bold>≤</bold> 0. 01) and PMS (B= 0.97, F = 101.149, <italic>p</italic> <bold>≤</bold> 0. 01). Climate stressors accounted for 38.9% of the eco-anxiety symptoms and 33.9% of the premenstrual symptoms (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>; Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Mediating effect of climate change anxiety</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Model</th><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Test (1)</th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Test (2)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Anxiety</th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">PMS</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SE</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta<italic>**</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">t (sig.)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">B</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">SE</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Beta<italic>**</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">t (sig.)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Stress</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.106</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.62</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.904(0.000)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.58</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10.05(0.000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><p>R square = 0.389</p><p>F test = 83.693**</p></td><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><p>R square = 0.339</p><p>F test = 101.149**</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>stress</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="4"/><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.183 (0.000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>anxiety</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.073 (0.000)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><p>R square = 0.416</p><p>F test = 69.792 **</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p110"><p>Unstandardized Coefficients: B and Std. Error (SE); Path Coefficients: Beta (β) **p values were significant at ≤ 0. 01</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p id="Par84"><bold>In the second model</bold>, when eco-anxiety was added, climate change-related stress significantly increased (β = 0.47; <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0. 01) and predicted PMS (B = 0.79). On the other hand, eco-anxiety significantly (<italic>β</italic> = 0.29; <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0. 01) predicted premenstrual symptoms (B = 0.31, <italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> = 41.6%, F = 69.792, <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0. 01), demonstrating that climate change mediated the relationship between climate stress and premenstrual symptoms among female nursing students (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>; Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17" disp-level="2"><title>Conditional analysis of the moderation effect</title><p id="Par87">The relationship between climate stress and eco-anxiety was positively moderated by nursing students’ climate change awareness. The conditional effect of stress was stronger and significant at a high level of climate change awareness (conditional effect = 0.60 with a 95% CI of 0.44– 0.77, SE =. 08, <italic>t</italic> = 7<italic>.12</italic>, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) and was significant at a moderate level of climate change awareness (conditional effect = 0.46 with a 95% CI of 0.25– 0.68, SE = 0.10, <italic>t</italic> = 4:28, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). Additionally, it was positive and significant at a low level of climate change awareness (conditional effect = 0.35 with a 95% CI of. 18- 0.51, SE = 0.07, <italic>t</italic> = 3.45, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05) (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>; Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab6" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Moderator effect of climate change awareness</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderator variable</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderator level</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effect</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SE</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">t</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI (LL)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI (UL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Awareness</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Low</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">. 51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.28</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.60</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.12</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.77</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p116"><p>Significance at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Moderating effect of climate change awareness on the relationship between nursing students’ climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1961" xlink:href="12912_2026_4812_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1be/13235141/5ac7ea04d02d/12912_2026_4812_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1958?><?original-width 2976?><?scaled-height 490?><?scaled-width 744?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="12912_2026_4812_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/e1be/13235141/8d8c5b404559/12912_2026_4812_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec18" disp-level="2"><title>Bootstrapping analysis of mediating effects</title><p id="Par90">The results of the bootstrapping procedure with 5000 resamples revealed the indirect and mediating roles of climate change-related stress on PMS through climate anxiety β = 0.31, with a 95% <italic>CI</italic> of 0.18–43, t = 5.073, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 excluding 0, whereas the total effect of climate change-related stress on PMS was also found (β = 0.97 <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05). Similarly, climate stress had a significant direct effect on premenstrual symptoms (β = 0.79, <italic>p</italic> &lt;. 05) (Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="Tab7" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Bootstrapping test of mediating effects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Predictors</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Effect</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SE</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">t</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sig.*</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">BC 95% CI</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">(β)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sig.*</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LLCI</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ULCI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total effect (Stress → PMS)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.376</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.000</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Direct (Stress → PMS)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.09</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.183</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.000</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Indirect (Stress → anxiety → PMS)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.073</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>0.000</bold>
</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.43</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="_fn_p122"><p><italic>n</italic> = 400; bootstrap sample size = 5000, BC 9 5% CI= bootstrap confidence intervals, *<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par92">Worldwide, climate change is an environmental factor that affects women in many areas, especially women’s psychological, mental, sexual and reproductive health. Global warming and subsequent climate change significantly increase stress, anxiety and premenstrual disorder levels among women [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="CR58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. </p><p id="Par93">Likewise, the effects of climate concerns are more common among university students. Climate change related to stress and anxiety causes female students to become vulnerable to changes in menstrual cycle length and/or negative changes in symptoms [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="CR60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. In this respect, the current study aimed to assess the relationships between climate change awareness, climate-related stress and eco-anxiety and the associations between climate-related stress and eco-anxiety and PMS.</p><p id="Par94">Notably, in the present study, the most of the nursing students were highly aware of climate change and were sufficiently knowledgeable about climate change and its effects on women’s health. A similar finding was also reported in a study conducted in Turkey (2024), which reported that the majority of women were aware of climate change and knew about the effects of climate change on health [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The present study was similar to other studies from 2020 to2025 in different countries and concluded that more than half of the undergraduate and nursing students were knowledgeable and aware of the effects of climate change on health [<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CR61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>–<xref rid="CR64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. </p><p id="Par95">The sufficient nursing students’ knowledge and high awareness level about climate change and its effect on human and female health in the present study might be related to two main factors. <bold>First</bold>, educational achievements related to climate change and environmental sustainability were strengthened through the use of nursing curricula and conferences. <bold>Second</bold>, the nursing students used different websites, mass media platforms and the internet, which made information easily accessible and increased their knowledge of climate change. Similarly, Bugaj et al. (2021) and Çolak et al. (2025) reported that climate change and health courses, friends, the internet and social media increased students’ awareness levels and acquisition of information about this issue [<xref rid="CR65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. </p><p id="Par96">The present study also revealed a positive correlation between nursing students’ knowledge and awareness of climate change and its effects on climate-related stress and eco-anxiety. A high level of climate change awareness and a satisfactory level of knowledge were associated with an increased risk for nursing students suffering from climate change related to stress and eco-anxiety.</p><p id="Par97">In the present study, the nursing students may have experienced heightened levels of climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety because most of them perceived climate change as a threat to their professional role in the future. They feel a sense of responsibility for climate change consequences as future nurses or health team members. This may be because climate change poses significant challenges to the future healthcare environment, potentially affecting both human health and environmental resources.</p><p id="Par98">When nursing students become confused about their professional role as nurses with respect to climate change, they try to acquire more knowledge about their role in managing the threat of climate change to humans. Awareness of climate change has been reported to be a stressful situation that causes high tension, hopelessness and fear, leading to difficulties in coping with stress and increasing the degree of stress experienced by students.</p><p id="Par99">Similarly, other studies reported that frequent and prolonged stressful situations related to climate change in nursing students have led to worsening mental health conditions, such as increased anxiety, irritability and difficulties in concentration. Individuals who were aware of the effects of climate change on human health presented higher levels of climate change-related stress, worry, anxiety and feelings of helplessness [<xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>–<xref rid="CR70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. </p><p id="Par100">The findings of the present study align with those of Pihkala (2020) [<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], who reported that knowing about climate change and its consequences can lead to many emotions, such as guilt, sadness, and anger, which constitute eco-anxiety. The constant barrage of disturbing news about environmental degradation and loss, or the uncertainty of the future, combined with a sense of hopelessness, can often worsen anxiety.</p><p id="Par101">The findings of the present study were similar to those of two Egyptian studies and other countries, which reported that nursing and medical students with higher perceptions, awareness and knowledge of climate change as a health hazard reported greater levels of climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety because they witnessed the impact of climate change on human health and their nursing profession [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="CR63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="CR65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="CR66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="CR71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].</p><p id="Par102">However, the findings of the present study contradict those of Ogunbode et al. (2022), who reported that exposure to information about possible solutions to climate change was not associated with climate anxiety, as learning about ways to combat climate threats helps decrease the resulting stress [<xref rid="CR72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. </p><p id="Par103">Moreover, the findings of the current work also contrast with those of Schwaab et al. in Germany in 2022, who reported that climate anxiety was significantly less common among medical students [<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The difference between the present study and the study of Schwaab et al. (2022) [<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] could be explained by the fact that it was carried out with medical students in Germany, where they may have learned how to develop personal care, defense abilities and mental health support, especially because the climate and culture of Germany greatly differ from the Egyptian climate and culture. Additionally, this difference can be attributed to differences in education and curriculum between the two countries.</p><p id="Par104">The present study revealed that climate change awareness moderated the relationship between climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety. The increase in climate change awareness was identified as an important moderating factor in the relationship between increased stress and eco-anxiety levels among nursing students. Notably, in the present study, nursing students with high awareness of climate change tended to evaluate situations with relatively high levels of concern, leading to climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety.</p><p id="Par105">This study was supported by studies in India (2014) [<xref rid="CR73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] and Turkey (2023 and 2024) [<xref rid="CR74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="CR75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], indicating that the climate change awareness of nursing students and nurses was correlated with elevated levels of climate change-related stress, which led to increased levels of environmental anxiety.</p><p id="Par106">The findings of the present study align with the appraisal and transactional model of stress and coping theories, as these nursing students may recognize climate change as a factor that could add excessive burden to their professional role. The appraisal theory suggests that an individual’s emotion is a result of an individual’s evaluation of and response to stressful situations, whereas the transactional model of stress and coping theory posits that stress is a dynamic interaction or transaction between an individual and their environment [<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. </p><p id="Par107">From the researchers’ point of view in the present study, climate change problems had a considerably more significant emotional and physical influence on nursing students. When nursing students know and become aware of climate change and its consequences for health, they may continuously perceive disruptive news about climate change as a threat to the uncertainty of the effectiveness of coping strategies in the future.</p><p id="Par108">Additionally, excessive student information obtained from the internet as well as the integration of climate change into their curriculum, especially if not associated with knowledge about related defense strategies, might increase their sense of professional responsibility for climate change consequences as future nurses or health team members.</p><p id="Par109">Therefore, increasing awareness of climate change can influence emotional responses, such as guilt, sadness, anger and a sense of hopelessness, which all increase the degree of perceived stress and can often lead to increased anxiety. The present study also revealed a relationship between climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety.</p><p id="Par110">Similar findings were reported in the studies of Bugaj et al. (2021) [<xref rid="CR65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], Ramírez-López (2023) [<xref rid="CR76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] and Mohamed et al. (2025) [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], who reported that when medical and nursing students experienced prolonged perceptions of climate stressors, this perceived stress was translated into eco-anxiety symptoms. Similar results were reported in studies from Nepal (2020) [<xref rid="CR77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>] and Egypt (2024) [<xref rid="CR78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], who reported that stressors were among the predictors of depression, anxiety, and burnout among medical students. Nevertheless, the present findings contrast with those of a previous study by Schwaab et al. (2022) [<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], which revealed that medical students experienced significant perceived stress related to climate change; however, this stress did not yet manifest as depressive, anxious, or traumatic symptoms [<xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Differences between the two studies were related to the study tools and the type and size of the sample.</p><p id="Par111">Climate change-related stress can lead to changes in the menstrual cycle. These disruptions are often caused by the hormonal response of the body to physical and psychological stressors [<xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The current study also revealed that female nursing students with climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety are more likely to have PMS. A significant positive correlation between climate stress and both eco-anxiety levels and the presence of PMS symptoms was found. Similar findings were reported in other studies, which revealed that there was a significant correlation between premenstrual signs and depression, anxiety, and stress disorders [<xref rid="CR79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>–<xref rid="CR84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. </p><p id="Par112">High levels of stress coupled with increased anxiety can increase the level of cortisol, which affects various hormone levels, leading to a significant effect on menstrual cycle parameters, including ovulatory function [<xref rid="CR82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Climate stress and eco-anxiety triggers affect the hypothalamic‒pituitary‒adrenal (HPA) axis to release cortisol, which can disrupt the balance of ovarian hormones involved in menstruation, potentially leading to increased PMS symptoms [<xref rid="CR82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. </p><p id="Par113">In the present study, climate change anxiety positively mediated the relationship between climate change-related stress and PMS. Nursing students struggle with stressors from climate change, and increasing levels of their eco-anxiety can cause hormonal disturbances that significantly worsen their PMS. Thus, climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety contributed to the prediction of PMS in the present study.</p><p id="Par114">A similar finding was reported in a study in Turkey, which revealed that eco-anxiety is a significant predictor of PMS among women [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The results of the present study were consistent with those of other studies in different countries, which revealed that the prevalence of menstrual cycle irregularity was associated with high levels of perceived stress and anxiety [<xref rid="CR79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>–<xref rid="CR86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. </p><p id="Par115">The present study revealed that 83% of the nursing students experienced moderate to severe PMS. The prevalence of PMS (moderate to severe) observed in the present study was comparable to that reported in the studies of Abu Alwafa R et al. (2021) [<xref rid="CR84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>] (75.4%), Upadhyay et al. (2023) (86%) [<xref rid="CR87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>], and Nandakumar et al. (2023) (76.35%) [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. However, it was lower than that reported in the studies of Shehadeh et al. (2017) (92.3%) [<xref rid="CR59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and Roomaney and Louren (2020) (92.3%) [<xref rid="CR60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], whereas it was higher than that reported in the studies of Trivedi (2024) [<xref rid="CR47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] (35.3%). This difference might be due to the different diagnostic tools used in the studies, namely, the selected sample, culture and geographic factors [<xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. </p><sec id="Sec20" disp-level="2"><title>Theoretical implications</title><p id="Par116">The current study provides five key theoretical contributions to climate change and its impact on women’s health, specifically regarding the moderating role of climate change awareness in the relationship between climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety, in addition to the mediating role of eco-anxiety in the relationship between climate change-related stress and PMS among female nursing students.</p><p id="Par117"><bold>First</bold>, this study adds new strengths to the concept that knowing and awareness about climate change and its consequences can lead to many emotions, such as guilt, sadness, and anger, which constitute climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety, according to the theory of analysis of Pihkala (2020) [<xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Awareness and perceptions of current and future climate change-related threats, coupled with insufficient climate action, are associated with a range of psychological and emotional responses, including anxiety, stress, distress, hopelessness, fear, anger, grief, helplessness, frustration, and guilt [<xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The findings of the present study are in line with those of previous studies that concluded that the effects of climate change on human health are associated with increased levels of climate-related stress, worry, anxiety and feelings of helplessness [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CR52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="CR67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>–<xref rid="CR79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. </p><p id="Par118"><bold>Second</bold>, the present study makes a novel contribution not only by investigating the influence and association between climate change awareness and climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety among nursing students but also by concentrating on how climate change-related stress has translated into climate change anxiety through the moderating role of climate change awareness. Awareness of climate change, coupled with excessive consumption of news, can contribute to increased stress and anxiety about climate change [<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. </p><p id="Par119"><bold>Third</bold>, this study contributes to the literature concerning the associations between awareness of climate change and climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety within the frameworks of appraisal theory and the transactional model of stress and coping. The current study links these theories to explore how climate change awareness impacts climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety through understanding and emphasizing the dynamic interplay between individuals and their environment in the stress response process (appraising stressors as the first appraisal), assessing coping methods in addressing the threat (secondary appraisal), evaluating climate change threats and continually reevaluating both the stressor and the available resources to address it [<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="CR50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="CR51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="CR58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Few studies have explored eco-anxiety in light of appraisal theory and the transactional model of stress and coping [<xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. </p><p id="Par120"><bold>Fourth</bold>, this study offers actionable insights for researchers by demonstrating how climate change-related stress influences nursing students’ PMS by testing the mediating effects of climate change anxiety, assisting healthcare providers in advocating for policies that support climate change mitigation and developing climate policy interventions for sexual and reproductive health as keys to improving the lives of women worldwide. When nursing students face heavy pressure and severe climate change stress, they consume their own energy to address their needs effectively. This process is accompanied by a decrease in the ability to cope with stress. Therefore, the continuous perceived pressure and stress of nursing students significantly affects anxiety.</p><p id="Par121">High levels of stress associated with increased anxiety can cause menstrual hormonal disturbances, leading to a significant effect on menstrual cycle parameters, including ovulatory function [<xref rid="CR82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>, <xref rid="CR89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. One study in Turkey reported that eco-anxiety was a significant predictor of PMS among women [<xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Therefore, this specific topic requires more attention from health policy makers and researchers to understand the global effects of climate change on women’s health and thereby the effects of adverse mental health conditions on women’s PMS, especially young women.</p><p id="Par122"><bold>Fifth</bold>, the study offers direction to health policymakers in incorporating stress management techniques as part of health promotion activities for women. Academic staff and administrators of faculties and universities should also help nursing students release life pressure and stressors related to climate change in academic and clinical settings through the application of stress management and mental health education methods to increase the ability of nursing students to resist pressure and stressors concerning climate change [<xref rid="CR90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Therefore, we should implement effective psychological support and counseling for nursing students, improve their mental health status, and help them deal with the threat of various negative emotions [<xref rid="CR90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. </p></sec><sec id="Sec21" disp-level="2"><title>Implications for nursing practice</title><p id="Par123">Nursing students, as nurses in the future, play a crucial role in addressing the consequences of climate change and global warming on women’s health. The present study emphasized the importance of developing strategies aimed at reducing climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety as well as alleviating the resulting PMS symptoms among nursing students. These strategies include the following:</p><p id="Par124"><bold>First</bold>, faculty administrators should consider certain approaches to reduce the climate change-related stress experienced by nursing students, such as incorporating climate literacy, stress management, menstrual health support and mental health support programs into their academic curriculum. These programs could include workshops on stress reduction techniques, the use of stress management, assertiveness skills, time management, counseling sessions, and peer support groups aimed at providing students with coping mechanisms and resources to manage the negative effects of climate change.</p><p id="Par125">Psychoeducational programs may not only contribute to lowering stress and anxiety but also foster a generation of healthcare professionals with increased awareness of climate-related challenges and a positive mindset toward addressing them.</p><p id="Par126">Encouraging climate change education can provide many benefits for nursing students. Integrating climate change education into nursing curricula can equip nursing students with the necessary knowledge and skills to understand and address the health impacts of climate change and the role of nurses in addressing environmental challenges. Educational institutions can empower nursing students to apply environmentally sustainable healthcare to mitigate the effects of climate change on health. Psychological counseling should be provided for nursing students to increase their awareness of sexual reproductive health problems associated with their psychological status.</p><p id="Par127">Courses on the effects of climate change, adaptation, and coping should be added to postgraduate nursing curriculum programs. Postgraduate students specializing in gynecological nursing should receive training aimed at raising awareness about the impact of climate change concerns on women’s psychological, mental, sexual and reproductive health and stress management.</p><p id="Par128"><bold>Second</bold>, university administrators should also provide adequate monetary resources to have educational materials such as pamphlets, posters, slides and models to impart knowledge of women’s psychological, mental, sexual and reproductive health and stress management in faculties.</p><p id="Par129">Climate change education may reduce climate change anxiety among female students and improve their awareness, perceptions, knowledge, behaviors, and policy expectations about climate change. Additionally, creating supportive environments is needed to minimize the burden of climate change on nursing students, with a focus on females.</p><p id="Par130"><bold>Third</bold>, health policy makers should focus on public health practices to reduce nursing students’ climate change-related stress, eco-anxiety and severity of PMS through education and awareness interventions. Platforms such as television and social media could prove beneficial in mitigating the effects of climate change on female nursing students and improving their climate literacy.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par131">The present work revealed that awareness of climate change plays a moderating role in the relationship between climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety among nursing students. Climate change anxiety plays a mediating role between perceived stressors related to climate change and PMS, which shows that climate change-related stress and eco-anxiety are among the key factors in understanding the prediction of PMS.</p><p id="Par132">The present study concluded that nursing students, as future nurses, should be prepared for topics such as global warming and climate change and their impact on women’s health. To address the impact of climate change on health, nurses must be skilled practitioners, advocates, and change agents.</p><sec id="Sec23" disp-level="2"><title>Limitations of the study</title><p id="Par133">The present study may be unique in that it aims to assess how climate change awareness affects climate stress and eco-anxiety, in addition to how moderating and mediating factors are related to PMS among nursing students. However, the current study has several limitations, as follows:</p><p id="Par134"><bold>First</bold>, the current study used a cross-sectional design, which hinders the ability to establish causal relationships between determinants and outcomes. Data were collected at a single time point. Therefore, future research should apply longitudinal designs to assess the impact of students’ awareness of climate change on their psychological responses over time. Likewise, future studies can adopt a cohort design. This design also strengthens the research methodology and improves the validity of the results in examining the impact of climate change on psychological response and PMSs. It also allows the observation of longitudinal trends and tracking, the analysis of a defined group of individuals over a designated period and the thorough exploration of connections between variables.</p><p id="Par135"><bold>Second</bold>, all questionnaires were self-reported by the students. This was considered a limitation since the responses, including awareness and knowledge, may change over time. Employing more objective measures could augment the robustness of the findings.</p><p id="Par136"><bold>Third</bold>, despite the large sample size of the study, the study was conducted at a single Egyptian university located in a coastal city. This limits the generalizability of the findings to all nursing students across Egypt. Thus, further large-scale and an in-depth survey are needed to evaluate the wide range of climate-related emotions and experiences. To improve the generalizability of the findings, a more comprehensive understanding of the impacts of climate change on psychological response and PMS should be obtained. Importantly, the manifestations of climate stress, eco-anxiety and PMS may vary across different demographic areas. Future research will need to replicate this study in rural and urban areas where the effects of climate change might be more prominent.</p><p id="Par137"><bold>Fourth</bold>, the use of a convenience sampling procedure may be considered a limitation, as it can introduce sampling bias and reduce the generalizability of the study findings. However, the large sample size may help minimize the impact of individual biases on the overall results and thereby improve the generalizability of the findings.</p><p id="Par138"><bold>Fifth</bold>, although the study used regression analysis to control for confounding variables such as demographic factors, the study was subjected to a lack of control for confounding variables such as general stress, lifestyle factors, hormonal influences, environmental differences or participant behavior. To ensure that the results reflect true causality, the study should involve design techniques (randomized, matching, restriction) and analytical methods (stratification) to isolate the relationships between independent and dependent variables.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24" disp-level="2"><title>Future research</title><p id="Par139"><bold>First</bold>, stress management has an important goal of psychological intervention in health emergencies to address the effects of climate change on mental health. Therefore, future research needs to explore the effects of stress management on alleviating the mental health impacts of climate change and PMS among nursing students.</p><p id="Par140"><bold>Second</bold>, nursing students, as future nurses, should be prepared to reduce the consequences of climate change for human health and to be ready to carry out their role in the protection of public health in the face of climate change. Future studies should assess the environmental literacy levels of nursing students as future nurses on global climate change and its impact. Future research should also aim to increase the knowledge and skills of nursing students with respect to their professional role responsibility as nurses with respect to climate change.</p></sec></sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are thankful to all the participants who helped us in this study.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors prepared, reviewed, and approved the final version of the manuscript. Nagah: Conceptualization, methodology, data analysis, validation, preparation, writing and interpretation of the results, and writing and revision of the manuscript. Elham , Safaa and Maha revised the results and reviewed and edited the manuscript. Wael: Writing-original draft preparation, reviewing results, and discussion.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &amp; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB). The study was self-funded by the authors.</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>All generated and analyzed data in this research are included in this manuscript. The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="FPar6" disp-level="2"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par141">The study was performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations. Ethical approval was obtained from the ethical committee of the Faculty of Medicine at Alexandria University (the IRB number was 0306822) and the Faculty of Nursing Administration at Matrouh University. The students signed informed consent before the data collection process. Nursing students were assured of the confidentiality and anonymity of information and that it would be used for research purposes. The data were analyzed via the use of code numbers for questionnaires and by removing students’ names.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7" disp-level="2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par142">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar8" disp-level="2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par143">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shinan-Altman S, Hamama-Raz Y. The interplay between climate change exposure, awareness, coping, and anxiety among individuals with and without a chronic illness. Climate. 2025;13(124). 10.3390/cli13060124.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Climate change and infectious diseases. 2022 Nov 27. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/ncezid/what-we-do/climate-change-andinfectious-diseases/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/ncezid/what-we-do/climate-change-andinfectious-diseases/index.html</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">World Health Organization. Climate change and health. 2023. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/climate-change-and-health" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/climate-change-and-health</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">WHO. Climate change. 2024 Mar 19. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/factsheets/detail/climate-change-and-health" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/factsheets/detail/climate-change-and-health</ext-link>.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Aksu A, Buldum A, Vefikuluçay Yılmaz D. Impacts of climate change on women’s health and solutions. In: Gümrükçüoğlu Yiğit M, editor. Climate justice for whom: impacts of climate change on women and solutions. Turkey: Sakarya University Press; 2024. p. 185–210. 10.59537/saupress.2373.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rothschild J, Haase E. Women’s mental health and climate change part II: socioeconomic stresses of climate change and eco-anxiety for women and their children. Int J Gynecol Obstet. 2023;160(2):414–20. 10.1002/ijgo.14514.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/ijgo.14514"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36254375"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rothschild J, Haase E. Women’s mental health and climate change part II: socioeconomic stresses of climate change and eco-anxiety for women and their children. Int J Gynecol Obstet. 2023;160(2):414–20. 10.1002/ijgo.14514."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Husaini S, Davies SE. Case report: another burden to bear: the impacts of climate change on access to sexual and reproductive health rights and services in Bangladesh. Front Clim. 2022;4:875515. 10.3389/fclim.2022.875515.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Husaini S, Davies SE. Case report: another burden to bear: the impacts of climate change on access to sexual and reproductive health rights and services in Bangladesh. Front Clim. 2022;4:875515. 10.3389/fclim.2022.875515."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cianconi P, Betrò S, Janiri L. The impact of climate change on mental health: a systematic descriptive review. Front Psychiatry. 2020;11. 10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00074.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fpsyt.2020.00074"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7068211"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32210846"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pandipati S, Abel DE. Anticipated impacts of climate change on women’s health: a background primer. Int J Gynecol Obstet. 2023;160(2):394–9. 10.1002/ijgo.14393.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/ijgo.14393"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35953877"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pandipati S, Abel DE. Anticipated impacts of climate change on women’s health: a background primer. Int J Gynecol Obstet. 2023;160(2):394–9. 10.1002/ijgo.14393."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bruinvels G, Blagrove RC, Goldsmith E, Shaw L, Martin D, Piasecki J. How lifestyle changes during the COVID-19 global pandemic affected the pattern and symptoms of the menstrual cycle. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(20):13622. 10.3390/ijerph192013622.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijerph192013622"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9602509"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36294200"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bruinvels G, Blagrove RC, Goldsmith E, Shaw L, Martin D, Piasecki J. How lifestyle changes during the COVID-19 global pandemic affected the pattern and symptoms of the menstrual cycle. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(20):13622. 10.3390/ijerph192013622."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Saglam HY, Sahin B. The impact of climate change anxiety on premenstrual syndrome: a cross-sectional study. J Eval Clin Pract. 2024:1–8.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/jep.14177"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12051412"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39431553"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Thakur J, Goswami M, Roy S. Do contrasting socio-ecological conditions bring difference in premenstrual syndrome and its concomitants? A sedente‐migrant comparative study from Eastern India. Am J Hum Biol. 2023;35(12):e23955. 10.1002/ajhb.23955.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/ajhb.23955"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37403742"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Thakur J, Goswami M, Roy S. Do contrasting socio-ecological conditions bring difference in premenstrual syndrome and its concomitants? A sedente‐migrant comparative study from Eastern India. Am J Hum Biol. 2023;35(12):e23955. 10.1002/ajhb.23955."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mohamed MA, Abd El-Hameed NAEL, Gabra RH, Abd El-Aziz AM. Climate Change related depression, anxiety and stress among faculty of nursing students at Assiut University. Assiut Sci Nurs J. 2025;13(49:5):13–22.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mohamed MA, Abd El-Hameed NAEL, Gabra RH, Abd El-Aziz AM. Climate Change related depression, anxiety and stress among faculty of nursing students at Assiut University. Assiut Sci Nurs J. 2025;13(49:5):13–22."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Da Fonte C, Caridade S, Dinis M. Mental health, well-being and climate change: scope and challenges. In: Climate Change Management. Springer Science+Business Media Deutschland GmbH; 2023. p. 41–55. 10.1007/978-3-031-26592-1_3.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Schwaab L, Gebhardt N, Friederich H, Nikendei C. Climate change related depression, anxiety and stress symptoms perceived by medical students. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022;19(15). 10.3390/ijerph19159142.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijerph19159142"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9332784"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35897512"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sanchez KL, Doreen G, Antipuesto DG, De Perio JEL, Campania JV. climate change awareness and eco-anxiety among undergraduate students. Int J Social Sci Educ Res Stud. 2024;4(9):1017–24.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sanchez KL, Doreen G, Antipuesto DG, De Perio JEL, Campania JV. climate change awareness and eco-anxiety among undergraduate students. Int J Social Sci Educ Res Stud. 2024;4(9):1017–24."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Abousoliman AD, Ibrahim AM, Abualruz H, Magdi HM, Fathi Zaghamir DE, Alhowimel A, El-Monshed AH, El-Gazar HE, Zoromba MA. Exploring the relationship between nursing students’ knowledge and attitudes toward climate change and their psychological distress: a cross-national investigation. BMC Nurs. 2024;23:294. 10.1186/s12912-024-01927-8.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12912-024-01927-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11057081"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38685002"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Abousoliman AD, Ibrahim AM, Abualruz H, Magdi HM, Fathi Zaghamir DE, Alhowimel A, El-Monshed AH, El-Gazar HE, Zoromba MA. Exploring the relationship between nursing students’ knowledge and attitudes toward climate change and their psychological distress: a cross-national investigation. BMC Nurs. 2024;23:294. 10.1186/s12912-024-01927-8."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Innab A, Alenezi A, Khaled A, Dewan M, Mostafa M. The relationship between premenstrual dysphoric symptoms, perceived stress, and sleep quality among nursing students: a cross-sectional study. Healthcare. 2025;13(2862). 10.3390/healthcare13222862.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/healthcare13222862"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12652963"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="41302248"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li H, Sarokhani M, Gilan MHS, Valizade R, Sayehmiri K. Prediction premenstrual syndrome (PMS) with anxiety, and depression in female students. MC Psychiatry. 2025;25:794. 10.1186/s12888-025-07250-z.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12888-025-07250-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12359940"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40826390"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Li H, Sarokhani M, Gilan MHS, Valizade R, Sayehmiri K. Prediction premenstrual syndrome (PMS) with anxiety, and depression in female students. MC Psychiatry. 2025;25:794. 10.1186/s12888-025-07250-z."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sakuma Y, Kanoya Y, Sato C. The Effects of Changes in Lives of University Fresh Female Students on the Various Symptoms with Menstrual Cycles. Jpn J Matern Health. 2008;49:286–94.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sakuma Y, Kanoya Y, Sato C. The Effects of Changes in Lives of University Fresh Female Students on the Various Symptoms with Menstrual Cycles. Jpn J Matern Health. 2008;49:286–94."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Krem EC, Akar A, Akar A. The relationship between climate change worry, premenstrual syndrome severity, and quality of life among women of reproductive age and related factors. Rev Latino-Am Enfermagem. 2026;34:e4837.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1590/1518-8345.7793.4837"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="41983788"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Krem EC, Akar A, Akar A. The relationship between climate change worry, premenstrual syndrome severity, and quality of life among women of reproductive age and related factors. Rev Latino-Am Enfermagem. 2026;34:e4837."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Abd Elgalil HM, Ali SI, Hammouda SM, AboElela AM. Eco-Anxiety among Undergraduates female medical students at Al-Azhar University, Cairo, Egypt. Al-Azhar Int Med J. 2025;6(1):70–5.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Abd Elgalil HM, Ali SI, Hammouda SM, AboElela AM. Eco-Anxiety among Undergraduates female medical students at Al-Azhar University, Cairo, Egypt. Al-Azhar Int Med J. 2025;6(1):70–5."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Clayton S, Karazsia BT. Development and validation of a measure of climate change anxiety. J Environ Psychol. 2020;69:10143.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Clayton S, Karazsia BT. Development and validation of a measure of climate change anxiety. J Environ Psychol. 2020;69:10143."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Boluda-Verdu I, Senent-Valero M, Casas-Escolano M, Matijasevich A, Pastor-Valero M. Fear for the future: Ecoanxiety and health implications, a systematic review. J Environ Psychol. 2022;1(84):101904.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Boluda-Verdu I, Senent-Valero M, Casas-Escolano M, Matijasevich A, Pastor-Valero M. Fear for the future: Ecoanxiety and health implications, a systematic review. J Environ Psychol. 2022;1(84):101904."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nandakumar H, Kuppusamy MK, Sekhar L, Ramaswamy P. Prevalence of premenstrual syndrome among students – Stress a potential risk factor. Clin Epidemiol Global Health. 2023;23:101368. 10.1016/j.cegh.2023.101368.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nandakumar H, Kuppusamy MK, Sekhar L, Ramaswamy P. Prevalence of premenstrual syndrome among students – Stress a potential risk factor. Clin Epidemiol Global Health. 2023;23:101368. 10.1016/j.cegh.2023.101368."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. Climate change 2022 – impacts, adaptation and vulnerability: working group II contribution to the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. 1st ed. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; 2023. 10.1017/97810093258442.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ballew MT, Uppalapati SS, Myers TM, Carman J, Campbell E, Rosenthal SA, Kotcher JE, Leiserowitz A, Maibach E. Climate change psychological distress is associated with increased collective climate action in the U.S. npj Clim Action. 2024;3:88. 10.1038/s44168-024-00172-8.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ballew MT, Uppalapati SS, Myers TM, Carman J, Campbell E, Rosenthal SA, Kotcher JE, Leiserowitz A, Maibach E. Climate change psychological distress is associated with increased collective climate action in the U.S. npj Clim Action. 2024;3:88. 10.1038/s44168-024-00172-8."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kaya L, Keles E, Baydili KN, Kaya Z, Kumr P. Impact of Climate Change Education on Pregnant Women’s Anxiety and Awareness. Public Health Nurs. 2025;42:54–60. 10.1111/phn.13455.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/phn.13455"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11700939"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39388505"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kaya L, Keles E, Baydili KN, Kaya Z, Kumr P. Impact of Climate Change Education on Pregnant Women’s Anxiety and Awareness. Public Health Nurs. 2025;42:54–60. 10.1111/phn.13455."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Schwartz SEO, Benoit L, Clayton S, Parnes MF, Swenson L, Lowe SR. Climate change anxiety and mental health: Environmental activism as buffer. Curr Psychol. 2022. 10.1007/s12144-022-02735-6.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s12144-022-02735-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8883014"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35250241"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Schwartz SEO, Benoit L, Clayton S, Parnes MF, Swenson L, Lowe SR. Climate change anxiety and mental health: Environmental activism as buffer. Curr Psychol. 2022. 10.1007/s12144-022-02735-6."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Maguire R. Gender, climate change and the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change. In: Research handbook on feminist engagement with international law. Edward Elgar Publishing; 2019.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Olson J. Whose voices matter? Gender inequality in the United Nations framework convention on climate change. Agenda. 2014;28(3):184–87. 10.1080/10130950.2014.951215.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Olson J. Whose voices matter? Gender inequality in the United Nations framework convention on climate change. Agenda. 2014;28(3):184–87. 10.1080/10130950.2014.951215."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Onieva-Zafra MD, Fernández-Muñoz JJ, Fernández-Martínez E, García Sánchez FJ, Abreu-Sánchez A, Parra-Fernández ML. Anxiety, perceived stress and coping strategies in nursing students: a cross-sectional, correlational, descriptive study. BMC Med Educ. 2020;20:370.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12909-020-02294-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7574568"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33081751"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Onieva-Zafra MD, Fernández-Muñoz JJ, Fernández-Martínez E, García Sánchez FJ, Abreu-Sánchez A, Parra-Fernández ML. Anxiety, perceived stress and coping strategies in nursing students: a cross-sectional, correlational, descriptive study. BMC Med Educ. 2020;20:370."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ergin E, Altinel B, Aktas E. A mixed method study on global warming, climate change and the role of public health nurses from the perspective of nursing students. Nurse Educ Today. 2021;107:105144.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.nedt.2021.105144"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34537496"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ergin E, Altinel B, Aktas E. A mixed method study on global warming, climate change and the role of public health nurses from the perspective of nursing students. Nurse Educ Today. 2021;107:105144."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Patrick R, Armstrong F, Hancock T, Capon A, Smith JA. Climate change and health promotion in Australia: Navigating political, policy, advocacy and research challenges. Heal Promot J Aust. 2019;30:295–8.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/hpja.278"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31531900"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Patrick R, Armstrong F, Hancock T, Capon A, Smith JA. Climate change and health promotion in Australia: Navigating political, policy, advocacy and research challenges. Heal Promot J Aust. 2019;30:295–8."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Han B. Associations between perceived environmental pollution and health-related quality of life in a Chinese adult population. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2020;18:198.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12955-020-01442-9"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7310336"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32576182"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Han B. Associations between perceived environmental pollution and health-related quality of life in a Chinese adult population. Health Qual Life Outcomes. 2020;18:198."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Salvarani V, Ardenghi S, Rampoldi G, Bani M, Cannata P, Ausili D. Predictors of psychological distress among nursing students: a multicenter cross-sectional study. Nurse Educ Pract. 2020;44:102758.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.nepr.2020.102758"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32234667"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Salvarani V, Ardenghi S, Rampoldi G, Bani M, Cannata P, Ausili D. Predictors of psychological distress among nursing students: a multicenter cross-sectional study. Nurse Educ Pract. 2020;44:102758."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lazarus RS, Folkman S. Stress, appraisal, and coping. Springer Publishing Company. 1984.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Smith AC, Lazarus RS. Emotion and adaptation. In: Handbook of personality: theory and research. 1990;21:609–37.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pihkala P. Anxiety and the Ecological Crisis: An Analysis of Eco-Anxiety and Climate Anxiety. Sustainability. 2020;12(19):7836. 10.3390/su12197836.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pihkala P. Anxiety and the Ecological Crisis: An Analysis of Eco-Anxiety and Climate Anxiety. Sustainability. 2020;12(19):7836. 10.3390/su12197836."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rishi P, Mudaliar R, Climate, Stress. Behavioral Adaptation and Subjective Well Being in Coastal Cities of India. Am J Appl Psychol. 2014;2(1):13–21. 10.12691/ajap-2-1-3.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rishi P, Mudaliar R, Climate, Stress. Behavioral Adaptation and Subjective Well Being in Coastal Cities of India. Am J Appl Psychol. 2014;2(1):13–21. 10.12691/ajap-2-1-3."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Innocenti M, Perilli A, Santarelli G. How does climate change worry influence the relationship between climate change anxiety and eco-paralysis? A moderation study. Climate. 2023;11(9):190. 10.3390/cli11090190.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Innocenti M, Perilli A, Santarelli G. How does climate change worry influence the relationship between climate change anxiety and eco-paralysis? A moderation study. Climate. 2023;11(9):190. 10.3390/cli11090190."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wahid SS, Raza WA, Mahmud I, Kohrt BA. Climate-related shocks and other stressors associated with depression and anxiety in Bangladesh: A nationally representative panel study. Lancet Planet Health. 2023;7:E137–46. 10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00315-1.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00315-1"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36754469"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Wahid SS, Raza WA, Mahmud I, Kohrt BA. Climate-related shocks and other stressors associated with depression and anxiety in Bangladesh: A nationally representative panel study. Lancet Planet Health. 2023;7:E137–46. 10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00315-1."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ngu F, Kelman I, Chambers J, Ayeb-Karlsson S. Correlating heatwaves and relative humidity with suicide (fatal intentional self-harm). Sci Rep Rep. 2021;11(1):22175. 10.1038/s41598-021-03089-y.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/s41598-021-01448-3"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8593067"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34782650"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ngu F, Kelman I, Chambers J, Ayeb-Karlsson S. Correlating heatwaves and relative humidity with suicide (fatal intentional self-harm). Sci Rep Rep. 2021;11(1):22175. 10.1038/s41598-021-03089-y."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ahmed B. The silent impact of climate change on menstrual health. 2024. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://paradigmforjustice.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/The-Silent-Impact–of-Climate-Change-on-Menstrual-Health.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">http://paradigmforjustice.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/The-Silent-Impact–of-Climate-Change-on-Menstrual-Health.pdf</ext-link>http//paradigmforjustice.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/The-Silent-Impact–of-Climate-Change-on-Menstrual-Health.pdf.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Muralidharan A, Broekhuijsen M, Lisondra L, Guru A, Haver J, Irfan S. The ripple effect: impacts of climate change on menstrual health and paths to resilience. Front Glob Women’s Health. 2025;6:1569046. 10.3389/fgwh.2025.1569046.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3389/fgwh.2025.1569046"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12058667"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40342356"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Muralidharan A, Broekhuijsen M, Lisondra L, Guru A, Haver J, Irfan S. The ripple effect: impacts of climate change on menstrual health and paths to resilience. Front Glob Women’s Health. 2025;6:1569046. 10.3389/fgwh.2025.1569046."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu Q, Lin Y, Zhang W. Psychological stress dysfunction in women with premenstrual syndrome. Heliyon. 2024;10:e40233.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e40233"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11693916"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39748962"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Liu Q, Lin Y, Zhang W. Psychological stress dysfunction in women with premenstrual syndrome. Heliyon. 2024;10:e40233."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Trivedi D, Patel K, Jain KG. Impact of Stress on Premenstrual Syndrome Among Young Women: A Cross-Sectional Study. Cureus. 2024;16(11):e74622. 10.7759/cureus.7462.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7759/cureus.74622"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11681971"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39735041"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Trivedi D, Patel K, Jain KG. Impact of Stress on Premenstrual Syndrome Among Young Women: A Cross-Sectional Study. Cureus. 2024;16(11):e74622. 10.7759/cureus.7462."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cochran WG. Sampling techniques. 2nd ed. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons; 1963;7(3): 203-13.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lopez JJD, Malay CA. Awareness and attitude toward climate change of selected senior high students in Cavite, Philippines. Asia Pac J Multidiscip Res. 2019;7(2 Part III):56–62.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lopez JJD, Malay CA. Awareness and attitude toward climate change of selected senior high students in Cavite, Philippines. Asia Pac J Multidiscip Res. 2019;7(2 Part III):56–62."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ezeudu SA, Ezeudu S, Sampson M. Climate change awareness and attitude of senior secondary students in Umuahia Education Zone of Abia State. Int J Res Humanit Social Stud. 2016;3(3):7–17.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ezeudu SA, Ezeudu S, Sampson M. Climate change awareness and attitude of senior secondary students in Umuahia Education Zone of Abia State. Int J Res Humanit Social Stud. 2016;3(3):7–17."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mekawy SH. Climate change and its relationship with environmental sustainability practices as perceived by staff nurses. J Nurs Sci - Benha Univ. 2023;4(1):1227–43.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mekawy SH. Climate change and its relationship with environmental sustainability practices as perceived by staff nurses. J Nurs Sci - Benha Univ. 2023;4(1):1227–43."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Er S, Murat M, Ata EE, Köse SK, Buzlu S. Nursing students’ mental health: How does eco-anxiety affect them? Int J Mental Health Nurs. 2024;33:1315–26.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/inm.13320"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38549230"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Er S, Murat M, Ata EE, Köse SK, Buzlu S. Nursing students’ mental health: How does eco-anxiety affect them? Int J Mental Health Nurs. 2024;33:1315–26."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR53"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. (A Global Measure of Perceived Stress. J Health Soc Behav. 1983;24(4):385. 10.2307/2136404.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="6668417"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. (A Global Measure of Perceived Stress. J Health Soc Behav. 1983;24(4):385. 10.2307/2136404."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Türkarslan KK, Kozak ED, Yıldırım JC. Psychometric properties of the Hogg Eco-Anxiety Scale (HEAS‐13) and the prediction of pro‐ environmental behavior. J Environ Psychol. 2023;92:102147. 10.1016/j.jenvp.2023.102147.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Türkarslan KK, Kozak ED, Yıldırım JC. Psychometric properties of the Hogg Eco-Anxiety Scale (HEAS‐13) and the prediction of pro‐ environmental behavior. J Environ Psychol. 2023;92:102147. 10.1016/j.jenvp.2023.102147."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Choijiljav D, Sukhbat T, Ogawa S, Yanjmaa E, Badamdorj O, Saito A, Arai Y, Shinozaki H. Validation of the premenstrual symptoms questionnaire among Mongolian nursing school students. BMC Womens Health. 2024;24:661. 10.1186/s12905-024-03492-3.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12905-024-03492-3"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11664845"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39710668"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Choijiljav D, Sukhbat T, Ogawa S, Yanjmaa E, Badamdorj O, Saito A, Arai Y, Shinozaki H. Validation of the premenstrual symptoms questionnaire among Mongolian nursing school students. BMC Womens Health. 2024;24:661. 10.1186/s12905-024-03492-3."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR56"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Steiner M, Macdougall M, Brown E. The premenstrual symptoms screening tool (PSST) for clinicians. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2003;6(3):203–9. 10.1007/s00737-003-0018-4.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00737-003-0018-4"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="12920618"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Steiner M, Macdougall M, Brown E. The premenstrual symptoms screening tool (PSST) for clinicians. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2003;6(3):203–9. 10.1007/s00737-003-0018-4."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Polit DF, Beck CT. The content validity index: Are you sure you know what’s being reported? Critique and recommendations. Res Nurs Health. 2006;29(5):489–97. 10.1002/nur.20147.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/nur.20147"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16977646"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Polit DF, Beck CT. The content validity index: Are you sure you know what’s being reported? Critique and recommendations. Res Nurs Health. 2006;29(5):489–97. 10.1002/nur.20147."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Stone K, Blinn N, Spencer R. Mental health impacts of climate change on women: a scoping review. Curr Environ Health Rep. 2022;9(2):228–43. 10.1007/s40572-022-00346-8.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s40572-022-00346-8"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35267174"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Stone K, Blinn N, Spencer R. Mental health impacts of climate change on women: a scoping review. Curr Environ Health Rep. 2022;9(2):228–43. 10.1007/s40572-022-00346-8."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shehadeh HJ, Mansour HAM. Prevalence and association of premenstrual syndrome and premenstrual dysphoric disorder with academic performance among female university students. Perspect Psychiatr Care. 2017;54(2):176–184. 10.1111/ppc.12219.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/ppc.12219"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28543046"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Roomaney R, Lourens A. Correlates of premenstrual dysphoric disorder among female university students. Cogent Psychol. 2020;7(1):1823608. 10.1080/23311908.2020.1823608(2020).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Roomaney R, Lourens A. Correlates of premenstrual dysphoric disorder among female university students. Cogent Psychol. 2020;7(1):1823608. 10.1080/23311908.2020.1823608(2020)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Çelik Eren D, Yıldız KM. Is climate change awareness a predictor of anxiety among nursing students? A cross-sectional study. Nurse Educ Today. 2024:106390. 10.1016/j.nedt.2024.106390.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.nedt.2024.106390"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39278183"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mat STB, Yilmaz BN. Is awareness of climate change a predictor of eco-anxiety? Research within the scope of nursing students. Nurse Educ Today. 2024;140:106274.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.nedt.2024.106274"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38865952"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mat STB, Yilmaz BN. Is awareness of climate change a predictor of eco-anxiety? Research within the scope of nursing students. Nurse Educ Today. 2024;140:106274."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Erkan FM, Budak FK. The relationship between future anxiety and awareness of global climate change in nursing students. Int J Soc Psychiatry. 2025:1–7. 10.1177/00207640251339892.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/00207640251339892"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40365770"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Álvarez-Nieto C, Richardson J, Navarro-Perán MÁ, Tutticci N, Huss N, Elf M, Anåker A, Aronsson J, Baid H, López-Medina IM. Nursing students’ attitudes toward climate change and sustainability: A cross-sectional multisite study. Nurse Educ Today. 2022;108:105185. 10.1016/j.nedt.2021.105185.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.nedt.2021.105185"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34717100"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Álvarez-Nieto C, Richardson J, Navarro-Perán MÁ, Tutticci N, Huss N, Elf M, Anåker A, Aronsson J, Baid H, López-Medina IM. Nursing students’ attitudes toward climate change and sustainability: A cross-sectional multisite study. Nurse Educ Today. 2022;108:105185. 10.1016/j.nedt.2021.105185."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bugaj TJ, Heilborn M, Terhoeven V, et al. What do Final Year Medical Students in Germany know and think about Climate Change? - The ClimAttitude Study. Med Educ Online. 2021;26(1):1917037.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1080/10872981.2021.1917037"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8079051"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33886438"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Bugaj TJ, Heilborn M, Terhoeven V, et al. What do Final Year Medical Students in Germany know and think about Climate Change? - The ClimAttitude Study. Med Educ Online. 2021;26(1):1917037."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR66"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Çolak M, Dogan R, Dogan S. Effect of Climate Change and Health Course on Global Warming Knowledge and Attitudes, Environmental Literacy, and Eco-Anxiety Level of Nursing Students: A Quasi-Experimental Study. Public Health Nurs. 2025;42:1315–24. 10.1111/phn.13536.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/phn.13536"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12001001"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39822057"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Çolak M, Dogan R, Dogan S. Effect of Climate Change and Health Course on Global Warming Knowledge and Attitudes, Environmental Literacy, and Eco-Anxiety Level of Nursing Students: A Quasi-Experimental Study. Public Health Nurs. 2025;42:1315–24. 10.1111/phn.13536."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hwang E, Kim J. Factors affecting academic burnout of nursing students according to clinical practice experience. BMC Med Educ. 2022;22(1):346. 10.1186/s12909-022-03422-7.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12909-022-03422-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9077997"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35524256"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Hwang E, Kim J. Factors affecting academic burnout of nursing students according to clinical practice experience. BMC Med Educ. 2022;22(1):346. 10.1186/s12909-022-03422-7."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR68"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Stanley S, Hogg T, Leviston Z, Walker I. From anger to action: Differential impacts of eco-anxiety, eco-depression, and eco-anger on climate action and wellbeing. J Clim Change Health. 2021;1:100003. 10.1016/j.joclim.2021.10000.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Stanley S, Hogg T, Leviston Z, Walker I. From anger to action: Differential impacts of eco-anxiety, eco-depression, and eco-anger on climate action and wellbeing. J Clim Change Health. 2021;1:100003. 10.1016/j.joclim.2021.10000."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR69"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Akbulut M, Kaya A. The psychological dimension of global climate change. GümüşhaneÜniversitesiSağlıkBilimleriDergisi. 2021;10(3):581–7. 10.37989/gumussagbil.889584.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Akbulut M, Kaya A. The psychological dimension of global climate change. GümüşhaneÜniversitesiSağlıkBilimleriDergisi. 2021;10(3):581–7. 10.37989/gumussagbil.889584."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR70"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Stevenson K, Peterson N. Motivating Action through Fostering Climate Change Hope and Concern and Avoiding Despair among Adolescents. Sustainability. 2015;8(1):6. 10.3390/su8010006.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Stevenson K, Peterson N. Motivating Action through Fostering Climate Change Hope and Concern and Avoiding Despair among Adolescents. Sustainability. 2015;8(1):6. 10.3390/su8010006."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR71"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Mat STB, Çalışkan BB, Baştarcan Ç. Worry and hope levels of nursing students about climate change: A cross-sectional study. J Psychiatric Nurs. 2023;15(1):9–16.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Mat STB, Çalışkan BB, Baştarcan Ç. Worry and hope levels of nursing students about climate change: A cross-sectional study. J Psychiatric Nurs. 2023;15(1):9–16."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR72"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ogunbode CA, Hanss DR. Climate Anxiety, Wellbeing and Pro-Environmental Action: Correlates of Negative Emotional Responses to Climate Change in 32 Countries. J Environ Psychol. 2022;84:101887. 10.1016/j.jenvp.2022.101887.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ogunbode CA, Hanss DR. Climate Anxiety, Wellbeing and Pro-Environmental Action: Correlates of Negative Emotional Responses to Climate Change in 32 Countries. J Environ Psychol. 2022;84:101887. 10.1016/j.jenvp.2022.101887."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR73"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rishi P, Mudaliar R, Climate, Stress. Behavioral Adaptation and Subjective Well Being in Coastal Cities of India. Am J Appl Psychol. 2014;2(1):13–21.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Rishi P, Mudaliar R, Climate, Stress. Behavioral Adaptation and Subjective Well Being in Coastal Cities of India. Am J Appl Psychol. 2014;2(1):13–21."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR74"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ediz Ç, Yanik D. The effects of climate change awareness on mental health: comparison of climate anxiety and hopelessness levels in Turkish youth. Int J Soc Psychiatry. 2023;69(8):2157–66.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/00207640231206060"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="37874036"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ediz Ç, Yanik D. The effects of climate change awareness on mental health: comparison of climate anxiety and hopelessness levels in Turkish youth. Int J Soc Psychiatry. 2023;69(8):2157–66."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tümer A, İpek M, Ercan Z. Nursing students’ awareness, worry and hope levels regarding climate change: a cross-sectional and correlational study. J Public Health Nurs. 2024;6(1):29–38. 10.54061/jphn.1396915.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR76"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ramírez-López AS, Rosetti MF, Poma A. Gender, exposure to news, knowledge about climate change, and prosociality predict climate anxiety scores in Mexican students. Ecopsychology. 2023;15(2):184–92. 10.1089/eco.2022.0049.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ramírez-López AS, Rosetti MF, Poma A. Gender, exposure to news, knowledge about climate change, and prosociality predict climate anxiety scores in Mexican students. Ecopsychology. 2023;15(2):184–92. 10.1089/eco.2022.0049."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR77"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pokhrel NB, Khadayat R, Tulachan P. Depression, anxiety, and burnout among medical students and residents of a medical school in Nepal: A cross-sectional study. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20(1):298.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12888-020-02645-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7294639"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32539732"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pokhrel NB, Khadayat R, Tulachan P. Depression, anxiety, and burnout among medical students and residents of a medical school in Nepal: A cross-sectional study. BMC Psychiatry. 2020;20(1):298."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR78"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ebrahim OS, Sayed HA, Rabei S, Hegazy N. Perceived stress and anxiety among medical students at Helwan University: A cross-sectional study. J Public Health Res. 2024;13(1):1–11. 10.1177/22799036241227891journals.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1177/22799036241227891"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC10838489"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38313630"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Ebrahim OS, Sayed HA, Rabei S, Hegazy N. Perceived stress and anxiety among medical students at Helwan University: A cross-sectional study. J Public Health Res. 2024;13(1):1–11. 10.1177/22799036241227891journals."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR79"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Iqbal S, Aljanoubi FA, Alzarah SA, Alrashedi HB, Algaw RK, Alqeshtaini SS, Ali SHM. Menstrual cycle relation with anxiety and other psychological symptoms in women. IAJPS. 2021;08(02):120–30.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Iqbal S, Aljanoubi FA, Alzarah SA, Alrashedi HB, Algaw RK, Alqeshtaini SS, Ali SHM. Menstrual cycle relation with anxiety and other psychological symptoms in women. IAJPS. 2021;08(02):120–30."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR80"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lane T, Francis A. Premenstrual symptomatology, locus of control, anxiety and depression in women with normal menstrual cycles. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2003;6(2):127–38. 10.1007/s00737-003-0165-7.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s00737-003-0165-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="12720063"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Lane T, Francis A. Premenstrual symptomatology, locus of control, anxiety and depression in women with normal menstrual cycles. Arch Womens Ment Health. 2003;6(2):127–38. 10.1007/s00737-003-0165-7."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR81"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nillni Y, Wesselink A, Hatch E, Mikkelsen E, Gradus J, Rothman K, Wise L. Mental health, psychotropic medication use, and menstrual cycle characteristics. Clin Epidemiol. 2018;10:1073–82. 10.2147/clep.s152131.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2147/CLEP.S152131"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6118267"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30214312"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nillni Y, Wesselink A, Hatch E, Mikkelsen E, Gradus J, Rothman K, Wise L. Mental health, psychotropic medication use, and menstrual cycle characteristics. Clin Epidemiol. 2018;10:1073–82. 10.2147/clep.s152131."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR82"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Schliep K, Mumford S, Vladutiu C, Ahrens K, Perkins N, Sjaarda L, Schisterman E. Perceived stress, reproductive hormones, and ovulatory function: a prospective cohort study. Epidemiology. 2015;26(2):177–84. 10.1097/ede.0000000000000238.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1097/EDE.0000000000000238"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4315337"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25643098"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Schliep K, Mumford S, Vladutiu C, Ahrens K, Perkins N, Sjaarda L, Schisterman E. Perceived stress, reproductive hormones, and ovulatory function: a prospective cohort study. Epidemiology. 2015;26(2):177–84. 10.1097/ede.0000000000000238."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR83"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Yen JY, Lin PC, Huang MF, Chou WP, Long CY, Chih-Hung K. Association between Generalized Anxiety Disorder and Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder in a Diagnostic Interviewing Study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:988. 10.3390/ijerph17030988.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijerph17030988"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7038147"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32033286"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Yen JY, Lin PC, Huang MF, Chou WP, Long CY, Chih-Hung K. Association between Generalized Anxiety Disorder and Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder in a Diagnostic Interviewing Study. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17:988. 10.3390/ijerph17030988."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR84"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Abu Alwafa R, Badrasawi M, Haj Hamad R. Prevalence of premenstrual syndrome and its association with psychosocial and lifestyle variables: a cross-sectional study from Palestine. BMC Womens Health. 2021;21:233. 10.1186/s12905-021-01374-6.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12905-021-01374-6"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8178841"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34090416"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Abu Alwafa R, Badrasawi M, Haj Hamad R. Prevalence of premenstrual syndrome and its association with psychosocial and lifestyle variables: a cross-sectional study from Palestine. BMC Womens Health. 2021;21:233. 10.1186/s12905-021-01374-6."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR85"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kamat SV, Nimbalkar A, Phatak AG, Nimbalkar SM. Premenstrual syndrome in Anand District, Gujarat: a cross-sectional survey. J Family Med Prim Care. 2019;8:640–7. 10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_302_.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_302_18"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6436252"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30984687"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Kamat SV, Nimbalkar A, Phatak AG, Nimbalkar SM. Premenstrual syndrome in Anand District, Gujarat: a cross-sectional survey. J Family Med Prim Care. 2019;8:640–7. 10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_302_."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR86"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Alshdaifat E, Absy N, Sindiani A, AlOsta N, Hijazi H, Amarin Z, Alnazly E. Premenstrual syndrome and its association with perceived stress: the experience of medical students in Jordan. Int J Womens Health. 2022;14:777–85. 10.2147/IJWH.S361964.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2147/IJWH.S361964"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9206437"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35726296"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Alshdaifat E, Absy N, Sindiani A, AlOsta N, Hijazi H, Amarin Z, Alnazly E. Premenstrual syndrome and its association with perceived stress: the experience of medical students in Jordan. Int J Womens Health. 2022;14:777–85. 10.2147/IJWH.S361964."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR87"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Upadhyay M, Mahishale A, Kari A. Prevalence of premenstrual syndrome in college going girls - A cross sectional study. Clin Epidemiol Glob. 2023;6:10.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Upadhyay M, Mahishale A, Kari A. Prevalence of premenstrual syndrome in college going girls - A cross sectional study. Clin Epidemiol Glob. 2023;6:10."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR88"><named-content content-type="citation-string">İlaslan N, Orak NS. Relationship between nursing students’ global climate change awareness, climate change anxiety and sustainability attitudes in nursing: a descriptive and cross-sectional study. BMC Nurs. 2024;23(1):573. 10.1186/s12912-024-02252-w.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12912-024-02252-w"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11330052"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39154184"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="İlaslan N, Orak NS. Relationship between nursing students’ global climate change awareness, climate change anxiety and sustainability attitudes in nursing: a descriptive and cross-sectional study. BMC Nurs. 2024;23(1):573. 10.1186/s12912-024-02252-w."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR89"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Huh I, Choi-Kwon S, Ki J, Kim S, Baek J. Premenstrual Symptoms Risk Factors among Newly Graduated Nurses in Shift Work: A Prospective Longitudinal Study. Asian Nurs Res. 2024;18:501–8.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.anr.2024.10.006"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39491721"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Huh I, Choi-Kwon S, Ki J, Kim S, Baek J. Premenstrual Symptoms Risk Factors among Newly Graduated Nurses in Shift Work: A Prospective Longitudinal Study. Asian Nurs Res. 2024;18:501–8."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Li T, Xie Q. Effects of college students’ perceived stress on anxiety in the time of COVID-19: the chain mediation role of psychological resilience and regulatory emotional self-efficacy. IJMHP. 2022;24(2):263–276.</named-content></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>All generated and analyzed data in this research are included in this manuscript. The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec></sec></body></article>