
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.4 20241031//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-4-mathml3.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clim Chang Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Clim Chang Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4814</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jcch</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Climate Change and Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2667-2782</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13089125</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC13089125.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13089125</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13089125</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">42005570</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joclim.2026.100650</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2667-2782(26)00005-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100650</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Climate worry and daily life impacts among a sample of Canadian youth accessing integrated youth services</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zachary</given-names></name><email>zachary.daly@ubc.ca</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names initials="EK">Emily K.</given-names></name><email>emily.jenkins@ubc.ca</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adair</surname><given-names initials="S">Sarah</given-names></name><email>sadair@foundrybc.ca</email><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names initials="AF">A. Fuchsia</given-names></name><email>fuchsia.howard@ubc.ca</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbic</surname><given-names initials="S">Skye</given-names></name><email>skye.barbic@ubc.ca</email><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">g</xref><xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">h</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>School of Nursing, T201-2211 Wesbrook Mall, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Wellstream: The Canadian Centre for Innovation in Child and Youth Mental Health and Substance Use, T308-2211 Wesbrook Mall, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>Human Early Learning Partnership (HELP), Suite 440, 2206 East Mall, School of Population and Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>d</label>Foundry, 915-1045 Howe Street, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>e</label>Women's Health Research Institute, 4500 Oak St, BC Women's Hospital and Health Centre, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>f</label>Fraser Health Authority, 13750 96th Avenue, Surrey, British Columbia, Canada</aff><aff id="aff0007"><label>g</label>Department of Occupational Science &amp; Occupational Therapy, T325-2211 Wesbrook Mall, Faculty of Medicine, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</aff><aff id="aff0008"><label>h</label>Centre for Advancing Health Outcomes, 588-1081 Burrard Street, Vancouver, BC, Canada, V6Z 1Y6</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: T325-2211 Wesbrook Mall, Vancouver, British Columbia, V6T 2A1, Canada. <email>skye.barbic@ubc.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2026</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>4</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">511871</issue-id><elocation-id>100650</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>18</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-04-20 15:25:19.677"><day>20</day><month>04</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2026 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2026</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"><?pdf-name main.pdf?><?pdf-size 732980?><?pdf-md5 071ab8ef767d02ba5d30d92c62e482ed?><?pdf-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?pdf-cloudpmc-urn urn:app:b6b3/13089125/071ab8ef767d/main.pdf?></self-uri><abstract id="abs0001"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Despite calls for service providers to support youth in navigating the mental health impacts of climate change, data from clinical contexts remain limited. Our research explores climate worry among youth accessing integrated youth services (IYS) in British Columbia, Canada.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Youth aged 16-24 years (n=393) were recruited from the waiting rooms of four IYS centres. Participants completed a survey to capture sociodemographic characteristics and assess mental health, including single items on level of climate change worry and whether feelings about climate change negatively impacted their daily lives.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Overall, 40.9% of participants were very or extremely worried about climate change and 28.0% of participants reported that their feelings about climate change resulted in negative impacts on their daily life. Gender diverse youth and older youth were more likely to report negative daily life impacts due to their feelings about climate change. Moreover, while climate worry was inconsistently associated with measures of mental health, reporting that climate change was negatively impacting daily life was associated with higher scores of depressive symptoms, psychological distress, and worsened functioning across multiple domains.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study is among the first to examine the relationship between climate change and youth mental health in a clinical sample. From these results, it is clear that a substantial subset of youth accessing clinical services are identifying that their feelings about climate change are negatively impacting their daily lives. Based on these results, service providers should be attuned to the impacts of climate change on youth mental health.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Climate distress</kwd><kwd>Mental health</kwd><kwd>Climate change</kwd><kwd>Climate anxiety</kwd><kwd>Youth</kwd><kwd>Integrated youth services</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0001"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0005">Climate change and its effects have been linked to a growing number of adverse consequences for human health [<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>]. One health consequence that is receiving increasing attention is the negative impacts of climate change on mental health, particularly among youth [<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>]. These mental health impacts can be either direct or indirect [<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The former refers to impacts resulting from experiences of climate change-induced disasters, such as wildfires, floods, and storms, as well as witnessing more gradual changes, such disruptions to local ecosystems. The latter refers to impacts resulting from the more existential concerns arising from overall awareness of climate change and its impacts [<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. As a whole, these impacts have been found to exacerbate or trigger mental health concerns, including anxiety, depression, and post-traumatic stress disorder [<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p id="para0006">Alongside these mental health concerns, climate change has been found to contribute to various challenging emotional responses, including but not limited to fear, anxiety, anger, despair, and grief [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>]. Various terms have been suggested to describe these responses, including climate anxiety, eco-anxiety, and climate worry, as well as more specialized terms such as solastalgia, ecological grief, Anthropocene horror, and eco-despair [<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>]. Given this profusion of terminology, <italic toggle="yes">climate distress</italic> has been used as an umbrella term to refer to these impacts collectively [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Of note, challenging emotions related to climate change are not inherently pathological [<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>]. Indeed, such reactions can be thought of as rational responses to the state of the world. Some scholars have suggested that they can even be adaptive [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], with positive relationships to pro-environmental behaviours [<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p id="para0007">However, research also suggests that, for some youth, experiences of climate distress are associated with mental ill-health [<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], with youth considered at increased risk of these negative mental health consequences [<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], owing to their stage of brain development [<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], higher exposure to distressing media [<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], and differing temporal orientation [<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Furthermore, research has identified that certain youth are more likely to experience climate distress, with girls and gender diverse youth often identified as having higher levels of climate distress [<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p id="para0008">Recognizing these risks, there is a growing body of literature exploring the mental health impacts of various forms of climate distress, including climate worry, on youth, mostly at a population-level [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The overall pattern is that various forms of climate distress are associated with worsened youth mental health [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], including climate worry [<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>].</p><p id="para0009">However, data on the mental health impacts of climate change among youth accessing clinical services remain limited [<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. This is concerning given that the studies that are available indicate this issue is leading to clinical presentations [<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. While it has been suggested that climate-change related emotional responses may reach the level of clinical significance when an individual is unable to able to cope with them on their own [<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] or when there are impacts to daily functioning [<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], there remain gaps in understandings about when clinical intervention might be warranted [<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p id="para0010">Given these knowledge gaps, the purpose of this paper is to understand how climate worry and daily life impacts due to emotions about climate change present in a sample of youth aged 16-24 years accessing health and social services in British Columbia (BC), Canada. The primary aim is to determine to what extent climate worry and negative daily life impacts due to emotions about climate change in a clinical sample are associated with measures of mental health and functioning. A secondary aim is to identify youth characteristics that may increase the likelihood of experiencing emotions about climate change that negatively impact their daily life.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><p id="para0011">This study presents findings on the mental health impacts of climate change for youth who accessed clinical services at Foundry, an integrated youth services (IYS) initiative in BC, Canada, between March 2023 and April 2024. Foundry consists of a network of community-based centres, and a virtual service, that co-locates low-barrier mental health, substance use, physical/sexual health, peer support, and social services [<xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. BC has experienced several climate events in recent years, such as a Heat Dome in 2021, which killed 619 people [<xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Furthermore, the interior region of BC experiences frequent, destructive wildfires [<xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], which result in air quality advisories across many areas of the province [<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p><p id="para0012">As part of a larger study examining youth health and functioning, youth aged 16-24 years were recruited from the waiting rooms of four Foundry centres; three centres are located in the Lower Mainland region of BC, and one is located in the Northern region of the province. Youth who were waiting to receive clinical services were approached by a member of the study team and informed about the opportunity to participate in the study.</p><p id="para0013">Ethical approval was attained from the University of British Columbia Behavioural Research Ethics Board (H20-03100). Informed consent was obtained from all participants. The consent form included information about the study, potential risks, how the data would be used, and who the youth could contact with further questions or concerns. Youth were informed that their data would be kept confidential and not shared with their healthcare team. Youth were provided with a tablet computer to complete the survey. Participants were compensated for their time with a $10 cash honorarium and entered into a gift card draw. They were also provided with information on locally available mental health resources.</p><sec id="sec0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Measures</title><p id="para0014">Sociodemographic questions characterized the sample according to a range of personal characteristics, including age, gender, housing status, and education.</p><p id="para0015">Mental Health was assessed using a variety of measures, including a single-item measure of overall mental health: “In general, would you say your mental health is…” with response options of “Excellent”, “Very good”, “Good”, “Fair” and “Poor”. This item has seen widespread use in the Canadian context [<xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p><p id="para0016">Given prior documented associations between climate worry and depression [<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], the Patient Health Questionnaire-8 (PHQ-8) [<xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] was also included, which measures depressive symptoms over the prior two weeks. The PHQ-8 has been used with youth samples [<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and was selected for this study as it omits an item on suicidal or self-injurious thoughts, while still being a valid measure of depressive symptoms [<xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. For the PHQ-8, cut-offs were used to categorize participants as having no significant depressive symptoms (scores &lt;5), mild depressive symptoms (scores ≥5 and &lt;10), moderate depressive symptoms (scores ≥10 and &lt;15), moderately severe depressive symptoms (scores ≥15 and &lt; 20), or severe depressive symptoms (scores ≥20) [<xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The Cronbach’s-alpha for the PHQ-8 in this sample was 0.89.</p><p id="para0017">Additionally, the 10-item version of the Kessler Psychological Distress Scale (K10) was used to measure psychological distress over the previous 30 days [<xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. For the K10, cut-offs were used to categorize participants as having no/low psychological distress (scores ≤15), moderate psychological distress (scores &gt;15 and ≤21), high psychological distress (scores &gt;21 and ≤29), or very high psychological distress (scores ≥30) [<xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The Cronbach’s alpha for this scale was 0.93.</p><p id="para0018">Finally, to explore impacts on functioning, the 36-item World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule-2.0 (WHODAS) [<xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] was used to assess functioning over the previous 30 days across six sub-domains: cognition, mobility, self-care, getting along with others, life activities, and participation. This scale has been previously validated among Canadian youth experiencing mental health challenges [<xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. WHODAS scores for each of the sub-domains were calculated using the Simple Scoring Method [<xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], in which values for individual items are summed and divided by the number of items in the sub-domain. This scoring method is considered suited to clinical contexts [<xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and process results in scores ranging from 1 to 5, with higher scores indicating greater difficulties with everyday functioning. The Cronbach’s alphas for the six sub-scales of the WHODAS were 0.86, 0.86, 0.75, 0.84, 0.94, and 0.93, respectively.</p><p id="para0019">To assess climate worry and daily life impacts due to feelings about climate change, we used two separate items drawn from a prior 10-country survey of youth [<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]; these items have also been used in research in Brazil [<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and with Canadian youth [<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. One item explored climate worry through the question: “I am worried that climate change threatens people and the planet”, with the response options including: “Not worried”, “A little worried”, “Moderately worried”, “Very worried”, “Extremely worried”, and “Prefer not to say”. Similar single-item measures of climate worry have been used in prior studies [<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>]. The other climate item assessed daily life impacts due to climate distress more generally: “My feelings about climate change negatively affect my daily life (at least one of the following is negatively affected: Eating, concentrating, work, school, sleeping, spending time in nature, playing, having fun, relationships)”, with the response options, “yes”, “no”, and “prefer not to answer”.</p></sec><sec id="sec0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Analysis</title><p id="para0020">Bivariate relationships between ordinal variables were examined using Goodman and Kruskal's gamma. Mann Whitney-U tests were conducted to compare median scores on the PHQ-8, K10, and WHODAS sub-scales for those who did and did not report any level of climate worry, those who did and did not report extreme climate worry, and those who did and did not report negative daily life impacts due to feelings about climate change. Given that prior research has found differences among youth based on age [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], age was dichotomized to compare older (19-24 years) and younger (16-18) youth. Chi-square tests were used to examine differences in the prevalence of reporting negative daily life impacts across sociodemographic characteristics; post-hoc comparisons using a Bonferroni correction were conducted as needed. All analyses were completed using SPSS 29.0 [<xref rid="bib0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. A p-value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant and pairwise deletion was used to address missing data.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0005"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec0006"><label>3.1</label><title>Sociodemographic characteristics</title><p id="para0021">A total of 393 youth participated in the survey. The mean age of participants was 20.4 years (standard deviation 2.58), and 48.1% identified as women. The majority of participants were living in market housing, although 9.9% were homeless or living in a shelter. Sociodemographic characteristics are presented in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sociodemographic characteristics of the sample.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Table 1 dummy alt text</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16-18</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19-24</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">292</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender identity</bold><xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Woman</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">189</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender diverse</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">108</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Man</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Missing</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Ethnicity</bold><xref rid="tb1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">⁎⁎</xref></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">White/Caucasian (European)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">177</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">First Nations/Métis/Inuit</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">East Asian (Chinese, Japanese, Korean)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Southeast Asian (Filipino, Indonesian, Thai)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other (mixed ethnicity)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hispanic/Latino (Chilean, Columbian, Mexican)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Middle Eastern/North African (Armenian, Egyptian, Iranian, Lebanese, Moroccan)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South Asian (Bangladeshi, Indian, Pakistani, Nepalese)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Black (Kenyan, Nigerian, Somali)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Caribbean (Haitian, Jamaican)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prefer not to answer</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Housing</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Market rental (apartment with roommates, family home)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">234</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">59.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Homeless/shelter</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shared housing (where more than 5 people share a bathroom)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8. 9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Supportive housing (group home, support staff in the building)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Missing</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Highest level of completed education</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Less than high school</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High school graduate</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">142</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Some college</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">101</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Undergraduate or graduate degree</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb1fn1"><label>⁎</label><p id="notep0001">: Participants were asked “How would you describe your gender identity? (check all that apply)”, and were provided the following response options: female, male, non-binary, Two-Spirit, Trans female, Trans male, not sure/questioning, I don’t identify with any of these options, and Prefer not to answer. Participants who selected only male were categorized as man and participants who selected only female were categorized as woman. Participants who chose other options, or combinations of options, were considered gender diverse.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb1fn2"><label>⁎⁎</label><p id="notep0002">: Participants were asked: “Which ethnicity do you identify with? (check all that apply)”.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0007"><label>3.2</label><title>Mental health characteristics</title><p id="para0024"><xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents mental health characteristics of the sample. There was a high degree of mental health concern among participants, with over half screening positive for very high psychological distress. Over one in five were categorized as experiencing severe depressive symptoms.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Mental health, and climate distress characteristics of the sample.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Table 2 dummy alt text</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold><underline>M</underline><underline>ental health characteristics</underline></bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Self-reported health</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Excellent</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Very good</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">77</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">156</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fair</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poor</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Self-reported mental health</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Excellent</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Very good</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Good</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fair</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">146</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Poor</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">114</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Depressive symptoms (PHQ8)</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No significant depressive symptoms</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mild depressive symptoms</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate significant depressive symptoms</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderately severe depressive symptoms</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">83</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Severe depressive symptoms</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Missing/unable to calculate</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">48</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Psychological distress (K10)</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">None to low psychological distress</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderate psychological distress</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">High psychological distress</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">80</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Very high psychological distress</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">210</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">53.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Missing/unable to calculate</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>WHODAS sub-domain scores</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interquartile range</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Cognition (n=345)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.33</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.17</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mobility (n=351)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.20</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Self-care (n=341)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.75</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Getting along with others (n=287)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Life activities (n=331)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.50</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Participation (n=293)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.50</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold><underline>Climate distress characteristics</underline></bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>I am worried that climate change threatens people and the planet</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not worried</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">A little worried</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Moderately worried</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">133</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Very worried</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Extremely worried</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prefer not to say</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Skipped question</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>My feelings about climate change negatively affect my daily life (at least one of the following is negatively affected: Eating, concentrating, work, school, sleeping, spending time in nature, playing, having fun, relationships)</bold></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">247</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">62.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">110</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prefer not to answer</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Skipped question</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0008"><label>3.3</label><title>Climate worry and daily life impacts due to emotions about climate change</title><p id="para0025">As shown in <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, a total of 40.9% of participants reported being very or extremely worried about climate change, and 28.0% reported experiencing negative impacts on their daily lives due to their feelings about climate change. There was a strong positive relationship between level of climate worry and negative impacts to daily life due to feelings about climate change (G=0.53, p&lt;0.001) (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Notably, even among participants who reported no climate worry, 11.5% indicated that their feelings about climate change had a negative impact on their daily life. Among those who endorsed extreme climate worry, 34.3% reported that their feelings were <italic toggle="yes">not</italic> impacting their daily life.<fig id="fig0001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Relationship between climate worry and reporting that feelings about climate change negatively impact daily life.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Figure 1: dummy alt text</alt-text><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="celink0001" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"><?image-name gr1.jpg?><?image-size 33672?><?image-md5 08e3c889790966fdac5c188adaa08385?><?image-image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?image-original-height 1492?><?image-original-width 2503?><?image-scaled-height 426?><?image-scaled-width 715?><?image-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/b6b3/13089125/08e3c8897909/gr1.jpg?><?thumb-name gr1.gif?><?thumb-size 2650?><?thumb-md5 072e406c0aa3ddf5e6cfe2ced66adf8f?><?thumb-image-server-status NEVER_LOAD?><?thumb-scaled-height 80?><?thumb-scaled-width 134?><?thumb-cloudpmc-urn urn:cdn:blobs/b6b3/13089125/072e406c0aa3/gr1.gif?></graphic></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0009"><label>3.4</label><title>Climate worry, daily life impacts due to emotions about climate change, and wellbeing</title><p id="para0026">There was a weak negative relationship between climate worry and self-reported mental health (G=-0.19, p&lt;0.001). However, there was no relationship between climate worry and depressive symptoms (G=0.06 p=0.32) or between climate worry and psychological distress (G=0.13, p=0.07). There was a moderate negative relationship between reporting negative daily impacts due to feelings about climate change and self-reported mental health (G=-0.22, p=0.01), as well as moderate positive relationships between reporting negative daily impacts due to feelings about climate change and both depressive symptoms (G=0.21, p=0.02) and psychological distress (G=0.35, p&lt;0.001).</p><p id="para0027">As shown in <xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, the difference in median scores between those reporting any level of climate worry and those who reported not being worried was not statistically significant for the PHQ-8, K10, or any of the WHODAS subdomains. Compared to those who did not report extreme climate worry, individuals who did report extreme climate worry had higher median scores for the Cognition, Self-care, and Getting along subdomains of the WHODAS. Those who reported negative daily life impacts had higher median scores for the PHQ-8 and K10, as well as five of the sub-domains of the WHODAS, with the life activities sub-domain the only exception.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of median scores on the PHQ-8, K10, and WHODAS sub-scales by climate distress responses<xref rid="tb3fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Table 3: dummy alt text</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Comparison 1<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Comparison 2<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">Comparison 3<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Scale or sub-scale</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Any climate worry <xref rid="tb3fn2" ref-type="table-fn">⁎⁎</xref></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No climate worry</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Extreme climate worry</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not extreme climate worry <xref rid="tb3fn3" ref-type="table-fn">⁎⁎⁎</xref></th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Daily life impacts</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No daily life impacts</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">PHQ-8</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>16.00</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>14.00</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.007</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">K10</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.85</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>35.00</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>30.00</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHODAS: cognition</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.33</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.33</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.83</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.33</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.83</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.17</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHODAS: mobility</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.70</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.73</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.90</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.60</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.00</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.60</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHODAS: self-care</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.75</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.75</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.13</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.75</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.01</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.00</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.75</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHODAS: getting along with others</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.00</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.61</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.40</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.00</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.03</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.40</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.00</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHODAS: life activities</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.56</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.72</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.81</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.75</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0. 31</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WHODAS: participation</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.88</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.63</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.38</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.75</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.25</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb3fn1"><label>⁎</label><p id="notep0003">: Mann Whitney-U tests used to compare median scores, p-values &lt;0.05 are bolded.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb3fn2"><label>⁎⁎</label><p id="notep0004">: Those who reported being “A little worried”, “Moderately worried”, “Very worried”, or “Extremely worried”.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb3fn3"><label>⁎⁎⁎</label><p id="notep0005">: Those who reported being "Not worried”, “A little worried”, “Moderately worried”, or “Very worried”.</p><p id="notep0006">K10: Kessler Psychological Distress Scale, PHQ-8: Patient Health Questionnaire-8, WHODAS: World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule-2.0</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>3.5</label><title>Sociodemographic variables and negative daily life impacts</title><p id="para0032">The relative prevalence of reporting that feelings about climate change negatively affect daily life by various sociodemographic variables is presented in <xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. Those who were gender diverse had a higher prevalence of negative daily life impacts than those who identified as men or as women. Furthermore, individuals aged 19-24 years were more likely to report negative life impacts compared to those who were younger.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0004" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Prevalence of reporting that feelings about climate change negatively affect daily life by sociodemographic characteristics.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Table 4: dummy alt text</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1">My feelings about climate change negatively affect my daily life<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">n</th><th valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">%</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">p-value <xref rid="tb4fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Gender identity</bold><xref rid="tb4fn2" ref-type="table-fn">⁎⁎</xref></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Woman (n=177)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24.9<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gender diverse (n=98)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.9<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Man (n=80)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.0<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Education level</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not completed high school (n=86)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23.3</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Complete high school or more (n=271)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Housing situation</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Market rental (apartment with roommates, family home) (n=217)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">29.0</td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Homeless/shelter (n=35)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Shared housing (where more than 5 people share a bathroom) (n=32)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Supportive housing (group home, support staff in the building) (n=22)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16-18 (n=92)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21.7</td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" colspan="1"><bold>0.03</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19-24 (n=265)</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">90</td><td valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb4fn1"><label>⁎</label><p id="notep0007">: Determined via Chi-square. Superscript letters for the gender variable indicate which categories differ at the p&lt;0.05 level, based on post-hoc analysis, using a Bonferroni correction.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tb4fn2"><label>⁎⁎</label><p id="notep0008">: Participants were asked “How would you describe your gender identity? (check all that apply)”, and were provided the following options: female, male, non-binary, Two-Spirit, Trans female, Trans male, not sure/questioning, I don’t identify with any of these options, and Prefer not to answer. Participants who selected only male were categorized as man and participants who selected only female were categorized as woman. Participants who chose other options, or combinations of options, were considered gender diverse.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0011"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="para0035">Despite calls to better support youth experiencing mental health concerns related to climate change [<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bib0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], there is limited available data from clinical contexts to provide evidence-based guidance. This paper, based on surveys of youth accessing services at one of four IYS centres in BC, presents some of the first quantitative data on climate worry and daily life impacts due to climate-related emotional responses among a clinical sample of youth.</p><p id="para0036">Nearly all of the youth in this study reported experiencing climate worry to some degree, many at a high level. Further, over a quarter reported that their feelings about climate change were negatively impacting their daily lives. This appears lower than what has been reported in community-based population surveys of youth in Canada [<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], although the reasons for this discrepancy are unclear. While there are limited clinical data to make comparisons, research conducted at a youth outpatient mental health practice in the United States found a high level of mental health concern related to climate change, with approximately two-thirds of participants reporting anxiety due to hearing about climate change, with symptoms including worry, anxiety about the future, and difficulty sleeping [<xref rid="bib0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p><p id="para0037">In the present study, there was a strong positive relationship between level of climate worry and reporting that one’s feelings about climate change negatively impact daily life. However, the associations between climate worry and measures of mental health and functioning were inconsistent, with only a weak relationship with self-reported mental health, and unsignificant associations with depressive symptoms and psychological distress. These findings support the notion that climate distress may not be inherently pathological [<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], but contrast with other research documenting significant relationships between climate worry and depression [<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><p id="para0038">What seems important, from a clinical perspective, is reporting impacts on daily life as a result of negative climate emotions. Youth who reported that their emotions about climate change negatively impacted their daily life had higher median scores on the PHQ-8, K10, and on five of the six sub-domains of the WHODAS. Given the associations with worsened wellbeing across multiple domains, reporting such impacts likely indicates the need for further assessment. This is in line with the view that impacts to daily functioning warrant clinical attention [<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. However, while there have been suggestions that clinicians screen for the impact of climate change on youth mental health [<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], none of the existing scales have been created for this purpose [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p id="para0039">Among youth who did not report any worry about climate change, a small number still indicated experiencing negative impacts to their daily lives because of their feelings about climate change. This suggests that worry is not the only emotional response to climate change associated with mental health concerns. Youth whose climate distress manifests in other feelings, such as grief, risk being “missed” if questions focus on worry alone. Open-ended questions may thus be of use during clinical assessment [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Conversely, even among those who reported being extremely worried about climate change, one in three did not endorse negative daily life impacts. This suggests that youth can potentially cope with even high levels of climate worry, supporting the notion that strong emotions in response to climate change do not necessarily manifest in a clinically significant manner. While there have been numerous studies into how youth cope with the emotions brought on by climate change [<xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0056" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0057" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>], to our knowledge, none are focused on clinical contexts.</p><p id="para0040">Our findings further show that the prevalence of reporting daily life impacts due to climate change varies by sociodemographic characteristics. Specifically, youth who are gender diverse are more likely to report negative daily life impacts due to climate change. This finding is consistent with prior population-level research in Canada [<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and elsewhere [<xref rid="bib0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. While the underlying reasons are not clear, it is important to note that gender diverse youth experience a number of mental health inequities [<xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="bib0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Findings indicating that older youth are more likely to experience negative impacts to daily functioning as a result of climate change-related emotions also align with population-level research into age and climate distress [<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p id="para0041">This study has important limitations. To start, the research is based on a convenience sample from a limited number of IYS centres in BC, Canada. As such, caution must be taken when generalizing to youth in other contexts or accessing different kinds of clinical services. This is particularly the case, given that none of the four centres in the study were located in rural areas; prior research has indicated that there may be differences in youth climate distress across urban and rural areas [<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p id="para0042">Another limitation is that of missing data. The question on housing status was only added partway through data collection, resulting in a relatively high amount of missingness and reducing statistical power. Furthermore, it was not possible to calculate PHQ-8, K10, or WHODAS scores for all youth. The fact that entire scales were often skipped, along with all subsequent questions, suggests that some youth may have been leaving surveys incomplete after being called to appointments. One exception is an item on the WHODAS related to sexual activity. This item had a higher degree of missingness than others, suggesting that youth may have been choosing not to respond to this question. This issue of missingness may be related to another limitation of the study, which was the relatively long length of the survey.</p><p id="para0043">Finally, there is the issue of causation. Indeed, the difficulty of disentangling causal pathways between various forms of climate distress and more general mental health concerns has been identified as a widespread issue [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. While climate change may be driving mental health concerns in some youth, it is also possible that existing mental health challenges predispose some youth to climate distress, or that causal pathways are bidirectional [<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. However, regardless of the causal direction, the clinical implications are clear: if a youth reports that their emotions about climate change are negatively impacting their life, further follow-up is needed to guide related supports.</p><p id="para0044">These findings suggest several areas for future research. For example, there is a need for research exploring how youth who report extreme climate worry, but no impact to their daily lives, differ from those who identify extreme worry alongside daily life impacts. Such differences could reveal protective factors and potential interventions. Further research is also needed to better understand the underlying pathways connecting climate distress and socio-demographic characteristics, such as gender. More broadly, given the limited data, it would be helpful to examine this issue in other, varied clinical contexts.</p></sec><sec id="sec0012"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="para0045">This study is among the first to examine climate change and mental health among youth accessing clinical services. Many of the youth were very or extremely worried about climate change, and a notable subset identified that their feelings about climate change were negatively impacting their daily lives, suggesting a need for clinical support. These results underscore the urgent need for service providers to be attuned to the impacts of climate change on youth mental health, and for further research to refine assessment methods for these impacts, determine protective factors, and understand what forms of support youth find most helpful.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec0013"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="para0046">The datasets generated and/or analysed during the current study are not publicly available due to privacy but are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="sec0013a"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="para0046a"><bold>Zachary Daly:</bold> Writing – original draft, Methodology, Formal analysis, Data curation, Conceptualization. <bold>Emily K. Jenkins:</bold> Writing – original draft, Supervision, Methodology, Conceptualization. <bold>Sarah Adair:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Project administration, Investigation, Data curation. <bold>A. Fuchsia Howard:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing. <bold>Skye Barbic:</bold> Writing – review &amp; editing, Supervision, Project administration, Methodology, Conceptualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="coi0001"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="para0047">Zachary Daly serves on the board of Canadian Association of Nurses for the Environment (CANE) and has accepted speaking fees from the Canadian Association of Physicians for the Environment (CAPE). Neither organization had any role in the collection of data, the writing of the manuscript, or the decision to submit for publication. Other authors declare that they have no competing or potential conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schnitter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Health of Canadians in a changing climate: advancing our knowledge for action</part-title><year>2022 Feb 09</year><publisher-name>Government of Canada</publisher-name><publisher-loc>OttawaCanada</publisher-loc><comment>Internet]cited 2023 Jan 31]. Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://geoscan.nrcan.gc.ca/starweb/geoscan/servlet.starweb?path=geoscan/fulle.web&amp;search1=R=329522" id="interref0001">https://geoscan.nrcan.gc.ca/starweb/geoscan/servlet.starweb?path=geoscan/fulle.web&amp;search1=R=329522</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romanello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walawender</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moskeland</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmeiro-Silva</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scamman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The 2024 report of the <italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic> Countdown on health and climate change: facing record-breaking threats from delayed action</article-title><source>The Lancet.</source><volume>404</volume><issue>10465</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>1847</fpage><lpage>1896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01822-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7616816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39488222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocque</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaudoin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ndjaboue</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poirier-Bergeron</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin-Rheault</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health effects of climate change: an overview of systematic reviews</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2021 June 1</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e046333</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/bmjopen-2020-046333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8191619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34108165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massazza</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teyton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benmarhnia</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Augustinavicius</surname><given-names>JL.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative methods for climate change and mental health research: current trends and future directions</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>e613</fpage><lpage>e627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35809589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00120-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwong</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chagwedera</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grzenda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doty</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate change and mental health research methods, gaps, and priorities: a scoping review</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>e281</fpage><lpage>e291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35278392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00012-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrance</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newberry</surname><given-names>Le</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of climate change on mental health and emotional wellbeing: A narrative review of current evidence, and its implications</article-title><source>Int Rev Psychiatry</source><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36165756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09540261.2022.2128725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godden</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrant</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yallup Farrant</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heyink</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carot Collins</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgemeister</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate change, activism, and supporting the mental health of children and young people: perspectives from Western Australia</article-title><source>J Paediatr Child Health</source><volume>57</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>1759</fpage><lpage>1764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34792244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jpc.15649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9299447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosh</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fallander</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tognela</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The relationship between climate change and mental health: a systematic review of the association between eco-anxiety, psychological distress, and symptoms of major affective disorders</article-title><source>BMC Psychiatry</source><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>833</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39567913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12888-024-06274-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11577747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gousse-Lessard</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamann Legris</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards a unified conceptual framework of eco-anxiety: mapping eco-anxiety through a scoping review</article-title><source>Cogent Ment Health</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2490524</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/28324765.2025.2490524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12443025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41262948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pihkala</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anxiety and the ecological crisis: an analysis of eco-Anxiety and climate anxiety</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>12</volume><issue>19</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>7836</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pihkala</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayall</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate anxiety in children and young people and their beliefs about government responses to climate change: a global survey</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><volume>5</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2021</year><fpage>e863</fpage><lpage>e873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34895496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(21)00278-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aylward</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunsolo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minor</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatwood</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Examining the mental health impacts of climate change on young people in Canada: a national cross-sectional survey</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><volume>8</volume><year>2024</year><fpage>S3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38632918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(24)00068-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galway</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate emotions and anxiety among young people in Canada: A national survey and call to action</article-title><source>J Clim Change Health</source><volume>9</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100204</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benomar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corvello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingsbury</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate emotions, pro-environmental behaviours, and activism among Canadian youth</article-title><source>J Ment Health Clim Change</source><year>2023</year><comment>Internet]cited 2024 Feb 20]; Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.10443325" id="interref0002">https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.10443325</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verplanken</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobromir</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the nature of eco-anxiety: how constructive or unconstructive is habitual worry about global warming?</article-title><source>J Environ Psychol</source><volume>72</volume><year>2020 Dec</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101528</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological grief and Anthropocene horror</article-title><source>Am Imago</source><volume>77</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>80</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galway</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beery</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones-Casey</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tasala</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping the solastalgia literature: A scoping review study</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><volume>16</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>2662</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31349659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph16152662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6696016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wortzel</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denga</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angrish</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manjón</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shabdar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pediatric climate distress: A scoping review and clinical resource</article-title><source>J Clim Change Health</source><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100349</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joclim.2024.100349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12851285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41647131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate Distress: A review of current psychological research and practice</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>15</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>8115</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>We need to (find a way to) talk about … eco-anxiety</article-title><source>J Soc Work Pract</source><volume>34</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>424</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhullar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunn</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rickwood</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate anxiety does not need a diagnosis of a mental health disorder</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>e383</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35550075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00072-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diffey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uchendu</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masithi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olude</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juma</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Not about us without us” – the feelings and hopes of climate-concerned young people around the world</article-title><source>Int Rev Psychiatry</source><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36165749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09540261.2022.2126297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunbode</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanss</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ojala</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmela-Aro</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Broek</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate anxiety, wellbeing and pro-environmental action: correlates of negative emotional responses to climate change in 32 countries</article-title><source>J Environ Psychol</source><volume>84</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101887</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>C.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manrique</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Empirical evidence for climate concerns, negative emotions and climate-related mental ill-health in young people: A scoping review</article-title><source>Early Interv Psychiatry</source><year>2023</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/eip.13374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36641809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergunst</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>HL.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change and children’s mental health: A developmental perspective</article-title><source>Clin Psychol Sci J Assoc Psychol Sci</source><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>767</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/21677026211040787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9280699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35846172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0026"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crandon</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>HJ.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A social–ecological perspective on climate anxiety in children and adolescents</article-title><source>Nat Clim Change</source><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0027"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadarajah</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bordel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moyon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Foll</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>We are running out of time”: temporal orientation and information seeking as explanatory factors of climate anxiety among young people</article-title><source>Psych</source><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>560</fpage><lpage>573</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Man</surname><given-names>L.L.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotenberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Eco-depression and eco-anxiety among youth: a sex and gender analysis</article-title><source>Can J Psychiatry</source><year>2024 Oct 1</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07067437241287153</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/07067437241287153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11562931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39350726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizeq</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ojala</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate worry and hope have different associations with well-being and Climate-friendly behaviors across young people from Sweden and Qatar</article-title><source>Ecopsychology</source><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025 Mar</year><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sciberras</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>JW.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change-related worry among Australian adolescents: an eight-year longitudinal study</article-title><source>Child Adolesc Ment Health</source><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34766705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/camh.12521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergunst</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paquin</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vitaro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of youth climate change worry with present and past mental health symptoms: a longitudinal population-based study</article-title><source>Clim Change</source><volume>177</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>153</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0032"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slemon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salway</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadermann</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations between periods of COVID-19 quarantine and mental health in Canada</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res</source><volume>295</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">113631</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.psychres.2020.113631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7718586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33310417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0033"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>V.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitmarsh</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poortinga</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Constable</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>There’s no helpline’: how mental health services can support young people with climate distress</article-title><source>Cogent Ment Health</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">41262662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/28324765.2024.2409815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12443002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0034"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0034"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Royal College of Psychiatrists</collab></person-group><part-title>The climate crisis is taking a toll on the mental health of children and young people</part-title><year>2020 Nov 10</year><publisher-name>Royal College of PsychiatristsRoyal College of Psychiatrists</publisher-name><publisher-loc>LondonUnited Kingdom</publisher-loc><comment>Internet]cited 2025 Nov 27]. Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/news-and-features/latest-news/detail/2020/11/20/the-climate-crisis-is-taking-a-toll-on-the-mental-health-of-children-and-young-people" id="interref0003">https://www.rcpsych.ac.uk/news-and-features/latest-news/detail/2020/11/20/the-climate-crisis-is-taking-a-toll-on-the-mental-health-of-children-and-young-people</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrance</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kioupi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diffey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vercammen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychological responses, mental health, and sense of agency for the dual challenges of climate change and the COVID-19 pandemic in young people in the UK: an online survey study</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><volume>6</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2022 Sept 1</year><fpage>e726</fpage><lpage>e738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36087603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00172-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9451498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0036"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallia</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuerth</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ow</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-David</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Implementing Foundry: A cohort study describing the regional and virtual expansion of a youth integrated service in British Columbia, Canada</article-title><source>Early Interv Psychiatry.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2024</year><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38736277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/eip.13538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0037"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0037"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuerth</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tee</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foundry</surname><given-names>Barbic S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>the British Columbia Integrated Youth Services Initiative: sharing lessons from a decade of innovation</article-title><source>Healthc Q Tor Ont</source><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2025 May</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12927/hcq.2025.27634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40792403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0038"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0038"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>British Columbia Coroners Service</collab></person-group><part-title>Extreme Heat and Human Mortality: A Review of Heat-Related Deaths in B.C. in Summer 2021</part-title><year>2022</year><publisher-name>British Columbia Coroners Service</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0039"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0039"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parisien</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>Q.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourbonnais</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannigan</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abrupt, climate-induced increase in wildfires in British Columbia since the mid-2000s</article-title><source>Commun Earth Environ</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023 Sept 5</year><fpage>309</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abay</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wildfire smoke, environmental justice, and young children in urban Pacific Northwest communities</article-title><source>Urban Clim</source><volume>50</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101581</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0041"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coker</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>SB.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Co-occurrence of wildfire smoke and extreme heat events in British Columbia, 2010–2022: evaluating spatiotemporal trends and inequities in exposure burden</article-title><source>ACS EST Air</source><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2025</year><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>330</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0042"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0042"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Statistics Canada</collab></person-group><part-title>Quality of life indicator: self-rated mental health</part-title><comment>Internet]</comment><source>Statistics Canada</source><year>2025 Nov 10</year><publisher-name>Government of Canada</publisher-name><publisher-loc>OttawaCanada</publisher-loc><comment>cited 2025 Nov 27]. Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www160.statcan.gc.ca/health-sante/mental-health-sante-mentale-eng.htm" id="interref0004">https://www160.statcan.gc.ca/health-sante/mental-health-sante-mentale-eng.htm</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0043"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0043"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Statistics Canada</collab></person-group><part-title>Canadian Health Survey on Children and Youth - 2025</part-title><comment>Internet]</comment><source>Staistics Canada</source><year>2025 Jul 15</year><publisher-name>Government of Canada</publisher-name><publisher-loc>OttawaCanada</publisher-loc><comment>cited 2025 Nov 13]. Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www23.statcan.gc.ca/imdb/p3Instr.pl?Function=assembleInstr&amp;lang=en&amp;Item_Id=1574659" id="interref0005">https://www23.statcan.gc.ca/imdb/p3Instr.pl?Function=assembleInstr&amp;lang=en&amp;Item_Id=1574659</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0044"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0044"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroenke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strine</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J.B.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mokdad</surname><given-names>AH.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PHQ-8 as a measure of current depression in the general population</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><volume>114</volume><issue>1–3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18752852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jad.2008.06.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonifay</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>KC.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishing the measurement precision of the patient health questionnaire in an adolescent sample</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><volume>342</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37708980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jad.2023.09.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0046"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0046"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colpe</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiripi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mroczek</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Normand</surname><given-names>S.L.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Short screening scales to monitor population prevalences and trends in non-specific psychological distress</article-title><source>Psychol Med</source><volume>32</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12214795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/s0033291702006074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0047"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0047"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pattison</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puyat</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giesbrecht</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zenone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examining mental health differences between transgender, Gender nonconforming, and cisgender young people in British Columbia</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><year>2021 Sept 29</year><comment>Internet]cited 2024 Dec 18];12. Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychiatry/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2021.720681/full" id="interref0006">https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychiatry/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2021.720681/full</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fpsyt.2021.720681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8511444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34658957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0048"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0048"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ustun</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostanjesek</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Measuring health and disability : manual for WHO Disability Assessment Schedule (WHODAS 2.0)</part-title><year>2010</year><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc><comment>Internet]cited 2024 June 3] p. 88. Available from:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/43974" id="interref0007">https://iris.who.int/handle/10665/43974</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0049"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0049"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>MA.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychometric properties and informant agreement of the WHODAS 2.0 in youth with mental disorder</article-title><source>J Can Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2023</year><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36776927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9879036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieves</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Worry related to climate change in Brazilian adults</article-title><source>Trends Psychiatry Psychother</source><volume>47</volume><year>2025</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e20240905</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.47626/2237-6089-2024-0905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12962364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39752257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0051"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0051"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roswell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Treble</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Measuring negative emotional responses to climate change among young people in survey research: A systematic review</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><volume>329</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">116008</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.socscimed.2023.116008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37329721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0052"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0052"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IBM Corporation</collab></person-group><part-title>IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows</part-title><year>2023</year><publisher-name>IBM Corp</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0053"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0053"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalglish</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Supporting young people with climate anxiety: mitigation, adaptation, and resilience</article-title><source>Lancet Planet Health</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2022</year><fpage>e190</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35278385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2542-5196(22)00015-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0054"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0054"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Root</surname><given-names>RA.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perception of climate change in adolescents and its psychiatric implications</article-title><source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source><volume>58</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>S229</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrasek MacDonald</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunsolo Willox</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiwak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective factors for mental health and well-being in a changing climate: perspectives from Inuit youth in Nunatsiavut, Labrador</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med.</source><volume>141</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26275362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.socscimed.2015.07.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0056"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0056"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barraclough</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Masters Thesis]</part-title><comment>[Internet]</comment><year>2022</year><publisher-name>Dalhousie University</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Halifax, Nova Scotia</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0057"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0057"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ojala</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulating worry, promoting hope: how do children, adolescents, and young adults cope with climate change?</article-title><source>Int J Environ Sci Educ</source><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>561</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0058"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0058"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>C.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate change concerns impact on young Australians’ psychological distress and outlook for the future</article-title><source>J Environ Psychol</source><volume>93</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102209</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0059"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0059"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forcier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gender diverse youth: opportunities to identify and address systemic inequities</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><volume>147</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2021050278</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1542/peds.2021-050278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34006617</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0001"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="para0048">ZD is supported by a Canada Graduate Scholarships Doctoral Award (CGS D) from the Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR). EJ holds a Tier II Canada Research Chair in Population Health Approaches to Mental Health and Substance Use. AFH holds a Scholar Award from Michael Smith Health Research BC. SB holds a Tier II Canada Research Chair in Integrated Youth Services. No funding source had any role in the writing of the manuscript, or the decision to submit it for publication. We would like to thank Xiaoxu Ding, Cassia Warren, and Taite Biggs for assistance with data collection. Thank you to the members of the Climate Youth Advisory Committee: Anurada U. Amarasekera, Preet Bains, &amp; Alisha Thapar. We also acknowledge the assistance and support of staff at Foundry Vancouver-Granville, Foundry Prince George, Foundry Richmond, and Foundry North Shore.</p></ack></back></article>