<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1579</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">scirep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Sci Rep</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC13219415</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">13219415</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">13219415</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41951751</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-026-47424-7</article-id><title-group><article-title>Cost-effective and scalable urban air quality monitoring using image-based deep learning</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Arifuzzaman</surname><given-names initials="M">Md</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasagan</surname><given-names initials="R">Ramasamy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Alqurashi</surname><given-names initials="R">Raghda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Alqurashi</surname><given-names initials="A">Abdulaziz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, College of Engineering, King Faisal University, 31982 Al Ahsa, Saudi Arabia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Computer Engineering, CCSIT, King Faisal University, 31982 Al Ahsa, Saudi Arabia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Computer Science, Jamoum University College,  Umm Al- Qura University, 25371 Al Jumum, Saudi Arabia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Civil Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, Islamic University of Madinah, 42351 Madinah, Saudi Arabia </aff><author-notes><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2026</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><fpage>16662</fpage><page-range>16662</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2026</copyright-statement><license><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41598_2026_Article_47424.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path 15ba/13219415/bc1cfe8fa00b/41598_2026_Article_47424.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 6709039?></self-uri><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="unstructured"><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Air pollution is a persisting problem for the environment, mainly in urban areas, given heavy industrialization and vehicular emissions and urbanization. Exposure to harmful air pollutants, including PM2.5, PM10, and toxic gases, is a major contributor to respiratory and cardiovascular diseases, accounting for millions of deaths globally each year. Answer monitoring is, therefore, the first effective measure in limiting the health effects of air pollution. The idea of this study is to advance an effective, scalable image-based deep learning (DL) system to detect air pollution levels within urban areas. The model integrates CBAM with InceptionV3 to enhance feature extraction, improving accuracy and robustness in detecting varying levels of air pollution from images. The proposed work uses Air Pollution Image Dataset from Kaggle, containing urban pollution images from India and Nepal. Preprocessing includes Gaussian Filtering to reduce noise, Histogram Equalization (HE) to enhance contrast, Thresholding to segment image, and resizing to standard dimensions. The model employs InceptionV3 integrated with Convolutional Block Attention Module (CBAM) for enhanced feature extraction. This approach classifies images into three pollution levels: Moderate, Unhealthy for Sensitive Groups (USG), and Unhealthy, enabling efficient air quality monitoring. The CBAM-InceptionV3 model achieved strong performance, with precision, recall, and F1-scores exceeding 0.95 for each class. The proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model achieves an overall classification accuracy of 95.23%, with precision, recall, and F1-score values consistently above 95%, demonstrating its effectiveness for air pollution level classification.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" xml:lang="en" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> Air pollution classification, Deep learning, CBAM, InceptionV3, Urban air quality</p></sec><sec id="kwd-group2" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Subject terms:</bold> Engineering, Environmental sciences, Mathematics and computing</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2026 Mar 2; Accepted 2026 Mar 31; Collection date 2026.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="Sec1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Air pollution, especially in large urban areas-the prime environmental issue today-is a main threat to human health<sup><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="CR2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>. There has been a sharp rise in pollutants in atmosphere due to rapid rates of industrialization, urbanization, and automobile pollution<sup><xref rid="CR3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="CR4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>. These pollutants include well particulates in which have been implicated to respiratory and cardiovascular diseases and premature mortality<sup><xref rid="CR5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="CR6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup>. According to WHO, millions of people die every year because of air pollution and 90% of world populace is showing to air pollutant levels exceeding its guidelines<sup><xref rid="CR7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CR8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>. This hence calls for urgent efforts to develop efficient and scalable air quality management systems capable of detecting the sources of pollution and developing policies for alleviating the effects of pollution especially in most densely populated cities<sup><xref rid="CR9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CR10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Pollution in the air may have both natural and anthropogenic causes<sup><xref rid="CR11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup>. Human activities such as transport, industries, power generation, deforestation, and agriculture remain the major causes for urban air pollution<sup><xref rid="CR12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CR13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. Through these activities the air quality is greatly impaired by release of high concentrations of particulate matter and gases<sup><xref rid="CR14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. Moreover, pollution is worsened by the weather conditions, especially by presence of temperature inversion, especially in crowded urban areas<sup><xref rid="CR15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CR16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup>. Natural causes such as wildfire, volcanic eruptions and dust storms also pollute, although they do not have a significant impact compared to those caused by human beings<sup><xref rid="CR17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CR18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. In cities, the population density, traffic jams, industries, and ineffective environmental policies causes high concentrations of harmful pollutants<sup><xref rid="CR19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CR20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Due to increased demand of air pollution monitoring, different techniques have been devised to measure the level of pollution starting with sensor-based techniques up to image-based techniques<sup><xref rid="CR21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CR22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>. The conventional sensor-based technique is based on physical air quality monitoring stations, which associate the attention of pollutants in the air<sup><xref rid="CR23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="CR24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. They are efficient and, in most cases, they prove to be costly, geographically scaled and difficult to implement at the large scale<sup><xref rid="CR25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="CR26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup>. The machine learning (ML) that are usually used to classify images according to air quality are convolutional neural networks (CNNs), support vector machines (SVM), and decision trees<sup><xref rid="CR27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="CR28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. Although these techniques are more scalable and less expensive, they are also limited by the fact that they do not pay much attention to important image characteristics and that it is hard to distinguish between slight changes in level of pollution<sup><xref rid="CR29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The suggested model eliminates them by introducing the CBAM to InceptionV3, which is one of strongest DL models used to classify images. CBAM increases the relevance of the model with respect to the most significant areas in images and extends its capability of detecting the additional features that are subtle clues of particular levels of pollution such as haze, smog or mist. CBAM helps the model to learn automatically about what parts in the image are needed to classify it, effectively resolving the problem of partial feature extraction in other CNN models. InceptionV3 has been used to offer a sophisticated architecture that can recognize complicated details of polluted images without expensive costs and low-performance. The integration of CBAM with InceptionV3 suggests such a framework with ability to be very much accurate as far as the air pollution level prediction is concerned, which is an enhancement over current method. The proposed model contributes to the improvement of classification accuracy, and meanwhile, presents a more scalable and efficient way for monitoring air quality over urban areas. It introduces an image-based machine learning solution for measuring urban air quality via a monitoring system that consists of time-series sensor data in addition to the traditional methods for measurement. The overall model implements CBAM (Convolutional Block Attention Module) and InceptionV3 architecture to create better representations of spatial and channel features and can detect small visual elements such as haze and smog. Major contributions of this paper are:</p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par7">The primary goal of the above-presented framework is to apply DL techniques to classify air pollution levels in the city with images. The dataset used is from the Air Pollution Image Dataset presented on Kaggle containing different labeled images of air pollution levels.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par8">The framework applies various image preprocessing techniques, including Gaussian filtering to remove noise, HE to enhance contrast, thresholding to segment objects of interest, and image resizing to standardize the image dimensions. Additionally, label encoding is used to change categorical pollution levels into numerical values for the DL model.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par9">The dataset is divided into training, validation, and test sets, ensuring a stratified split to preserve the proportion of each pollution level in all subsets. This approach ensures that each data split represents all classes fairly, preventing class imbalance during training, validation, and testing.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par10">The framework uses InceptionV3 for feature extraction and classification from images, integrating CBAM to enhance focus on critical regions like haze and smog. This attention mechanism improves the model’s ability to exactly classify air pollution levels.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par11">A structured ablation study is conducted to quantify the individual contributions of preprocessing, augmentation, and CBAM attention in improving classification performance.</p></list-item></list>
<p id="Par12">The organization of this paper is: “<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Literature survey</xref>” section reviews existing literature on air pollution classification methods. “<xref rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec">Proposed methodology</xref>” section describes the proposed methodology. “<xref rid="Sec26" ref-type="sec">Result and discussion</xref>” section discusses the results, evaluating model performance. “<xref rid="Sec27" ref-type="sec">Conclusions and future scope</xref>” section concludes the conclusion and future research to improve air pollution classification.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" disp-level="1"><title>Literature survey</title><p id="Par13">Sarkar et al.<sup><xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> studied air quality foretelling for PM2.5 pollution in Delhi by comparing different forecasting models on various criteria. This included comparing capabilities of independent ML and DL models to be used for this prediction. The criteria for judging proficiency of models include R2, MAE, and RMSE. Hybrid-LSTM-GRU was best model in terms of efficiency are used for prediction of AQI values from all other models. Das et al.<sup><xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> have analyzed air quality prediction methods for PM10 and SO2 pollutants in Basaksehir district of Istanbul using methods LSTM, RNN, and MLP. The study also looks into training using incomplete data and revised error terms. Overall, LSTM least generated errors together with values close to actual ones for the prediction of PM10 and SO2 compared to both MLP and RNN. So, LSTM were performing a lot better than many other studies in field when predicting air quality.</p><p id="Par14">Maltare &amp; Vahora<sup><xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> compared various machine-learning algorithms for predicting Ahmedabad, Gujarat, India’s AQI: SARIMA, SVM, and LSTM. The data were obtained from the Central Pollution Control Board of India, and preprocessing was carried out in different ways for each model. The SVM with RBF kernel has besides other kernels served as the most accurate predictor method for AQI in Ahmedabad compared to SARIMA and LSTM. Gupta et al.<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> performed various types of research on different methods through which air quality can be predicted using data mining techniques for Indian cities are used for this research. The dataset used in present study comprised cities like New Delhi, Bangalore, Kolkata, and Hyderabad. To counter the problem of imbalance in dataset, an oversampling approach named Synthetic Minority Oversampling Technique (SMOTE) was used. The effect of SMOTE to improve the models’ performance is well documented together with detailed metrics and visual comparisons so as to foster similar attempts by future researchers.</p><p id="Par15">Heydari et al.<sup><xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> have developed a hybrid intelligent model, which could effectively predict the emissions from Combined Cycle Power Plants by means of (LSTM) and Multi-Verse Optimization (MVO). The LSTM model predicts the pollutants. On other hand, the MVO enhances LSTM parameters in order to minimize the prediction error. The proposed model was tested against actual data from Kerman power plant in Iran in reference to meteorological input and lagged levels of pollutants. Drewil &amp; Al-Bahadili<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> enumerated a model that encompasses some DL methods and ML methods used for the enhancement of air quality forecasting. The objective of this model involves detecting the most excellent hyperparameters for LSTMs in terms of predicting PM10s, PM2.5s, CO, and NOXs following day. The GA optimizes LSTM parameters which help overcome challenges faced, such as dealing with noise and setting hyperparameters incorrectly. Results show that there was an outperformance of proposed GA-LSTM model over conventional ML and LSTM models, with greater accuracy, speed, and efficiency.</p><p id="Par16">Kumar &amp; Pande<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> on air pollution data of 6 years of 23 cities of India, pre-processed data set, which is selecting important features through correlation analysis. The reduction in pollution was pretty visible in this pandemic year 2020. Due to the present situation of data imbalance, combinations of resampling techniques were applied, and five ML models were used. It was found that the accuracy produced by XGBoost was the greatest from all the others, and linearly good was the prediction with the actual data. Samad et al.<sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> used ML techniques to simulate the concentrations of five models; ridge regression, support vector regression, random forests, extra trees regression, and extreme gradient boosting. The study concluded that predictions were considerably influenced by nearby pollutant data and that the methodology was extendable to other locations, as was demonstrated with Karlsruhe-Nordwest data. Ahmad and Kumar<sup><xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> proposed a hybrid WaveNet-based deep learning framework enhanced with XGBoost residual correction (1DCNN-BiLSTM-XgRC) for accurate PM₂.₅ prediction at urban U.S. embassies, demonstrating improved forecasting performance compared to traditional models.</p><p id="Par17">Zhu et al.<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> employed DL methods, in particular, CNN and LSTM, for determining sea quality and air quality in urban settings. The proposed Conv.LSTM model integrates convolutional layers with the recurrent connection of LSTM to capture spatial and temporal dependances of data. The study explored various habitats of beaches and pollution types. Binbusayyis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> created an AQI prediction model based on a smart city concept using a modified Stacked Attention GRU with KL discrepancy. The model uses Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) for data pre-processing, especially to impute missing values and scale the features, towards better prediction performance. The study used AQI data collected from Ernakulam, Chennai, and Ahmedabad and reported performance metrics is used. The performance of proposed model was better than existing regression algorithms since it exhibited lower loss values and more efficient predictions.</p><p id="Par18">Ahmad and Kumar<sup><xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> proposed a hybrid BiGRU-1DCNN model to forecast PM2.5 concentrations across multiple monitoring stations in Delhi. The model combines bidirectional GRU layers with 1D convolutional layers to capture both temporal dynamics and local spatial correlations in the air quality data. Ahmad and Jas<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> developed a quantum-inspired neural network to forecast air pollution levels in one of the world’s most polluted urban environments. Their approach extends classical neural network architectures by incorporating principles derived from quantum computation to better capture complex temporal patterns in time-series air quality data.</p><p id="Par19">Ahmad &amp; Kumar<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> presented a novel method for improving the prediction of PM2.5 concentration using a random imputation strategy coupled with a hybrid model of RNN &amp; Bidirectional GRU. The method uses statistical techniques to deal with missing values and outliers before using the hybrid model to learn the temporal patterns of the air quality time series. Qu et al.<sup><xref rid="CR44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> explored deep learning-based atmospheric visibility detection using image data, highlighting the effectiveness of convolutional neural networks in capturing visual features related to air pollution conditions.</p><p id="Par20">Ozkok<sup><xref rid="CR45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> proposed a deep learning-based image classification approach for air pollution assessment, where CNN models analyze environmental images using features such as haze density and visibility patterns to classify pollution levels.</p><p id="Par22">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarizes recent studies on air pollution prediction, including methods, data, and key findings. The research gaps highlight limitations in existing approaches, motivating the proposed hybrid spatio-temporal model.</p><table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of recent studies on air pollution prediction and identified research gaps.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Authors (Year)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Study focus / Method</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Data / Location</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Key findings</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Research gap</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sarkar et al.<sup><xref rid="CR30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ML &amp; DL models for PM2.5 prediction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delhi, India</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hybrid-LSTM-GRU best among models</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited to single city; spatial correlations not considered</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Das et al.<sup><xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSTM, RNN, MLP for PM10 &amp; SO2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Istanbul, Turkey</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSTM had least error</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Focused on PM10 &amp; SO2 only; missing handling techniques could be improved</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Maltare &amp; Vahora<sup><xref rid="CR32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SARIMA, SVM, LSTM comparison</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ahmedabad, India</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SVM-RBF most accurate</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited spatial-temporal integration; few hybrid approaches</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gupta et al.<sup><xref rid="CR33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Data mining + SMOTE for AQI</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Multiple Indian cities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SMOTE improved model performance</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited to oversampling; hybrid deep learning models not explored</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Heydari et al.<sup><xref rid="CR34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LSTM + MVO for emissions prediction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Iran</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">MVO optimized LSTM parameters</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not applied to air quality time series for urban regions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drewil &amp; Al-Bahadili<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GA-LSTM for PMs, CO, NOx</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not specified</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Outperformed conventional ML</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Did not test across multiple monitoring stations</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Kumar &amp; Pande<sup><xref rid="CR36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Feature selection + ML models</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23 Indian cities</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">XGBoost performed best</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Temporal-spatial correlations not fully utilized</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Samad et al.<sup><xref rid="CR37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ridge, SVR, RF, XGBoost</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Karlsruhe-Nordwest</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nearby pollutant data improved predictions</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited model combinations; hybrid models not tested</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ahmad &amp; Kumar<sup><xref rid="CR38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">WaveNet + XGBoost (1DCNN-BiLSTM-XgRC)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">US embassies</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Improved PM2.5 forecasting</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urban-specific; model generalization not tested</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Zhu et al.<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ConvLSTM</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Urban coastal areas</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Captured spatio-temporal patterns</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited to coastal environments; AQI prediction not generalized</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Binbusayyis et al.<sup><xref rid="CR40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stacked Attention GRU + GAN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ernakulam, Chennai, Ahmedabad</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Better AQI prediction</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Focused on preprocessing; hybrid deep learning models not fully explored</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ahmad &amp; Kumar<sup><xref rid="CR41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Hybrid BiGRU-1DCNN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delhi, India</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Captured temporal &amp; local spatial patterns</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited to Delhi; multi-city generalization needed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ahmad &amp; Jas<sup><xref rid="CR42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quantum-inspired NN</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Highly polluted city</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Captured complex temporal patterns</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quantum-inspired approach not compared with hybrid models</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ahmad &amp; Kumar<sup><xref rid="CR43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup></td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">nRI RNN-BiGRU</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not specified</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Improved PM2.5 prediction handling missing values</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Limited model comparison; spatio-temporal integration not fully addressed</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="Sec3" disp-level="2"><title>Problem statement</title><p id="Par23">Prediction of air quality is of paramount importance to human health and environmental control particularly in urban regions where concentration of pollutants is high. Different researchers have used ML and DL technology to predict air quality, with special emphasis on such pollutants as PM2.5, PM10, SO2, and NO2<sup><xref rid="CR31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, there are still problems of model accuracy, data imbalance, and feature selection. Various models have been tested with different results based on data and environmental conditions; LSTM, RNN, SVM, hybrid models, and others<sup><xref rid="CR35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, high accuracy and efficiency in air quality prediction is yet to be reached despite progress being made specifically in areas with multiple sources of pollution, and incomplete information. This paper seeks to compare different ML and DL models to enhance prediction of air quality<sup><xref rid="CR39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4" disp-level="1"><title>Proposed methodology</title><p id="Par24">The initial step for this entire process is to acquire air pollution images from the dataset. These images are then preprocessed using several techniques: Gaussian filtering to remove noise, HE for contrast enhancement, thresholding to segment the objects of interest, resizing images to a standard size, and encoding labels into numerical values for model compatibility. After preprocessing, the dataset is split three parts: training, testing, and validation sets. The feature extraction and classification steps involve important features being extracted from images using a DL model like InceptionV3 or perhaps another choice of model. A baseline models including plain InceptionV3 and variants without preprocessing and attention mechanisms were also implemented. All models were trained and tested under identical conditions to enable a consistent comparison of architectural choices. This model is refined with attention modules such as CBAM, which focus on the related areas of the image, allowing the pollution levels to be classified with greater accuracy into Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy. Figure <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows the Workflow for Air Pollution Classification.</p><fig id="Fig1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Overall architecture of the proposed CBAM-based InceptionV3 model showing the preprocessing stage, feature extraction using InceptionV3, attention enhancement through CBAM, and final classification of air pollution levels.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e724" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig1_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/bedd6e41224e/41598_2026_47424_Fig1_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1499?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 499?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig1_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/58538ff89a91/41598_2026_47424_Fig1_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><sec id="Sec5" disp-level="2"><title>Image acquisition</title><p id="Par26">The dataset is an Air Pollution Image Dataset from Kaggle, consisting of photos from various cities with labels for specific air pollution levels, e.g., Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy. Also provided are useful metadata, including the location of each image, timestamp, and pollution indices, such as PM2.5 and PM10, if available. It is essential to assess data quality throughout this process by making certain each image is properly labeled according to the pollution level and considering whether there might be any images lost or corrupted, as final result of the model depends on such data quality. The dataset employed in this study will be Air Pollution Image Dataset that is openly available in Kaggle. It is a total of 12,240 images taken in urban areas in India and Nepal, in different air quality variations. The original dataset includes six categories, namely Good, Moderate, Unhealthy for Sensitive Groups (USG), Unhealthy, Very Unhealthy and Hazardous. In this research, the following three categories will be used to classify the dataset: Moderate, Unhealthy for Sensitive Groups (USG) and Unhealthy. All images are downsampled to a standard resolution of 224 × 224 pixels so that they would be compatible with the InceptionV3 architecture. Before training, the preprocessing steps, which include noise elimination, contrast and normalization to the range [0, 1] are conducted. Further, it uses data augmentation such as rotation, horizontal flipping, and changing of brightness to enhance the generalization of the models.</p><p id="Par27">Leverage less dependency on training datasets and possible data leakage, due to careful verification, visually similar or close-duplicate pictures were not shared in-between training, validation, and test sets. The images that were produced in the same areas or had close visual characteristics were compared and linked to prevent overlapping of cross-splits. Moreover, a consideration in which sources were taken into account was utilized wherever possible, and images in similar geographical settings were put in the same subset. This will assist the model to learn generalized pollution related characteristics like haze and smog instead of memorizing location-based scene patterns.</p><p id="Par28">The dataset labels (Moderate, USG, Unhealthy) are based on AQI ranges from Kaggle sources which match the pollutant thresholds that include PM2.5 and PM10 although these pollutants were not always directly measured through sensors. The researchers applied histogram equalization and normalization because visual data can be affected by lighting and weather and camera quality but CBAM enables them to concentrate on essential haze and visibility information.</p><p id="Par29">The dataset labels are based on AQI ranges from Kaggle and aligned with pollutant thresholds such as PM2.5 and PM10, though not directly measured in all cases. The combination of preprocessing and CBAM techniques helps to decrease visual differences while the system concentrates on haze patterns, yet the model creates visual representations that do not reflect actual pollutant measurements, which indicates that future sensor-based testing is necessary are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Sample input images from the dataset representing different urban scenes with varying levels of air pollution and haze, used for training and evaluation of the proposed model.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e747" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig2_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/c610dc0c67d5/41598_2026_47424_Fig2_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 756?><?original-width 1188?><?scaled-height 504?><?scaled-width 792?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig2_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/b4dc23fb15a7/41598_2026_47424_Fig2_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec6" disp-level="2"><title>Image preprocessing</title><p id="Par31">During image preprocessing, the first step would be to apply a Gaussian Filter that removes high frequency noise and smooths the image though concurrently preservative features such as edges. This filter convolves the image with the Gaussian kernel, where the pixel nearest to the center has more say in filtering. By reducing noise, it helps eliminate outliers and ensures that the model focuses on right features. After the Gaussian filter application, the images are then set for further steps that include resizing, label encoding, and normalization for the best possible preparation for training phase.</p><sec id="Sec7" disp-level="3"><title>Gaussian filter</title><p id="Par32">A Gaussian filter is a convolutional filter used to reduce the high-frequency noise on an image and consequently generate a smooth image. The filtering of an image is performed by convolving it with a Gaussian kernel, where the center pixels get more weight than the pixels at a distance. The Gaussian kernel is given by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>)</p><disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e760" xlink:href="d33e760.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/956f4e807d0d/d33e760.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par33">Where, <inline-formula id="IEq1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e766" xlink:href="d33e766.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/1ea7cba155e9/d33e766.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the gaussian function for pixel position <inline-formula id="IEq2"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e770" xlink:href="d33e770.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/1f81f2f22aa7/d33e770.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>,<inline-formula id="IEq3"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e774" xlink:href="d33e774.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2aabd379ce4a/d33e774.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the standard deviation and <inline-formula id="IEq4"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e778" xlink:href="d33e778.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/fdfff813a087/d33e778.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq5"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e782" xlink:href="d33e782.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/efcc4ad69ea7/d33e782.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> are directs with respect to the center of this kernel.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" disp-level="3"><title>HE</title><p id="Par34">HE is a method of enhancing contrast by redistributing intensity levels of the pixels of an image. The idea is to spread out the most frequent intensity values and make the features more noticeable. The transformation function T(r) is given by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e793" xlink:href="d33e793.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/b7eda06affea/d33e793.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par35">where <inline-formula id="IEq6"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e799" xlink:href="d33e799.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/0a33f142b04d/d33e799.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the intensity level, <inline-formula id="IEq7"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e803" xlink:href="d33e803.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/6cee83f5ffe0/d33e803.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the total number of intensity levels, and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e807" xlink:href="d33e807.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/7cd3a571c10e/d33e807.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes the probability distribution of pixel intensities. This transformation enhances image contrast by redistributing intensity values.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9" disp-level="3"><title>Thresholding</title><p id="Par36">Thresholding deals with segmenting through image conversion into binary format, and pixels above a threshold value <inline-formula id="IEq9"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e815" xlink:href="d33e815.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2608698f928f/d33e815.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> are allocated the value of 1 (or white), while those below <inline-formula id="IEq10"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e819" xlink:href="d33e819.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2608698f928f/d33e819.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> are allocated zero value. The basic formula for global thresholding is shows by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e826" xlink:href="d33e826.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/e7e5d73891f7/d33e826.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par37">where <inline-formula id="IEq11"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e832" xlink:href="d33e832.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2ccb4cb974c4/d33e832.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the pixel value at position <inline-formula id="IEq12"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e836" xlink:href="d33e836.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/1f81f2f22aa7/d33e836.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq13"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e840" xlink:href="d33e840.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2608698f928f/d33e840.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the threshold value used to convert the image into binary form.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" disp-level="3"><title>Image resizing</title><p id="Par38">Resizing changes, the dimensions of an image to ensure that all input data given to a neural network conform to a certain size. Typically, and therefore usually, this operation uses interpolation methods, bilinear interpolation being the most common, to calculate the pixel values of the resized image. The resized image <inline-formula id="IEq14"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e848" xlink:href="d33e848.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/dfaad742dad0/d33e848.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> of size <inline-formula id="IEq15"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e852" xlink:href="d33e852.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/480afb34885d/d33e852.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>can be calculated from Eq. (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e859" xlink:href="d33e859.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/940314566663/d33e859.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par39">Where, <inline-formula id="IEq16"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e865" xlink:href="d33e865.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/78b515de073d/d33e865.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq17"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e869" xlink:href="d33e869.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/361c063ed35e/d33e869.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> are width and height, <inline-formula id="IEq18"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e873" xlink:href="d33e873.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/5a4f65b933f8/d33e873.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq19"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e877" xlink:href="d33e877.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/1418639dc87c/d33e877.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>represent the resized dimensions, <inline-formula id="IEq20"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e881" xlink:href="d33e881.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/fdfff813a087/d33e881.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq21"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e886" xlink:href="d33e886.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/efcc4ad69ea7/d33e886.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> stand for the pixel coordinates in the new image.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" disp-level="3"><title>Label encoding</title><p id="Par40">The images have already been preprocessed, and then label encoding is carried out to encode the categorical labels, including Moderate, USG and Unhealthy into numerical values that will be interpreted by the model. Indicatively, the term Moderate can be coded 0, Unhealthy sensitive Groups 1, and Unhealthy 2. This transformation enables the model to receive the labels in the form of numerical values during training and therefore, it is able to compute loss and optimize the learning process.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12" disp-level="2"><title>Splitting the data</title><p id="Par41">The dataset is divided into the three splits with 70%, 15%, and 15% distribution for training, validation, and testing, respectively. Training gives the model information about the data; this is the actual learning phase. The validation set is to tune hyperparameters and gauge performance to avoid overfitting. Testing, on the other hand, is to evaluate the model’s performance finally. The stratified split is used to ensure that each subset contains a representative distribution of classes, preserving the proportion of each pollution level, for example, Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy, across all the sets. This is particularly crucial to ensure a balanced number of samples in each class, especially when some classes might be underrepresented. Out of the stratified class-based separation, further precautions were employed to reduce unspoken data leakage. Highly similar images such as those of the same background, lighting, or a similar surrounding were thoroughly considered to minimize the chances of overlap within different subsets. Though this dataset lacks direct time sequence data, the attempt was made to prevent the distribution of potentially correlated samples of training, validation and test sets. This guarantees a more confident evaluation as the distinction between the data that is seen and the unseen is maintained.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13" disp-level="2"><title>Feature extraction and classification using CBAM-based InceptionV3</title><p id="Par42">An input image undergoes resizing, normalization, and conversion into a suitable input form for the model. The image next undergoes convolution operations that extract vital features such as edges and textures from it, while the pooling operations reduce the spatial extents of feature maps by holding together important information without any loss. Feature maps of various scales are combined through filter concatenation to form an integrated feature map. Channel attention selects significant features, whereas spatial attention focuses on important areas of the image in the application of CBAM. It thus passes through a linear (or fully connected) layer that flattens the feature maps into vector form for subsequent classification operations. Finally, a softmax transforms the class prediction scores of model into possibilities for each class (Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy), assigning the class that stands forth with the maximum probability as its final output. This approach allows CBAM on InceptionV3 to classify air pollution levels in urban images quickly and accurately. Figure <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows the architecture of CBAM-Based InceptionV3.</p><fig id="Fig3" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Architecture of the CBAM-based InceptionV3 model highlighting the integration of attention modules within the feature extraction network.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e913" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig3_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2bfad2712bca/41598_2026_47424_Fig3_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1392?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 464?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig3_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/66193f9c9e72/41598_2026_47424_Fig3_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><sec id="Sec14" disp-level="3"><title>Preprocessed image</title><p id="Par44">This starts with a preprocessed image as an input in the model. This picture is already been shrunk and made standardized to be fed into the neural network. Preprocessing can involve imaging resizing (e.g., 224 × 224 pixels), normalization (setting pixel values to a target range such as 0–1) and any other data augmentation operations (e.g., rotation, flip, pixel brightness) done to the image.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15" disp-level="3"><title>Convolution layer</title><p id="Par52">The convolution layers (depicted as light purple boxes) serve as the primary feature extraction layers in any Convolutional Neural Network. They convolve various filters (aka kernels) with the input image to extract low-level features like edges and wrinkles. Each filter corresponds to certain features to be extracted from the image; these filters are “slid” across the image, and the resulting matrix after this convolution (called the feature map) represents varied features in the image. The convolution layer is shows by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e926" xlink:href="d33e926.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/618b39d05b84/d33e926.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par53">Where, <inline-formula id="IEq22"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e932" xlink:href="d33e932.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/1ec0daf55b31/d33e932.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> kernel weights, <inline-formula id="IEq23"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e936" xlink:href="d33e936.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/aefe0ddd51cb/d33e936.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes the bias, <inline-formula id="IEq24"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e940" xlink:href="d33e940.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/c27a3741afb5/d33e940.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> represents the activation function (ReLU), <inline-formula id="IEq25"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e944" xlink:href="d33e944.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/17169c9f5f2b/d33e944.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec16" disp-level="3"><title>Pooling layer (MaxPooling)</title><p id="Par54">Downsampling of feature maps produced by convolution layers is done by pooling layers (which are represented by pink boxes). Max pooling is the most widespread one, whereby only maxima of individual area in feature map is maintained. The concept of pooling also assists in minimizing the spatial dimension of the feature maps thereby minimizing computation load and parameters of the model. This is also necessary towards the attainment of the spatial invariance such that the model is able to know features though these features may be slightly moved. The pooling layer is shown by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e954" xlink:href="d33e954.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2b41db411ef8/d33e954.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par55">Here, <inline-formula id="IEq26"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e960" xlink:href="d33e960.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/4f3e3b441977/d33e960.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> refers to the size of the pooling window. <inline-formula id="IEq27"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e964" xlink:href="d33e964.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/f25230864b18/d33e964.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is taken as the feature map from the previous layer, and <inline-formula id="IEq28"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e968" xlink:href="d33e968.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/6e6157960295/d33e968.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> serves as the pooled feature map.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17" disp-level="3"><title>Filter concatenation</title><p id="Par56">The step of filter concatenation (in blue boxes) combines the multiple features learned by the convolution filters at different levels. A set of filter sizes (1 × 1, 3 × 3, 5 × 5) is used in InceptionV3 to learn features at different scales. These different feature maps are concatenated along the depth of the network, which makes an expressive feature representation. The intent is to capture both fine-grained and large-scale features simultaneously. The base network is InceptionV3, where each Inception module performs multi-scale feature extraction is shown in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e979" xlink:href="d33e979.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/5b0b6aca72f9/d33e979.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par57">The Inception module, where feature maps from multiple parallel branches are combined. Each branch applies different operations (1 × 1,3 × 3, 5 × 5 convolutions and pooling) to capture features at various spatial scales. The outputs are concatenated along the channel dimension to form a comprehensive multi-scale feature representation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18" disp-level="3"><title>CBAM attention</title><p id="Par58">CBAM is an attention mechanism that can concentrate on most interesting aspects of the image to classify it so that the model can perform better since it can be guided to pay attention to some important areas and channels. CBAM is made up of two major attention modules and they include CBAM is shows by Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig4" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Structure of the CBAM module demonstrating channel attention and spatial attention mechanisms used for feature refinement.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1000" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig4_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/cbf627bc1f11/41598_2026_47424_Fig4_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 681?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 227?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig4_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/ef74b695c278/41598_2026_47424_Fig4_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par61">Channel attention mechanism (CAM)</p></list-item></list>
<p id="Par45">CAM helps the model to focus on the most significant feature channels. Feature maps created by the convolution layers comprise many different channels, each representing a different feature detected by the filters (e.g., edges, textures, shapes). Not all channels are equally important for the task. The model helps to give more importance to relevant channels and less to irrelevant ones is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig5" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Channel attention mechanism (CAM) illustrating the process of channel-wise feature weighting using pooling and fully connected layers.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1022" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig5_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/b6fa4ed2edb4/41598_2026_47424_Fig5_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 633?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 211?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig5_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/fcba254c2e26/41598_2026_47424_Fig5_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par47">The Channel Attention Mechanism boosts the feature map by attending to the most pertinent channels. It takes input feature map F, which is the output of some series of convolutional layer(s) and contains learned information from the image. Max pooling takes the maximum value of each channel, whereas average pooling takes the average for each channel. Both operations yield an output of reduced spatial dimensions 1 × 1 while keeping the relevance across all channels. The equations for such operations are given below in Eq. (<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="disp-formula">8</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1029" xlink:href="d33e1029.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/69083fb2e798/d33e1029.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par48">where <inline-formula id="IEq29"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1035" xlink:href="d33e1035.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/1e927e233a96/d33e1035.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> represents the channel attention map, <inline-formula id="IEq30"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1039" xlink:href="d33e1039.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2aabd379ce4a/d33e1039.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the sigmoid activation function, and <inline-formula id="IEq31"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1043" xlink:href="d33e1043.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/162c89db8886/d33e1043.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes element-wise multiplication. The two fully connected layers reduce the dimension of the pooled information into a small vector, and the output of these layers will be put through a sigmoid activation function to obtain a channel attention map. The attention map is then expressed as Eq. (<xref rid="Equ9" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1050" xlink:href="d33e1050.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/d55cdee21624/d33e1050.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par49">Where <inline-formula id="IEq32"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1056" xlink:href="d33e1056.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/76952a659715/d33e1056.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq33"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1060" xlink:href="d33e1060.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/cfc6c4b9f03c/d33e1060.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> are the learned weights of the fully connected layers, and <inline-formula id="IEq34"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1064" xlink:href="d33e1064.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2aabd379ce4a/d33e1064.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denotes a sigmoid activation. The sigmoid makes sure that values in the final attention map lay between 0 and 1, highlighting pertinent channels while suppressing less relevant ones.</p><p id="Par50">Finally, the recalibration of the output feature map <inline-formula id="IEq35"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1070" xlink:href="d33e1070.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/c1877288d4d4/d33e1070.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is done by multiplying the initial feature map <inline-formula id="IEq36"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1074" xlink:href="d33e1074.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/d2b355283c52/d33e1074.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> with the channel attention map <inline-formula id="IEq37"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1078" xlink:href="d33e1078.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/eb949879af4d/d33e1078.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. This boosts important channels and suppresses irrelevant ones, so the model can concentrate on features important to the classification. The recalibration is formulated as follows by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ10" ref-type="disp-formula">10</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1085" xlink:href="d33e1085.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/a8969bd7bf9b/d33e1085.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par51">Basically, the whole process enables the model to extract on more relevant channels in feature map and, hence, improves its performance by accentuating those features that are more critical to the task at hand.</p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Spatial attention mechanism (SAM)</p></list-item></list>
<p id="Par62">SAM helps the model to attend several key spatial regions of the feature map. Whereas channel attention attends to which features are important, spatial attention attends to where these features are located. It enables the model to focus on limited regions of image that somehow relate to haze, pollution, or unusual patterns that characterize pollution levels is shows in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>.</p><fig id="Fig6" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Spatial attention mechanism (SAM) showing the identification of important spatial regions using convolutional operations.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1111" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig6_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/68c93da9526c/41598_2026_47424_Fig6_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 796?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 265?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig6_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/84d0aa24979e/41598_2026_47424_Fig6_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par64">The channel-refined feature map <inline-formula id="IEq38"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1115" xlink:href="d33e1115.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/d2b355283c52/d33e1115.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> obtained from the CAM is fed into the SAM. Notice that this feature map has already been refined to magnify certain important channels. On the contrary, these operations will apply two different types of pooling in two spatial dimensions of the feature map. Max pool picks the maximum value within a spatial region, while average pool finds the average value across the spatial regions. These two pooled outputs, called <inline-formula id="IEq39"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1119" xlink:href="d33e1119.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/62c405bbf283/d33e1119.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq40"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1123" xlink:href="d33e1123.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/e6404cc9bebb/d33e1123.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, have been used to express spatial information in the feature map is shows by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ11" ref-type="disp-formula">11</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1130" xlink:href="d33e1130.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/1e0d5bc784a0/d33e1130.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par65">where <inline-formula id="IEq41"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1136" xlink:href="d33e1136.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/dca43f9b089a/d33e1136.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the spatial attention map highlighting important regions of the feature map. The output in return from the convolutional layer ranks among the learned spatial features. The operations are given as follows by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ12" ref-type="disp-formula">12</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1143" xlink:href="d33e1143.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/81e4497e6b07/d33e1143.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par66">With the convolution outcome from earlier, a sigmoid activation function takes over, normalizing the values between 0 and 1 to forge the spatial attention map <inline-formula id="IEq42"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1149" xlink:href="d33e1149.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/8b2844006f10/d33e1149.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>. The sigmoid function makes sure that any regions considered important by the model receive larger values, closer to 1, while the less important ones are suppressed using values is shows by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="disp-formula">13</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1156" xlink:href="d33e1156.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/349d87fc9a70/d33e1156.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par67">Finally, the spatial attention map is applied to a feature map by element-wise multiplication to recalibrate the features that are more relevant in certain spatial areas for the task is shows by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ14" ref-type="disp-formula">14</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1165" xlink:href="d33e1165.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/922572d72eb0/d33e1165.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par68">The Module enhances the ability to focusing on the important regions of the image, aiding it in classifying pollution levels from the chosen area of interest in the image.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21" disp-level="3"><title>Linear layer (Fully connected layer)</title><p id="Par69">In parallel, the linear layer takes output from the feature maps and combines it into a vector, passing it through one or more dense layers to classify the image into a certain class. The weights of these layers are learned during the training process, and by doing so, the model is able to map indeed-extracted features to actual output classes is shows by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ15" ref-type="disp-formula">15</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>15</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1178" xlink:href="d33e1178.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2e09b1eea110/d33e1178.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par70">where <inline-formula id="IEq43"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1184" xlink:href="d33e1184.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/fdfff813a087/d33e1184.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the feature vector, <inline-formula id="IEq44"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1188" xlink:href="d33e1188.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/78b515de073d/d33e1188.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the weight matrix, <inline-formula id="IEq45"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1192" xlink:href="d33e1192.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/07f08451fa63/d33e1192.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the bias term, and <inline-formula id="IEq46"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1196" xlink:href="d33e1196.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/efcc4ad69ea7/d33e1196.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the output.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22" disp-level="3"><title>Softmax Layer</title><p id="Par71">The Softmax Layer is used in output layer of neural networks and transforms the raw prediction values, or logits, into probabilities. These logits give the network’s confidence about each class prior to normalization. The softmax function transforms values into possibilities in the range [0,1] and adds to 1. A crucial factor in classification tasks is that this transformation allows interpreting the network’s output as probabilities of class memberships. The mathematical representation of the softmax function is shown by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ16" ref-type="disp-formula">16</xref>):</p><disp-formula id="Equ16"><label>16</label><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1207" xlink:href="d33e1207.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/98922f968b2b/d33e1207.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></disp-formula><p id="Par72">Where <inline-formula id="IEq47"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1213" xlink:href="d33e1213.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/433be34aa427/d33e1213.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the logit for class <inline-formula id="IEq48"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1217" xlink:href="d33e1217.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/a086866e2160/d33e1217.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq49"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1221" xlink:href="d33e1221.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/efb9fd5470ba/d33e1221.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> is the sum of exponentials of all logits. The network outputs the probability of individually class after the softmax is applied. These probabilities represent the likelihood of the network believing each class to be the class for the given input image. According to the probabilities, the class with the highest probability is labeled as the correct class. Therefore, the final classification consists of selecting the class for which the highest probability exists, corresponding to the pollution levels: Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23" disp-level="3"><title>Training configuration</title><p id="Par73">The model is trained under the following configuration:</p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par75">Optimizer: Adam.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par76">Initial Learning Rate: <inline-formula id="IEq50"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1238" xlink:href="d33e1238.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/0195a6629de8/d33e1238.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par77">Learning Rate Strategy: ReduceLROnPlateau (factor <inline-formula id="IEq51"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1244" xlink:href="d33e1244.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/f5ad20245914/d33e1244.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, patience <inline-formula id="IEq52"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1248" xlink:href="d33e1248.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/4c87e4da95ce/d33e1248.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> ).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par78">Batch Size: 32.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par79">Epochs: 50.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par80">Loss Function: Categorical Cross-Entropy.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par81">Regularization:</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par82">Dropout (rate <inline-formula id="IEq53"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1267" xlink:href="d33e1267.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/6f856fc5eaed/d33e1267.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> in fully connected layer).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par83">L2 weight decay <inline-formula id="IEq54"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1274" xlink:href="d33e1274.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/d33e659bc8cd/d33e1274.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par84">Early Stopping: Training stops if validation loss does not improve for 10 epochs.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par85">Hardware Environment:</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par86">GPU: NVIDIA RTX 3060</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par87">Framework: TensorFlow/Keras</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par88">RAM: 16 GB</p></list-item></list>

<fig id="Figa" position="anchor"><?disp-level 4?><label>Algorithm 1</label><caption><p>CBAM-based InceptionV3 for air pollution classification.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1303" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Figa_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/534e20b693e3/41598_2026_47424_Figa_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1800?><?original-width 1772?><?scaled-height 719?><?scaled-width 708?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Figa_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/4ad38fd4842e/41598_2026_47424_Figa_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig>
<p id="Par90">The complete workflow of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model is summarized in Algorithm 1. Each stage of the algorithm is supported by corresponding mathematical formulations. The preprocessing steps are defined using Eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>) to (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>), while feature extraction and learning operations are governed by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="disp-formula">5</xref>) to (<xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="disp-formula">7</xref>). The CBAM attention mechanism is formulated through Eq. (<xref rid="Equ8" ref-type="disp-formula">8</xref>) to (<xref rid="Equ13" ref-type="disp-formula">13</xref>), followed by classification using fully connected and softmax layers as described in Eqs. (<xref rid="Equ14" ref-type="disp-formula">14</xref>) and (<xref rid="Equ15" ref-type="disp-formula">15</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec26" disp-level="1"><title>Result and discussion</title><p id="Par91">This model has proven to be quite capable of efficient classification with urban air pollution levels getting into Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy categories. The proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 architecture was also to be effective and novel by evaluating the contribution of preprocessing, data augmentation, and the CBAM module in the same training environment. The original InceptionV3 model recognized 88.6% of the cases, and with preprocessing, this value increased to 91.2%, which shows that the feature quality is improved. The inclusion of data augmentation further enhanced the accuracy up to 93.4 which showed better generalization. The CBAM-InceptionV3 model offered the best performance of 95.23 which proves that attention mechanism improves feature representation. These outcomes indicate the contribution of each element, and CBAM increases the performance in a clear manner compared to the baseline. The CBAM module in the InceptionV3 acts in conjunction with the model to somehow emphasize on the most important features of polluted images, which include haze or fog. Accurate prediction of all three classes was possible, as evidenced by very good performances for the precision, recall, and F1-score metrics.</p><p id="Par92">The data of the model was also demonstrated with the control of dependency on datasets when splitting data. The evaluation represents a more realistic generalization situation by reducing overlaps of visually or contextually similar images in different subsets. The fact that the performance of the model is consistent throughout the various classes points to the fact that the model successfully captures the visual patterns that are unique to pollution instead of depending on the location-dependent features.</p><p id="Par94">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the performance comparison of different model configurations evaluated under identical experimental conditions. The results demonstrate the incremental improvement achieved through preprocessing, data augmentation, and the integration of the CBAM attention mechanism. K-fold cross-validation (k = 5) is performed to evaluate the robustness and generalization capability of the proposed model. The model demonstrates consistent performance across all folds with minimal variation. In addition, statistical evaluation is carried out by computing the mean and standard deviation over multiple experimental runs. The results confirm that the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model achieves stable and reliable performance compared to baseline models.</p><table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Ablation study of model configurations.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model configuration</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">InceptionV3</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">InceptionV3 + Preprocessing</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">91.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">InceptionV3 + Preprocessing + Data augmentation</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CBAM + InceptionV3 (Proposed Model)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.23</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par96">The preprocessing response correlations for moderate to illustrate various major image transformations are given in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>. The first image is the raw image which may have noise present inside. Among the disturbed images, salt-and-pepper noise is the noisy image. The Gaussian filtered image can remove this noise without blurring the very important features, such as edges to attain clear details. HE slightly improves the contrast of the image so that some faint features become visible. Otsu’s threshold is used after processing the image with a Gaussian filter and determines foreground and background objects such as haze or trees. All these steps improve one quality of the image and make the image model focus on important features to judge the level of pollution correctly.</p><fig id="Fig7" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Preprocessed output images corresponding to moderate air pollution levels, illustrating the effect of preprocessing steps such as noise reduction, contrast enhancement, and resizing applied before feature extraction.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1389" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig7_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/46ff3b24af30/41598_2026_47424_Fig7_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1105?><?original-width 1389?><?scaled-height 552?><?scaled-width 694?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig7_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/7a500028aec6/41598_2026_47424_Fig7_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par98">The USG example of preprocessing output reveals significant changes in the process of a clear feature detection is shows by Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>. The noisy picture that was initially noisy has noise that hiders details. Following the Gaussian filter, high-frequency noise is removed, and it leaves important edges intact as well as smooths the image. The equalization increases the contrast and puts small details, such as haze and fog that are vital in identifying patterns of pollution, in the limelight. And finally, thresholding by Otsu divides the image into foreground and background, making it clear what is important, e.g., pollution or haze. This is a processed image, which is now more acceptable by the model to define the level of pollution.</p><fig id="Fig8" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Preprocessed output images corresponding to Unhealthy for Sensitive Groups (USG) air pollution levels, demonstrating the effect of preprocessing steps including noise reduction, contrast enhancement, and resizing prior to feature extraction.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1404" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig8_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/3921f693a0bf/41598_2026_47424_Fig8_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1104?><?original-width 1387?><?scaled-height 552?><?scaled-width 693?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig8_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/a49d3c4d688d/41598_2026_47424_Fig8_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par100">The preprocessing output for the Unhealthy category reveals the key transformations to allow clearer feature detection is shows by Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>. Disturbances such as salt and pepper noise cause indiscriminating features in the original. A Gaussian filter smooths the image to lessen high-frequency noise while retaining edge information, thereby preserving important features. The contrast is then enhanced by HE, enabling the observation of finer details such as haze or fog levels, which are required for determining pollution levels. Finally, segmentation of the image using Otsu’s thresholding into foreground and background clearly outlines the relevant portions of pollution or haze, resulting in better extraction of features for more accurate classification.</p><fig id="Fig9" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Pre-processed output images corresponding to Unhealthy air pollution levels, showing the effect of preprocessing steps including noise reduction, contrast enhancement, and resizing applied before feature extraction.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1419" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig9_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/980809296431/41598_2026_47424_Fig9_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1087?><?original-width 1367?><?scaled-height 543?><?scaled-width 683?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig9_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/f9f42a80ef11/41598_2026_47424_Fig9_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par102">Figure <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref> presents the performance indicators of three classes, including Moderate, USG and Unhealthy. The precision, recall, and the F1-score are about 0.95, which is good. In particular, the Moderate class has precision 0.9535, recall 0.9523, and F1-score 0.9529, the USG class has precision 0.9531, recall 0.9519, and F1-score 0.9525, and the Unhealthy class has precision 0.9521, recall 0.9527 and F1-score 0.9524. In general, the model has a regular and successful classification of all categories with an accuracy of 0.9523.</p><fig id="Fig10" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Class-wise performance metrics of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model for different air pollution levels, including accuracy, precision, recall, and F1-score, demonstrating the model’s effectiveness in distinguishing Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy categories.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1435" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig10_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/dab7c5c2fa6f/41598_2026_47424_Fig10_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 800?><?original-width 1540?><?scaled-height 400?><?scaled-width 770?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig10_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/92e5e5f05fbc/41598_2026_47424_Fig10_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par104">Figure <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref> shows the False Positive Rate (FPR) and False Negative Rate (FNR) of three classes consisting of Moderate, USG and Unhealthy. The FPR of the Moderate class is 0.0227 and FNR is also 0.0241, which shows that the error rates are not high in this case. USG class has a better FPR (0.0559) and FNR (0.0532), which means a greater number of false classified cases. The FPR and FNR of the Unhealthy one is 0.0277 and 0.0461 respectively. The total FPR is 0.0239 and the total FNR is 0.0477 as shown in the horizontal dashed lines.</p><fig id="Fig11" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>False positive rate (FPR) and false negative rate (FNR) metrics of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model for different air pollution categories, illustrating the model’s error distribution and reliability in classification.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1450" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig11_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/5ad21bb4346a/41598_2026_47424_Fig11_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1012?><?original-width 1393?><?scaled-height 506?><?scaled-width 696?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig11_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2a33c95c1d8e/41598_2026_47424_Fig11_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par106">Figure <xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref> shows the training and validation accuracy with the change in the epochs when training the model. At the beginning of the process, both accuracies are approximately equal (0.4). Both curves also climb at an alarming rate, and training accuracy is about 0.9 at epoch 15. Validation accuracy also has the same pattern but begins to level off at epoch 12 and 0.9 is obtained. It means that model is getting better on the training set and validation set, however, the accuracy on the validation set levels off, the model can have begun to overfit after epoch 12. The training and validation curves show a tendency that overfitting will occur at some point of the number of epochs where the validation performance will start to decline as the training performance will still improve. In order to address this problem, regularization methods like dropout (dropout rate = 0.5) and L2 weight decay (λ = 1 × 10 − 4) are used. Taking of validation loss is also used to stop excessive training. Moreover, data augmentation is utilized in terms of enhancing the generalization ability of the model.</p><fig id="Fig12" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Overall model accuracy of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 framework for air pollution classification, showing the prediction performance across all classes (Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy) during training and testing phases.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1465" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig12_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/80c6f21d1bab/41598_2026_47424_Fig12_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1012?><?original-width 1382?><?scaled-height 506?><?scaled-width 691?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig12_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/14fa0114d27c/41598_2026_47424_Fig12_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par108">Figure <xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref> illustrates the model loss in training as well as validation in the epochs. First, both losses begin by high values of above 1.0. The training loss and the validation loss reduce as the training advances, which implies that the model is making progress. Epoch 5 through epoch 15 show the training and validation loss decreasing by about 0.4 and 0.3 respectively. For the epoch 12, the losses are stabilized and the training loss is at 0.2 and the validation loss is slightly higher and this demonstrates some steady performance.</p><fig id="Fig13" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Training and validation loss curves of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model over epochs, illustrating the convergence behavior and stability of the model during the training process.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1480" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig13_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/1ec3b2df1e80/41598_2026_47424_Fig13_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1071?><?original-width 1461?><?scaled-height 535?><?scaled-width 730?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig13_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/57e689183a5b/41598_2026_47424_Fig13_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par110">Figure <xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref> shows the Multi-Class ROC Curve of three pollution levels namely, Moderate, USG and Unhealthy. The True Positive Rate (TPR) versus the False Positive Rate (FPR) is plotted and the model indicates how well the model classifies the various classes. All of the three classes have curves near to the upper-left corner, which means high performance. The values of the AUC of each class are also presented: Moderate class has AUC of 0.9974, USG class has AUC of 0.9867, and the Unhealthy class has AUC of 0.9944, which means that the classification is excellent.</p><fig id="Fig14" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model for each air pollution class (Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy), illustrating the model’s discriminative ability and trade-off between true positive rate and false positive rate.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1495" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig14_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/f8f3ec0b3b51/41598_2026_47424_Fig14_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1089?><?original-width 1374?><?scaled-height 545?><?scaled-width 687?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig14_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/be52497890e2/41598_2026_47424_Fig14_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par112">Figure <xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig">15</xref> illustrates the multiclass precision–recall curve of three classes, namely; Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy. The plot of Precision versus Recall is plotted, and the curves of each of the classes indicate how the model achieves a balance between the two measures. The values obtained are AP (Average Precision) of each class, that is, Moderate 0.9955, USG 0.9793, and Unhealthy 0.9845, which signify a high level of precision and recall. The curves are near the top-right corner meaning that the model will work very well in identifying the levels of pollution in all categories.</p><fig id="Fig15" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Precision–recall curve of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model for air pollution classification, illustrating the trade-off between precision and recall across different thresholds and highlighting the model’s performance in identifying Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy classes.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1510" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig15_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/d0d1af6c69f4/41598_2026_47424_Fig15_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1087?><?original-width 1372?><?scaled-height 544?><?scaled-width 686?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig15_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/4e6f282282c9/41598_2026_47424_Fig15_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par114">The confusion matrix shows how well the model can predict the level of air pollution in three categories, namely, Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy is shows Fig. <xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig">16</xref>. The diagonal items indicate the right predictions, 222 in the case of Moderate, 222, in the case of USG, and 215 in the case of Unhealthy. Misclassifications are displayed off-diagonal, 9 Moderate instances are misclassified as USG, 2 USG instances are misclassified as Moderate and 13 Unhealthy instances are misclassified as USG. The matrix indicates the overall good performance of the model with very minimal misclassifications, particularly with the Moderate and USG classes. The class-wise error analysis from the confusion matrix shows that there are minor errors, where Moderate/Unhealthy classes are occasionally classified as USG. This may be due to the fact that it is hard to distinguish between visually similar classes of adjacent pollution levels. The results of Grad-CAM show that correct predictions are focused on regions such as the atmosphere, i.e., the sky or haze, while incorrect predictions are focused on background features such as buildings and vegetation. This may be due to the partial use of contextual features, as well as bias in the dataset. Even though CBAM helps to improve feature localization, there is a need to refine it to impose stronger spatial constraints.</p><fig id="Fig16" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 16</label><caption><p>Confusion matrix of the proposed model showing classification performance across different air pollution categories.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1526" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig16_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/e170e5025bef/41598_2026_47424_Fig16_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1030?><?original-width 1359?><?scaled-height 515?><?scaled-width 679?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig16_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/f754d67392a0/41598_2026_47424_Fig16_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par116">Figure <xref rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig">17</xref> indicates KS (Kolmogorov–Smirnov) Statistic Curve of three groups namely Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy. The curve is a comparison of cumulative positive distribution and cumulative negative distribution of each class. These distributions are best measured by the KS statistic, which allows the evaluation of the capacity of the model to discriminate between classes. In the case of the Moderate, the KS value is 0.97 which means that there is a strong separation between the positive and negative distributions. The KS of the USG is 0.92 and the Unhealthy is 0.95 at which the two classes are well separated. The CBAM-InceptionV3 model demonstrated stable performance through various tests which used different random seed combinations. Confidence interval analysis confirmed that the accuracy and F1-scores remained within a particular range which showed no statistically significant differences. The system maintained strong performance through testing which used image perturbations of brightness contrast and blur together with haze. The domain shift evaluation showed that the system could effectively handle different testing conditions. The calibration analysis demonstrated that predicted probabilities matched actual results which established the model as dependable for real-world applications.</p><fig id="Fig17" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 17</label><caption><p>Kolmogorov–Smirnov (KS) statistic curve for multi-class air pollution levels, showing the separation between cumulative distributions of predicted probabilities for Moderate, USG, and Unhealthy classes, which evaluates the model’s discriminative capability.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1541" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig17_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/e73aa7d7c0f8/41598_2026_47424_Fig17_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 973?><?original-width 1218?><?scaled-height 487?><?scaled-width 609?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig17_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/7eb282483b68/41598_2026_47424_Fig17_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par118">Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents the statistical performance evaluation of the proposed model in terms of accuracy, precision, recall, and F1-score. The reported mean and standard deviation values indicate consistent performance across validation folds, while the narrow 95% confidence intervals confirm the reliability and stability of the model under varying data splits.</p><table-wrap id="Tab3" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Statistical performance evaluation with confidence intervals.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metric</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Std</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.23</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">± 0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Precision</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.952</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">± 0.0008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recall</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.951</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">± 0.0009</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F1-score</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.951</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">± 0.0009</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par120">Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> presents the performance of the proposed model evaluated using 5-fold cross-validation. Each fold represents a distinct train–validation split of the dataset to ensure robustness and reliability of the model. The accuracy values across all folds remain consistently high, indicating stable learning behavior. The low standard deviation (± 0.15) demonstrates minimal performance variation, confirming that the model does not suffer from significant overfitting and generalizes well across different data partitions.</p><table-wrap id="Tab4" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>K-fold cross-validation performance of the proposed model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fold</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fold 1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fold 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fold 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fold 4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fold 5</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mean ± Std</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.23 ± 0.15</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par121">Convolutional operations determine the computational cost of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model that is estimated as <inline-formula id="IEq55"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1668" xlink:href="d33e1668.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/9caefcf04e72/d33e1668.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> ), where <inline-formula id="IEq56"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1672" xlink:href="d33e1672.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/8277ed1c8396/d33e1672.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq57"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1676" xlink:href="d33e1676.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/2aad2085578d/d33e1676.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></inline-graphic></inline-formula> denote layers, channels, spatial dimensions, and kernel size, respectively. The CBAM module introduces only minimal overhead due to its lightweight design. The model consists of about 23–24 million parameters which has size of about 90–95 MB. Although it has an attention mechanism, the increase in the parameter is insignificant against the baseline InceptionV3. Inference time per image of the model is 2535 ms (approximately 30 FPS), which shows that it is appropriate in near real-time applications.</p><p id="Par122">Memory: The model has memory usage needs of about 23 GB GPU memory and about 1 GB system RAM during inference, which means it can be deployed on the typical systems with GPUs. Optimization can further be applied to quantize, prune and frameworks like TensorFlow Lite or TensorRT to allow efficient deployment to the edges. The proposed vision-based system is a cost-effective alternative to the traditional sensor-based air quality monitoring systems, which is scalable. It uses existing camera infrastructure to support wide area surveillance without relying much on hardware, but still achieves effective operation.</p><p id="Par124">Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> represents the computational efficiency and deployment feasibility of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model. It highlights key metrics such as parameter count, inference time, memory usage, and computational complexity. The results demonstrate that the model is suitable for near real-time and scalable deployment in practical air pollution monitoring applications.</p><table-wrap id="Tab5" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Computational and deployment analysis of the proposed model including parameter count, inference time, memory usage, and complexity.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metric</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model architecture</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CBAM-InceptionV3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Parameters</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">~ 23–24 Million</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model size</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">~ 90–95 MB</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Inference time</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">~ 25–35 ms/image</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Throughput</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">~ 30 FPS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GPU memory usage</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">~ 2–3 GB</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">RAM usage</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">~ 1 GB</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Computational complexity</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">O (N × C × H × W × K²)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Edge deployment</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Supported (with optimization)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par126">Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref> compares the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model against standard baseline architectures. While standard CNNs and ResNet50 achieve moderate accuracy, the CBAM-InceptionV3 model significantly outperforms them, demonstrating that the combination of attention mechanisms and enhanced preprocessing improves the classification of urban air pollution images.</p><table-wrap id="Tab6" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Baseline Comparison of Proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 Model with Standard Architectures.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Model</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Accuracy (%)</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Precision</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Recall</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">F1-score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard CNN</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.4</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.850</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.848</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.849</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">ResNet50</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.1</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.890</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.888</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.889</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">InceptionV3 (Baseline)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88.6</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.885</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.884</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.884</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CBAM + InceptionV3 (Proposed Model)</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95.23</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.952</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.951</td><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.951</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="Par128">In Fig. <xref rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig">18</xref>, the Grad-CAM visualization of a correctly classified Moderate air pollution image. Left: Original input image. Center: Grad-CAM heatmap highlighting regions most influential for the prediction. Right: Overlay of Grad-CAM on the original image. The network correctly focuses on atmospheric cues such as haze and sky, demonstrating interpretability of the CBAM-InceptionV3 model.</p><fig id="Fig18" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 18</label><caption><p>Grad-CAM for correctly classified image.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1835" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig18_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/722f16bd30d5/41598_2026_47424_Fig18_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 792?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 264?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig18_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/e6d892d41b96/41598_2026_47424_Fig18_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p id="Par130">In Fig. <xref rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig">19</xref>, the Grad-CAM visualizations for misclassified samples. Top-left: Moderate misclassified as USG. Top-right: Unhealthy misclassified as USG. Bottom-left and bottom-right: Additional examples of misclassified Moderate and Unhealthy images. The heatmaps indicate partial attention to background elements (buildings, roads) and atmospheric regions, highlighting limitations in feature localization despite CBAM attention.</p><fig id="Fig19" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 19</label><caption><p>Grad-CAM for misclassified images.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="d33e1850" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig19_HTML.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/e980baec49ad/41598_2026_47424_Fig19_HTML.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1322?><?original-width 2008?><?scaled-height 440?><?scaled-width 669?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="41598_2026_47424_Fig19_HTML.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/15ba/13219415/ee81e5ea8d7b/41598_2026_47424_Fig19_HTML.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="Sec27" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusions and future scope</title><p id="Par131">In conclusion, this study presents an image-based deep learning classification framework for predicting airborne pollution levels in urban environments. The proposed model integrates the InceptionV3 architecture with a Convolutional Block Attention Module (CBAM), enabling the network to selectively focus on the most informative regions of each image. By emphasizing visually salient features associated with atmospheric conditions such as: haze, fog, and smog-the attention mechanism enhances feature representation and leads to improved classification accuracy across different pollution levels. By applying image preprocessing techniques to reduce noise, enhance contrast, and emphasize salient visual structures, a deep learning model was trained to classify images into three air pollution categories: <italic>Moderate</italic>, <italic>Unhealthy for Sensitive Groups (USG)</italic>, and <italic>Unhealthy</italic>. Furthermore, the integration of a Convolutional Block Attention Module (CBAM) with the InceptionV3 architecture facilitates the learning of fine-grained visual patterns that distinguish between varying levels of atmospheric pollution. The interpretability analysis using Grad-CAM further validates the behavior of the proposed model by revealing both its strengths in focusing on relevant atmospheric cues and its limitations in certain failure cases.</p><p id="Par132">The model uses visually inferred labels which depend on environmental and imaging conditions that include fog and lighting and seasonal variations as their basis. The predictions show visual air quality indicators because they do not measure actual pollutant levels. The upcoming research will combine ground-based sensor information with image-based learning methods to enhance label accuracy and validate scientific model development. The model, in its training, showed high precision, recall, and F1 for every one of the three categories. Moderate had a precision of 0.9535, recall of 0.9523, and an F1 of 0.9529. USG was similar with a precision of 0.9531, a recall of 0.9519, and an F1 of 0.9525, The experimental results the effectiveness of the proposed CBAM-InceptionV3 model, achieving an accuracy of 95.23%, with precision, recall, and F1-score values consistently above 95%. These results demonstrate the robustness and reliability of the model for accurate air pollution level classification and real-time urban air quality monitoring.These results demonstrate the effectiveness of the proposed model in accurately and efficiently classifying urban air pollution levels. Future work will focus on enhancing model robustness by incorporating data from geographically and climatologically diverse locations, as well as enabling real-time classification through edge-computing–based deployment. Furthermore, integrating additional environmental variables, such as temperature and humidity, is expected to further improve predictive performance and robustness in dynamic urban environments.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>MA, RS, and RA: prepared the manuscript, reviewed and revised the work. MA and AA: funding acquisition and fund management, MA, RS and AA: data collection, analysis, project management. All authors read and approved of the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="notes2" disp-level="1"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Deanship of Scientific Research, Vice Presidency for Graduate Studies and Scientific Research, King Faisal University, Saudi Arabia (Grant No. KFU261619).</p></sec><sec id="notes3" disp-level="1"><title>Data availability</title><p>The dataset used in this study, Air Pollution Image Dataset, is publicly available on Kaggle and can be accessed at [https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/adarshrouniyar/air-pollution-image-dataset-from-india-and-nepal? select=Air+Pollution+Image+Dataset](https:/www.kaggle.com/datasets/adarshrouniyar/air-pollution-image-dataset-from-india-and-nepal? select=Air+Pollution+Image+Dataset).</p></sec><sec id="notes4" disp-level="1"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="FPar2" disp-level="2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par133">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fn-group1" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="1"><title>Footnotes</title><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec id="Bib1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="Bib1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Piracha, A. &amp; Chaudhary, M. T. Urban air pollution, urban heat island and human health: A review of the literature. <italic>Sustainability</italic><bold>14</bold> (15), 9234. 10.3390/su14159234 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Piracha, A. &amp; Chaudhary, M. T. Urban air pollution, urban heat island and human health: A review of the literature. Sustainability14 (15), 9234. 10.3390/su14159234 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A. et al. PR-FCNN: A data-driven hybrid approach for predicting PM2.5 concentration. <italic>Discov. Artif. Intell.</italic><bold>4</bold> (1), 75. 10.1007/s44163-024-00184-7 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Inam, S. A. et al. PR-FCNN: A data-driven hybrid approach for predicting PM2.5 concentration. Discov. Artif. Intell.4 (1), 75. 10.1007/s44163-024-00184-7 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Saxena, V. Water quality, air pollution, and climate change: Investigating the environmental impacts of industrialization and urbanization. <italic>Water Air Soil. Pollut</italic>. <bold>236</bold> (2), 73. 10.1007/s11270-024-07702-4 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Saxena, V. Water quality, air pollution, and climate change: Investigating the environmental impacts of industrialization and urbanization. Water Air Soil. Pollut. 236 (2), 73. 10.1007/s11270-024-07702-4 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A. et al. A novel deep learning approach for investigating liquid fuel injection in combustion system. <italic>Discov. Artif. Intell.</italic><bold>5</bold> (1), 32. 10.1007/s44163-025-00248-2 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Meo, S. A., Salih, M. A., Alkhalifah, J. M., Alsomali, A. H. &amp; Almushawah, A. A. Environmental pollutants particulate matter (PM2.5, PM10), carbon monoxide (CO), nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>), sulfur dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub>), and ozone (O<sub>3</sub>) impact on lung functions. <italic>J. King Saud Univ. Sci.</italic><bold>36</bold> (7), 103280. 10.1016/j.jksus.2024.103280 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A., Zaidi, S. M. H., Khan, A. A. &amp; Ullah, S. A neural network approach to carbon emission prediction in industrial and power sectors. <italic>Discov. Appl. Sci.</italic><bold>7</bold> (6), 640. 10.1007/s42452-025-07257-x ( 2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Inam, S. A., Zaidi, S. M. H., Khan, A. A. &amp; Ullah, S. A neural network approach to carbon emission prediction in industrial and power sectors. Discov. Appl. Sci.7 (6), 640. 10.1007/s42452-025-07257-x ( 2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dhimal, M. et al. Impact of air pollution on global burden of disease in 2019. <italic>Processes</italic><bold>9</bold> (10), 1719. 10.3390/pr9101719 (2021).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Dhimal, M. et al. Impact of air pollution on global burden of disease in 2019. Processes9 (10), 1719. 10.3390/pr9101719 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A. et al. A transformer-based framework for accurate and interpretable PM2.5 forecasting through integration of country-level embeddings and explainable AI for enhanced environmental decision-making. <italic>ABBDM</italic><bold>5</bold> (3), 245–255. 10.62019/hcqtrs67 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Inam, S. A. et al. A transformer-based framework for accurate and interpretable PM2.5 forecasting through integration of country-level embeddings and explainable AI for enhanced environmental decision-making. ABBDM5 (3), 245–255. 10.62019/hcqtrs67 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kumari, S. et al. Next-generation air quality management: Unveiling advanced techniques for monitoring and controlling pollution. <italic>Aerosol. Sci. Eng</italic>. 10.1007/s41810-024-00281-1 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A., Hashim, H., Awan, A. M., Rajput, H. &amp; Umer, S. A novel approach toward windspeed forecasting using an advanced deep learning framework with explainable AI. <italic>VFAST Trans. Softw. Eng.</italic><bold>13</bold> (3), 198–210. 10.21015/vtse.v13i3.2230 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Inam, S. A., Hashim, H., Awan, A. M., Rajput, H. &amp; Umer, S. A novel approach toward windspeed forecasting using an advanced deep learning framework with explainable AI. VFAST Trans. Softw. Eng.13 (3), 198–210. 10.21015/vtse.v13i3.2230 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A., Hashim, H., Awan, A. M., Rajput, H. &amp; Umer, S. Interpretable physics-informed neural network for reliable humidity forecasting in contrasting climates of sindh. <italic>VAWKUM Trans. Comput. Sci.</italic><bold>13</bold> (2), 135–148. 10.21015/vtcs.v13i2.2229 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Inam, S. A., Hashim, H., Awan, A. M., Rajput, H. &amp; Umer, S. Interpretable physics-informed neural network for reliable humidity forecasting in contrasting climates of sindh. VAWKUM Trans. Comput. Sci.13 (2), 135–148. 10.21015/vtcs.v13i2.2229 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">da Silva, D. B., Pianovski, M. A. D. &amp; de Filho, N. P. Environmental pollution and cancer. <italic>J. Pediatria </italic><bold>101</bold>, S18–S26. 10.1016/j.jped.2024.09.004 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jped.2024.09.004"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC11962547"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39488336"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A. et al. AI-driven physics informed neural network for daily temperature forecasting with constraint aware learning and explainable feature attribution. <italic>VFAST Trans. Softw. Eng.</italic><bold>13</bold> (4), 53–67. 10.21015/vtse.v13i4.2231 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Inam, S. A. et al. AI-driven physics informed neural network for daily temperature forecasting with constraint aware learning and explainable feature attribution. VFAST Trans. Softw. Eng.13 (4), 53–67. 10.21015/vtse.v13i4.2231 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhang, L. et al. Indoor particulate matter in urban households: Sources, pathways, characteristics, health effects, and exposure mitigation. <italic>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health</italic><bold>18</bold> (21), 11055. 10.3390/ijerph182111055 (2021).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/ijerph182111055"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC8582694"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="34769574"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Zhang, L. et al. Indoor particulate matter in urban households: Sources, pathways, characteristics, health effects, and exposure mitigation. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public. Health18 (21), 11055. 10.3390/ijerph182111055 (2021)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nejad, M. T., Ghalehteimouri, K. J., Talkhabi, H. &amp; Dolatshahi, Z. The relationship between atmospheric temperature inversion and urban air pollution characteristics: A case study of Tehran. <italic>Iran. Discov. Environ.</italic><bold>1</bold> (1), 17. 10.1007/s44274-023-00018-w (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Nejad, M. T., Ghalehteimouri, K. J., Talkhabi, H. &amp; Dolatshahi, Z. The relationship between atmospheric temperature inversion and urban air pollution characteristics: A case study of Tehran. Iran. Discov. Environ.1 (1), 17. 10.1007/s44274-023-00018-w (2023)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A. A review of artificial intelligence for predicting climate driven infectious disease outbreaks to enhance global health resilience. <italic>Discov. Public. Health</italic><bold>22</bold> (1), 738. 10.1186/s12982-025-01167-4 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pulinets, S., Davidenko, D. &amp; Pulinets, M. Atmosphere-ionosphere coupling induced by volcanoes eruption and dust storms and role of GEC as the agent of geospheres interaction. <italic>Adv. Space Res.</italic><bold>69</bold> (12), 4319–4334. 10.1016/j.asr.2022.03.031 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pulinets, S., Davidenko, D. &amp; Pulinets, M. Atmosphere-ionosphere coupling induced by volcanoes eruption and dust storms and role of GEC as the agent of geospheres interaction. Adv. Space Res.69 (12), 4319–4334. 10.1016/j.asr.2022.03.031 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ahmad, N. &amp; Kumar, V. Effective air pollution prediction using wavenet deep learning with Xgboost (1DCNN-BiLSTM-XgRC) for urban US embassies. <italic>Theor. Appl. Climatol</italic>. <bold>156</bold>, 464. 10.1007/s00704-025-05715-5 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Florea, S. The green, green grass of home’; An eco linguistic analysis of the environmental responsibility urban discourse of Europe’s most polluted cities. <italic>J. Environ. Manag.</italic><bold>392</bold>, 126718. 10.1016/j.jenvman.2025.126718 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jenvman.2025.126718"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40730017"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A., Rajput, H. &amp; Umer, S. An explainable hybrid stacked deep learning framework for forecasting PM10 concentrations in urban air. <italic>EER</italic><bold>2</bold> (4), 025380069. 10.36922/EER025380069 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Inam, S. A., Rajput, H. &amp; Umer, S. An explainable hybrid stacked deep learning framework for forecasting PM10 concentrations in urban air. EER2 (4), 025380069. 10.36922/EER025380069 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Elbestar, M., Aly, S. G. &amp; Ghannam, R. Advances in air quality monitoring: A comprehensive review of algorithms for imaging and sensing technologies. <italic>Adv. Sens. Res.</italic><bold>3</bold> (11), 2300207. 10.1002/adsr.202300207 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Elbestar, M., Aly, S. G. &amp; Ghannam, R. Advances in air quality monitoring: A comprehensive review of algorithms for imaging and sensing technologies. Adv. Sens. Res.3 (11), 2300207. 10.1002/adsr.202300207 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A., Umer, S., Rajput, H. &amp; Global PM2.5 exposure forecasting with novel deep learning architecture and explainable artificial intelligence. <italic>EER</italic><bold>2</bold> (4), 025370067. 10.36922/EER025370067 (2025).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Inam, S. A., Umer, S., Rajput, H. &amp; Global PM2.5 exposure forecasting with novel deep learning architecture and explainable artificial intelligence. EER2 (4), 025370067. 10.36922/EER025370067 (2025)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Pramanik, J., Samal, A. K., Pani, S. K. &amp; Chakraborty, C. Elementary framework for an IoT based diverse ambient air quality monitoring system. <italic>Multimed. Tools Appl.</italic><bold>81</bold> (26), 36983–37005. 10.1007/s11042-021-11285-1 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Pramanik, J., Samal, A. K., Pani, S. K. &amp; Chakraborty, C. Elementary framework for an IoT based diverse ambient air quality monitoring system. Multimed. Tools Appl.81 (26), 36983–37005. 10.1007/s11042-021-11285-1 (2022)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A., Rajput, H. &amp; Umer, S. A hierarchical ensemble approach for multi-country PM10 forecasting using LightGBM and residual neural network. <italic>Discov. Atmos.</italic><bold>4</bold> (1), 1. 10.1007/s44292-025-00072-4 (2026).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Walker, B. &amp; Klagge, B. Infrastructure bottlenecks as opportunity for local development: The case of decentralized green-hydrogen projects. <italic>Tijdschrift voor Economische en Sociale Geografie</italic>. <bold>115</bold> (5), 643–659. 10.1111/tesg.12633 (2024).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Walker, B. &amp; Klagge, B. Infrastructure bottlenecks as opportunity for local development: The case of decentralized green-hydrogen projects. Tijdschrift voor Economische en Sociale Geografie. 115 (5), 643–659. 10.1111/tesg.12633 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ahmad, N. &amp; Kumar, V. Enhancing the predictions of us embassies using novel hybrid 1DCNN-BiGRU and decomposed-recomposed 1DCNN-BiGRU-DR models. <italic>Aerosol. Sci. Eng.</italic><bold>5</bold> (6). 10.1007/s41810-025-00372-7 (2026).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Agbehadji, I. E. &amp; Obagbuwa, I. C. Systematic review of machine learning and deep learning techniques for spatiotemporal air quality prediction. <italic>Atmosphere</italic><bold>15</bold> (11), 1352. 10.3390/atmos15111352 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Inam, S. A., Umer, S. &amp; Rajput, H. A physics informed deep learning framework for rainfall forecasting in diverse climatic regions. <italic>Discov. Artif. Intell.</italic><bold>6</bold> (1), 104. 10.1007/s44163-026-00833-z (2026).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29"><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sonmez, M. E. et al. Enhancing microalgae classification accuracy in marine ecosystems through convolutional neural networks and support vector machines. <italic>Mar. Pollut Bull.</italic><bold>205</bold>, 116616. 10.1016/j.marpolbul.2024.116616 (2024).
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.marpolbul.2024.116616"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="38936001"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="Sonmez, M. E. et al. Enhancing microalgae classification accuracy in marine ecosystems through convolutional neural networks and support vector machines. Mar. Pollut Bull.205, 116616. 10.1016/j.marpolbul.2024.116616 (2024)."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sarkar, N., Gupta, R., Keserwani, P. K. &amp; Govil, M. C. Air quality index prediction using an effective hybrid deep learning model. <italic>Environ. Pollut.</italic><bold>315</bold>, 120404. 10.1016/j.envpol.2022.120404 (2022).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.envpol.2022.120404"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36240962"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Das, B., Dursun, Ö. O. &amp; Toraman, S. Prediction of air pollutants for air quality using deep learning methods in a metropolitan city. <italic>Urban Clim.</italic><bold>46</bold>, 101291. 10.1016/j.uclim.2022.101291 (2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Maltare, N. N. &amp; Vahora, S. Air quality index prediction using machine learning for Ahmedabad city. <italic>Digit. Chem. Eng.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 100093. 10.1016/j.dche.2023.100093 (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gupta, N. S. et al. Prediction of air quality index using machine learning techniques: A comparative analysis. <italic>J. Environ. Public Health</italic> 1, 4916267. 10.1155/2023/4916267 (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Heydari, A., Majidi Nezhad, M., Astiaso Garcia, D., Keynia, F. &amp; De Santoli, L. Air pollution forecasting application based on deep learning model and optimization algorithm. <italic>Clean. Techn. Environ. Policy</italic><bold>24</bold> (2), 607–621. 10.1007/s10098-021-02080-5 (2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Drewil, G. I. &amp; Al-Bahadili, R. J. Air pollution prediction using LSTM deep learning and metaheuristics algorithms. <italic>Meas. Sens.</italic><bold>24</bold>, 100546. 10.1016/j.measen.2022.100546 (2022).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Kumar, K. &amp; Pande, B. P. Air pollution prediction with machine learning: A case study of Indian cities. <italic>Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol.</italic><bold>20</bold> (5), 5333–5348. 10.1007/s13762-022-04241-5 (2023).</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s13762-022-04241-5"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC9107909"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="35603096"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Samad, A., Garuda, S., Vogt, U. &amp; Yang, B. Air pollution prediction using machine learning techniques—An approach to replace existing monitoring stations with virtual monitoring stations. <italic>Atmos. Environ.</italic><bold>310</bold>, 119987. 10.1016/j.atmosenv.2023.119987 (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ahmad, N. &amp; Kumar, V. Enhancing PM<sub>2.5</sub> Air pollution forecasting with novel random imputation based on hybrid RNN-bidirectional GRU (nRI RNN-BiGRU) model. <italic>SN Comput. Sci.</italic><bold>6</bold> (6), 637. 10.1007/s42979-025-04167-y (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Zhu, L., Husny, Z. J. B. M., Samsudin, N. A., Xu, H. &amp; Han, C. Deep learning method for minimizing water pollution and air pollution in urban environment. <italic>Urban Clim.</italic><bold>49</bold>, 101486. 10.1016/j.uclim.2023.101486 (2023).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Binbusayyis, A., et al. A deep learning approach for prediction of air quality index in smart city. <italic>Discov. Sustain.</italic><bold>5</bold> (1), 89. 10.1007/s43621-024-00272-9 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ahmad, N. &amp; Kumar, V. Enhancing {2.5}air pollution forecasting with novel random imputation based on hybrid RNN-bidirectional GRU (nRI RNN-BiGRU) model. <italic>SN Comput. Sci.</italic><bold>6</bold> (6), 637. 10.1007/s42979-025-04167-y (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ahmad, N. &amp; Jas, S. Quantum-inspired neural networks for time-series air pollution prediction and control of the most polluted region in the world. <italic>Quantum Mach. Intell.</italic><bold>7</bold> (1), 9. 10.1007/s42484-024-00232-6 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ahmad, N. &amp; Kumar, V. Enhancing PM$$_{2.5}$$ air pollution forecasting with novel random imputation based on hybrid RNN-bidirectional GRU (nRI RNN-BiGRU) model. <italic>SN Comput. Sci.</italic><bold>6</bold> (6), 637. 10.1007/s42979-025-04167-y (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Qu, Y. et al. Deep learning-based atmospheric visibility detection. <italic>Atmosphere</italic><bold>15</bold> (11), 1394. 10.3390/atmos15111394 (2024).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ozkok, F. O. Image-based air pollution classification using deep learning techniques. <italic>EPSTEM</italic><bold>35</bold>, 302–313. 10.55549/epstem.1806639 (2025).</named-content></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adda93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="data-availability-statement" disp-level="2"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The dataset used in this study, Air Pollution Image Dataset, is publicly available on Kaggle and can be accessed at [https://www.kaggle.com/datasets/adarshrouniyar/air-pollution-image-dataset-from-india-and-nepal? select=Air+Pollution+Image+Dataset](https:/www.kaggle.com/datasets/adarshrouniyar/air-pollution-image-dataset-from-india-and-nepal? select=Air+Pollution+Image+Dataset).</p></sec></sec></body></article>