<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="article-commentary"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">379</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">blackwellopen</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The New Phytologist</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>New Phytol</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12780301</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12780301</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12780301</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41388618</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.70836</article-id><title-group><article-title>Engineering plant stress responses to combat climate change</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names initials="MA">Matthew A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="nph70836-aff-0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="_fncrsp93pmc__">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="nph70836-aff-0001"><label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>Plant Science Group, School of Molecular Biosciences, University of Glasgow, University Avenue, Glasgow, G12 8QQ, UK</aff><author-notes><fn id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><p>

email: <email>matt.jones@glasgow.ac.uk</email>

</p></fn><fn id="_fncrsp93pmc__"><label>✉</label><p>Corresponding author.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>249</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1092</fpage><page-range>1092–1094</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2025 The Author(s). <italic>New Phytologist</italic> © 2025 New Phytologist Foundation.</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="NPH-249-1092.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path ea03/12780301/31f2c7512073/NPH-249-1092.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 257587?></self-uri><related-article related-article-type="companion">See "<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12780315">Modulation of SAL retrograde signalling promotes yield and water productivity responses in dynamic field environments</ext-link>" on page 1219.</related-article><abstract id="nph70836-abs-3101" abstract-type="short"><title>Short abstract</title><p>This article is a Commentary on <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.70579" ext-link-type="uri">Bowerman <italic>et al</italic>. (2026), <bold>249</bold>: 1219–1233.</ext-link>
</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> circadian, phenotypic plasticity, photoreceptor, retrograde signalling, thermosensor</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-in-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Issue date 2026 Feb.</p></sec></notes></front><body><p>Climate change has already begun to limit crop growth due to elevated temperatures and increased frequency of climate events, including drought and heatwaves. These environmental changes present a particular challenge for plants due to their inherent phenotypic plasticity that allows adaptation to prevailing conditions. Should plants maximise their growth to increase fecundity or invest in strategies that improve stress tolerance? The difficulty of this developmental decision reveals a trade‐off between growth and resilience that is most dramatically observed in experiments that constitutively activate stress‐responsive signalling networks. This results in plants that are typically hardy yet smaller than their unmodified brethren, making this an imperfect solution for crops (Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2020</sup></xref>). A new paper by Bowerman <italic>et al</italic>., published in this issue of <italic>New Phytologist</italic> (Bowerman <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2026</sup></xref>; pp. 1219–1233), demonstrates how alternative approaches that instead manipulate plants' responses to environmental signals can influence development to increase field‐grown yield.</p><disp-quote id="nph70836-blkfxd-0001"><p>
<italic>Manipulation of retrograde signalling by Bowerman</italic> et al. <italic>provides an example of how responses to environmental signals can be engineered without inducing constitutive stress signalling</italic>.</p></disp-quote><sec id="nph70836-sec-0002" disp-level="1"><title>Translating fundamental science into the field</title><p>Laboratory experiments are controlled by design, with limited variables to aid interpretation and often apply large stresses to induce measurable responses (Lundberg <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2025</sup></xref>). By contrast, field experiments and practical applications are inevitably multifactorial and perhaps milder in magnitude, with at least light and temperature changing on a continual basis (Prado <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2025</sup></xref>). Given this complexity, it is perhaps unsurprising that transgenic lines created and tested in the laboratory typically have reduced benefits in field trials (Prado <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2025</sup></xref>). Changes in approach will be needed to improve the pipeline from laboratory to field, including the careful consideration of agronomically relevant responses when designing experiments to identify, characterise, and engineer climate‐resistant crops (Prado <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2025</sup></xref>).</p></sec><sec id="nph70836-sec-0003" disp-level="1"><title>Engineering responses to environmental change</title><p>A combination of agronomic approaches and crop improvement will be required to maintain and increase crop yield despite the consequences of global warming (Prado <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2025</sup></xref>). Croplands are already moving away from the equator to avoid elevated temperatures while minimising irrigation requirements (Beyer <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2022</sup></xref>). These geographical movements come with the caveat that changes in seasonal day length and temperature have increased magnitude away from the equator, which could result in impaired flowering time and altered development (McClung, <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Domestication has already selected varietals with altered circadian rhythms, and the alignment of crop chronotype with latitude provides opportunities to refine flowering time as farmers revise their planting strategies (McClung, <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Steed <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2021</sup></xref>).</p><p>An alternative target to combat climate change is to manipulate plants' responses to heat and drought stress (Fig. <xref rid="nph70836-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Plants perceive environmental signals through a combination of receptor proteins and metabolic changes arising from photosynthesis and respiration (Jones, <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Queiroz <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2023</sup></xref>). Temperature and light signalling are increasingly recognised as being interlinked, with the biological activity of many photoreceptors being temperature‐dependent (Kerbler &amp; Wigge, <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>; Sharma <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2025</sup></xref>). Alongside these dedicated environmental sensors, retrograde signals conveying the ‘operational status’ of the chloroplast (and mitochondria) have also been co‐opted through evolution to serve as environmental sensors. Photosynthates (or indeed toxic by‐products such as Reactive Oxygen Species) govern biochemical reactions elsewhere in the cell by providing chemical energy, cofactors, or other signalling molecules (Lee &amp; Kim, <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). The regulation of nuclear gene expression by these retrograde signals enables coordination of chloroplast function with other sensory pathways (Jones, <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Operational retrograde signalling has previously been thought to have a primary role in short‐term responses to stress. The question remains whether these short‐term retrograde signalling events are sufficient to induce longer‐term changes in growth and development (van Veen <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2025</sup></xref>). In particular, it remains unclear how signalling pathways initiated during the initial stages of stress contribute to longer‐term developmental changes such as flowering time and yield.</p><fig id="nph70836-fig-0001" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Engineering of plant responses to environmental stimuli provides opportunities to create climate‐resistant crops. Environmental signals, including temperature and light, are perceived by a combination of sensory proteins and the metabolic consequences of photosynthesis. Integration of these signals via a combination of anterograde and retrograde signals is modulated by the circadian system to facilitate short‐term and long‐term developmental responses. Understanding and engineering these responses will contribute to the development of climate change‐resistant crops.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" id="jats-graphic-1" xlink:href="NPH-249-1092-g001.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/ea03/12780301/f2d867e60680/NPH-249-1092-g001.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 1328?><?original-width 1064?><?scaled-height 885?><?scaled-width 709?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="NPH-249-1092-g001.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/ea03/12780301/fff9628627dc/NPH-249-1092-g001.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="nph70836-sec-0004" disp-level="1"><title>Priming retrograde signalling pathways to regulate developmental responses</title><p>Despite the opportunities to edit crop responses to environmental stress, we have comparatively few case studies that examine this strategy in practice. Bowerman <italic>et al</italic>. begin to address this hypothesis by examining the consequences of priming a retrograde signalling pathway to be more responsive to drought stress. SAL1 is an adenosine phosphatase that catabolises 3′‐PhosphoAdenosine 5′‐Phosphate (PAP) into adenosine monophosphate (Estavillo <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2011</sup></xref>). Oxidative stress in the chloroplast (and/or mitochondria) inhibits SAL1 enzymatic activity, leading to accumulation of PAP in the cytosol with consequent pleiotropic effects upon transcription and RNA stability in Arabidopsis (Estavillo <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2011</sup></xref>; Chan <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2016</sup></xref>). Despite these pleiotropic effects, Arabidopsis mutants that constitutively accumulate PAP are more drought tolerant, with PAP accumulation inducing stomatal closure in parallel with abscisic acid signalling (Pornsiriwong <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2017</sup></xref>). Bowerman <italic>et al</italic>. exploited genetic redundancy in wheat to create mutant lines with impaired SAL activity that accumulate greater amounts of PAP during stress while retaining low PAP levels in control conditions. Reduced SAL activity effectively lowers the threshold of PAP‐mediated retrograde signalling, promoting stomatal closure during periods of drought and increasing the yield of field‐grown wheat.</p><p>Manipulation of retrograde signalling by Bowerman <italic>et al</italic>. provides an example of how responses to environmental signals can be engineered without inducing constitutive stress signalling. There are also opportunities to modulate retrograde signalling by regulating photosynthesis, for example, by limiting nonphotochemical quenching (Zuo, <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2025</xref>). Application of this approach to other environmental sensing pathways, for example, photoreceptor or thermosensor engineering, or modification of circadian clock activity, is an interesting avenue to create climate change‐resistant crops (Hart <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2019</sup></xref>; Hu <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2020</sup></xref>; Steed <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2021</sup></xref>; Battle <italic>et al</italic>., <xref rid="nph70836-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2024</sup></xref>).</p><p>The toolkit of approaches to manipulate plant behaviour is now expanding, building on the evidence base that short‐term signalling responses can cumulatively control crop development. These examples illustrate how crucial fundamental research identifying stress‐responsive pathways can now be exploited to maintain crop production in the face of climate change.</p></sec><sec id="nph70836-sec-0006" disp-level="1"><title>Disclaimer</title><p>The New Phytologist Foundation remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in maps and in any institutional affiliations.</p></sec><sec id="nph70836-sec-0005" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Work in the Jones lab is supported by UKRI/BBSRC (grants BB/P006868/1, BB/S005404/1, BB/Z514469/1). MAJ thanks Tally Sharples for artistic assistance with Fig. <xref rid="nph70836-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="notes1" disp-level="1"><sec id="nph70836-ntgp-0001" sec-type="fn-group" disp-level="2"><fn-group><fn id="nph70836-note-0001"><p>This article is a Commentary on <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.70579" ext-link-type="uri">Bowerman <italic>et al</italic>. (2026), <bold>249</bold>: 1219–1233.</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group></sec></sec><sec id="nph70836-bibl-0001" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="nph70836-bibl-0001_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="nph70836-bib-0001"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0001"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Battle MW, Ewing SF, Dickson C, Obaje J, Edgeworth KN, Bindbeutel R, Antoniou‐Kourounioti RL, Nusinow DA, Jones MA. 2024. Manipulation of photosensory and circadian signaling restricts phenotypic plasticity in response to changing environmental conditions in Arabidopsis. Molecular Plant
17: 1458–1471.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.molp.2024.07.007"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39014898"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Molecular Plant&amp;title=Manipulation of photosensory and circadian signaling restricts phenotypic plasticity in response to changing environmental conditions in Arabidopsis&amp;author=MW Battle&amp;author=SF Ewing&amp;author=C Dickson&amp;author=J Obaje&amp;author=KN Edgeworth&amp;volume=17&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=1458-1471&amp;pmid=39014898&amp;doi=10.1016/j.molp.2024.07.007&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0002"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0002"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Beyer RM, Hua F, Martin PA, Manica A, Rademacher T. 2022. Relocating croplands could drastically reduce the environmental impacts of global food production. Communications Earth &amp; Environment
3: 82.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Communications Earth &amp; Environment&amp;title=Relocating croplands could drastically reduce the environmental impacts of global food production&amp;author=RM Beyer&amp;author=F Hua&amp;author=PA Martin&amp;author=A Manica&amp;author=T Rademacher&amp;volume=3&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;pages=82&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0003"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0003"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Bowerman AF, Moore M, Yadav A, Zhang J, Mortimer MD, Plšková Z, Tee EE, Au EK, Collinge DP, Estavillo GM
<italic>et al</italic>. 2026. Modulation of SAL retrograde signalling promotes yield and water productivity responses in dynamic field environments. New Phytologist
249: 1219–1233.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/nph.70579"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12780315"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40948317"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytologist&amp;title=Modulation of SAL retrograde signalling promotes yield and water productivity responses in dynamic field environments&amp;author=AF Bowerman&amp;author=M Moore&amp;author=A Yadav&amp;author=J Zhang&amp;author=MD Mortimer&amp;volume=249&amp;publication_year=2026&amp;pages=1219-1233&amp;pmid=40948317&amp;doi=10.1111/nph.70579&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0004"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0004"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Chan KX, Mabbitt PD, Phua SY, Mueller JW, Nisar N, Gigolashvili T, Stroeher E, Grassl J, Arlt W, Estavillo GM
<italic>et al</italic>. 2016. Sensing and signaling of oxidative stress in chloroplasts by inactivation of the SAL1 phosphoadenosine phosphatase. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA
113: E4567–E4576.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1604936113"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4978270"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="27432987"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA&amp;title=Sensing and signaling of oxidative stress in chloroplasts by inactivation of the SAL1 phosphoadenosine phosphatase&amp;author=KX Chan&amp;author=PD Mabbitt&amp;author=SY Phua&amp;author=JW Mueller&amp;author=N Nisar&amp;volume=113&amp;publication_year=2016&amp;pages=E4567-E4576&amp;pmid=27432987&amp;doi=10.1073/pnas.1604936113&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0005"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0005"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Estavillo GM, Crisp PA, Pornsiriwong W, Wirtz M, Collinge D, Carrie C, Giraud E, Whelan J, David P, Javot H
<italic>et al</italic>. 2011. Evidence for a SAL1‐PAP chloroplast retrograde pathway that functions in drought and high light signaling in Arabidopsis. Plant Cell
23: 3992–4012.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1105/tpc.111.091033"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3246320"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22128124"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Cell&amp;title=Evidence for a SAL1‐PAP chloroplast retrograde pathway that functions in drought and high light signaling in Arabidopsis&amp;author=GM Estavillo&amp;author=PA Crisp&amp;author=W Pornsiriwong&amp;author=M Wirtz&amp;author=D Collinge&amp;volume=23&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=3992-4012&amp;pmid=22128124&amp;doi=10.1105/tpc.111.091033&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0006"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0006"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Hart JE, Sullivan S, Hermanowicz P, Petersen J, Diaz‐Ramos LA, Hoey DJ, Łabuz J, Christie JM. 2019. Engineering the phototropin photocycle improves photoreceptor performance and plant biomass production. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA
116: 12550–12557.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1902915116"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC6589663"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="31160455"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA&amp;title=Engineering the phototropin photocycle improves photoreceptor performance and plant biomass production&amp;author=JE Hart&amp;author=S Sullivan&amp;author=P Hermanowicz&amp;author=J Petersen&amp;author=LA Diaz‐Ramos&amp;volume=116&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=12550-12557&amp;pmid=31160455&amp;doi=10.1073/pnas.1902915116&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0007"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0007"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Hu W, Figueroa Balderas R, Chi Ham C, Lagarias JC. 2020. Regulation of monocot and dicot plant development with constitutively active alleles of phytochrome B. Plant Direct
4: 401.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1002/pld3.210"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7184922"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="32346668"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Direct&amp;title=Regulation of monocot and dicot plant development with constitutively active alleles of phytochrome B&amp;author=W Hu&amp;author=R Figueroa Balderas&amp;author=C Chi Ham&amp;author=JC Lagarias&amp;volume=4&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=401&amp;pmid=32346668&amp;doi=10.1002/pld3.210&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0008"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0008"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Jones MA. 2019. Retrograde signalling as an informant of circadian timing. New Phytologist
221: 1749–1753.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/nph.15525"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="30299544"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytologist&amp;title=Retrograde signalling as an informant of circadian timing&amp;author=MA Jones&amp;volume=221&amp;publication_year=2019&amp;pages=1749-1753&amp;pmid=30299544&amp;doi=10.1111/nph.15525&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0009"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0009"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Kerbler SM, Wigge PA. 2023. Temperature sensing in plants. Annual Review of Plant Biology
74: 341–366.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1146/annurev-arplant-102820-102235"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="36854477"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Annual Review of Plant Biology&amp;title=Temperature sensing in plants&amp;author=SM Kerbler&amp;author=PA Wigge&amp;volume=74&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;pages=341-366&amp;pmid=36854477&amp;doi=10.1146/annurev-arplant-102820-102235&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0010"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0010"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Lee KP, Kim C. 2024. Photosynthetic ROS and retrograde signaling pathways. New Phytologist
244: 1183–1198.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/nph.20134"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39286853"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytologist&amp;title=Photosynthetic ROS and retrograde signaling pathways&amp;author=KP Lee&amp;author=C Kim&amp;volume=244&amp;publication_year=2024&amp;pages=1183-1198&amp;pmid=39286853&amp;doi=10.1111/nph.20134&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0011"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0011"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Lundberg DS, Bergelson J, Roux F, Weigel D, Karasov TL. 2025. Lab to field: challenges and opportunities for plant biology. Cell Host &amp; Microbe
33: 1212–1216.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.chom.2025.05.027"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40812171"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Cell Host &amp; Microbe&amp;title=Lab to field: challenges and opportunities for plant biology&amp;author=DS Lundberg&amp;author=J Bergelson&amp;author=F Roux&amp;author=D Weigel&amp;author=TL Karasov&amp;volume=33&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=1212-1216&amp;pmid=40812171&amp;doi=10.1016/j.chom.2025.05.027&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0012"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0012"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
McClung CR. 2021. Circadian clock components offer targets for crop domestication and improvement. Genes
12: 374.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.3390/genes12030374"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC7999361"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33800720"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Genes&amp;title=Circadian clock components offer targets for crop domestication and improvement&amp;author=CR McClung&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=374&amp;pmid=33800720&amp;doi=10.3390/genes12030374&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0013"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0013"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Pornsiriwong W, Estavillo GM, Chan KX, Tee EE, Ganguly D, Crisp PA, Phua SY, Zhao C, Qiu J, Park J
<italic>et al</italic>. 2017. A chloroplast retrograde signal, 3′‐phosphoadenosine 5′‐phosphate, acts as a secondary messenger in abscisic acid signaling in stomatal closure and germination. eLife
6: e23361.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.23361"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC5406205"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="28323614"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=eLife&amp;title=A chloroplast retrograde signal, 3′‐phosphoadenosine 5′‐phosphate, acts as a secondary messenger in abscisic acid signaling in stomatal closure and germination&amp;author=W Pornsiriwong&amp;author=GM Estavillo&amp;author=KX Chan&amp;author=EE Tee&amp;author=D Ganguly&amp;volume=6&amp;publication_year=2017&amp;pages=e23361&amp;pmid=28323614&amp;doi=10.7554/eLife.23361&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0014"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0014"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Prado K, Holland BL, McSpadden Gardener B, Lundquist PK, Santiago JP, VanBuren R, Rhee SY. 2025. Building climate‐resilient crops: genetic, environmental, and technological strategies for heat and drought stress tolerance. Journal of Experimental Botany
76: 4395–4413.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/jxb/eraf111"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40062368"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Journal of Experimental Botany&amp;title=Building climate‐resilient crops: genetic, environmental, and technological strategies for heat and drought stress tolerance&amp;author=K Prado&amp;author=BL Holland&amp;author=B McSpadden Gardener&amp;author=PK Lundquist&amp;author=JP Santiago&amp;volume=76&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=4395-4413&amp;pmid=40062368&amp;doi=10.1093/jxb/eraf111&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0015"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0015"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Queiroz MV, Battle MW, Jones MA. 2023. Interactions between photosynthesis and the circadian system. In: Understanding and improving crop photosynthesis: Burleigh Dodds Series in Agricultural Science. Cambridge, UK: Burleigh Dodds Science Publishing, 75–92.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="title=Understanding and improving crop photosynthesis: Burleigh Dodds Series in Agricultural Science&amp;author=MV Queiroz&amp;author=MW Battle&amp;author=MA Jones&amp;publication_year=2023&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0016"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0016"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Sharma A, Samtani H, Laxmi A. 2025. Molecular dialogue between light and temperature signalling in plants: from perception to thermotolerance. Journal of Experimental Botany
76: 677–694.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/jxb/erae356"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="39167699"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Journal of Experimental Botany&amp;title=Molecular dialogue between light and temperature signalling in plants: from perception to thermotolerance&amp;author=A Sharma&amp;author=H Samtani&amp;author=A Laxmi&amp;volume=76&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=677-694&amp;pmid=39167699&amp;doi=10.1093/jxb/erae356&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0017"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0017"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Steed G, Ramirez DC, Hannah MA, Webb AAR. 2021. Chronoculture, harnessing the circadian clock to improve crop yield and sustainability. Science
372: 1289.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.abc9141"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33926926"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Science&amp;title=Chronoculture, harnessing the circadian clock to improve crop yield and sustainability&amp;author=G Steed&amp;author=DC Ramirez&amp;author=MA Hannah&amp;author=AAR Webb&amp;volume=372&amp;publication_year=2021&amp;pages=1289&amp;pmid=33926926&amp;doi=10.1126/science.abc9141&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0018"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0018"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
van Veen E, Küpers JJ, Gommers CMM. 2025. Plastids in a pinch: coordinating stress and developmental responses through retrograde signalling. Plant, Cell &amp; Environment
48: 6897–6911.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/pce.15664"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC12319301"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40474490"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant, Cell &amp; Environment&amp;title=Plastids in a pinch: coordinating stress and developmental responses through retrograde signalling&amp;author=E van Veen&amp;author=JJ Küpers&amp;author=CMM Gommers&amp;volume=48&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=6897-6911&amp;pmid=40474490&amp;doi=10.1111/pce.15664&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0019"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0019"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Zhang H, Zhao Y, Zhu J‐K. 2020. Thriving under stress: how plants balance growth and the stress response. Developmental Cell
55: 529–543.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.devcel.2020.10.012"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33290694"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Developmental Cell&amp;title=Thriving under stress: how plants balance growth and the stress response&amp;author=H Zhang&amp;author=Y Zhao&amp;author=J‐K Zhu&amp;volume=55&amp;publication_year=2020&amp;pages=529-543&amp;pmid=33290694&amp;doi=10.1016/j.devcel.2020.10.012&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="nph70836-bib-0020"><mixed-citation id="nph70836-cit-0020"><named-content content-type="citation-string">
Zuo G. 2025. Non‐photochemical quenching (NPQ) in photoprotection: insights into NPQ levels required to avoid photoinactivation and photoinhibition. New Phytologist
246: 1967–1974.
</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/nph.70121"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="40186372"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytologist&amp;title=Non‐photochemical quenching (NPQ) in photoprotection: insights into NPQ levels required to avoid photoinactivation and photoinhibition&amp;author=G Zuo&amp;volume=246&amp;publication_year=2025&amp;pages=1967-1974&amp;pmid=40186372&amp;doi=10.1111/nph.70121&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec></body></article>